<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author>Elizabeth Fay</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>2023-10-31</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2023-10-31T23:05:00Z</date><name>Elizabeth Fay</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Julie A. Carlson is Professor of English and Associate Dean/Faculty Equity Advisor in
                the Division of Humanities and Fine Arts at UC Santa Barbara. She is author of
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">In the Theatre of Romanticism: Coleridge, Nationalism, Women </hi>(Cambridge
                UP, 1994),
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">England's First Family of Writers: Mary Wollstonecraft, William Godwin, Mary Shelley </hi>(Johns
                Hopkins UP, 2007), and coeditor with Elisabeth Weber of
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Speaking About Torture </hi>(Fordham UP,
                2012). Her current work is on the interconnection between friendship and creativity
                as the radical legacy of white Romantic-era writing.</p>
            <p>Elizabeth A. Fay is Professor of English at the University of Massachusetts Boston.
                She specializes in British Romantic literature. Her most recent monograph is <hi
                    rend="italic">Romantic Egypt: Abyssal Ground of British Romanticism</hi>
                (Lexington Books, 2021). She has also published five previous monographs, including
                    <hi rend="italic">Fashioning Faces: The Portraitive Mode in British
                    Romanticism</hi> (UPNE, 2010) and <hi rend="italic">Romantic Medievalism:
                    History and the Romantic Literary Ideal</hi> (Palgrave, 2002). Her current
                project is <hi rend="italic">Romantic Immanence</hi>, forthcoming from SUNY
                Press.</p>
            <p>David Sigler is Associate Professor of English at the University of Calgary,
                specializing in British Romanticism and literary theory. He is the author of
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Sexual Enjoyment in British Romanticism: Gender and Psychoanalysis 1753–1835 </hi>(McGill-Queenʼs
                UP, 2015) and of <hi rend="italic">Fracture Feminism: The Politics of Impossible
                    Time in British Romanticism (</hi>SUNY Press, 2021). He is coeditor, with
                Daniela Garofalo, of <hi rend="italic">Lacan and Romanticism</hi> (SUNY Press, 2019)
                and editor of <hi rend="italic">Women and War, vol 2: British Women and War
                    1660–1835</hi> (Routledge History of Feminism Series, 2020).</p>
            <p>Kate Singer is Associate Professor of English at Mount Holyoke College and a member
                of the Critical Social Thought program. She has published
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Romantic Vacancy: The Poetics of Gender, Affect, and Radical Speculation </hi>(SUNY
                Press, 2019) and has coedited, with Ashley J. Cross and Suzanne L. Barnett, <hi
                    rend="italic">Material Transgressions: Beyond Romantic Bodies, Genders,
                    Things</hi> (Liverpool UP, 2020). She coedits the Pedagogies section of Romantic
                Circles and is currently at work on a book about Romantic shapeshifting and
                ontologies of change.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
