<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3283</idno><idno type="nines">rce4554</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3283. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles
						Bedford, 19 April 1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3283.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3283" type="letter"><head>3283. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles
						Bedford</ref>, <date when="1819-04-19">19 April 1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row<lb/> Endorsements: 19 April 1819; 19 April
						1819<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute rend="indent0">My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref> has just received
					a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> announcing that he is elected
					Fellow of Oriel,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Hartley Coleridge had been elected a Probationary Fellow at
						Oriel College, Oxford, for one year, on 16 April 1819.</note> – you need not be told the importance of this
					intelligence to all his family</p><p rend="indent1"> I fear my intended journey must be put off <title>sine die</title>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as: ‘without assigning a day for a future meeting’.</note> This tardy
						abscess<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was concerned about his wife <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, who had been ill since the birth of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Charles Cuthbert Southey</ref> on 24 February 1819. </note> continues
					in the same state, it is more than three weeks since it began to appear, &amp; it is impossible to guess when it
					may end. This is very unfortunate in every way. And in spite of all exertions it is as you may well suppose a heavy
					weight upon my spirits, – which God knows, needed no &lt;additional&gt; burden to depress them, – for no man has a larger
					lot of <del>xxxx</del> cares in reversion.</p><p rend="indent1"> You run away wildly from my meaning about the Westminster meeting,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">An annual reunion in London of ex-pupils at Westminster School, the school that Southey attended
						1788–1792.</note> as if I had meant to undervalue my Westminster friends, – whereas what I meant was that it would
					be no pleasure to me to meet a number of men, most of whom I never saw, many of whom I did not care a straw for,
					&amp; some of whom, if I rememberd them at all, it would only be with dislike, – for tho I have a proper love for
					the very walls of Westminster, it by no means follows that I should have a regard for all <del>who have</del>
					Westminster men, some of whom were great beasts in the Westminster sense of the word.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bullies.</note> I have been more than usually fortunate in retaining two lasting friendships from
					the intimacies found there,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford and <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>.</note> – <del>xx</del> there are perhaps
					two or three more which might ripen into <del>something more than</del> &lt;familiar&gt; acquaintance if opportunity
					offerd, – - but only one which would ever <del>be</del> again become a friendship. I think if <ref type="m" target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> were in my neighbourhood we should draw together by attraction
					– as we did thirty years ago.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have sent off something to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> this
					evening for the lucre of gain.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Southey’s article ‘Cemeteries and
						Catacombs of Paris’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359–398.</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> must be much gratified by the
					honours which have been shown to his fathers memory.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Herries
						(1745–1819), a merchant, and Colonel of the London and Westminster Light Horse Volunteers, had died at Hastings on
						3 April 1819; the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 9 April 1819, announced that his ‘remains are to be brought to
						town and interred with military honours’. He was buried in Westminster Abbey on 17 April 1819 and a memorial
						erected in his honour. Herries’s wife was Mary Ann Johnson (dates unknown).</note> He has been a fortunate man in
					having both parents live to a good old age. I hope his children may &lt;all&gt; be equally favoured, – &amp; this is the
					best wish that I can form for him &amp; for them.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Herries and his wife
						Sarah, née Dorington (1787–1821), eventually had six children: Sir Charles John Herries, financier (1815–1883);
						Sarah Herries (1816–1824); Captain William Robert Herries, of the 3rd Light Dragoons (1818–1845); Isabella Ann
						Herries (1818–1897); Maria Julia Herries (1819–1857); and Edward Herries, diplomat (1821–1911).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your godson</ref> thrives surprizingly,
					– more so than any of his predecessors. Poor child, I did not wish for him, – but he is welcome now he is here, –
					&amp; will I doubt not be well provided for in this world, or in the next. Go when I may he will find friends, even
					if I should be called away before I have made a fair provision for him. – Yesterday I received a circular letter
					desiring me to subscribe to a monument for Burns at Edinburgh.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Burns
						(1759–1796; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish poet. A meeting in London in 1819 had formed a committee to raise funds
						for what became the Burns Monument in Edinburgh (1831).</note> I must be paid better as a living poet before I
					subscribe to build monuments for dead ones. And were I overflowing with wealth I would never contribute to such a
					purpose while any deserving man of letters was in distress</p><p rend="indent1"> I had nearly forgotten to request you to pay <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Osiris</ref> for a certain machine<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A machine to give patients mild electric shocks. It was being used on Edith Southey; see Southey to
						Henry Herbert Southey, 7 April 1819, Letter 3279.</note> which I commissioned him to send me down. – We must
					trouble <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murraylemagne</ref> with no inclosures for his parcels in
					future. He is too great a man to be made use of for such purpose, – &amp; that greatness is communicated to his
					people, – they throw such things aside &amp; forget them. However I have had nothing from him since Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 4.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Since the parcel containing <title>Quarterly
							Review</title>, 19 (July 1818), published on 2 February 1819.</note> The discovery which he has made of my
					disposition I think may be explained thus; – he learnt, <hi rend="ital">I believe</hi>, that I had expressed a
					strong disapprobation of the system of Blackwoods Magazine, &amp; wrote rather warmly (not angrily) to ask why I
					would not assist him in it: I told him in reply<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey to John
						Murray, 7 October 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3201.</note> how
					I abhorred the use of such personalities as that Magazine abounded with, – <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murraylemagne</ref> was very shortly involved in some scrapes by the very fault
					which I had objected to, – &amp; glad to get rid of his share in the concern.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray had taken a share in <title>Blackwood’s Magazine</title> in 1817, but had been horrified by
						the public controversy and legal actions caused by the attack on Hazlitt in ‘Hazlitt Cross Questioned’,
							<title>Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</title>, 3 (August 1818), 550–552, as well as the <title>Magazine</title>’s
						denigration of William Gifford and Thomas Moore. In March 1819 he severed his connections with the
						publication.</note> And I dare say, he likes me the less for having been right when I differed from him in opinion
					about it.</p><p rend="indent1"> I hope <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> is recovered. – Thank you for
					the trouble you have taken about <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> obdurate
						verses.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor’s Latin ode, ‘Ad Gustavum Regem Suedorum’ (1819),
						unpublished until it appeared in <title>Poemata et Inscriptiones</title> (London, 1847), pp. 219–220. Landor had
						entered it for a prize offered by the Royal Swedish Academy of Letters, History and Antiquities (founded
						1786).</note> His Latin is marvellously difficult.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1819-04-19">19 Ap. 1819.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>