<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3362</idno><idno type="nines">rce4633</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3362. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 13 October 1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3362.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 3p. .  Previously  published: John
                  Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
               142–146.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3362" type="letter"><head>3362. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1819-10-13">13 October 1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
                  M.P/ Welsh Pool<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Previously published: John
                  Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
               142–146.</note></head><opener><salute rend="indent0"> My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> My absence from home was longer than I had expected, – it reached into the seventh week.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s tour of Scotland lasted from 17 August until 1 October 1819. For his record of events, see <title>Journal
                     of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> I went as far north as Fleet Mound<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Fleet Mound was a massive causeway, commissioned in 1803, designed by Telford, and built between
                  1814–1816, to carry the road over Loch Fleet. It comprised an earthwork, and a bridge with self-regulating sluice gates that allowed
                  the waters from the river to flow out, but prevented seawater from coming in.</note> &amp; saw the wildest part of the Highlands, in
               crossing from Dingwall to Jeantown. If these roads, bridges &amp; piers had been constructed in France instead of Scotland, – or if the
                  <del>Cal</del> Canal had been one of Bonapartes<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769–1821; Emperor of the
                  French 1804–1814, 1815).</note> works, our newspapers would have been full of their praises. I verily believe that no Government in
               modern times ever did half so much for the improvement of its dominions, as has been done in Scotland within the last fifteen years. </p><p rend="indent1"> If Parliament should be convoked before Xmas, I shall not see you till we meet in town. But I doubt whether Ministers
               have courage to convoke it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Parliament did reconvene, on 23 November 1819, largely to pass the
                  ‘Six Acts’ to suppress radical agitation.</note> Their miserable imbecillity, as you well know, is such, that they will make any
               concession, &amp; risque any <del>mischief</del> &lt;evil&gt; to obtain a respite from the baiting which they undergo in the H of Commons.
                  <del>Xxx</del> Never was there a time when we stood more in need of an efficient Minister, – &amp; never was there <ref type="m" target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">a more irresolute head</ref>, nor a more disjointed administration, none of the members having
               any confidence in each other, nor in themselves, nor in <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Regent</ref>. And as
               for the Opposition, it is plain that they would make common cause with the Devil <del>himself</del>, for the sake of annoying <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Prince</ref> &amp; embarrassing the Government. I know not which is most
               wonderful the blindness or the baseness of this besotted &amp; suicidal party. But this I know, that should I ever be under the knife
               of the Radical Reformers, it would be some satisfaction to think how soon these abettors of all mischief would be in the same
               situation.</p><p rend="indent1"> Whatever the process may be, I do not doubt that we shall lose part of our liberties in the upshot. The abuse of
               liberty has always been punished by its loss. This is the natural &amp; just consequence. I would willingly submit at once to such
               restraints of the press as the times require, &amp; give such powers to the Executive as <del>could</del> &lt;might&gt; enable it to meet
               &amp; quell the danger. The laws as they are present interpreted serve only to protect those whom they ought to punish, &amp; to
               intimidate those whom they ought to protect. </p><p rend="indent1"> When I was at Lisbon in the year 1801 there was every human reason for expecting that the yellow fever would be
               communicated to that city from Cadiz, so violent was the contagion, &amp; so absurdly inefficient all means that were taken for cutting
               it off. The people however ate drank &amp; were merry, – &amp; I among others, went on quietly with my usual pursuits, tho I never laid
               down at night, without thinking it likely that I should hear the plague had appeared among us in the morning. The present state of
               things reminds me of what my feelings were then. This danger also may pass away, &amp; in spite of all appearances I cannot think it
               can be in the order of Providence that a country like this should be brought to ruin. But it is upon this persuasion that I rely, not
               upon the strength of the laws, the measures of the Government or the good sense of the people.</p><p rend="indent1"> My third volume has been provokingly delayed owing to the loss of a proof sheet. I knew nothing of this during my
                  absence.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and final volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810–1819). There was a second edition of the first volume only in 1822.</note> I shall be able to improve the book materially for
               a future edition, tho very possibly it may not be reprinted during my life. Be that as it may I shall carefully correct it, &amp;
               insert <del>much</del> as much additional information as may come to my hands. I have just received one manuscript from Brazil, – &amp;
               another which is said to be of considerable value, is on the way to me.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">When the parcel
                  containing the expected work arrived, Southey found it to be nothing more than another copy of Manoel Aires de Casal (1754–1821),
                     <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Relação Historico-Geografica do Reino do Brazil</title> (1817), no. 3252 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library. Koster had already sent Southey a paper on Para, probably by Thomaz Antonio Maciel Monteiro (1780–1847),
                  Brazilian lawyer, later a member of the Supreme Court and 1st Baron Itamarca.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am not surprized at the difficulty you find in forming a Welsh Committee in London.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn was closely involved in efforts to found a society of Welshmen based in London that would promote Welsh
                  historical research. These activities eventually led to the re-foundation of the Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion in 1820.</note>
               – The only qualified person whom I can call to mind is <ref type="m" target="people.html#ReesThomas">Rees</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ReesOwen">the booksellers</ref> brother, – who is a Unitarian Minister. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref> is either too much an invalid, or too much a hypochondriac to be capable of
               attendance. The difficulty about the publicans is comical enough, &amp; not easily to be got over. In Portugal two of the first members
               of the Royal Academy<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese Royal Academy of Sciences, founded in 1779.</note> were a
               Barber, &amp; a man who kept a universal shop, more like a <hi rend="ital">hucksters</hi> than any thing else, &amp; these men
               associated at the Academy with nobles &amp; Princes of the blood. But in Portugal a nobleman takes snuff with his servant, &amp; plays
               at cards with him. You must make your Bishops &amp; Judges patrons &amp; presidents &amp; get the work done without any more personal
               intercourse than they are liable to in the ordinary course of business.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Watkin Williams Wynn
                  became the first President of the re-founded Cymmrodorion in 1820 and George IV became its Patron.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I shall now be getting on with Oliver Newman.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished epic, set in
                  New England. The completed sections were published after Southey’s death in <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished):
                     With Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1–90.</note> Some parts of this poem will have the same kind of interest
               for a New Englander that the first part of Madoc has for a Welshman,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Madoc in Wales’,
                     <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> who is conversant with the history of this country. The fourth book in particular is of this
               kind – I allude in it to Roger Williams,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Roger Williams (c. 1603–1683) was a Londoner, not a
                  Welshman. He founded Providence Plantation in 1636 as a religiously tolerant community, advocated peaceful relations with native
                  peoples and was an abolitionist. He was praised in ‘Oliver Newman’, Book 4, lines 722–731.</note> who, take him for all in all,
               appears to me one of the greatest Worthies of Wales, – perhaps the greatest; &amp; who by fair desert is really entitled to that high
               place in public opinion which William Penn<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">William Penn (1644–1718), Quaker and founder of
                  Pennsylvania.</note> has obtained rather by accident than by right.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Your godson</ref> is a fine creature, large enough &amp;
               strong enough for one of the race of the Giants. The young ones<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> remember your roaring well. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Their elder sister</ref> is shot up, till she is as tall as <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">her mother</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Clive<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Watkin Williams Wynn had married Lady
                  Henrietta Antonia Clive (1786–1835), daughter of Edward Clive, 1st Earl of Powis (1754–1839; <title>DNB</title>) on 4 February 1817,
                  thus connecting the Clive and Wynn Welsh political dynasties. Southey had been called on in his absence by Lady Henrietta’s brother,
                  Hon. Robert Henry Clive (1789–1854), MP for Ludlow 1818–1832, MP for Shropshire South 1832–1854. Clive had spent much time
                  travelling in Spain during the Peninsular War and wished to offer help to Southey with his <title>History of the Peninsular
                     War</title> (1823–1832).</note> did not make his appearance. He probably heard at the Inn that I was absent. – I know not what is
               become of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>. – There is a paper of mine about
               the Catacombs in the last Quarterly,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris’, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359–398.</note> – &amp; I have corrected for the next the proofs of one upon the Monastic
               Orders, written for the purpose of bringing forward Braybrook House at the end.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Isabella
                  Lettice King (1772–1845; <title>DNB</title>) founded the Ladies’ Association at Bailbrook House, near Bath, in June 1816. It
                  provided a home for orphaned gentlewomen with no income and was duly praised by Southey in his review of Thomas Fosbrooke
                  (1770–1842; <title>DNB</title>), <title>British Monachism; or, Manners and Customs of the Monks and Nuns of England</title> (1817),
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 22 (July 1819), 59–102 (96–101).</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3">
                  RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1819-10-13">13 Oct. 1819.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>