<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3526</idno><idno type="nines">rce4797</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3526. Robert Southey to John May, 16
						August-18 November 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3526.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Department of Rare Books,
						Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers
						A.S727. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
							Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 15–18 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3526" type="letter"><head>3526. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1820-08-16">16
						August-18 November 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books,
						Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers
						A.S727. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
							Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 15–18 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1820-08-16">August 16. 1820.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear
						friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">Since <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt Marys</ref> arrival I have learnt
					from her a few circumstances which I did not know when my two former letters were written. &lt;I must begin&gt; This
					therefore <del>must be a letter of scraps consisting of</del> &lt;with&gt; corrections &amp; additions, which in my
					transcript I will insert in their proper places. And first of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my fathers</ref> family. – John Southey (my Grandfathers Uncle, who married the heiress)<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey (1666–1728), a lawyer, who married Mary Cannon (1678–1730), heiress to the Fitzhead
						estate. He was the uncle of Southey’s grandfather, Thomas Southey (1696–1777).</note> was as I had supposed him to
					be, an excellent man, very much respected &amp; beloved. My grandfather regarded him with the utmost reverence; –
					it was always sufficient authority for him that his Uncle said, or thought so or so, – as one from whose judgement
					there could be no appeal. His wife was a proud woman, – &amp; for that reason it seems to have been that his
						mother<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Southey (dates unknown).</note> lived with her grandson Thomas,
					instead of with him. Both his daughters were married, – one to the last of the Periam family, whom she
						survived.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Southey (1705–1767) married John Periam, of Sandhill
						Park, Bishops Lydeard (1701–1755). The Periams had originally been merchants in Exeter, but various branches of
						the family had become landowners in Devon and Somerset. The couple had no surviving children.</note> Madame Periam
					she was called. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt Mary</ref> in her childhood &amp; early
					youth spent most of her time with her, or with her sister Madame Lethbridge.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Southey (1704–1789) married the landowner Christopher Lethbridge, of Westaway House, Devon (1685–1746).
						Lethbridge’s brother, Thomas Lethbridge (b. 1698), married Sarah Periam (d. 1771), a sister of John Periam, and
						their descendants inherited the Periam estates. There was a third sister, Jane Southey (d. 1722), who died
						young.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey (my Uncle)</ref> in like manner lived
					more with Cannon Southey<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cannon Southey (d. 1768), son of John Southey
						(1666–1728).</note> than with his parents, in his boyhood &amp; youth, – but it was a bad school for him. He was
					looked upon as the probable heir of the family, even after the birth of young Somerville,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765–1819; <title>DNB</title>), agricultural
						reformer and Southey’s third cousin. He was the grandson of Mary Southey (1704–1789) and heir to his great-uncle,
						John Cannon Southey.</note> who was always a weakly child. – My grandfather was a quiet, contented, neat little
					old man, who lived to the age of fourscore.</p><p rend="indent1">My maternal grandmother<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Bradford
						(1710–1782).</note> had been addressed by her second husband<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill
						(1705–1765), a lawyer, of Bedminster, Somerset.</note> before she married her first.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tyler (1709–1747), of Court of Noke, Pembridge, Herefordshire.</note> She became acquainted
					with him at Bristol whither she had gone to visit some distant relations, – their family name I have forgotten, if
					I ever heard it, but one of them married a merchant by name Prankerd,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Richard Prankerd (or Pranchard), a Bristol merchant in the West India trade (dates unknown).</note>
					&amp; after his death, <del>was</del> went to Lisbon with <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss
						Tyler</ref> as a sort of Ama or Duenna. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tyler killed himself by hard drinking, he left his
						children<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Tyler, John Tyler (dates unknown), William Tyler
						(1742–1789) and Edward Tyler (1744–1786).</note> 600£ each: &amp; his widows jointure was 200£ a year. My
					grandfather, who in the interim had married also &amp; become a widower, went down in due time to Herefordshire,
					quartered himself in the house, &amp; took care the next morning to have his clothes <del>xxxx</del> spread out to
					air in full sight of the neighbours. He was a kind &amp; indulgent husband, &amp; she was a woman whom every body
					loved who knew her. But her life was embittered by her children, &amp; especially by her son John.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. John Tyler.</note> He sold the reversion of her jointure as he did every thing
					else, – &amp; she parted with half of it to deliver him from prison.</p><p rend="indent1"> The story of his marriage is worse than I had represented it. He picked his wifes<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> pocket while she was asleep, &amp; left her at an inn in Bath,
					with a Welsh servant girl, &amp; three halfpence! A Welsh gentleman overheard them in the streets deploring their
						<del>misfortune</del> condition in their own language; &amp; enquiring into the case, assisted them to get back to
					their own country.</p><p rend="center"> ———</p><p rend="indent1"> During my Grandfathers life the three breeds of which his family consisted had continued in
					harmony with each other; &amp; had it not been for the turn which affairs took upon his death, a marriage would
					probably have taken place between Capt Hill<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant-Colonel Edward Hill (d. 1824) of the
						Royal Marines, the son of Edward Hill by his first marriage and step-brother of Elizabeth Tyler.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>. But Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Hill behaved most
					unfeelingly concerning the division of his property. He demanded his fathers clothes, &amp; told the widow to pack
					them up for him; – she replied that she had not been used to perform such offices, &amp; that if he chose to take
					them from the boys his brothers, he might pack them himself. This he actually did, &amp; he even searched for the
					Tyler plate, but it was successfully concealed from him in a secret cupboard, made in the wall of my grandmothers
					bed chamber. I remember the place. Poor woman, she was obliged to hide the plate there from two of her own sons. –
					The dispute continued for years, &amp; was not terminated when <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle Herbert</ref> took orders.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill was ordained at Oxford
						in 1774.</note> An angry correspondence at that time past between them, in which the Captain told <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> that nothing but his gown protected him, &amp; was told in
					reply that a red coat sometimes covered a coward. It ended in an incurable breach, – nearly fifty years have
					elapsed, <del>thxx &amp;</del> &amp; no approach has ever been made on either side to a reconciliation. This I have
					always regarded as unfortunate, – for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> never
					spoke of her half-brother without affection. Ill as he behaved, he was not without good qualities; &amp; perhaps
					disappointment took the form of irritation when he found that his father had left much less than he expected to
					inherit. </p><p rend="indent1">My grandmother’s jointure (from her first husband) was 200£ a year, which was probably equivalent
					to thrice that sum in these days. The Tylers had from their father 600£ each. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> lived with her Uncle Bradford,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Bradford (1701–1768), Herefordshire clergyman; Curate of Shobdon 1728–1768, Rector of
						Cefyn-Llys 1748–1768, Vicar of Aymestry 1762–1768. </note> of him &amp; of her I shall speak hereafter. I must now
					speak of the Hills. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My uncle</ref> (κατ εξοχηυ)<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Par excellence’, ‘pre-eminent’, a signal of Southey’s affection for Herbert
						Hill.</note> – it is so habitual to me to speak &amp; write of him, &amp; of him only by that name, that I will
					not constrain myself to use any farther designation,) — <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My
						Uncle</ref> then &amp; his brother Joseph<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the
						information given here.</note> went by day to a school in the village kept by one of the strangest fellows that
					ever wore a cassack or <del>opened a school</del> &lt;took up the trade of tuition&gt;. His name was Collins,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Emanuel Collins (<hi rend="ital">fl.</hi> 1732–1762), clergyman, alehouse-keeper, poet
						and schoolmaster. He ran a school at Shannon Court, Corn Street, Bristol.</note> &amp; he was grandfather to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mitchell<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Sampson Michell (1755–1809), British sailor
						who rose to be an Admiral in the Portuguese navy. His wife was Ann Shears (1765–1838), the daughter of Samuel
						Shears (dates unknown), a Bedminster surgeon, and a granddaughter of Emanuel Collins.</note> (the poor Commodores
					wife) &amp; to Sir Rufan Donkin,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Rufane Donkin (1772–1841;
							<title>DNB</title>), soldier, geographer and politician. His mother was Mary Collins (1748–1815), daughter of
						Emanuel Collins.</note> who very probably may not know quite so much of his own family history as I do. He was a
					clever &lt;&amp;&gt; profligate <del>fellow</del>, &amp; eked out his ways &amp; means by authorship. I remember one of
					his works among <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle’s</ref> books in <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tylers</ref> possession, its title is Hell Gates Open,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Hell-gates Open to All Men: or an Invitation to Persons of Every Age, Sex and
							Quality, to a Residence in the Infernal Regions</title> (1751), by ‘Lucifer’.</note> but not having
						<del>seen</del> &lt;looked into&gt; it since I was a mere boy, I only know that it is satirical, as the name may seem to
					import. I sent for another of his publications some years ago from a catalogue, not as expecting any thing of
					value, but because he had been <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> first
					schoolmaster, &amp; I knew who &amp; what he was. It is a little book in the unusual form of foolscap quarto, &amp;
					because it contains one fact which is really curious as matter of history I will give its title*<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">* Miscellanies in Prose &amp; Verse, consisting of Essays, Abstracts, Original Poems,
						Letters, Tales, Translations, Panegyricks, Epigrams &amp; Epitaphs. <lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">Sunt bona, sunt quædam mediocria, sunt mala plura </l><l rend="indent3">Quæ legis, hic aliter non fit, Avite, liber. </l><l rend="indent3">Things good, things bad, things middling when you look</l><l rend="indent3">You’ll find to constitute, my friends, this book. Martial</l></lg> By Emanuel Collins AB. Late of Wadham College, Oxford. Bristol. Printed by E Farley in Small Street. 1762
						[Southey’s note.] [Editors’ note: This is a free translation of Marcus Valerius Martialis (c. AD 38/41–102–104),
							<title>Epigrams</title>, Book 1, no. 16. The book was no. 663 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library and
						Southey had ordered it in 1809; see Southey to Herbert Hill, [started before and continued on] 22 December 1809,
							<title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 1723.]</note> at the bottom of the
					page. The publication is in no respect creditable to its author, &amp; in one respect highly discreditable to him,
					– on the score of decency. But the fact which is well worth the two shillings I gave for the book, is, that as late
					as the end of George the seconds reign, or the beginning of George the third’s,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. in about 1760, when George II (1683–1760; King of Great Britain 1727–1760; <title>DNB</title>)
						was succeeded by his grandson, George III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
					there were persons at Bristol who from political scruples of conscience refused to take King Williams
						half-pence.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Emanuel Collins ‘To Mr. R – B–’, <title>Miscellanies in Prose
							and Verse</title> (Bristol, 1762), pp. 25–27. The persons in question refused to take coins bearing the head of
						William III (1650–1702; King of Great Britain 1689–1702; <title>DNB</title>) because they did not accept his right
						to the throne and supported the claims of James II (1633–1701; King of Great Britain 1685–1688;
						<title>DNB</title>) and his descendants. William III had ended the production of tin coins in 1694 and replaced
						them with copper halfpence and farthings.</note> &lt;&amp; these persons were so numerous that the magistrates
					thought it necessary to interfere, because of the inconvenience which they occasioned in the common dealings of
					trade &amp; of the market&gt;. They were then in common currency, – &amp; indeed I myself remember them, having about
					the years 1786–1790 – laid by some half dozen with the single or double-head, among the foreign pieces &amp; others
					of rare occurrence which came into my hands.</p><p rend="indent1">Devoid as his Miscellanies are of any merit, Parson Collins, as he was called (not in honour of
					the cloth) had some humour. In repairing the public road, the labourers came so near his garden wall, that they
					injured the foundations &amp; down it fell. He complained to the waywardens, &amp; demanded reparation, which they
					would have evaded if they could, telling him it was but an old wall, &amp; in a state of decay. Gentlemen, he
					replied, old as the wall was, it served my purpose. But however I have not the least objection to your putting up a
					second-hand one in its place. This anecdote I heard full five &amp; thirty years ago from one of my schoolmasters,
					who had been a rival of Collins’s, &amp; is satirized in the Miscellanies.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Emanuel Collins, <title>Miscellanies in Prose and Verse</title> (Bristol, 1762), pp. 137–142, including ‘The
						Quack School-Master’. Southey interpreted this poem as an attack on William Williams (d. 1811), his schoolmaster
						at Merchants’ Hall School, Bristol, 1782–1786.</note> – His school failed him, not because he was deficient in
					learning, of which he had a full share, but for his gross misconduct. He afterwards kept something so much like an
					alehouse, that he got into a scrape with his Superiors; &amp; to make the matter worse he had daughters who made
					themselves no &lt;more&gt; agreable to the guests than they ought to have done. They contrived however &lt;some of them&gt; to
					do better in life than might have been expected from such a beginning. One married a surgeon at Bristol, &amp; this
						<del>I believe</del> &lt;I think&gt; was M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mitchells mother (<del>xxxxxxx this was a favourite
						sister</del>) – but this poor woman behaved ill after marriage &amp; died miserably. <del>The</del> &lt;A&gt; second
					&lt;(her character I believe was blameless) went into Ireland as Lady’s maid with the family of a Lord Glenair<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified. </note> or Glen-something like it, &amp; married&gt;
						<del>married</del> Rufan Donkin,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">General Robert Donkin (1727–1821); he
						married Mary Collins (1748–1815) in 1772.</note><del>an officer in the army, who xxxx xxxxxxxxx</del> &lt;when I knew
					him in my childhood was&gt; a Colonel, &amp; <del>died</del> &lt;is now&gt; a General, &amp; whose son is <del>xxxx</del> a
						KCB*<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">* He is the person who managed that counter-intrigue in Sicily which
						is related in the Ed. Ann. Reg. Vol 4. 436; – he conducted the whole affair, &amp; he it was whom the assassins
						were sent to murder, by the French General. [Southey’s note.] [Editors’ note: <title>Edinburgh Annual Register,
							for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 436–437, describing a French plan to seize the navy of British-occupied
						Sicily.]</note> &amp; I know not what besides. A third daughter who was the very image of Sir Rufan kept a village
					shop at Chew Magna in Somersetshire,<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Patty Collins (dates unknown); the
						Collins family were originally from Chew Magna in Somerset.</note> &amp; dealt with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my father</ref> for such things as were in his way. <del>I remember her
						perfectly</del>, she used to dine with us whenever she came to Bristol, &amp; was always a welcome guest, for her
						<del>thorough good nature</del> &lt;honest blunt manners&gt; &amp; her &lt;comical&gt; oddity. Her face was broad &amp;
					coarse, like a Tartars, but with quick dark eyes, &lt;&amp; a fierce expression, –&gt; &amp; she was one of those persons
					who could say, <hi rend="ital">quidlibet cuilibet <del>xxx</del> de quolibet</hi>.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">‘What pleases, to whom it pleases, about what it pleases’.</note><title/></p><p rend="indent1">I perceive that I should make an excellent correspondent for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Urban,<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Correspondents to the <title>Gentleman’s Magazine</title> (1731–1922) addressed
						themselves to ‘Sylvanus Urban’.</note> &amp; that I have mistaken my talent in writing histories &amp; poems,
					instead of following the rich veins of gossip &amp; garrulity. All this however is not foreign to my purpose. For I
					wish not only to begin <hi rend="ital">ab ovo</hi>,<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">‘From the egg’, i.e.
						from the beginning.</note> but to describe every thing <del>that</del> relating to the nest. And he who paints a
					birds nest ought not to represent it nakedly &lt;<hi rend="ital">per se</hi>&gt;, but &lt;<hi rend="ital">in</hi> situ&gt; in
					its place &amp; with as many of its natural accompaniments as his canvas will admit. It is not manners &amp;
					fashions alone that change with us, – the very constitution of society may undergo (&amp; in all likelihood will)
					as great a change in the course of the next two or three centuries, as it has done in the last. The change is
					likely to be more violent &amp; far more rapid. And at no very distant time these letters may derive no small part
					of their interest &amp; value from the sketches which they contain of a stage of society which <del>shall
						have</del> has (already) past away, &amp; of a state of things which <del>xxxx</del>-shall &lt;then&gt; have ceased to
					exist.</p><closer><dateline><date when="1820-11-18">Nov 18. 1820</date></dateline></closer></div></body></text></TEI>