<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3442</idno><idno type="nines">rce4713</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3442. Robert Southey to John Murray, 19 February 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3442.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42552.
						ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Samuel Smiles, A Publisher and His Friends. Memoir and Correspondence
							of the Late John Murray, with an Account of the Origin and Progress of the House, 1768–1843, 2 vols
						(London, 1891), II, pp. 109–110 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3442" type="letter"><head>3442. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1820-02-19">19 February 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John
						Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re.</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London.<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 22 FE
						22/ 1820<lb/> Seal: black wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb/> Watermark: W D &amp; Co/ 1819<lb/>
						Endorsement: R Southey Esq / Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 19. 1820 <lb/> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552.
						ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Samuel Smiles, <title>A Publisher and His Friends. Memoir and Correspondence
							of the Late John Murray, with an Account of the Origin and Progress of the House, 1768–1843</title>, 2 vols
						(London, 1891), II, pp. 109–110 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1820-02-19">19 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1820.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0">My
						dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your letter &amp; its inclosure. I reckoned upon Marlborough for this number,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of John Duke of Marlborough,
							with his Original Correspondence; Collected from the Family Records at Blenheim, and Other Authentic Sources.
							Illustrated with Portraits, Maps, and Military Plans</title> (1818–1819) appeared in <title>Quarterly
							Review</title>, 23 (May 1820), 1–73. He did not, as he had hoped, have an article in <title>Quarterly
							Review</title>, 22 (January 1820), published on 17 March 1820.</note> &amp; the New Churches for the next.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Benjamin Haydon, <title>New Churches, Considered with
							Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the Encouragement of Painting</title> (1818) and other volumes
						appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549–591.</note> Let the latter paper have the last
					place in the number, for which it will be fitted, by its direct bearing upon the diseased opinions of the
					times.</p><p rend="indent1"> You have sent me duplicates of Chaboulon de Fleury<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre
						Alexandre Édouard, Baron Fleury de Chaboulon (1779–1835), <title>Memoirs of the Private Life, Return, and Reign of
							Napoleon in 1815</title> (1820), published by Murray. Southey had a copy of the French edition, <title>Mémoires
							pour servir à l’Histoire de la Vie Privée: du Retour et du Règne de Napoléon</title> (1819–1820), no. 563 in the
						sale catalogue of his library.</note> &amp; of Burkhardt,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Swiss
						traveller and orientalist Johann Ludwig Burckhardt (1784–1817). Murray had published his <title>Travels in
							Nubia</title> (1819) on behalf of the Association for Promoting the Discovery of the Interior Parts of
						Africa.</note> which I will return <hi rend="ital">cum multis aliis</hi>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘With many others’.</note> Burkhardt is an excellent traveller, in every respect.</p><p rend="indent1"> Oliver Cromwells Book is one of the very worst that was ever made by a dull man, &amp; will
					hardly be of the smallest use in drawing up a life of old Oliver.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Oliver
						Cromwell (c. 1742–1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Protector, Oliver Cromwell, and of His Sons,
							Richard and Henry. Illustrated by Original Letters, and Other Family Papers</title> (1820). This book provided
						one of the occasions for Southey’s ‘Life of Cromwell’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 25 (July 1821),
						279–347.</note> It will serve however for text. The French life<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Abel
						Francois Villemain (1790–1870), <title>Histoire de Cromwell, d’après les Mémoires du Temps et les Recueils
							Parlementaires</title> (1819).</note> I have not yet examined, farther than to see that some pains have been
					taken with it, &amp; that even pains-taking French&lt;men&gt; are wretchedly acquainted with our bibliography; –
					the author conceives De-Foe’s Mem: of a Cavalier to be authentic history,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel Defoe’s (c. 1660?–1731; <title>DNB</title>) fictional <title>Memoirs of a Cavalier</title> (1720).</note>
					&amp; knows nothing of what Noble has done. Nobles Cromwell I will return in the next parcel, having a copy of it.
					I want his Memoirs of the Regicides.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Mark Noble (1754–1827;
							<title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Protectoral House of Cromwell: Deduced from an Early Period, and
							Continued Down to the Present Time</title> (1787), no. 2040 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; and
							<title>The Lives of the English Regicides, and Other Commissioners of the Pretended High Court of Justice,
							Appointed to Sit in Judgement Upon their Sovereign, King Charles the First</title> (1798), no. 2041 in the sale
						catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> The subject is very good, &amp; much to my liking.</p><p rend="indent1"> The reign of George 3. is a wide subject, – &amp; I must talk seriously with you concerning
						it.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not produce the proposed history of the reign of George
						III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Such a work, in its general design,
					as Voltaires Age of Louis 14,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. Francois-Marie Arouet (1694–1778),
							<title>Siècle de Louis XIV</title> (1751), a history of Europe 1661–1715.</note> upon a larger scale in
					proportion to the greater extent of the subject, is what I have long thought of. A comprehensive &amp;
					philosophical view of all the revolutions which have occurred during those eventful sixty years, with no more
					detail than is required for effect: for a <hi rend="ital">detailed</hi> history would be a tremendous undertaking,
					almost beyond any mans strength. But I am sure that a most popular work upon my plan might be produced within the
					compass of four octavos, or perhaps of three; – a book which every body would read, &amp; which would keep its
					place. – And this may, &amp; would in all likelihood, be so great an object, that <del>I</del> you &amp; I must
					consider whether it be good policy <del>to employ as much time</del> in treating it upon a smaller scale for the
					Review to employ as much time, as would suffice for one third of the work, upon a likely computation.</p><p rend="indent1"> Antar will be a manageable subject &amp; a good one.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not review <title>Antar, A Bedoueen Romance. Translated from the Arabic by Terrick Hamilton</title>
						(1819) for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> – There is a life of Camoens announced, – upon which I dare
					say the author has bestowed a great deal of minute labour. I can make a good article upon this subject, – the
					limits of a review being quite sufficient.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The book was by Southey’s
						occasional correspondent <ref type="m" target="people.html#AdamsonJohn">John Adamson</ref>, <title>Memoirs of the
							Life and Writing of Luis de Camoens</title> (1820); Southey’s copy was no. 10 in the sale catalogue of his
						library. Southey noticed it favourably in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), 1–39.</note> You
					should consign to me also Prince Maximilian Travels in Brazil.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The
						explorer, ethnographer and naturalist, Prince Maximilian zu Wied-Neuwied (1782–1867), who had travelled
						extensively in south-eastern Brazil. He published an account of his journeys, <title>Reise Nach Brasilien in
							Denjahren 1815 bis 1817</title> (1820), which was translated into English as <title>Travels in Brazil in the
							Years 1815 to 1817</title> (1820); Southey’s copy was no. 1865 in the sale catalogue of his library. Southey did
						not review it for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Dobrizhoffer calls his book a History.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin
						Dobrizhoffer (1717–1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784).
						Murray was to publish Sara Coleridge’s translation as <title>An Account of the Abipones</title> (1822).</note> It
					will be better to announce it as “An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian people &lt;in the interior&gt; of South
					America translated from the original Latin of Martin Dobrizhoffer, one of the Ex-Jesuits, two &amp; twenty years a
					Missionary in Paraguay.” The best way of describing the nature &amp; value of the book will be by annexing the
					following passage from my Hist: of Brazil – – “the Abipones have been in one thing fortunate above all other
					savages; for the history of their manners &amp; fortunes by Martin Dobrizhoffer, a German Jesuit, who devoted the
					prime of his years to the task of converting them, &amp; in old age after the extinction of his order, found
					consolation in recording the knowledge which he had so painfully acquired, &amp; the labours which had so miserably
					been frustrated, is of all books relating to savage life, the most curious, &amp; in every respect the most
						interesting.”<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
						1810–1819), III, p. 397. Murray took Southey’s advice, advertising <title>An Account of the Abipones</title> thus,
						and as no. 25 on the list of ‘Works Preparing for Immediate Publication’ that he issued in December
					1820.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I must tell Lord Radstock<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">William Waldegrave, 1st Baron
						Radstock (1753–1825; <title>DNB</title>), admiral, philanthropist and Governor of Newfoundland, 1797–1800. He was
						of central importance in helping John Clare (1793–1864; <title>DNB</title>) to publish his <title>Poems
							Descriptive of Rural Life and Scenery</title> (1820).</note> what you will not be surprized &lt;to hear,&gt;
					because you will very well understand the reason of my resolution, – that I have been obliged to make the
					resolution <del>never</del> of never reviewing a volume of poems.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very
						truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"> Will you lay by for me a set of proofs of the Marlborough<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of John Duke of Marlborough, with his Original
								Correspondence; Collected from the Family Records at Blenheim, and Other Authentic Sources. Illustrated with
								Portraits, Maps, and Military Plans</title> (1818–1819) appeared in<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (May
							1820), 1–73. </note> – that I may have it as it is written. Its great length is a reason for curtailment: but I
						know not how I could have written it in less compass, the quantity of matter being so great in <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoxeWilliam">Coxes</ref> volumes. I have avoided throughout all technical details, all
						general history, &amp; kept as close as possible to Marlborough. Yet it is longer by a full third that you would
						have wished to have, or I to make it. The length however may show that I never spare time or labour.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>