<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3257</idno><idno type="nines">rce4528</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3257. Robert Southey to Sir
                  George Beaumont, 5 March 1819 </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3257.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                  William Knight (ed.), Memorials of Coleorton, 2 vols (London,
                  1887) .  Previously  published: William Knight (ed.), Memorials of
                     Coleorton: Being Letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his Sister, Southey,
                     and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont of Coleorton,
                     Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp.
                  188–190.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3257" type="letter"><head>3257. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir
                  George Beaumont</ref>,<date when="1819-03-05"> 5 March 1819 </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                  William Knight (ed.), <title>Memorials of Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (London,
                  1887)<lb/> Previously published: William Knight (ed.), <title>Memorials of
                     Coleorton: Being Letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his Sister, Southey,
                     and Sir Walter Scott to Sir George and Lady Beaumont of Coleorton,
                     Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp.
                  188–190.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1819-03-05"> 5th March 1819.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear Sir George, –</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am indeed gratified by your offer of becoming one of the sponsors
               to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">this
               infant</ref>, and truly proud should I have been to have received
               so kind a mark of friendship, if it could have been so. But <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford</ref> requested
               some months ago that if the child should prove a boy, he might hold the same relation
               to it which he had done to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">his dear
                  brother</ref>, and that same feeling induced me, as soon as he
               was born, to desire that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles W.
                  Wynn</ref> would do the same. I mean to call him Cuthbert; you who know <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth’s</ref> poems so well
               will understand why.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth’s
                  ‘Inscription: For the Spot where the Hermitage Stood on St. Herbert’s Island,
                  Derwent-Water’ (1800). The poem recounts how St Herbert (d. 687;
                     <title>DNB</title>) lived in seclusion, but prayed that he and his friend, St
                  Cuthbert (c. 634–687; <title>DNB</title>), should die at the same time – a prayer
                  that was granted. The name ‘Cuthbert’ indissolubly linked the new child to his
                  dead older brother, Herbert, as did his other name, ‘Charles’, the name of both
                  his godparents, Bedford and Wynn, who had also been Herbert’s godparents.</note>
               From most people I keep such feelings out of sight, as if I were ashamed of them, and
               for them it is reason enough that it is a good Saxon name, still in use in
               Northumberland and Durham, and neither so general as to be common, nor so strange as
               to have any appearance of affectation. </p><p rend="indent1"> He was born in the study, and when he opened his eyes, I would say,
               if wishes could influence the course of his life, what he was born to was before him.
               You will wonder how this should have happened. The high winds about Christmas gave an
               ugly shake to a high chimney which, if it were to receive such another <hi rend="ital">airquake</hi>, might probably make its way through the roof into our
               bedroom. The masons cannot pull it down and rebuild it while there is any chance of
               frost; they patched it as well as they could, but lest we should both be killed, or
               one of us frightened to death, it was necessary that we should shift our quarters,
               and as no other apartment in the house would afford the needful accommodation, my
               study was converted into <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my
                  lady’s</ref> chamber, and I have taken up my abode in what was
               formerly <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge’s</ref>, but now goes by the name of All Saints’ Room, in honour
               of my delectable folios.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The room had been
                  renamed in honour of Southey’s prized – and long wished-for – copy of the
                     <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643–1794), a huge, 53-volume compendium of
                  hagiographies that he had bought in 1817; no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The places which I am very desirous you should see in Switzerland are
               luckily of the easiest access, partly by water, partly by the carriages of the
               country. Protestant Switzerland has probably suffered less in the general dislocation
               of principles and morals than any other part of Europe; still, it has suffered much.
               This I learnt from some ministers in the Pays de Vaud.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Pays de Vaud was roughly equivalent to the modern Swiss
                  Canton of Vaud, north of Lake Geneva. The region is French-speaking and has been
                  mainly Protestant since the sixteenth century. Southey visited the area on 1–3
                  June 1817 and met a Minister of the local Protestant Church, whose name he thought
                  was Conobé, on 1–2 June; this encounter seems to be the source of Southey’s
                  information.</note> But the German cantons are likely to have escaped better than
               the French. </p><p rend="indent1"> I have heard of the <hi rend="ital">Peasant of Auburn</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Isabella Byron (1792–1860;
                     <title>DNB</title>), née Milbanke, wished Southey to draw public attention to
                  the work of the American loyalist and Anglican clergyman Thomas Coombe (1747–1822;
                     <title>DNB</title>). His <title>The Peasant of Auburn; or, The Emigrant: A
                     Poem</title> (1783) was an imitation of Oliver Goldsmith’s (1728?–1774;
                     <title>DNB</title>) <title>Deserted Village</title> (1770), and told a
                  cautionary tale about the perils of leaving an English village for a new life in
                  America. The poem was reissued by Longmans in 1819.</note> Lady Byron wrote to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my
               brother</ref> expressing a wish that I would introduce it to
               public notice. But as to all such purposes I am completely out of the world, and
               could as soon get a place in Parliament as in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> for
               any one whom I wished to serve. I believe the book is now at <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray’s</ref>, waiting till he sends me a parcel. </p><p rend="indent1"> My visit to London will take place at the end of April. By that time
               the last volume of <hi rend="ital">Brazil</hi> will be published,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and final volume of the <title>History
                     of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> and I will leave <hi rend="ital">Wesley</hi><note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life
                     of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note>
               unfinished rather than delay my journey to a less convenient season. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Mother</ref> and
                  daughters<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s daughters, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>.</note> desire their kindest
               remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady
                  Beaumont</ref>. Present mine also, and believe me, my dear Sir George, with the
               sincerest regard, your obliged friend, </p><closer><signed rend="indent7">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>