<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3536</idno><idno type="nines">rce4807</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3536. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn,
						8 October [1820] </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3536.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.
						.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3536" type="letter"><head>3536. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>,
						<date when="1820-10-08">8 October [1820] </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address:
						[deletion and readdress in another hand] CW Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Llangedwin/ near/
						Oswestry/ &lt;Welshpool&gt;<lb/> Stamped: [illegible]<lb/> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
						Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute rend="indent0">My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The Wiltshire Bennets bill<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Benett (1773–1852), MP for
						Wiltshire 1819–1832, MP for South Wiltshire 1832–1852. He had been one of the leading figures in supporting the
						Appointment of Special Constables Act (1820), which increased the powers of local Justices of the Peace to recruit
						special constables at times of civil disorder.</note> empowers the Magistrates when they apprehend a riot to swear
					in every man whom they think proper to call upon as a special constable. By this means many a man may be made to
					act against a mob who would otherwise be engaged in it, &amp; with common prudence a strong civil force may be
					collected whenever it is wanted. This which would at all times have been useful, appears to me of great importance
					now, when the military can no longer be trusted. </p><p rend="indent1"> If you succeed in founding a Keltic Professorship,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn
						had a central role in re-founding the Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion in June 1820, a society of London-based
						Welshmen interested in the history of Wales; Southey later became an honorary member of the Society. However, they
						did not succeed in founding a professorship in Celtic studies. </note> as I hope you may, do not commit the error
					of making the appointment for three or four years, which is the case with the Saxon Professorship,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Rawlinsonian Professorship of Anglo-Saxon at Pembroke College, Oxford, established
						in 1795.</note> &amp; makes the thing of no use. Your meetings &amp; societies are <del>x</del> useful, &amp; much
					to the honour of those who bring them into fashion. I hope you will make <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref> an honorary member, if it were only for his Vindication of
					the Bards.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sharon Turner’s <title>A Vindication of the Genuineness of the
							Ancient British Poems of Aneurin, Taliesin, Llywarch Hen, and Merdhin, with Specimens of the Poems
					</title>(1803), no. 2776 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Turner’s <title>History of the Anglo–Saxons</title>
						(1799–1805) also made use of Welsh sources to construct early British history, no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of
						Southey’s library. Turner was made a member of the Cymmrodorion, and
						later served on its council.</note> He deserves some special mark of honour as the first person who resorted to
					the Welsh remains for the purpose of elucidating our early history. The man who has extracted most from them, wild
					as he sometimes runs, is Davies of Olveston.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Davies (1756–1831;
							<title>DNB</title>), Curate of Olveston, Gloucestershire and author of <title>Celtic Researches, on the Origin,
							Traditions, &amp; Language, of the Ancient Britons</title> (1804) and <title>The Mythology and Rites of the
							British Druids</title> (1809), nos 796–797 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> My old acquaintance
						<ref type="m" target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen</ref> I perceive is metamorphosed into Owen Pugh,
					&amp; the Welsh critics extol his translation of the Paradise Lost into Welsh verse.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Owen added ‘Pughe’ to his name in 1806 when he inherited the Denbighshire estate of a
						distant relative. His <title>Coll Gwynfa</title> (1819) was a translation of John Milton (1608–1674;
							<title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667).</note> If it be a good translation, it is certainly a
					miraculous one, for of this I am perfectly sure that <ref type="m" target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William
						Owen</ref>, who was of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcotes</ref> four &amp;
					twenty elders, is as incapable of understanding the original as I am of understanding the translation.</p><p rend="indent1"> This detestable business of the Queen,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Under extreme
						pressure from George IV, the Cabinet had reluctantly agreed to introduce a Bill of Pains and Penalties into the
						House of Lords to deprive the King’s wife, Caroline of Brunswick (1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>), of the title of
						Queen, and to dissolve her marriage to the King. On the Third Reading of the Bill on 10 November 1820, the
						government majority was only nine votes and it seemed very unlikely the Bill could pass the House of Commons. Lord
						Liverpool, the Prime Minister, therefore announced the Bill would be withdrawn.</note> among other evils excludes
					foreign news from the newspapers, at a time when it is peculiarly interesting. The Spaniards proceed <hi rend="ital">more suo</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">‘In their own manner’.</note> slowly, but
					surely, in their revolutionary career.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">An army mutiny in Spain in January
						1820 led to the restoration of the Constitution of 1812 in March 1820, and the election of a Cortes.</note> I see
					they have abolished the <hi rend="ital">mayorazgos</hi>, – which I suppose may best be rendered entails; &amp;
					thereby cut the roots of their nobility.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Spain possessed a system whereby
						certain landed estates (often associated with titles of nobility) could not be divided or sold and had to be
						passed in their entirety to the landholder’s eldest son; it was abrogated by the Ley Desvinculadora (1820).</note>
					Such nobility, &amp; such dynasties as those in Sp. &amp; P. are not to be regretted for their own sakes; if we
					looked to their deserts we might say they have cumbered the earth too long. But they never could have received
					their death blow at a more inauspicious time. In Spain I expect, sooner or later, a civil war, &amp; of the most
					inveterate character. The peasantry will stand by the church, &amp; I very much doubt whether a majority of the
					soldiers will not take the same side; – on the other side, there will be authority, talents, activity &amp; the
					press; &amp; both parties will be enough in the right, to prosecute the war with conscientious virulence, &amp;
					think it their duty to exterminate each other. I do not think there will be any such struggle in Portugal: – but
					there may probably be a separation from Brazil, which will leave the country helpless.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A Liberal revolution in Portugal in August 1820 led to the election of a Cortes and demands for the
						monarchy to return from Brazil, where it had fled in 1807–1808. This process led to the separation of Portugal and
						Brazil in 1822, though Brazil did not become a republic, or split into separate states.</note> And if the
					revolution extends to Brazil, as may reasonably be apprehended, that country will be split into as many republics
					as there may be successful adventurers to place themselves at the head of a sufficient number of bandits to call
					themselves an army. – Look where we will, I see nothing but evil aspects. Yet I am less alarmed at the home
					prospect than those persons with whom I converse or correspond. I think that the length <del>of the</del> to which
					the business must be protracted, will tire that beast the people; – that the men of property who <del>do</del> are
					not actually aiming at a revolution, will be afraid of one &amp; bestir themselves in time; – that many persons who
					were at first deluded have been convinced that the Queen is guilty, as much by her conduct during the inquiry as by
					the evidence, &amp; perhaps more so; – &amp; if these considerations do not suffice to dispel any gloomy
					apprehensions – I fly to the good old saying God’s above, &amp; rest <del>upon them</del> there as in a strong
					hold. This I think certain that the license of the press will not continue much longer. For Government must
					restrain it; or be destroyed; &amp; in case <del>of its destr</del> the Press should triumph &amp; effect its
					object, we know that the first act of a Revolutionary Government will be to bind it in fetters of iron. I believe
					there will not be a free press in Europe twenty years hence.</p><p rend="indent1"> Barry Cornwall,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Bryan Procter (1787–1874;
							<title>DNB</title>), who wrote under the name ‘Barry Cornwall’. His <title>Dramatic Scenes and Other
							Poems</title> (1819), no. 617 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library (a presentation copy), won some
						admirers, and his play, <title>Mirandola</title>, was performed at Covent Garden in 1821.</note> whose name is
					Procter, breakfasted with me about a fortnight ago. I think there is more power &amp; more feeling in his poetry
					than you seem to allow. But his dramatic verse is feeble &amp; ill –constructed; &amp; how far he may be capable of
					constructing a drama remains to be proved. No opinion can be formed from such fragments as he has produced. He is a
					modest man, of infirm health, &amp; of a mind which seems to have gone thro much more wear &amp; tear of feeling,
					than of thought.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1820-10-08">Oct 8</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>