<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3318</idno><idno type="nines">rce4589</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3318. Robert Southey to Wade Browne, 15 June
                  1819</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3318.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 346–348 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3318" type="letter"><head>3318. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref>, <date when="1819-06-15">15 June
                  1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Wade Browne Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Ludlow<lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 346–348 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName></address><date when="1819-06-15">15 June. 1819</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> When you hear that my journey to the south must be postponed till the fall of the leaf, I fear you will think me infirm
               of purpose, &amp; as little to be depended on as the wind &amp; weather in this our mutable climate. The cause however lies rather in a
               good obstinate principle of perseverance, than in any fickleness of temper. This history,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  third and final volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> of which the hundredth sheet is now upon my desk,
               will confine me here so far into the summer (beyond all previous or possible calculation) that if I went into the South as soon as it
               is compleated, I should be under the necessity of shortening my stay there, &amp; leaving part of my business undone, in order to
               return in time for a long-standing engagement, which in the autumn will take me into the Highlands.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey visited Scotland, in the company of <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> and
                     <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Thomas Telford</ref>, from 17 August until 1 October 1819; see <title>Journal of
                     a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> – All things duly considered, it seemed best to put
               off my journey to London till November, by which time all my running accounts with the press will be settled.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> tho still with some remains of her
               complaint, is so much better that I look with much confidence to her compleat recovery. And <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>, who is now four months old, is beginning to serve me as well as his
                  sisters<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate Southey</ref>.</note> for a play thing. – The country is in its
               full beauty at this time, – perhaps in greater than I may ever again see it, for it is reported that the woods on Castlet are condemned
               to come down next year, this, if it be true, is the greatest loss that <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> could
               possibly sustain, &amp; in no place will the loss be more conspicuous than from the room wherein I am now writing.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">One of the views from Southey’s home was of Castlehead wood, which was part of the estates around
                  Derwentwater that were owned by the Greenwich Hospital. The Hospital was under increasing pressure to maximise its income from its
                  estate and some tree-felling was planned. However, Castlehead wood was saved from this process. The Hospital’s administrators had
                  also ordered the draining of some of their land next to Derwentwater, by lowering the level of the lake.</note> But this
               neighbourhood has suffered much from the axe since you were here. The woods about <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lodore">Lowdore</ref> are gone, so are those under Castle-crag, so is the little knot of fir trees on the way to Church, which were so
               placed as to make one of the features of the vale, &amp; worst of all, so is that beautiful birch grove on the side of the lake between
               Barrow &amp; <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lodore">Lowdore</ref>. Not a single sucker is springing up in its place, – &amp; indeed
               it would require a full century before another grove could be reared which would equal it in beauty. It is lucky that they cannot level
               the mountains, nor drain the lake, – but they are doing what they can to lower it, &amp; have succeeded so far as to render all the old
               landing-places useless. If the effect of this should be to drain the marshy land at the head &amp; foot of the lake, without
                  <del>laying as xx</del> leaving as much more swamp uncovered, it will do rather good than harm. The Island<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Island, which Peachy had purchased in 1796.</note> however will be deformed for a few years by the naked belt
               which is thus made around it.</p><p rend="indent1"> Two cases so extraordinary as to appear almost incredible occurred in the course of last month in this country. A child
               four years old wandered from its mother who was cutting peat among the Ennerdale mountains, &amp; after four days was found alive.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The story of the lost child, discovered ‘in a place called Clea Gill’ after ‘six days and five
                  nights of incessant hunger and exposure on these bleak mountains’, was widely reported, including in the <title>New Annual Register,
                     or General Repository of History, Politics, and Literature for the Year 1819</title> (London, 1820), p. 98. Southey probably
                  learned of the matter from a more detailed report in the <title>Westmorland Gazette</title>, 12 June 1819, headed ‘Miraculous
                  Incident’.</note> A man <del>among</del> &lt;upon&gt; the Eskdale fells was found after eighteen, still living, &amp; able to wave his
               hand as a signal, by which he was discovered. He had fallen in a fit, &amp; was incapable of moving when he recovered his senses;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">This incident does not seem to have found its way into newspaper reports.</note> – in both cases
               there was water close by, by which life was preserved. The child is doing well. Of the man I have heard nothing since the day after he
               was found, when <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> was in Eskdale &amp; learnt the story; at that
               time there seemed to be no apprehension that his life was in danger.</p><p rend="indent1"> I think you will be pleased with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> “Waggoner”, –
               if it were only for the line of road which it describes.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth’s <title>The Waggoner. A
                     Poem. To Which are Added Sonnets</title> (1819). The title poem describes the waggoner’s journey on the road from Grasmere to
                  Keswick.</note> The master of the Waggon was my poor Landlord<ref type="m" target="people.html#JacksonWilliam"> Jackson</ref>, – the
               cause of his exchanging it for the one-horse-carts was just as is represented in the poem; – nobody but Benjamin could manage it upon
               these hills, &amp; Benjamin could not resist the temptations by the way side.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey describes
                  the end of Wordsworth’s poem. It was summarised in the <title>Literary Gazette and Journal of Belles Lettres, Arts, Politics,
                     &amp;c.</title>, 125 (12 June 1819), 369, as: ‘at day-break the master of the waggon rides up from Keswick, and dismisses Ben
                  [the waggoner] for his loitering humanity, and degradation of his charge, by associating with tippling vagrants and vicious asses.
                  No one else can drive the horses, and the waggon is soon laid down for a substitute of one-horse carts’. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> In the course of July you will receive my ponderous volume,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The third volume of
                  Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819) ran to 950 pages.</note> – will it <del>be xx</del> suit your convenience
               that I should take Ludlow in my way up – toward the end of November; or two months afterwards on my way back? Whichever may suit you,
               will be equally convenient to me.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; her sisters<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> desire their kindest remembrances to you &amp; yours. Present mine
               also to the Ladies,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Browne’s wife <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">Elizabeth</ref>
                  and daughters (Lydia (c. 1789–1864); <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneElizabethdau">Elizabeth</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneSarah">Sarah</ref> from his first marriage; and Mary (dates unknown), from his second
               marriage).</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> &amp; believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>