<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3485</idno><idno type="nines">rce4756</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3485. Robert Southey to [Robert Gooch], 21 May 1820
                  </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3485.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS;
                  3p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3485" type="letter"><head>3485. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Robert Gooch</ref>], <date when="1820-05-21">21 May 1820
                  </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Watermark: KER 1818<lb/> MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS;
                  3p.<lb/> Unpublished. <lb/> Note on correspondent: Identified from the content, which refers to the recent death of Gooch’s
                  son.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1820-05-21">21 May. 1820</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0">My dear Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Ever since I heard of your affliction<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Times</title>, 9 May 1820, had
                  announced the death of Gooch’s son, Robert Knighton Gooch (1815–1820).</note> I have wished to write to you. Here, in the quietness
               of the country &amp; of a sabbath day, leisure &amp; opportunity are given me. And I may write to you now in a strain from which at any
               other time, I should have been withheld by the usages of the world &amp; the feelings which grow out of them.</p><p rend="indent1"> I had been married six years before I had a <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">child</ref>. At
               the age of twelve months that child, who had till then been as beautiful, &amp; in all respects as promising a creature as a parents
               heart could desire, was taken from me by the same dreadful &amp; hopeless disease<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret
                  Southey died of hydrocephalus in 1803.</note> which has bereaved you. Six years afterwards<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">1809.</note> I lost another <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">little girl</ref>, just when she was beginning to talk
               &amp; to run about: &amp; after another interval of seven years<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">1816.</note> a slow &amp;
               wasting malady deprived me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">my son</ref>, my only son at that time,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Cuthbert Southey had been born on 24 February 1819.</note><del>whom I had</del> – a boy too
               whose equal could hardly have been found, upon whom I had bestowed five years of careful instruction, &amp; whose attainments were as
               much the wonder of all who knew him, as his disposition &amp; manners &amp; genius <del>&amp; happy nature</del> were their delight. I
               had been his playfellow as well as his teacher: he was the constant companion of my walks. When absent from home I was never so
               chearfully employed as in writing to him, never so happily as when devising means for his present gratification or future advantage. My
               hopes were centered in him. I saw in him all that was good in myself. I thought it would be possible to prove in his person what might
               be done with the most promising nature <del>by</del> &lt;under&gt; the most favourable circumstances by the most diligent cultivation. The
               proudest &amp; dearest thought of my heart was that I should have a son to succeed me, who would take up the pursuits which I should
               leave unfinished, &amp; start from the point at which my career had ended: —a son who loved me with his whole heart &amp; soul &amp;
               strength, – as I loved him, <del>&amp;</del> &lt;for I&gt; almost lived in his existence. If any grief could have killed me it would have
               been this deprivation: &amp; had it not been for the sake of those whose well being depends upon my life, I should at that time
               earnestly have desired &amp; prayed for death.</p><p rend="indent1"> But in the freshness of that grief, as of those which preceded it, I felt the uses of affliction, &amp; by God’s
               blessing I continue to feel them. Gibbon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737–1794; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776–1788).</note> had loosened my belief in revealed
               religion, &amp; the contagious spirit of the age for a short time effaced it. Happily I retained a sense of natural <del>xxxxx of</del>
               piety which no sophistry could shake, &amp; very <del>xx</del> soon took refuge from <del>xxxx</del> infidelity in the creed of the
                  Socinians.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The doctrines of Fausto Sozzini (1539–1604); at this time another way of
                  describing Unitarianism.</note> In their loose belief I continued many years; &amp; perhaps I might never have <del>xxxx</del>
               perceived their error, nor have understood how much more than they teach is necessary for the heart &amp; soul of man, if God had not
               chastened me by these severe but merciful dispensations. I sought for consolation in religion, — &amp; more than consolation was given
               me: — strength &amp; hope &amp; assurance, —the peace which passeth all understanding,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Philippians</title> 4: 7.</note> &amp; that calm abiding happiness which nothing in this world can give or can take
               away.</p><p rend="indent1"> What the state of your mind may have been upon the most important of all subjects I know not. Perhaps you have been too
               much <hi rend="ital">in</hi> the world &amp; <hi rend="ital">of</hi> it, to think seriously of that which is to come. Perhaps you have
               not wholly escaped (for who can?) from those “sturdy doubts &amp; boisterous objections” which Sir Thomas Brown tells us he used to
               “conquer, not in a martial position, but upon his knees.”<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Browne (1605–1682;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Religio Medici</title> (London, 1643), p. 45. Southey’s copy, undated, was no. 1960 in the sale
                  catalogue of his library. This was a particularly apt quotation, as Browne, like Gooch, was a doctor who was closely associated with
                  Norfolk – Browne lived in Norwich from 1637 and Gooch was from Great Yarmouth.</note> Be that as it may, this letter cannot come
               unseasonably to you <del>xx</del> at a time <del>xx</del> when you must inevitably feel the unspeakable value of a firm &amp; lively
               faith.</p><p rend="indent1"> Among the many evils which are done by canting &amp; trading professors of religion, it is not the least that they make
               us keep our best &amp; wisest &amp; holiest feelings to ourselves, lest we should be thought to resemble them. Under an apprehension of
               this kind I have sometimes been silent, when my heart would have led me to speak, &amp; when perhaps the hearts of others have been
               open. I could hardly <del>xx</del> <hi rend="ital">say</hi> to you what I have here written. Philosophy may teach us to bear affliction
               bravely, —but religion converts afflictions into blessings. When we attain the middle stage of life years pass away more rapidly then
               weeks in youth. The separations which death makes are only for a season, &amp; it is no light benefit that they bind our feelings to
               our faith; — that they make us regard the termination of our mortal existence, not with distrust &amp; unwillingness, but with hope
               &amp; with desire. This is my state of mind, &amp; I am thankful for the afflictions which have brought me to it. May yours be blest
               &amp; sanctified as mine have been.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">Yrs faithfully</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>