<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author>
				<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>David Rettenmaier</name>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3386</idno>
				<idno type="nines">rce4657</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner
						without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor
						and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent
						from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address></p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from
								Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list></p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is
						not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most
						current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a
						link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title type="main" level="a">3386. Robert Southey to John Murray, 10 November 1819</title>
						<author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
						<title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date>
							<biblScope type="URL"
								>http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3386.html</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
				<p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 4p. . Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of
					Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 203–205.</p>
				<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in
						brackets.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
						decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="g">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
					<category xml:id="people">
						<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
					<category xml:id="places">
						<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
				<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
				<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list>
					<item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item>
				</list></change>
			<change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list>
					<item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item>
				</list></change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div n="3386" type="letter">
				<head>3386. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date
						when="1819-11-10">10 November 1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John
						Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London.<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 18 NO 18/
						1819<lb/> Seal: red wax, design illegible<lb/> Endorsement: 1819 Nov 10/ Southey, R <lb/> MS: National Library of
						Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
							Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 203–205.</note></head>
				<opener><dateline><address>
							<placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
						</address><date when="1819-11-10"> 10 Nov. 1819</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear
					Sir</salute></opener>
				<p rend="indent1"> I would do what you desire if it were possible. But when I wrote to <ref type="m"
						target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gifford</ref> immediately on my return
						<del>xxxxxx</del> from Scotland, I then declined writing upon this subject,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"
						>Southey had been asked to write ‘an article upon the state of the country’; see Southey to William Gifford, 3
						October 1819, Letter 3355.</note> because it <del>then</del> appeared to me too late to undertake it for the next
					number, writing as I do, slowly, in every thing but narration. You talk of a week; – it would be the principal
					business of a month, work as diligently as I could.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly
							Review</title>, 22 (July 1819) appeared on 11 December 1819.</note> That I am not an unconcerned looker-on in
					these portentous times you may well suppose; &amp; if preventive means had been used when first I pointed out the
					coming danger in the Q.R. much of the existing evil might have been easily averted.<note n="3" place="foot"
						resp="editors">Southey’s ‘Inquiry into the Poor Laws’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812),
						319–356.</note> All that you say of the advantages afforded by publishing in such a journal as yours is true,
					&amp; you may remember that I yielded to those same arguments three years ago, &amp; cast into the shape which you
					advised what would otherwise have been brought forward in a more regular &amp; extended form.<note n="4"
						place="foot" resp="editors">Southey, at Murray’s urging, had abandoned his plans to write a book on the ‘State of
						the Nation’ and had instead published his thoughts on ‘Parliamentary Reform’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16
						(October 1816), 225–278, and the ‘Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16
						(January 1817), 511–552.</note> The immediate object was obtained, – but I believe it was at the expence of a
					greater good. A review is laid upon the shelf sooner than a substantive volume, &amp; is not so likely to be taken
					from it. And I am inclined to think that if I had brought forward my views of the state of society &amp; its
					impending dangers in a connected shape, – &amp; with that perfect freedom which I should have felt when publishing
					in my own name, – there would have been a regular set of opinions before the public, to which the well disposed
					might have been contented to appeal as their articles of political belief.</p>
				<p rend="indent1"> The advantages of writing anonymously are imaginary <del>in my case</del> as far as I am
					concerned. <del>A</del> I <del>enjoy</del> &lt;have&gt; already as large a portion of critical &amp; Jacobinical
					abuse as can possibly be bestowed upon me. Whoever hates the government &amp; the religion of his country, whoever
					has renounced his Saviour &amp; would dethrone his King, regards me <del>as his</del> with a deadly hatred. If I
						<del>regarded</del> &lt;cared for&gt; this <del>with</del> (which I do not) I am not in the slightest degree
					protected from it by writing in the Review; <del>but on the contrary</del> I am just as much exposed – &amp;
						<del>am less able to d</del> which is a real evil, I am exposed to disadvantage which I should not be, if standing
					alone. For in the first place, I cannot speak out, as I would do, tho by so doing I should serve the Government
					with far greater effect. This passage must be softened, &amp; that must be expunged, – till sometimes a paragraph
					appears so mutilated in argument &amp; so emasculated in style, that I scarcely recognize my own writing &amp;
					should be unable to defend it. <del>And perhaps in the next number there appears an article there expressly written
						for the purpose of contradicting what I had advanced</del> – I am in the situation of a man brought into the lists
						<del>to</del> as a Champion, if those persons for whom he fights were <del>to every now &amp; then</del> to insist
					upon his laying aside his own weapons which he has been accustomed to wield &amp; on which he can depend; &amp;
					were moreover every now &amp; then to catch him by the arm when he is about to strike, for the purpose of giving
					the blow a different direction, or adding <del>force</del> &lt;strength&gt; to it, whereas the effect of such
					interference is effectually to frustrate <del>the</del> &lt;his&gt; aim &amp; <del>destroy xx its force</del> take
					away this force. </p>
				<p rend="indent1"> You are not aware how much my articles have suffered by this sort of mutilation, – to say nothing
					of what they lose by being written under a sense of restraint.</p>
				<p rend="indent1"> On the whole then I am not displeased that there should be so unanswerable a reason as the
					shortness of time, for not writing a political <del>arti</del> paper just now. Sometime or other I shall find an
					opportunity of treating upon the Prospects of Society when I can do it in my own way, &amp; to my own
						satisfaction.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the
							Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note></p>
				<p rend="indent1"> You are an excellent purveyor, – a quality in which <ref type="m"
						target="people.html#LongmanThomas">my good friends in the Row</ref> are sadly deficient. I am making myself master
					(as far as I can) of the history of this reign;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The reign of George III
						(1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>); Southey did not write a book on this
						subject.</note> – part of my reading every day is &amp; long has been given to this subject. But whether it be for
					your interest &amp; mine that the result of this reading, should be compressed into your review, instead of
					appearing as a separate work, which would have <del>ever</del> good probability of becoming a standard book,
						<del>if</del> is what you &amp; I must confer about. The West Indies I have a motive for delaying – which is this.
					My brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Capt S.</ref> has been for many years making a
					Chronological Hist. of the W Indies, which he will ere long endeavour to publish by subscription. And if he
					succeeds in bringing it out, – I shall be able to give him a hearty shove by making a very amusing article.<note
						n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey’s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).
						Southey puffed it in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 38 (July 1828), 193–241. </note> He has taken a great
					deal of pains with this, – &amp; it will be a good book of its kind. The French have many histories of this kind, –
					they are more for reference than reading, – but he who refers to them, often goes on reading, – &amp; this will be
					very much the c[MS missing] with his. I shall revise it for him, &amp; write certain connecting parts.</p>
				<p rend="indent1"> The Account of Q Anns Churches<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Commission for Building
						Fifty New Churches was set up by the New Churches in London and Westminster Act (1710), passed during the reign of
						Anne (1665–1714; Queen of Great Britain 1701–1714; <title>DNB</title>). It is not clear which ‘Account’ of its
						activities Southey requested. He needed this, and related publications, for what became his article on ‘New
						Churches’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549–591.</note> will certainly be desirable. You have
					sent me Yates’s Basis of National Welfare, – but there is a former work of his which I ought to have – “The Church
					in Danger.”<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Yates (1769–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Basis
							of National Welfare: Considered in Reference Chiefly to the Prosperity of Britain, and Safety of the Church of
							England</title> (1817), and <title>The Church in Danger: a Statement of the Cause, and of the Probable Means of
							Averting that Danger, Attempted in a Letter to the Earl of Liverpool</title> (1815).</note></p>
				<closer><salute rend="indent2"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent3"> Yrs very
						truly</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
