<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3626</idno><idno type="nines">rce4897</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3626. Robert Southey to James
                  Everett, 7 February 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3626.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus
                  Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3626" type="letter"><head>3626. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#EverettJames">James
                  Everett</ref>,<date when="1821-02-07"> 7 February 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> James Everett/ West Street/ Sheffield/ Paid<lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Seal: red wax<lb/> Watermark: HAGAR &amp; CO/ 1820<lb/>
                  MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus
                  Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
                  Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1821-02-07">7 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1821</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0">Dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I was much gratified by receiving your letter of Dec. 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. It has heightened the respect with which the liberal &amp; Christian
               spirit of your controversial letter had made me regard its author. In wishing to
               withhold that paper from the press, &amp; in declining to appear against me as the
               Champion of a Connection<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. Methodists,
                  many of whom had been offended by Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the
                     Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> which thinks proper to
               treat me as an enemy rather than a friend, you have evinced a generous feeling such
               as few men would have displayed.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1817
                  Southey had contributed a sketch of the life of John Wesley (1703–1791;
                     <title>DNB</title>) to <title>The Correspondent; Consisting of Letters, Moral,
                     Political, and Literary, between Eminent Writers in France and England; and
                     designed by presenting to each Nation a Faithful Picture of the Other, to
                     Enlighten both to their True Interests, promote a Mutual Good Understanding
                     between them, and render Peace the Source of a Common Prosperity</title>, 1–2
                  (1817), 26–48, 157–176. This attracted some attention from Methodists. Everett
                  replied to it in the <title>Methodist Magazine</title>, n.s. 15 (April–June 1818),
                  260–280, 340–353, 419–434 – the ‘controversial letter’, a pre-publication copy of
                  which Everett sent Southey. In turn, Southey informed Everett of his plans for a
                  full-scale life of Wesley. On learning this, Everett tried unsuccessfully to
                  withdraw his article from the <title>Methodist Magazine</title>. In 1820 Southey
                  sent a copy of his <title>Life of Wesley</title> to Everett, and the latter wrote
                  to thank him, explaining that he had been asked, but refused, to write a
                  refutation of Southey’s biography. See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 11
                  December 1820, Letter 3581. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> Among the many circumstances which have prevented me from expressing
               to you my sense of this generosity as soon as I wished &amp; ought to have done,
               there is one in which you will take some interest. About the time that your letter
               reached me, I received from a most respectable quarter, a communication affecting
                  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wesleys moral &amp; religious character more seriously than
               any direct charge which was ever brought against him by his enemies &amp;
                  calummiators.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had received his
                  information from John Banks Jenkinson (1781–1840; <title>DNB</title>), Dean of
                  Worcester, 1817–1825. </note> It is a fragment given by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               Wesley to <del>one of her</del> &lt;a female&gt; friend<del>s</del> as part of one of those
               letters which she took from her husbands bureau when she finally left him.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Wesley (1709/10–1781). She was a widow at the
                  time of her marriage to John Wesley (1703–1791; <title>DNB</title>) in 1751. The
                  relationship was troubled, and on 23 January 1771 Mary left her husband, taking
                  with her some of his correspondence. </note> This fragment she produced as having
               been written by Miss Briggs, whose name appears among M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wesley’s
                  correspondents.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Briggs
                  (1751–1822), whose family were devout Methodists and close friends of John
                  Wesley.</note> It is written in a most empassioned strain of personal affection,
               &amp; spiritual reverence, remonstrating with him upon the liberties which he had
               taken with her, in language that at the same time confesses a boundless love, &amp;
               expresses the alarm &amp; indignation of a mind which still retained its virtuous
               principles. In a word, it is such a letter as such a woman would have written to
               James Wheatley.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">James Wheatley (d. 1775),
                  a cobbler turned lay preacher. He was a Methodist itinerant from 1742 and served
                  as John Wesley’s lay assistant 1745–1747. He was expelled from the movement by
                  Wesley in 1751, following allegations of sexual misconduct; see <title>The Life of
                     Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820),
                  II, pp. 312–314.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> This communication was accompanied with a reference to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonGloster">gentleman</ref> from
               whom the copy originally came, &amp; to whose mother M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wesley
               herself had given it. Of its authenticity I was assured there could be no doubt,
               &amp; I was left at full liberty to make such use of it as I might think proper &amp;
               necessary, after satisfying myself concerning the source from which it came.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wrote accordingly to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonGloster">Gentleman</ref> in whose
               possession the original was said to be.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to [Glocester Wilson], 29 December 1820, Letter 3596.</note> He
               confirmed the statement in all its parts; tho it appears that what he possesses is
               not the original letter, but a copy of it given by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wesley to
               his mother. He is perfectly convinced that the letter is genuine, &amp; he tells me
               that having once shown it to a person who had known Miss Briggs, that person
               pronounced it to be such a letter as she was very likely to have written.</p><p rend="indent1"> And now my dear Sir, you will be anxious to know what my own thoughts
               upon this subject are, &amp; how I am disposed to act. I cannot tell you whether I
               was more grieved or surprized at the communication. From the letter itself I
               concluded it genuine; it has the true stamp of passion: very few persons would be
               capable of writing it, unless under the influence of the feelings which it so
               strongly &amp; naturally expresses. At the same time I felt the strongest reluctance
               to publish a fact which would fix so foul a stain upon the character of one to whose
               errors (as I conceive them to be) I am not blind, but for whose virtues I have as
               much veneration as can possibly be felt by the most devoted of his disciples. On the
               other hand, in the relation wherein I stand as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wesleys
               biographer, the suppression of such a fact would expose me to charges, against which
               I know not what defence could be opposed. For that the letter will get abroad sooner
               or later there can be no doubt; &amp; it is of main importance that the real
               character of such a man should be searched &amp; understood.</p><p rend="indent1"> Had the original letter been in existence I would have spared neither
               cost nor pains to ascertain whether it was the writing of Miss Briggs; &amp; had that
               full evidence been obtained, I must have made the fact public. It happens however,
               that no such proof is possible: &amp; on an inferior degree of proof I may reasonably
               demur where any character, &amp; especially such a one as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               Wesley’s is at stake. Another consideration also weighs with me. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonGloster">Gentleman</ref> who vouches
               for the authenticity of the letter repeats on his mothers authority some things said
               by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wesley concerning her husband which very much weaken the
               opinion that otherwise I should certainly have entertained. She said that she
               considered her life in danger from him. Now I think a woman who could say this of
                  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wesley would not scruple at forging a letter for the
               purpose of blasting his reputation. These considerations incline me to let the matter
               rest till another edition of my work may be called for. By that time more
               circumstances may possibly come to light, &amp; enable me to form an opinion with
               less hesitation than I now feel. At present I suspect the charge is false: but then I
               wish to find it so, &amp; therefore must in some degree distrust my own judgement
               more than I should otherwise do.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have not yet seen M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Watsons book.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Watson (1781–1833; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Observations on Southey’s ‘Life of Wesley’: Being a Defence of the
                     Character, Labour, and Opinions, of Mr Wesley Against the Misrepresentations of
                     that Publication</title> (1820).</note> There is an account of it in the last
               Evangelical Magazine written in a spirit every way worthy of that journal.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Watson and other publications in response to
                  Southey’s controversial biography were noticed in the <title>Evangelical Magazine
                     and Missionary Chronicle</title>, 29 (February 1821), 65–68. This praised
                  Watson for exposing Southey’s ignorance (67) and concluded: ‘Mr. Southey … writes
                  like “a man of the world,” to please the world: and he will have his reward – “the
                  world will love its own.” But the great question is – Will God be pleased? Will
                  the writer receive the plaudit of the great Judge at the last day? Will he say to
                  the author of this work – “Well done! good and faithful servant?” The conscience
                  of the writer and the judgment of the reader will answer the question’
                  (68).</note> To me it of no consequence in what temper an antagonist may chuse to
               treat me. I have long been used to ill-treatment, &amp; no person can possibly regard
               it less. Contumely &amp; misrepresentation will never provoke an answer from me, much
               less a return. But courtesy, &amp; fair dealing &amp; that generous spirit which
               renders justice to the motives of an opponent, &amp; allows to others the freedom
               that it claims for itself, will always command my attention &amp; respect. Therefore
               it is, dear Sir, that I subscribe myself</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Yours with sincere esteem</salute><signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>