<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3602</idno><idno type="nines">rce4873</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3602. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 8 January 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3602.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 202. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood
						Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
						224–227.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3602" type="letter"><head>3602. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>,<date when="1821-01-08"> 8 January 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The
						Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey.<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: 10 o’Clock/ JA.11/ 1821 F.Nn;
						E/ 11 JA 11/ 1821<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 202. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John Wood
						Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
						224–227.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1821-01-08"> 8 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1821</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> The death of poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> has given me, &amp;
					indeed my whole household a severe shock, for he had been with us so much that he seemed almost like one of the
					family. It is little more than five years since I became acquainted with him, &amp; we had spent more than twelve
					months of that time together, at home &amp; abroad. And the more we knew of him the better we loved him, – he was
					so sensible of any kindness, so thoroughly amiable, &amp; bore his cross so meekly.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Nash was a hunchback.</note> With regard to himself his
					removal to a better state is not to be regretted: but notwithstanding this consideration, I fear it will be some
					time before my spirits recover from the shock they have sustained. At my time of life new friendships are rarely
					formed, &amp; the man of middle age who is richest in friends, can ill afford to lose one of them.</p><p rend="indent1"> Had it not been for this event I should have given you a chearful account of our goings on. The
					weather has been much less severe here than in the south. I went on Tuesday to bring <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> home from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth’s</ref>, &amp; returned on Thursday, &amp; nothing could be
					pleasanter than the weather, – it quite reconciled one to an English January.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> takes his rides on Sunday
					because his shop is shut on that day, &amp; he comes at an unlawful hour to suit his own dinner time. If you had
					seen him he would have told you that the hexameters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A
							Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> are finished &amp; have past thro his hands on their way to the press.
					I am now busy upon the Preface, in which I have taken occasion immediately to repay some of my obligations to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> by a few comments on D Juan.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’, pp. xvii–xxii, where Southey
						denounced ‘the Satanic school’ of poetry without naming any one poet. This was a response to the first two Cantos
						of Byron’s <title>Don Juan</title> (1819), which had been published by Murray. The coruscating and hilarious
						‘Dedication’, which attacked Southey and others, had been suppressed (and was not published until 1833), but
						Southey knew of its existence.</note> The Odes which I wrote ex officio in Dec. 1819 &amp; Dec. 1820<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Warning Voice. Ode I’ and ‘The Warning Voice. Ode II’, the New Year’s Odes for
						1820 and 1821, were not published until they appeared in <title>The Englishman’s Library: Comprising a Series of
							Historical, Biographical and National Information</title> (London, 1824), pp. 381–389. They were not published
						with <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> will be added partly for the sake of adding twenty pages
					to a thin book, &amp; still more because they will be well-timed, &amp; are in their way, <hi rend="ital">me
						judice</hi><note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘in my judgement’.</note> the one very respectable, the other
					of a higher order. I entitle them the Warning Voice.</p><p rend="indent1"> I received the four first proofs of the Peninsular War<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832). The printer was Thomas Davison
						(1766–1831).</note> on Christmas day, &amp; the printer has in his hands copy enough for a dozen more. </p><p rend="indent1"> There is nothing of mine in the Q.R.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly
							Review</title>, 24 (October 1820), published 19 December 1820.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> having prorogued my account of the Sinner Saved till the next
						number.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of <title>The Works of the Reverend William
							Huntington, S. S. Minister of the Gospel, at Providence Chapel, Gray’s Inn Lane, Completed to the Close of the
							Year 1806</title> (1811) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 462–510, published 6
						April 1821.</note> The N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. has not reached me yet.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> received from me the
					information of Sir C Wolseleys reference to him, &amp; sent me his answer that I might transmit it to the
						Courier.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles Wolseley, 7th Baronet (1769–1846; <title>DNB</title>),
						radical politician. A public meeting in Birmingham on 12 July 1819 elected him ‘legislatorial attorney and
						representative’ for the town, and in April 1820 he was sentenced to eighteen months imprisonment for sedition and
						conspiracy for a speech he had given at Stockport on 28 June 1819. He had written from prison to the government,
						offering to go to Italy and collect information concerning Queen Caroline (1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>), who was
						facing a Bill of Pains and Penalties that would have dissolved her marriage to George IV on the grounds of her
						adultery. Not receiving a reply, Wolseley had published the letter in <title>The Times</title>, 11 October 1820,
						noting his acquaintance with Caroline when she lived at Como in 1817 and stating he could obtain information ‘that
						no Englishman but myself and a Mr. Walter Landon, who is now in Italy, can have the opportunity of knowing’.
						Southey saw the letter and transcribed it for Landor; see Southey to Landor, 29 October 1820, Letter 3547. Landor
						responded by sending a letter to <title>The Times</title>. He also asked Southey to get the same letter into the
							<title>Courier</title>; John Forster, <title>Walter Savage Landor. A Biography</title>, 2 vols (London, 1869), I,
						pp. 466–467. <title>The Times</title> published Landor’s letter on 4 December 1820; in it he insisted, ‘whatever I
						may have heard relating to the Queen, I know nothing positive, and never made a single inquiry that either could
						inculpate or acquit her in the cause now pending’.</note> This I did not think proper to do, because if I could
					have seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">L.</ref> or written to him in time, he would have
					altered the temper of his letter. Parr no doubt sent it to the Times.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor
						had sent a copy of his letter to <title>The Times</title> to his friend and mentor Samuel Parr (1747–1825;
							<title>DNB</title>), clergyman, schoolmaster, writer, Whig and supporter of Queen Caroline.</note> But it is
					worth knowing because it is a specimen of <hi rend="ital">radical</hi> veracity, that in his conversation
					concerning their neighbour the Princess at Como, Wolseley never attempted to deny the notorious fact of her
					whoredom, but used to justify <del>xxxx xx</del> it! – I knew Robert Wolseley<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Wolseley (1770–1815), former lawyer and army officer, who became a clergyman in 1813. He had
						overlapped at Westminster School with Southey and spent some time in the Lake District in 1808–1809.</note> his
					brother, who at different times spent about 18 months here, – he was a very good man, of melancholy temperament,
					who having been bred to the law, &amp; afterward in the militia, at the age of three or four &amp; forty had a
					fancy for studying Hebrew, took orders, &amp; preached himself into a consumption. The family principles were
						Oliverian,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles Wolseley’s ancestor, Sir Charles Wolseley, 2nd
						Baronet (c. 1630–1714; <title>DNB</title>), had been a prominent supporter of Oliver Cromwell (1599–1658; Lord
						Protector 1653–1658; <title>DNB</title>), serving on his Council of State.</note> modified in Robert into
					Whiggery.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt Mary</ref> bears the winter well. Old age
					nev[MS obscured] wore a <del>xxx</del> happier appearance in woman than it does in her, &amp; every b[MS obscured]
					this. It is delightful to see the enjoyment she has in amusing <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>, &amp; letting him do with her whatever he pleases.
					That <del>xx</del> drawing which you have seen, is as excellent a likeness as ever was taken.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a drawing by Edward Nash.</note> Thank God he continues to thrive, &amp; is
					as happy &amp; as good-humoured as he can be.</p><p rend="indent1"> The difference of grammars at Westminster is not so great a disadvantage as you seem to
						apprehend.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Latin grammar was the central course of instruction at
						Westminster School, which used its own textbooks; for example, <title>The Construction of the Latin Verse-Grammar.
							For the Use of the Lower Forms in Westminster School</title> (1774). Herbert Hill was concerned, as his son,
						Edward Hill, was about to enter Westminster School.</note> – My love to the boys, not forgetting <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillAlfred">Alfred</ref> &amp; the two younger ones. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> was here last month, wearing wonderfully
					well.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> would send the reprint of the
						Carmina to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctors</ref> for you. the postscript to the
						Notes is an excerpt from my half finished letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">A combined second edition of <title>Carmen
								Triumphale</title> (1814) and <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness the Prince Regent, His
								Imperial Majesty the Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814), published as
								<title>Carmen Triumphale, for the Commencement of the Year 1814: Carmen Aulica. Written in 1814, on the Arrival
								of the Allied Sovereigns in England</title> (1821); ‘Postscript’, pp. 45–53, is part of a letter Southey drafted
							to Brougham following reports of the latter’s attack on him at the hustings for the Westmorland election on 30
							June 1818.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>