<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3771</idno><idno type="nines">rce5042</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3771. Robert Southey to John May,
                  26 December 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3771.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Beinecke
                  Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14145. ALS; 4p.
               .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3771" type="letter"><head>3771. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,
                  <date when="1821-12-26">26 December 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 224 1821/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 26<hi rend="sup">th </hi>December/
                     rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.
                  1822/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April<lb/> MS: Beinecke
                  Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14145. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1821-12-26">26. Dec. 1821</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I return you the Power of Attorney<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had lent May his entire savings of £625 in government
                  stocks to help May out of his financial difficulties.</note> without delay. Right
               glad should I be if it were for a sum equal to the whole pressure upon you at this
               time, – but it has not been my fortune to have means commensurate with my will. – If
               however I receive payment (as I expect) for my first volume<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular
                     War</title> (1823–1832).</note> in the spring, I shall be able to transfer it
               into your hands. The bargain made nine years ago was a thousand guineas for the work
               in two volumes;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Herbert
                  Hill, 18 July 1813, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part
                     Four</title>, Letter 2283.</note> – it will now be in three, – &amp; if I am
               not paid in proportion to the increased extent of the book, I shall think myself ill
               treated. But whatever I receive you shall have.</p><p rend="indent1"> William Young<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified
                  beyond the information given here.</note> whom you mention, I suppose to be a
               little, good natured, vulgarish, bustling man who married a sister of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Arthur,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note>
               &amp; was when I was last in Lisbon,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e.
                  in June 1801.</note> the greatest smuggler there. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has not
               detailed the circumstances to me, nor am I desirous of learning any thing concerning
               it, except so far as it may palliate the apparently great imprudence of your
                  brother.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Henry May (1785–1849),
                  May’s younger brother and business partner in Brazil.</note> – Your last report is
               certainly favourable. The Revolution<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                  army revolt in Porto in August 1820 led to the election of a Cortes in December
                  1820 and demands that the monarchy return from Brazil, where it had fled in
                  1807–1808 following the French invasion. John VI (1767–1826; King of Portugal
                  1816–1826) arrived back in Lisbon on 3 July 1821 and eventually agreed to a new
                  liberal Constitution in October 1822. John VI appointed his son, Pedro (1798–1834;
                  Emperor of Brazil 1822–1831), as Regent in Brazil, and Pedro summoned an elected
                  advisory council to represent the different Brazilian provinces. These events
                  eventually led to the separation of Portugal and Brazil on 7 September 1822, but
                  Brazil did not become a republic or disintegrate.</note> has not had time &lt;yet&gt; to
               destroy that national honour on which you rely, &amp; which I estimate in the
               Portugueze as highly you do. I have therefore good hope that these bills will be duly
               paid.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, thank God, is
               so much better than when I wrote to you concerning her, that she appears hardly like
               the same person. She was at that time <del>so much depress on</del> in such a state,
               that I was under serious apprehensions of its terminating in <hi rend="ital">mania</hi>. You may judge therefore under what a weight I wrote &amp; how great
               must be the relief which I now feel.</p><p rend="indent1"> When I have expanded the life of Cromwell, &amp; stated facts as well
               as conclusions, I am well persuaded there will not remain any differences of
               sentiment between you &amp; me concerning the history of that disastrous age.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s assessment of the life of Oliver
                  Cromwell (1599–1658; Lord Protector 1653–1658; <title>DNB</title>) had appeared in
                  the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 25 (July 1821), 279–347. He was hoping to
                  expand it into a separate work as he had previously done with his <title>Life of
                     Nelson</title> (1813), which started as an article in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218–262. This did not happen.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has made me a paltry
               offer for the work, &amp; announced it<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">These advertisements seem to have appeared slightly later than Southey
                  suggests, for example, ‘A Life of Oliver Cromwell. By Mr. Southey’,
                     <title>Gentleman’s Magazine</title>, 92 (February 1822), 157.</note> without
               waiting for my answer, or asking my approbation. I did not intend that it should be
               announced for a considerable time. And tho, no doubt he will ultimately have the work
               it must be upon very different terms indeed from those which he has proposed.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> whom I
               saw yesterday, told me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref>
               charge of slander. I have already answered it, except that the introductory paragraph
               of my answer cannot be written till I <hi rend="ital">see</hi> the attack.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In the ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two
                     Foscari’,<title> Sardanapalus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A
                     Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: ‘I am not ignorant
                  of Mr. Southey’s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which
                  he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others’. Southey
                  had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May–August 1817. Byron believed
                  that Southey had subsequently spread rumours that Byron and Shelley engaged in a
                  ‘League of Incest’ during their residence in Switzerland in 1816.</note> My reply
               will be sent to the Courier, in the form of a letter to the Editor.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to the Editor of the
                     <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822. The letter appeared in the
                     <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">His Lordship</ref> will not like it.
                  <del>Xxxxxxx when I</del> knowing the substance of his charge, &amp;
                  <del>xxx</del> not &lt;having&gt; seen the form &amp; manner of it, I have had the great
               advantage of writing without any feeling of irritation. – It is well for those who
               assail me that both from principle &amp; disposition I detest controversial &lt;writing&gt;
               for there is nothing which I compose with so much readiness, nor with such a sense of
               compleat power.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember us to your fireside circle, – &amp; may you &amp; yours
               partake many &amp; happy returns of this festive season. – You know the Long
               Parliament ordered Xmas day to be kept as a <hi rend="ital">fast</hi>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">During the civil war many Puritans were hostile
                  to Christmas as a ‘pagan’ celebration. The date 25 December 1644 coincided with
                  the regular monthly fast on which Parliamentarians and their supporters prayed for
                  the success of their cause, and the <title>Directory for the Public Worship of
                     God</title> (1645), which replaced the Church of England’s <title>Book of
                     Common Prayer</title>, made no mention of Christmas at all. The public
                  celebration of Christmas became an offence in 1647.</note> I think we shall agree
               in sentiment upon that ordinance.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear friend</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>