<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3656</idno><idno type="nines">rce4927</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3656. Robert Southey to John May, 20 March 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3656.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus
                  Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 24–31 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3656" type="letter"><head>3656. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1821-03-20">20 March 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus
                  Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 24–31 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1821-03-20">March 20. 1821</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> The popular Saint of the Democratic Cantons in Switzerland, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Nicholas de Flue,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas of Flue (1417–1487). In middle age he left his wife and children and became a hermit and
                  ascetic. He was beatified in 1669, but not canonised until 1947. He was a native of Unterwalden, one of the original ‘forest
                  cantons’ of the Swiss Confederation, with a tradition of direct democracy.</note> remembered his own birth, knew his mother &amp;
               the midwife as soon as he was born, &amp; never forgot the way by which he was taken to be christened, nor the faces of the persons who
               were present at that ceremony. But he was an extraordinary child, who tho he neither danced, nor sung, nor preached before he was born
               (which certain other Saints are said to have done) had revelations in that state, &amp; saw the light of heaven, before he came into
               the light of day. It has pleased &lt;the metaphysico-critico-<del>xxxxxxxx</del>-politico-patriotico-phoolo-philosopher,&gt; Jeremy Bentham
               to designate me &lt;in one of his opaque works&gt; by the title of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey, for which I humbly thank his
               Jeremy-Benthamship, &amp; have in part requited him.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeremy Bentham (1748–1832;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Church-of-Englandism and its Catechism Examined</title> (London, 1818), p. 26. Southey had responded
                  in his review of <title>The Works of the Reverend William Huntington, S. S. Minister of the Gospel, at Providence Chapel, Gray’s Inn
                     Lane, Completed to the Close of the Year 1806</title> (1811) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 462–510,
                  published 6 April 1821, by bracketing Bentham with a number of others as an example of a famous contemporary ‘quack’ (510). </note>
               It would be very convenient if I had the same claim to this honour on the score of miraculous memory as the said Nicholas, to whom I
               paid my respects in his own church at Saxeln.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had visited the church dedicated to St
                  Nicholas at Saxeln (Sachseln) on 10 July 1817 during his continental tour. </note> But the twilight of my recollections does not
               begin till the third year of my age.</p><p rend="indent1"> However tho I did not, like him, know the Midwife at the time when she had most to do with me, I knew her afterwards,
               for she brought all my brothers &amp; sisters into the world. She was the wife of a superannuated Baptist Preacher, who <del>made her a
                  wretched husband</del> as was formerly common with Baptist Preachers kept a shop, dealing in medicines &amp; quackery among other
                  things.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &lt;Preachers of this grade have probably entirely disappeared, for
               even the Methodists will not allow their ministers to engage in any kind of business. They were stiff Oliverians<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Admirers of Oliver Cromwell (1599–1658; Lord Protector 1653–1658; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in their
               politics.&gt; He was always at his studies, which were probably old puritanical divinity, &amp; I well remember hearing him spoken of as a
               miserable morose tyrant. The only son of this poor woman lost his life by a singularly dismal accident, after he was grown up, &amp;
               doing well in the world.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly George Armstrong (d. 1799). The drawbridge crossed St
                  Augustine’s Reach in the centre of Bristol.</note> Hastening one day to see his mother upon the alarm of a sudden &amp; dangerous
               illness which had seized her, he came to the draw-bridge just as they were beginning to raise it for the passage of a vessel; in his
               eagerness he attempted to spring across, but not calculating upon the rise, he fell in, &amp; the vessel past over him; I used to cross
               this bridge &lt;almost&gt; every day for many years of my life, &amp; the knowledge of his fate warned me from incurring the same danger, as
               otherwise in all likelihood I should very often have done.</p><p rend="indent1"> The blow which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> had received on the breast was
               attended with serious consequences, she underwent several operations, &amp; the functions of that breast were destroyed. She was able
               to nurse her younger children with the other, but it was my lot to be consigned to a <del>wet</del> foster mother whom my Uncle William
               had qualified for the office.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. Southey’s uncle, William Tyler (1742–1789), had impregnated
                  the foster mother.</note> This girl had been from her childhood employed at my grandmothers, first in the garden, then in household
               affairs; – a poor thoughtless simple creature, somewhat amorously inclined: her child died as soon as it was born, just at the time
               when I stood in need of her care. Her “misfortune” did not diminish the sort of compassionate attachment with which she was regarded by
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>, so she was taken into the house, &amp; certainly no one could
               have proved a more affectionate nurse than poor Pat as she was called, proved to me. The first day that I was taken to school <del>to
                  learn to read</del> she was almost heart broken at the scene between me &amp; the school mistress, which no doubt appeared to me
               &lt;also&gt; sufficiently tragical at the time. Having ushered me into the room &amp; delivered me into custody, she made a hasty retreat,
               but stood at the door on the outside, looking thro a window which gave light into the passage, &amp; listening to what ensued.
                  <del>Young as I was</del> Upon this occasion I gave <del>the first</del> &lt;good&gt; proof of <del>that</del> &lt;a&gt; sense of physiognomy
               which never misled me yet, <del>&amp;</del> of <del>fearlessness</del> &lt;honesty&gt; in speaking my opinion, &amp; of a temerity in doing
               it by which my after life has often been characterized. Ma’am Powell<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Powell (dates unknown)
                  ran a Dame School in Bristol, which Southey attended between the ages of three to six years old.</note> had as forbidding a face (I
               well remember it) as can easily be imagined, &amp; it was <del>rendered worse by the total</del> remarkable for having no eye lashes, –
               a peculiarity which I instantly perceived. When the <del>poor</del> old woman therefore led me to a seat on the form, I rebelled as
               manfully as a boy of three years could do, crying out lustily, – “take me to Pat, – I don’t like ye, – you have got ugly eyes, – take
               me to Pat, I say. Poor Pat went home with the story, &amp; cried as bitterly in relating it as I had done during the contest, &amp;
                  <del>th</del> at the utter discomfiture to which I was fain to submit, when might as it appeared to me overpowered right.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEliza">My sister Eliza</ref> was born in 1776. &amp; died of the measles in
                  .<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey leaves a space for the date after ‘measles in’: the date was 1779.</note><del>My
                  recollections of her are more imperfect than it might otherwise have been, because much of my early childhood was spent with Miss
                  Tyler, – still</del> I remember her as &lt;my earliest&gt; playmate <del>in certain situations</del> by help of some local circumstances,
               &amp; sometimes fancy that I <del>will</del> can call to mind a faint resemblance of her face. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother Thomas</ref> came into the world in Dec. 1777. Louisa next in 1779.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Louisa Southey (1779–1782).</note> This was a beautiful creature, – the admiration of all who beheld
               her. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt Mary</ref> was walking with her one day down Union Street, as Wesley<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wesley (1703–1791; <title>DNB</title>); the subject of Southey’s controversial <title>The
                     Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> was coming up. The old man <del>xx</del> was so
               struck with the little girls beauty, that he stopt &amp; exclaimed Oh sweet creature! &amp; took her by the hand &amp; gave her a
               blessing. That which in affliction we are prone to think a blessing, &amp; which perhaps in sober reflection <del>xx</del> may &lt;be&gt;
               justly thought so, befell her soon afterwards, — an early removal to a better world. She died of hydrocephalus,*<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">* Induced I believe by the cursed custom of dipping her every morning in a tub of &lt;the&gt; coldest water.
                  [Southey’s note.] </note> a disease to which the most promising children are the most liable.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s first child, Margaret Edith, had died of hydrocephalus in 1803.</note> John the next child was born in 1782
               &amp; died in infancy.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John Southey (b. 1782).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My recollections of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEliza">Eliza</ref> &amp; Louisa are more imperfect than
               they might otherwise have been, because during those years I was very much from home, being sometimes at school &amp; sometimes with
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>, of whose situation &amp; previous history I must now speak,
               because they had so material an influence upon &lt;the course of&gt; my <del>future</del> life.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> who was born in the year 1739 passed the
                  <del>greater</del> &lt;earlier&gt; part of her <del>youth</del> &lt;life&gt; with her maternal uncle at Shobdon, a little village in
               Herefordshire, where he resided upon a Curacy. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bradford<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Bradford
                  (1701–1768), Herefordshire clergyman, Curate of Shobdon 1728–1768, Rector of Cefyn-Llys 1748–1768, Vicar of Aymestry
                  1762–1768.</note> had been educated at Trinity College, Oxford, &amp; was in much better circumstances than country curates in
               general. He had an estate in Radnorshire of respectable value, &amp; married the <del>only</del> sister of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               Greenly of Titley in Herefordshire.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Bradford’s wife was Frances (d. 1763), the half-sister of
                  William Greenly (1741–1834) of Titley Court, Herefordshire.</note> In the first years of their marriage she narrowly escaped death
               in childbed, having been delivered by instruments; from the nature of the case it was understood that the same dreadful issue would be
               inevitable if she were again <del>pregnant</del> &lt;parturient&gt; &amp; of course they never afterwards cohabited as man &amp; wife, tho
               they continued to live together. He appears to have possessed some taste for letters &amp; his library was well provided with the
               professional literature of his age. Shobdon tho a remote place gave him great opportunities of society: Lord Bateman<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Either William Bateman, 1st Viscount Bateman (1695–1744), of Shobdon Court, or his son, John Bateman,
                  2nd Viscount Bateman (1721–1802).</note><del>having</del> &lt;had&gt; his residence there, in one of the finest midland situations that
               England affords &amp; A clergyman of companionable <del>means</del> talents &amp; manners was of course a welcome guest
                  <del>there</del> &lt;at his table&gt;. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> also became a favourite with
               Lady Bateman<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Anne, née Spencer (1702–1769), second daughter of John Churchill, 1st
                  Duke of Marlborough (1650–1722; <title>DNB</title>) and wife of William Bateman, 1st Viscount Bateman.</note><del>so that she</del>
               &lt;&amp;&gt; spent a great deal of her time there; – enough to acquire the manners of high life, &amp; too many of its habits &amp; notions.
                  M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bradford died some years before her husband, not however till he was too far advanced in life or too
               confirmed in celibate habits to think of marrying again. By that time he had become a victim to the gout. <del>In xxxxxxxx to hxx
                  xxxxxx of</del> An odd accident <del>which</del> happened to him during one of his severe fits &lt;at a time&gt; when no persuasion would
               have induced him to put his foot to the ground, or to fancy it possible for him to walk. He was sitting with his legs up in the full
               costume of that respectable &amp; orthodox disease; when the cieling being somewhat out of repair, a <del>xxxxx</del> part of it
                  <del>fell</del> &lt;gave way, &amp; down fell&gt; a fine nest of rats old &amp; young together, – plump upon him. He had what is called an
               antipathy to these creatures, &amp; forgetting the gout in the horror <del>of</del> &lt;which&gt; their visitation &lt;excited&gt; sprung from his
               easy chair, &amp; fairly ran down stairs.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> had the management of his house after his wifes
               death, &amp; had also in no small degree the management of the parish. She had influence enough to introduce inoculation there, &amp; I
               believe great merit in the exertions which she used in that occasion, &amp; the personal attention which she bestowed. It occurs to my
               recollection now also that she effected a wholesome innovation in the poor house, by persuading them to use beds stuffed with beech
               leaves, according to the practice in the south of France, which she had heard or read of. It was M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bradford who
               placed <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> at Oxford, first at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Mary <del>x</del>
               Hall, afterwards at Christ Church, where he obtained a studentship, which must have been by means of some Shobdon connections. When
                  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bradford died which was about the year 1772, he left the whole of his property to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>, except 100£ to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                  mother</ref>, &amp; a small provision charged upon his estates to my poor Uncle William,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tyler (1742–1789), Southey’s uncle.</note> as one utterly incapable of providing for himself. My Grandmother<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Bradford (1710–1782).</note> was wholly overlooked in his will &amp; the <del>xxxx</del> pain
               which she felt at this unkindness was not mitigated by the use which her daughter made of her accession of fortune. The use which she
               ought to have made of it was obvious. She should have made Bedminster her home, as long as she might remain single, her presence there
               would have kept the worst of her brothers<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">John Tyler (dates unknown).</note> at a distance,
               &amp; the others<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tyler and Edward Tyler (1744–1786).</note> in order, &amp; her mother
               would have past the remainder of her days without <del>any</del> the anxieties <del>concerning her xxxxxx of</del> &lt;of&gt; a structured
               income, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> during those years would have had so much to spare,
               that with common prudence she might ever afterwards have <del>been</del> had money at command. </p><p rend="indent1"> Instead of this finding herself mistress of 1500£ in money &lt;from his effects&gt; besides the estate &lt;&amp; 600£ of her
               own&gt; she began to visit watering places, &amp; at one of them falling in with D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Armstrong well known for his poem
               on Health, &amp; infamously known for another of his compositions,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The physician and poet John
                  Armstrong (1708/9–1779; <title>DNB</title>). His works included the georgic <title>Art of Preserving Health</title> (1744) and the
                  blank-verse sex manual the <title>Oeconomy of Love</title> (1736). </note> was recommended by him <del>for</del> to try the climate
               of Lisbon, I believe not so much for any real or apprehended complaint, as because he perceived that the advice would be agreable. – In
               this manner did Armstrong before you &amp; I were born, prepare the way for our friendship, &amp; for the great literary labours of my
                  life.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Armstrong had not inspired Southey to write either blank-verse georgics or a sex
                  manual. Rather, by initiating the connection between Southey’s family and Portugal, he had put Southey in the way both of John May,
                  whose family were members of the expatriate merchant community, and of Portuguese society and culture, which were key to his planned
                  magnum opus the ‘History of Portugal’ and to many of his other works.</note> To <del>xx</del> Lisbon accordingly she went, taking
               with her <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> who had lately <del>been o</del> entered into orders, &amp;
               &lt;a distant relation&gt; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Prankard, the widow of a decayed merchant, as a sort of <hi rend="ital">Ama</hi>.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">This distant relative had possibly married Richard Prankard (or Pranchard) (dates unknown), a
                  Bristol merchant in the West India trade.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref> one of her friends,
               joined the party. They remained about a year abroad. Some of your friends no doubt remember them there – it was in <del>th</del> 1774
               the year of my birth. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> was then <del>in her</del> 34. She was
               remarkably beautiful, if that face can be called beautiful &lt;in&gt; which the indications of a bad temper are apparent. She had looked too
               high for marriage when in her prime, I have heard that there was an attachment between her &amp; Lord Robert Spencer,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord Robert Spencer (1747–1831), third son of Charles Spencer, 3rd Duke of Marlborough (1706–1758), Whig
                  politician and gambler. Lady Bateman was his aunt.</note> which Lady Bateman had some difficulty to break off. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> also told me that while she was at Lisbon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpole<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Walpole (1736–1810), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Portugal,
                  1771–1800. His first wife, Diana, née Grosset, died in July 1784, and he married, for the second time, Sophia Stert (d. 1829), in
                  May 1785. </note> admired her (I believe it was while he was a widower -) but that she gave more encouragement than was prudent to
               an American Adventurer who followed her to England. His name was Digges. If <del>perhaps</del> &lt;I am not mistaken&gt; he wrote a sort of
               novel called the adventures of Automathes, in which there is a story of a man endeavouring to smuggle diamonds from the Forbidden
               District in Brazil, – &amp; I know that he was a mere adventurer, who afterwards acquired some dishonourable notoriety by his
               &lt;political&gt; intrigues during the American war.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Atwood Digges (1742–1822) of Maryland,
                  expatriate and embezzler. His book was the <title>Adventures of Alonso: Containing Some Striking Anecdotes of the Present Prime
                     Minister of Portugal</title> (1775), possibly the first American novel. Southey had confused the title with that of John Kirkby
                  (1705–1754), <title>Life of Automathes</title> (1745).</note></p></div></body></text></TEI>