<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3571</idno><idno type="nines">rce4842</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3571. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 29 November 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3571.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 201. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3571" type="letter"><head>3571. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1820-11-29">29 November 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The
						Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey.<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmarks: E/ 3 DE 3/ 1820; [partial]
						lock/ E.2/ N<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 201. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.
					</note></head><opener><dateline><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName><date when="1820-11-29">29 Nov. 1820.</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> I have taken your advice concerning the Vision of Judgement,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> &amp; proceeded with it to such good
					purport, that I have a fair prospect of bringing it to its close tomorrow. It has been tried upon a good many ears,
					&amp; never without an effect more or less favourable; persons who did not think it possible that the metre could
					be introduced into our language without producing something forced or ridiculous, having acknowledged that the
						<del>xxx xxx</del> attempt <del>was</del> &lt;is&gt; succesful. I shall probably soon publish it, with an introductory
					account of the various attempts which have been made to naturalize the hexameter &amp; other classical metres in
					the different modern languages, as well as in our own. This with a few specimens will help out a lean book, &amp;
					extend it to about fifty pages in foolscap quarto.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of
							Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’ (pp. ix–xxvii), ‘Notes’ (pp. 47–65), ‘Specimens’ (pp. 67–79). It was
						not published in foolscap quarto, but in quarto.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The present state of affairs while I am pursuing my usual employments, as if all things were well
					&amp; as they should be, remind me very much of the year 1800, when there seemed every probability that the yellow
					fever would make its appearance at Lisbon. Anxious as all persons who suffered themselves to think upon the subject
					were, &amp; as I myself was, tho at a time of life when such anxieties are more easily put aside than in maturer
					years, I have often thought how little that frightful apprehension appeared to affect those among whom I lived, –
					their business &amp; their amusements went on as usual; &amp; the Government itself did not appear more indifferent
					to the imminent danger, than even the reflecting part of the people. That poor country was spared from the
					visitation of pestilence; to undergo others not less terrible in their action &amp; perhaps more lasting.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The French invasion of 1807; the flight of the Portuguese court to Brazil in
						1807–1808; and the Liberal revolution in Portugal in August 1820.</note> Whether the moral plague which is raging
					among us will be stayed, or whether it will bring on that tremendous convulsion which so many causes have prepared,
					&amp; <del>xxx</del> &lt;seems&gt; at this time &lt;to be&gt; accelerating, God only knows. This infernal woman<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Under extreme pressure from George IV, the Cabinet had reluctantly agreed to introduce
						a Bill of Pains and Penalties into the House of Lords to deprive the King’s wife, Caroline of Brunswick
						(1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>), of the title of Queen and to dissolve her marriage to the King. On the Third
						Reading of the Bill on 10 November 1820, the government majority had been only nine votes and it had seemed very
						unlikely the Bill could pass the House of Commons. Lord Liverpool, the Prime Minister, therefore had announced the
						Bill would be withdrawn. As was customary when a national victory was celebrated, many householders put lighted
						candles in their windows. This occurred at different dates in towns across the country, mostly between 11 November
						and 16 November 1820; the celebrations in Keswick were on 15 November 1820.</note> will raise a rebellion if she
					can. – King Mob bore his faculties meekly here, &amp; offered no violence to the half dozen houses in the town
					which were not illuminated. I stood in a conspicuous situation, &amp; thought it not unlikely that my windows might
					be attacked, in which case I should certainly have faced the assailants, &amp; have tried what fair words &amp; a
					resolute avowal of opinion would have done. Much to my satisfaction they let me alone.</p><p rend="indent1"> When next you have an hour to spare in London, call at <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash’s</ref> (2 Duchess Street, Portland Place) &amp; look at his portfolio. He
					has an excellent likeness of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>, some very
					good ones of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The identity of the portraits is unclear, but they are probably those depicting Edith May in three
						different dresses, lilac, red and uncoloured, described in Southey to John May, 8 April 1821, Letter 3667. The
						location of the ‘lilac’ portrait is unknown; the ‘redder’ one is probably the pencil and watercolour sketch now in
						the collections of the Wordsworth Trust, Grasmere; and the ‘uncoloured’ one is in Keswick Museum and Art
						Gallery.</note> &amp; a picture of one of our mountain parties which will please you very much.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have a M.S.S. on the road from the Inquisition at Majorca, containing I believe an account of
					its proceedings. Col: Shipley<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Shipley (1778–1820), MP for St Mawes
						1807, 1812–1813 and MP for Flint Boroughs 1807–1812. A former soldier, he was Wynn’s brother-in-law, having
						married Charlotte Williams Wynn (1773–1819) in 1806. In 1813 his huge gambling debts forced him to flee to Majorca
						and he died in France on 29 November 1820. The manuscript Southey mentions was not in the sale catalogue of his
						library and he found it of little interest; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 2 December 1820, Letter
						3574.</note> laid hold of it at the wreck &amp; sent it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, &amp; he sends it to me. It will probably relate wholly to Jews &amp; Moriscoes, – &amp; to those
					cases which have nothing to do with religious opinions, such as witchcraft, bigamy &amp;c. Something curious might
					perhaps have been found in their archives concerning Ramon<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a
						reference to Ramon Llull (c. 1232–1315), a Franciscan from Majorca, writer and philosopher. Many of his works were
						condemned as heretical in 1376.</note> [MS missing] – but can hardly be expected here.</p><p rend="indent1"> [MS missing] tolerably well thank God, &amp; I hope the stock of exercise &amp; excitement which
					I laid in in the South will carry <del>xxx</del> &lt;me&gt; well thro the winter. A thorough shaking of that kind does me
					a great deal of good. If I could afford the time &amp; the cost, &amp; muster the resolution, I should prescribe
					for myself a six weeks journey every year.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have written to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> to see whether he
					has Oviedo y Baños<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Richard Heber, 25 November 1820, Letter
						3566, asking if he had a copy of José de Oviedo y Baños (1671–1738), <title>Historia de la Conquista y Población
							de la Provincia de Venezuela</title> (1723), no. 3605 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey wanted
						this volume for his <title>The Expedition of Orsua; and the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821), a version of which
						had first appeared in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), i–l.</note> &amp; I am
					printing the Carmen Triumphale &amp; the three Court Odes in a little volume to range with my other poems; – it
					will bind up with the Carmen Nuptiale.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A combined second edition of
							<title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814) and <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness the Prince
							Regent, His Imperial Majesty the Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814), published
						as <title>Carmen Triumphale, for the Commencement of the Year 1814: Carmen Aulica. Written in 1814, on the Arrival
							of the Allied Sovereigns in England</title> (1821). At 93 pages, this edition was slightly longer than the
						77-page <title>Lay of the Laureate</title> (1816).</note> – I have written a book of Oliver Newman<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Portrait’, the fifth book of Southey’s unfinished epic, set in New England. The
						completed sections were published after Southey’s death in <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished):
							With Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1–90.</note> since my return. And this reminds me that a
					certain M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sedgwick of New York<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly one of three
						brothers, the sons of the politician and judge, Theodore Sedgwick I (1746–1813): Theodore Sedgwick II (1780–1839);
						Henry Dwight Sedgwick (1785–1831); and Robert Sedgwick (1787–1841), all of whom practised law in New York.</note>
					has sent me Hubbards Indian War,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hubbard (1621/2–1704),
							<title>Narrative of the Troubles with the Indians in New England</title> (1677) and <title>Narrative of the
							Indian Wars in New-England</title> (1803), nos 1385 and 1266 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note>
					supposing it might be useful to me in this work, whereas I happen to possess both the original edition, &amp; the
					modern one. The book came by the Venus Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Candler,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Candler (1792–1842), an American sea captain, who worked for various Boston shipowners. During the War of
						1812 he had been Master’s Mate on USS <title>Constitution</title>.</note> &amp; is left with “Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> John &amp; James Dunlop, Merchants, London”<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John Dunlop
						(1779–1830) and his brother James Dunlop (b. 1781), Scottish merchants and bankers, mainly engaged in trade with
						America.</note> till called for. Get some of your city friends to send for it, &amp; place it upon your
					shelves.</p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the children. God
					bless you. RS.</p></div></body></text></TEI>