<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3597</idno><idno type="nines">rce4868</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3597. Robert Southey to John
                  Hookham Frere, 30 December 1820</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3597.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Newnham College, Cambridge, Harold Young Papers 382a. ALS;
                  4p. .  Previously  published: Gabrielle Festing, John Hookham Frere and
                     His Friends (London, 1899), pp. 229–230 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3597" type="letter"><head>3597. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">John
                  Hookham Frere</ref>, <date when="1820-12-30">30 December 1820</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Right Honble/ J
                  Hookham Frere/ &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c<lb/> Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of
                  Lorraine<lb/> MS: Newnham College, Cambridge, Harold Young Papers 382a. ALS;
                  4p.<lb/> Previously published: Gabrielle Festing, <title>John Hookham Frere and
                     His Friends</title> (London, 1899), pp. 229–230 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1820-12-30"> 30 Dec. 1820</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am now in the press with the history of the Peninsular War. The
               first chapter is merely introductory, concerning the state of the three countries
               which were directly involved in the contest.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1823–1832), I, pp. 3–62.</note> With this therefore I had no occasion to trouble
               you, but upon coming to matters of fact I have desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to send you the proof sheets.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to John Murray, 30 December
                  1820, Letter 3598. </note> I should have preferred sending you the manuscript, –
               but you will read it with much greater facility in the printed copy. My hand writing
               has become a very difficult one, unless I make a transcript for the press, which in
               the present case is not necessary.</p><p rend="indent1"> Now with regard to the communication of your corrections. My way with
               proof sheets (which make some of the happiness of my life) is to read them aloud on
               the evening when they arrive, keep them one post, read them aloud a second time the
               next day, &amp; despatch them on the second night. In case of smaller corrections,
               such as are at once to be received thankfully, &amp; without doubt, there is no need
               to communicate them, – return the proof at such times to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, &amp; your corrections may go at
               once to the Printer.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison
                  (1766–1831), printer for Murray and Longman.</note> But in matters of more moment,
               where your remarks may call upon me to change an expressed opinion, to see things in
               a different point of view, &amp; to modify, or totally to alter the tenour of the
               narrative <del>of</del> in that part, – then if you send me your remarks on the day
               after the proof has been sent to you, – they will reach me (who am always at home) on
               my second evening, &amp; in good time.</p><p rend="indent1"> The sooner you can let me have such papers in your possession as may
               be useful, the better. And there are some points upon which <del>hearing your
                  xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx</del> by letter would be more serviceable than any other
               documents, as giving me what in no other way could be obtained. These, with your
               permission I will propose to you as they occur in my progress. At present what would
               be most serviceable to me would be that sort of information which you could
               communicate in a leisure hour concerning the leading members of the Central
                  Junta,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Supreme Central and
                  Governing Junta of the Kingdom, set up on 25 September 1808 to govern those parts
                  of Spain which were not occupied by the French. The Junta dissolved itself on 29
                  January 1810 and was replaced by a Council of Regency.</note> – who they were,
               what were their views, &amp; characters. In the few opportunities which I have had of
               conversing with you upon Spanish affairs, a single expression of yours has given me
               light where I most wanted it.</p><p rend="indent1"> You probably know that I wrote the whole historical part of the
               Edinburgh Annual Register for the years 1808–9-10 &amp; 11.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808 to 1811</title>
                  (1810–1813). Much of this material was recycled in the <title>History of the
                     Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> During the three latter years I was
               well supplied with Spanish materials, by a man whom you may likely have known <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Manuel Abella</ref>, – I obtained
                  <del>from him</del> by his means many private communications, but these sources
               were cut off by his disgrace, which I believe was soon followed by his death. The
               time spent upon that obscure labour I do not regret, (tho it would have sufficed for
               compleating my history of Portugal<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted ‘History of Portugal’.</note>) because it not only gave
               me an insight into this great subject which I could hardly else have attained, but
               also because it compelled me to look into my own opinions, &amp; see upon what
               foundation they rested. Some portions of that narrative I shall incorporate.</p><p rend="indent1"> During the contest my anticipations for Spain were always hopeful. I
               wish they were so now.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">An army revolt in
                  January 1820 led to the restoration of the liberal Constitution of 1812 in March
                  1820; but Spain remained deeply divided between Royalists and Liberals.</note> But
               at present my best hope is that other countries, &amp; especially Portugal, may be
               warned in times, by the <del>evils which</del> tremendous example which is likely to
               be afforded them there.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A liberal
                  revolution in Portugal in August 1820 had led to the election of a Cortes in
                  December 1820 and demands for the monarchy to return from Brazil, where it had
                  fled in 1807–1808.</note> Brazil I hope may escape; – for if a revolution should
               take place there, the <del>whole</del> country will soon be divided among hordes of
               banditti as is now the case with the provinces of the Plata, where the Revolutionists
               have been left to themselves.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The United
                  Provinces of the Rio de la Plata, centred in modern Argentina, had been
                  self-governing since 1810 and had declared their independence in 1816. They were
                  at this time torn by a civil war between federalists and centralists.</note> If
               Spain were under a settled government I believe it would not be long before deputies
               from Buenos Ayres would be sent to solicit that it would send out a Viceroy &amp; put
               an end to their miserable state of anarchy.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>