<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3676</idno><idno type="nines">rce4947</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3676. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert
						Southey, Easter Monday [23 April] 1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3676.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG
						1996.5.114. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3676" type="letter"><head>3676. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert
						Southey</ref>,<date when="1821-04-23"> Easter Monday [23 April] 1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square <lb/>
						Postmarks: [partial] TwoPyPst/ Unpaid; 4 o’Clock/ 26. AP/ 1821 EV<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG
						1996.5.114. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1821-04-23">Easter Monday. 1821</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear
						Harry</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You have here the whole epistle of P. Martyr, – in perfect form.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Martyr d’Anghiera (1457–1526), <title>Opus Epistolarum</title> (Amsterdam, 1670), p. 34, no.
						1902 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey believed this letter of April 1488 described a case of
						syphilis in Europe before the discovery of North America in 1492, so disproving the idea that the disease had an
						American origin.</note> His epistles were first printed at Alcala 1530 in folio,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The original edition of the <title>Opus Epistolarum</title> had been printed at Alcala de Henares,
						near Madrid, in 1530.</note> &amp; the book had become exceedingly rare, so much so that when the President
						Lamoignon<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Guillaume de Lamoignon (1617–1677), French jurist.</note> gave a
					copy from his library to Charles Patin<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Patin (1633–1693), French
						physician and numismatist, edited <title>Opus Epistolarum</title> (1670).</note> for the purpose of reprinting it,
					– another copy, it is said, was hardly to be found. Patin’s edition is that which I possess.</p><p rend="indent1"> There can be no mistake about the date of the letter, because they are arranged chonologically,
					in books, a book for each year. – I am not much surprized that men writing professedly upon the subject should not
					have found the passage, because they would have been likely to look in P. Martyrs Decades<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey also possessed Peter Martyr d’Anghiera’s <title>De Rebus Oceanicus et Novo Orbe … De
							Babylonicae Legatione … et … De Rebus Aethiopicis</title> (1574), an edition of this author’s ‘Decades’, no. 1811
						in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> (which contain the earliest history of the Discovery) &amp; therefore
					to disregard the other work. But it is very extraordinary that it should not have been noted by persons writing
					upon the history of those times (the age of Ferdinand &amp; Ch. 5)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand
						II (1452–1516; King of Aragon 1479–1516); and Charles V (1500–1558; King of Spain 1516–1556).</note> – or, – like
					myself, reading more for <del>fxx</del> the sake of general knowledge than with any single &amp; specific purpose.
					Robertson includes the book in his list of authorities &amp; <hi rend="ital">ought</hi> to have read it.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Robertson (1721–1793; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of America</title>
						(1788), no. 2456 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. <title>Opus Epistolarum </title>(1670) is listed in
						the ‘Catalogue of Spanish books and Manuscripts’. Southey was habitually dismissive of Robertson’s work.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoe</ref> ought to have read it.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William Roscoe, <title>The Life of
							Lorenzo de’ Medici</title> (1796).</note> – I had been looking for it twenty years, as one of the collateral
					authorities necessary for my H. of Portugal.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished ‘History
						of Portugal’.</note> – P Martyr gives but sorry comfort to his friend, – but the Epistle shows that poor
						Arius<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Arias Barbosa (c. 1465/70–1540), Portuguese scholar and Professor of
						Greek at the University of Salamanca 1495–1530.</note> was the first person who taught Greek at Salamanca.</p><p rend="indent1"> The hat &amp; the magnifico cap arrived yesterday, – the latter is just made large enough by
					taking out the slips meant to cover the ears in travelling. It is much approved of. The hat fits well. Let me know
					the cost. – I will trouble you with another commission, larger &amp; rather <del>xx</del> more troublesome, – &amp;
					then send you a draft for the whole amount. – It is to buy for me <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref> Parliamentary History,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">William Cobbett,
							<title>Parliamentary History of England: From the Norman Conquest, in 1066 to the Year 1803</title> (1806), no.
						2183 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This work was in 36 volumes. It is not clear where Southey
						expected to buy a copy cheaply, but it was possibly from the shop run by John Hatchard (1768–1849;
							<title>DNB</title>) at 187 Piccadilly, which is about half way between Old Bond Street and Haymarket.</note>
					which is to be had cheap somewhere in Piccadilly, – somewhere I believe between Bond Street &amp; the top of the
					Haymarket. It is a huge number of volumes – more than 20 – published at a guinea &amp; half each. It may probably
					be had at half price, – but you may go as high as two thirds for it, in binding – or half-binding. I do not want
					his Debates<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William Cobbett, <title>Parliamentary Debates</title>
						(1804–1812), no. 618 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> nor his State Trials<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">William Cobbett, Thomas Bayly Howell (1768–1815; <title>DNB</title>) and Thomas Jones
						Howell (1793–1858; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Cobbett’s Complete Collection of State Trials and Proceedings for
							High Treason and Other Crimes and Misdemeanors from the Earliest Period to the Present Time</title> (1809–1826),
						no. 2734 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> (which are likewise to be had) because I have the
					latter, &amp; with the former have nothing more to do. But I am frequently at a stand for want of a Parl. History,
					&amp; indeed cannot longer do without it. Let it be sent by waggon.</p><p rend="indent1"> I wish we were near London that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith
						May</ref> might have the benefit, or chance, of medical advice, for this cutaneous <del>complaint</del> affection
					which continues on her forehead &amp; the back part of her neck &amp; shoulders, but chiefly on the forehead. There
					is a great languor in her system. I wrote to you three months ago about an inert tumour on the eyelid, – a wisp in
					fact, which after gathering, began to go back, – it is still in the same state, tho a mercurial ointment was
					applied for about a fortnight. She is exceedingly pale. And this is not to be accounted for by her time of life,
					because she is &amp; has for some time been perfectly <hi rend="ital">regular</hi>. When <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> comes to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>, I shall take her there for the sake of sea bathing. It makes me anxious, for I am afraid it
					will prey upon her spirits <del>xxx</del> to have this sort of disfigurement – at her age, – <del>xx</del> an evil
					against which of course I endeavour to do my best.</p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref></p><closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1">I have had three invitations to Public Dinners in London lately.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Two of these invitations were to the annual dinners of the Royal Literary Fund and the Artists’
							General Benevolent Institution. </note> – Now to correct the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> sheet of the Pen: War.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>