<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3636</idno><idno type="nines">rce4907</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3636. Robert Southey to William Peachy, 16 February
                  1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3636.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3636" type="letter"><head>3636. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>,<date when="1821-02-16"> 16 February
                  1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/ 66. Baker Street/ Portman Square/
                  London<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: [partial] 19 FE 19/ 1821<lb/> MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
                  Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1821-02-16">16 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1821.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear
               Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am glad to hear that you &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>
               after your long circum-journeyings are safely &amp; comfortably settled for a season in Baker Street. You are I verily believe the most
               unweariable traveller that ever traversed this island of Great Britain. You make Edinburgh in the way from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> to London, &amp; I should not be surprized to hear that you made Penzance, or the Scilly
               Islands, in the way from London to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. Fortunatus himself hardly possessed
               greater powers of locomotion.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Fortunatus was the hero of a series of tales widely published in
                  sixteenth- and seventeenth-century Europe. He had a cap that could carry the wearer wherever he wished. </note></p><p rend="indent1"> I am glad also to see you confirm what the papers say concerning the abatement of the Queens-fever,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Under extreme pressure from George IV, the Cabinet had reluctantly agreed to introduce a Bill of Pains
                  and Penalties into the House of Lords to deprive the King’s wife, Caroline of Brunswick (1768–1821; <title>DNB</title>), of the
                  title of Queen and to dissolve her marriage to the King. On the Third Reading of the Bill on 10 November 1820, the government
                  majority was only nine votes and it seemed very unlikely the Bill could pass the House of Commons. Lord Liverpool, the Prime
                  Minister, therefore had announced the Bill would be withdrawn. The Queen’s supporters included many opposition politicians, and the
                  controversy dominated political debate into the spring of 1821.</note> which has raged so long &amp; so violently throughout the
               country, to the disgrace of our national character, &amp; to the indelible infamy of the Whigs who did not act with greater baseness in
               the affair of the Popish Plot,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The idea that the mythical ‘Popish Plot’ was a reality was
                  promoted by Whig politicians in 1678–1681 to discredit the Stuart monarchy.</note> than they have done, &amp; are doing on the
               present occasion. Some other popular question will arise, – some new apple of discord be thrown, &amp; Queen Caroline will be as little
               thought of as Queen Elizabeth.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth I (1533–1603; Queen of England 1558–1603;
                     <title>DNB</title>).</note> It should be part of the policy of an English Minister to throw out tubs to the Whale.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Seamen who hunted whales were believed to throw empty tubs into the water to distract the whales so they
                  would not notice the approaching hunters.</note> This might often be done with good effect. Vansittart<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Vansittart, 1st Baron Bexley (1766–1851; <title>DNB</title>), Chancellor of the Exchequer 1812–1823.</note>
               got all his grants last year without the slightest trouble; – the Opposition who would otherwise have baited him like a badger whenever
               the budget appeared, were so hot upon the Queens scent, that they let him do the whole business without molestation. A good tub-maker
               would be one of the most serviceable members of administration.</p><p rend="indent1"> We have had one of the finest winters that ever was remembered. The glass has been almost as high as the temperate
               point very frequently, &amp; generally is nearer 50 than 40. There has been no snow in sight, on any of the mountains, for many weeks,
               – &amp; there were many days in which January &amp; this month as well, had it not been for the appearance of the trees, might have
               been mistaken for June.</p><p rend="indent1"> The weather, I believe, affords the only news which I can send you from this place, – except that <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondson</ref> has been several times at the point of death, with a disease
               which I suppose to have been the iliac passion.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A disease characterised by griping pain,
                  costiveness and violent vomiting, including of faecal matter. It is caused by inflammation or obstruction of the large or small
                  intestine.</note> He is very much recovered, but the escape has been a very narrow one, &amp; I never saw any person so much &amp;
               so suddenly reduced as he was at one time. – M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fryer has taken Ormathwaite for a year, while his own house is
                  repairing.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777–1855), surveyor, geologist and mining engineer from
                  Newcastle. From 1808 he spent part of each year at Keswick. He had been living at Lyzzick Hall, about two miles north of the town.
                  Ormathwaite was a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick and two miles from Derwentwater; see Southey to William
                  Wilberforce, 3 June 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3146.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> My History of the War<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                  (1823–1832). The printer was Thomas Davison (1766–1831).</note> is fairly in the Press, &amp; I &amp; the printers keep on at a good
               steady pace. I have a poem<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> forthcoming
               which will probably occasion some discussion, as a metrical experiment, being written in a measure as nearly upon the model of the
               hexameter as the nature of our language will admit. This novelty, &amp; the subject (relating to the late King<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note>) will bring on some thing like a
               hail stone chorus of abuse, which I shall regard as much as I do one of your London fogs while I am breathing the free fresh air of
               these mountains.</p><p rend="indent1"> You would be sorry to hear of the death of my poor friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref>, a man for whom I had the greatest regard. His loss is a great grief to us all, more particularly to me; for
               in my pleasantest recollections of later years he made a part, &amp; I had hoped to make one more journey on the continent in company
               with him.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Nash had accompanied Southey on his continental tour of May–August 1817.</note> The
               loss of an intimate friend is a severe calamity at any time; &amp; at my time of life new connections are seldom formed to stand in the
               place of those which are thus broken.</p><p rend="indent1"> We all unite in kind remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>
               &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henry.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">One of Peachy’s two stepsons, James Henry (1803–1884) and
                  Charles Edward Henry (1807–1833).</note> Remember us also to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Senhouse’s</ref> family. It gives me great pleasure to think that he will soon return to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3">
                  Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>