<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3755</idno><idno type="nines">rce5026</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3755. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 8 December
                  1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3755.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and
                  Art Gallery, WC 212. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 287–289.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3755" type="letter"><head>3755. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1821-12-08">8 December
                  1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill./ Streatham/ Surry.<lb/>
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: 10 o’Clock/ DE. 11/ 1821 F N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 11 DE 11/ 1821<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and
                  Art Gallery, WC 212. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 287–289.</note></head><p rend="indent0"> I was vexed at discovering that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor’s <title>Idyllia Heroica Decem Phaleuciorum Unum Partim jam Primo Partim Iterum atq Tertio Edit
                     Savagius Landor</title> (1820), no. 1598 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> had been overlooked when the parcel
               was made up. If however there be in this place paper large enough for such an enclosure, I will frank it with my next dispatches to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, in the course of a week, &amp; he will consign it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> care</p><p rend="indent1"> Two or three days ago I received a rich present from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, – three score volumes – of all sorts &amp; kinds, none that are without value, &amp; some that are of considerable
               worth. The only one connected with Portugal is <hi rend="ital">Osorius de Nobilitate</hi> 1542, printed at Lisbon.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Jerónimo Osório (1506–1580), <title>De Vera Sapienta et de Nobilitate Civili ey Nobilitate
                     Christiana</title> (1542–1576), no. 2124 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note><del>Ax</del> There is the <hi rend="ital">Speculum Historiale Vincentii Beloacensis</hi> 1494<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Vincent of Beauvais (c.
                  1190-c. 1264), <title>Speculum Historiale</title> (1494), no. 2899 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> A folio
               Terence printed at Milan without a date, not I think later than 1500<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Terentius, cum
                     Commentariis Donati et Calphurnii, etc</title> (n. d.), no. 2672 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library; an edition of the
                  work of the Roman playwright, Publius Terentius Afer (c. 195/185–159 BC).</note> – A Milan Salust 1501 -<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sallustii Opera, cum Commentariis L. Vallae</title> (1501), no. 2400 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library, an edition of the work of the Roman historian, Gaius Sallustius Crispus (86–34 BC).</note><hi rend="ital">Laurentii
                  Vallensis Opus Elegantiarum Lingua Lat</hi>. 1487<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lorenzo Valla (c. 1407–1457),
                     <title>Elegentiae Linguae Latinae</title> (1487), no. 2895 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> all folios a great
               many volumes of Italian poetry &amp; modern Latin, one volume of poems in the Genoese,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Gian-Giacomo Cavalli (1590–1657), <title>Cittara Zeneize</title> (1745), no. 3065 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library.</note> &amp; another in the Neapolitan, or Sicilian dialect, I know not which.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Giulio Cesare Cortese (1570–1640), <title>Micco Passaro Namorato</title> (1666), no. 549 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library.</note> And an account of the sacking of Rome in 1527 by Jacopo Buonaparte, who was present: first printed in 1756
               at Lucca with the false date of Cologne, &amp; supprest by the Austrian influence, – so that very few copies are extant.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacopo Buonaparte (dates unknown), <title>Ragguaglio Storico Di Tutto l’Occorso Giorno per Giorno nel
                     Sacco di Roma dell’Anno MXXXVII</title> (1756), no. 429 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> It is a long while
               since I have had so miscellaneous a cargo of rarities.</p><p rend="indent1"> So the poor old Admiral never lived to receive his Admirals pay.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">James Burney
                  had died on 17 November 1821, just after being promoted to Rear Admiral, on the retired Navy List, in July 1821.</note> I am reading
               Kotzebues voyage,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Otto von Kotzebue (1787–1846), <title>Voyage of Discovery into the South Sea
                     and Bering’s Straits</title> (1821), no. 1576 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &amp; the thought often occurs
               that no man in this country will feel so much interest in it as he would have done. – About the same time I lost my friend at Ludlow,
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Wade Browne</ref>, an excellent man, for whom I had a great regard, &amp; in whose
               house I always found a joyful welcome.</p><p rend="indent1"> Knox<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John William Knox (1784–1862), clergyman, scholar and usher at Westminster
                  School 1806–1821.</note> must be the best judge of what is advisable for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>. The Greek examination for College<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">At Westminster School there are 40 King’s
                  (or Queen’s) Scholars, based in their own boarding house, called ‘College’. Entrance to this elite is by means of an examination
                  known as ‘The Challenge’. Successful Scholars have the right to special privileges; at this time these included Scholarships
                  reserved for them at Christ Church, Oxford and Trinity College, Cambridge.</note> is exclusively in the Epigrams.</p><p rend="indent1"> That monkey is a great favourite with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>, who
               looks at it every night on his way to bed, &amp; says it is very uggy, &amp; he tells me that when I am shaving I am almost as uggy as
               that monkey.</p><p rend="indent1"> The reprint of Brazil will be finished immediately.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of the
                  first volume of the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1822). There were no second editions of volumes two and three.</note> I have
               only to receive the table of contents &amp; preface, which I expect every day. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> has helped me to some materials for improving the second volume: he has given me one volume of the Paraguay Annual
               Letters, &amp; lent me another,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Fernao Guerreiro (c. 1550–1617), <title>Relaçam Annal das
                     Cousas que Fizeram os Padres da Companhia de Jesus na India e Japao, Brazil, Angola, Cabo Verde, Guine</title> (1607–1611), nos
                  3483–3484 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Heber had lent Southey some of the missing volumes from this series.</note>
               &amp; Montoyas Conquista Espiritual.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Ruiz de Montoya (1585–1652), <title>Conquista
                     Espiritual hecha por los Religiosos de la Compañia de la Jesus en la Provincias del Paraguay, Parana, Uruguay, y Tape</title>
                  (1639).</note> I also purchased at Edinburgh when I was there with <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> that
               volume concerning Madagascar &amp; Brazil a copy of which once past thro your hands at Lisbon.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Francois Cauche (1616–1699), <title>Relations Veritable et Curieuse de l’Isle de Madagascar et du Bresil, et Histoire des Derniers
                     Troubles du Bresil</title> (1651), no. 2363 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> The part relating Brazil is a
               history of the recovery of Pernambuco by Pierre Moreau, an adventurer in the Dutch service.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre Moreau (dates unknown), <title>Histoire des Derniers Troubles du Bresil Entre les Hollandois et les Portugais</title>
                  (1651).</note> But there is a separate, &amp; perhaps an enlarged edition of this which I saw in Buonapartes library at
                  Fontainebleau,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The library of Napoleon Bonaparte (1769–1821; Emperor of the French
                  1804–1814, 1815), which Southey had seen when he visited Fontainebleau on 21 May 1817.</note> – unless it were the same book
               separated from the Madagascar part.</p><p rend="indent1"> You may have heard of a History of Brazil by James Henderson.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">James Henderson
                  (c. 1783–1848), <title>History of Brazil</title> (1821), no. 1182 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Henderson had sailed
                  to South America in 1819 and was Consul-General in Columbia 1823–1836.</note> He has thought proper to send me the book. It is an
               account &amp; not a history of the country, – made up almost wholly from Cazal<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Manoel Aires de
                  Casal (1754–1821), <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Relação Historico-Geografica do Reino do Brazil</title> (1817), no. 3252 in the
                  sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> &amp; the Papers in the Patriota,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>O
                     Patriota, Jornal Litterario, Politico, Mercantil &amp;c do Rio de Janeiro</title> (1813–1814), no. 3641 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey’s library.</note> with what little information he picked up in the country during a short stay there. The prints are
               ill-drawn &amp; worse executed upon stone. He is a man of this country, without any education, &amp; I believe not in the best repute,
               – this book however is creditable to his industry, &amp; not discreditable in any point of view. – Luccocks book<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">John Luccock (1770–1826), <title>Notes on Rio de Janeiro, and the Southern Parts of Brazil; Taken During
                     a Residence of Ten Years in that Country, from 1808 to 1818 </title>(1820), no. 1645 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.
                  He did not make it the subject of a paper in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> has a great deal of interesting matter in
               it. I shall perhaps make it the subject of a paper in the Q R. At present I am finishing <del>an xxxx</del> a reviewal of
                  Dobrizhoffer,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed Sara Coleridge’s <title>An Account of the Abipones, an
                     Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26 (January 1822), 277–323. The book was a
                  translation of Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717–1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title>
                  (1784).</note> – my next subject is to be <ref type="m" target="people.html#AdamsonJohn">Adamsons</ref> Life of Camoens.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">John Adamson, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Luis de Camoens</title> (1820), no. 10 in the
                  sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), 1–39.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> The French are in good time supplying materials for my Hist: of the War.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> There is an account of Soults Campaigns in Portugal
               recently published,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre-Madeleine Le Noble (1772–1824), <title>Mémoires sur les Opérationes
                     des Français en Galice, en Portugal, et dans La Vallée du Tage, en 1809, sous le Commandement du Maréchal Soult</title>
                  (1821).</note> – as rascally a one as could be desired; &amp; one of a very different description by Marshal Gouvion S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cyr, concerning his own campaign in Catalonia.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Laurent de Gouvion Saint-Cyr
                  (1764–1830), <title>Journal des Opérations de l’Armée de Catalogne, en 1808 et 1809</title> (1821).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesley</ref> is a fit <del>xxxxx</del> man to civilize
               the Irish, if the Ministry here could be relied upon to support him.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Wellesley was appointed
                  Lord Lieutenant of Ireland on 8 December 1821.</note> I have been reading Spensers dialogue on the state of Ireland this
                  morning;<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Spenser (c. 1552–1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A View of the Present
                     State of Ireland</title> (1596).</note> – &amp; the country stands as much in need of Roman civilization now as it did in his
               days. Such a people must be under military law, or a permanent armed police, till they are fit for any thing</p><p rend="indent1"> I have to perform the disagreable task of writing a new-years ode, which must be about that miserable country.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s ‘Ireland’, published in <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and
                     Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829), I, pp. [295]–302. Southey felt compelled to write on Ireland to celebrate
                  George IV’s state visit there 12 August–3 September 1821, the first by a British monarch since the fourteenth century.</note> If
               that subject had not occurred I meant to have written one which would have saved me the trouble of ever writing another till that was
               called for. This I did with the birthday.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Ode for St George’s Day’, unpublished until
                     <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837–1838), III, pp. 258–262.</note> My odes for the last two years are better
               than any thing that I ever expected to write in that form.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Warning Voice. Ode I’ and ‘The
                  Warning Voice. Ode II’, the New Year’s Odes for 1820 and 1821, not published until they appeared in <title>The Englishman’s Library:
                     Comprising a Series of Historical, Biographical and National Information</title> (London, 1824), pp. 381–389.</note> On the
               present occasion I go to the task with an ill will &amp; with no anticipation of doing any thing well.</p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the Children</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1821-12-08"> Dec 8. 1821.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>