<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 6: 1819-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>David Rettenmaier</name><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2017-01-20</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3645</idno><idno type="nines">rce4916</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3645. Robert Southey to John May, 4–20 March
                  1821</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2017-01-20">January 20, 2017</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Six/HTML/letterEEd.26.3645.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14140.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 62–64 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#DR" when="2016-07-22" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 6</item></list></change><change who="#DR" when="2016-12-23" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Incorporated new header info per Averill Buchanan and other minor fixes.</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3645" type="letter"><head>3645. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1821-03-04">4–20 March
                  1821</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 4. Tavistock Street/
                  Bedford Square<lb/> Stamped: [illegible]<lb/> Postmark: [partial] ‘Clock/ MR/ xxx<lb/> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 218
                  1821/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>–20 March/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April<lb/> MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14140.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 62–64 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1821-03-04"> 4 March. 1821.</date></dateline><salute rend="indent0"> My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday I received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> with the news of
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler’s</ref> death, an event which you will probably have learnt before this
               reaches you. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> is thus relieved from a considerable charge;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Tyler had been a drain on the finances of her half-brother Herbert Hill for many years.</note>
               &amp; from the apprehension which he must have felt of her surviving him. She was in the 82 year of her age. She will be interred
               (tomorrow I suppose) in the burial place of the Hills, where her mother &amp; two of the Tylers are laid, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my father</ref> with five of my brothers &amp; sisters. – <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Long Ashton, Somerset (now a suburb of Bristol), the ancestral home of the Hills and burial place of: Southey’s
                  maternal grandmother Margaret Hill, née Bradford (1710–1782); William Tyler (1742–1789) and Edward Tyler (1744–1786), two of her
                  sons by her first marriage to William Tyler (1709–1747); Southey’s father; and five of Southey’s siblings who had died in infancy,
                  John Cannon Southey (1773–1774), Eliza Southey, Louisa Southey (1779–1782), John Southey (b. 1782) and Margaretta Southey
                  (1787–1788). </note></p><p rend="indent1"> Her death was, even for herself, to be desired as well as expected. My affection for her had been long &amp; justly
               cancelled; I feel no grief therefore, but such an event of necessity presses for a while <del>upon</del> like a weight upon the mind.
               Had it not been for the whim which took her to Lisbon in the year of my birth, you &amp; I should never have known each other, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> would never have seen Portugal,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill had accompanied his half-sister to Portugal in 1774 and had presumably there made the connections that led to him
                  being appointed Chaplain to the British Factory in Oporto in 1777 and to his subsequent career in Portugal for the next thirty
                  years. Hill’s residence in Portugal led to Southey visiting him in 1795–1796 and meeting John May.</note> &amp; in how different a
               course would his life, &amp; mine in consequence have run! – I have known many strange characters in my time, but never so
               extraordinary a one as hers, <del>&amp; hers</del> &lt;which&gt; of course I know intimately. I shall come to it in due course, – &amp;
               sooner than you may expect from the long intervals between my letters.</p><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday’s post brought me also an intimation from my musical colleague <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Shield</ref> that “<ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">our most gracious &amp; royal Master</ref> intends to command the performance of an Ode at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> James,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">St James’s Palace, London, the official base of the monarch and the court.</note> on the day fixed for
               the celebration of his birth day.”<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was required, as Poet Laureate, to commemorate the
                  official birthday of the monarch with an ode, which would be set to music by the Master of the King’s Musick and performed at court.
                  This custom had been suspended since 1810 due to the illness of George III (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820;
                     <title>DNB</title>), but Southey had been informed that it had been reinstated by his successor in 1820. It had been decided that
                  George IV would celebrate his official birthday on St George’s Day, 23 April, apart from years when that fell on a Sunday, when the
                  celebrations would be deferred until Monday 24 April. Southey had therefore written a Birthday Ode for 1820 (the unpublished ‘Ten
                  fateful years have passed away’) and was about to embark upon a second one (‘Ode for St George’s Day’, unpublished until
                     <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837–1838), III, pp. 258–262). Neither ode was performed at court and the
                  tradition lapsed.</note> – Of course therefore my immediate business is to get into harness &amp; work in the mill. Two or three
               precious days will be spent in producing what will be good for nothing; for as for making any thing good of a Birth Day Ode I might as
               well attempt to manufacture silk purses from sows ears. Like Warton, I shall give the poem an historical character, – but I shall not
               do this so well as Warton; who has done it very well.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Warton (1728–1790;
                     <title>DNB</title>), one of Southey’s predecessors as Poet Laureate 1785–1790. Southey admired Warton’s efforts to take the
                  annual odes he was required to write for the New Year and the monarch’s birthday seriously. Here Southey may be thinking of ‘Ode on
                  His Majesty’s Birth-Day’, <title>Gentleman’s Magazine</title>, 63 (June 1788), 540.</note> He was a happy, easy minded, idle man, to
               whom literature in its turn was as much an amusement as rat-hunting, &amp; who never aimed at any thing above such Odes.</p><p rend="indent0"><date when="1820-03-20">March 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi></date></p><p rend="indent1"> I now send you the fourth letter of the promised series, dated at the beginning nearly four months before it was
               brought to an end!<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The fourth of the autobiographical letters Southey was writing for May; see
                  Southey to John May, 1 December 1820–19 March 1821, Letter 3572.</note> Were I to proceed always at this rate with it, I should die
               of old age before I got breeched in the narrative. But with all my undertaking I proceed faster in proportion as I advance in them.
               Just now I am in the humour for going on, &amp; you will hear from me again sooner than you expect, – for I shall begin the next letter
               as soon as this packet is dispatched.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is a long while since I have heard from you, &amp; I am somewhat anxious to hear how your brother<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William Henry May (1785–1849), May’s younger brother and business partner in Brazil.</note> goes on in
               Brazil. Surely he has had time &amp; warning to provide against the storm. – Wretched as the government was both in Portugal &amp;
                  Brazil,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">An army revolt in Oporto in August 1820 had led to the election of a Cortes in
                  December 1820 and demands that the monarchy should return from Brazil, where it had fled from the French invasion in
                  1807–1808.</note> in the latter country certainly, the remedy will be worse than the disease, &amp; in the former the evils of
               revolutionary process are much more certain, than its beneficial end. If O Grande Marquez<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">‘the
                  great Marquis’: Sebastião José de Carvalho e Melo, Marquis of Pombal (1699–1782), Prime Minister of Portugal 1750–1777.</note> could
               have been raised from the dead, he would have had courage &amp; capacity to have modelled both countries according to the circumstances
               of the age. – But I am more anxious about the manner in which these events may affect you, than concerning their general course; – <hi rend="ital">that</hi> is in the will of Providence, &amp; with regard to the state of the Peninsula, &amp; of Italy,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">An army revolt in Spain in January 1820 had led to the restoration of the liberal Constitution of 1812
                  in March 1820; there had also been an army revolt in Naples in July 1820, which also led to the adoption of a liberal
                  constitution.</note> I really see so much evil on <del>all</del> &lt;both&gt; sides, &amp; so much good intent acting erroneously on both,
               that if I could turn the scale with a wish I should not dare to do it.</p><p rend="indent1"> Did you get the portrait<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A portrait of Edith May Southey, John May’s
                  goddaughter. For the three sketches Nash had made of Edith May during his last visit to Greta Hall in 1820, see Robert Southey to
                  John May, 8 April 1821, Letter 3667.</note> from my poor friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> before his
               death? His death is a great grief &amp; a great loss to me.</p><p rend="indent1"> I desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to send you the reprint of the Odes,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A combined second edition of Southey’s Laureate poems <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814) and
                     <title>Odes to His Royal Highness the Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty the Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of
                     Prussia</title> (1814). It was published under the title <title>Carmen Triumphale, for the Commencement of the Year 1814: Carmen
                     Aulica. Written in 1814, on the Arrival of the Allied Sovereigns in England</title> (1821).</note> – &amp; the Vision of
                  Judgement.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> – In my last I
               asked you when the Strong Beer might be tapt &amp; bottled?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">A barrel of strong beer sent to
                  Keswick by John May; see Southey to John May, 29 December 1820, Letter 3595. </note> forget not to answer this important question, I
               have waited your reply with heroic self-denial.</p><p rend="indent1"> We are all tolerably well. I am busy upon the private Memoir which I mentioned in a former letter,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been paid for writing a ‘private Memoir’ of David Pike Watts (1754–1816), a fabulously rich
                  wine merchant and philanthropist, who had been an important supporter of Andrew Bell’s educational schemes and owned the Storrs Hall
                  estate on Windermere. He was also the uncle of the painter John Constable (1776–1837; <title>DNB</title>). The work had been
                  commissioned by Watts’s daughter and heiress, Mary Watts-Russell (1792–1840), who had married in 1811 another heir to a business
                  fortune, Jesse Watts-Russell (1786–1875), MP for Gatton 1820–1826. Southey had mentioned it to John May on 15 November 1820, Letter
                  3556.</note> &amp; which I hope to finish in the course of a month. The printer proceeds very slowly with the Peninsular War.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832). The printer was Thomas
                  Davison (1766–1831).</note> Last week I compleated the revision of that strange story of Lope de Aguirre, &amp; sent it off, to be
               printed in a little volume by itself.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The conquistador Lope de Aguirre (c. 1510–1561),
                  notorious for his final expedition down the Amazon in search of El Dorado. Southey had written an account of these events for the
                     <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), [i]–l. It was revised and republished as <title>The Expedition of
                     Orsua; and the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821).</note> I have also done a good deal to the first vol. of Brazil, which is far
               advanced in the press.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">A second edition of the first volume of the <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1822).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Let me hear from you soon. Where is your son,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">May’s son John (1802–1879).
                  Following his expulsion from Eton in 1818 he was being educated at Thomas Arnold’s (1795–1842; <title>DNB</title>) school at
                  Laleham, near Staines.</note> &amp; how do you think of disposing of him? – Remember me most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>, &amp; to him &amp; your daughters.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">May’s daughters, Mary Charlotte (b. 1804), Susanna Louisa (1805–1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note> To <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> also: – I hope he received <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelleys</ref> correspondence<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith May Southey had
                  made copies of the correspondence in 1820 between Southey and Shelley. These were sent by Southey to John Taylor Coleridge on 19
                  January 1821; see Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, [c. 29 July 1820], Letter 3517, and Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, 12 October
                  1820, Letter 3538. For Shelley’s side, see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline
                     Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 357–366.</note> in which case you will have seen it. Did I tell you of the curious
               communication concerning Wesley which has been made to me, &amp; which perplexes me, – for I hardly now how I ought to act?<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had received information, via John Banks Jenkinson (1781–1840; <title>DNB</title>), the Dean of
                  Worcester 1817–1825, that implied the improper conduct of John Wesley (1703–1791; <title>DNB</title>) towards a female follower,
                  Elizabeth Briggs (1751–1822). He had been unable to confirm the authenticity of the material, though; see Southey to [Glocester
                  Wilson], 29 December 1820, Letter 3596, and Southey to James Everett, 7 February 1821, Letter 3626. </note> – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">My little boy</ref> thrives as well as could be wished, – thank God.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear friend</salute><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>