<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
            <title type="subordinate">About this Edition</title>
            <editor>
               <name>Robert W. Rix</name>
            </editor>
            <editor role="editor">Robert W. Rix</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="nines">rce1044</idno>
            <idno type="edition">about</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
               Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                  or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                  purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                  use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                  are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                  with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                  permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                  requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                  forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                  conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                        without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                        other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                  them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                  have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                  Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                  continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                  generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                  a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">About This Edition</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
                  <title level="m" type="subordinate">Themes in British Literature,
                     1760–1830</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Robert W.</forename>
                        <surname>Rix</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                        Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used for titles.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
               10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
               xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                  on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g21"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <date>2011-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>xslt transforms</item>
               <item>change from APEX to RC TEI encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <div type="section">
         <head>About this Edition</head>
               <p><title level="m">Norse Romanticism: Themes in British Literature, 1760–1830</title> is a collection of texts that illustrate how the ancient North was re-created for contemporary national, political and literary purposes. The anthology features canonical authors (such as <ref target="./Thomas_Gray.html">Thomas Gray</ref>, <ref target="./Blake.html">William Blake</ref>, <ref target="./Wordsworth.html">William Wordsworth</ref>, <ref target="./Southey.html">Robert Southey</ref>, <ref target="./Scott.html">Walter Scott</ref>, and <ref target="./Radcliffe.html">Ann Radcliffe</ref>). Standard editions of these authors’ works generally lack the contextual framework and necessary commentary that explain the way in which they repurpose Norse material. There are also more unusual selections of lesser known writers, whose texts have not previously been available to modern readers. The range of material presented in the edition has the scope and breadth to allow for new research into the Norse-inflected writing during the period.</p>
                  <p>The anthology shows how a number of writers utilized the Norse tradition to address issues of political and cultural concern, as well as find new aesthetic models for their poetry. Importantly, the interest in Norse literature and mythology came at a time when the need to recover ancient literary heritage came under tremendous pressure. Before the discovery of <title level="m">Beowulf</title> (and the realization of its importance), the Norse past was taken up in an attempt to substitute for a missing Anglo-Saxon tradition. In England, the need for Anglo-Saxon heroic verse was given an increased sense of urgency as Celtic antiquaries began to publish heroic traditions associated with Wales, Ireland and not least Ossian’s Scotland. The Norse material also appealed to romantic-era writers for its ideals of Liberty, while the dark Norse imagination was exploited as a vehicle for the creation of Gothic terror. Therefore, the anthology contains texts that will be of relevance to researchers and students pursuing a number of different projects.</p>
                  
                  <p>The introduction, headnotes and extensive annotations place the texts in relation to their original Norse sources. The extensive editorial matter also discusses the perception of the Norse Middle Ages, as these were shaped by sometimes fanciful antiquarian and romanticizing discourses in the period. The electronic edition is a unique resource that makes it easy to compare and search for the characters, themes and ideas that were central to the Norse revival in English letters.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section">
               <head>About The Editor</head>
               <p rend="noCount"><hi>Robert W. Rix</hi> is currently on a contract with the University of Aalborg, Denmark. His project on the reception of the North in Anglophone literature was funded by the Carlsberg Foundation. He has published widely in several areas relating to the eighteenth century: politics, language, poetry, nationalism, and religion. In recent years, Rix has written a number of articles of relevance to the present anthology. These have centered on Norse themes in relation to British discourses of chivalry, romance literature, antiquarianism and the gothic. Rix is also the author of the book <title level="m">William Blake and the Cultures of Radical Christianity</title> (2007) and has edited Charles Pigott’s <title level="m">A Political Dictionary (2005)</title>.</p></div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>About The Design</head>
         <p rend="noCount">
            This hypertext edition was marked up for Romantic Circles by <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/AccessTEI/">APEX CoVantage's AccessTEI service</ref>. It was designed at the University of Maryland by Michael Quilligan, Site Manager at <title level="m">Romantic Circles</title>. The image associated with this edition includes elements from the illustration <title level="a">Ragnarok, The Last Battle</title> from <title level="m">Asgard and the Gods: The Tales and Traditions of our Northern Ancestors, Adapted from the work of Dr. W. Wagner by M. W. MacDowall</title>, edited by W.S.W. Anson, (London [Paternoster Square] : W. Swan Sonnenschein &amp; Allen, 1880). This edition makes extensive use of tables and style sheets for layout and presentation, it will work best when viewed with Internet Explorer and Mozilla Firefox versions 5.0 and higher. The HTML markup is XHTML 1.0 Transitional compliant, as set out by the <ref target="http://www.w3c.org/">World Wide Web Consortium</ref>.</p></div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>