<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
            <title type="subordinate">Themes in British Literature, 1760–1830</title>
            <editor>
               <name>Robert W. Rix</name>
            </editor>
            <editor role="editor">Robert W. Rix</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="nines">rce1004</idno>
            <idno type="edition">Glossary</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                    Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                        forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Glossary</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Robert W.</forename>
                        <surname>Rix</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
                  <title level="m" type="subordinate">Themes in British Literature,
                            1760–1830</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Robert</forename>
                        <surname>W. Rix</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                                Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used for titles.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                        on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g21"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <date>2011-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>xslt transforms</item>
               <item>change from APEX to RC TEI encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:id="book">
      <body>
         <div type="glossary">
            <head>Glossary of Frequently Recurring Terms and Names</head>
            <list type="simple"><item>
               <label>Angantyr</label>. The eldest of twelve sons of the warrior Arngrim.
                        Angantyr was given possession of the  magic sword Tyrfing, which had
                        lightning properties, but killed a man every time it was  unsheathed.
                        His daughter Hervor awakened Angantyr’s ghost in his tomb to
                        successfully claim the  magic sword.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Asgard</label>. The home of the Norse gods known as the <hi rend="ital">Æsir</hi>, ruled over by Odin. Asgard was in the
                         centre of the Norse universe.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Æsir</label>. Warrior deities of the sky, who lived in <hi rend="ital">Asgard</hi>. Based on a false etymology, Snorri Sturluson
                         claimed that the Æsir derived from the word Asia, making them
                        euhemerized warriors from Troy.  They were opposed to the pantheon of
                        (perhaps older deities) Vanir, who were associated with the  earth and
                        fertility. The most important Æsir mentioned in English poetry were
                        Odin and his wife  Frea/Frigg; Thor, the thunder god; and Balder, the
                        dying god.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Balder</label>. Son of Odin by his wife Frea/Frigg. He was seen as the
                        purest and best of the Æsir. His  mother persuaded everything in
                        the world to swear an oath not to harm him, but she did not extract 
                        this promise from the mistletoe. The cunning god Loki tricked the blind god
                        Hoder to aim a dart  made of mistletoe at Balder, which killed him.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Bartholin, Thomas</label> (Bartholinus) (1616–1680). Danish
                        physician, mathematician and antiquary.  Bartholin wrote the patriotic
                        history <hi rend="ital">Antiquitatum Danicarum de causis contemptæ a
                            Danis adhuc  gentilibus mortis</hi> (1689; <hi rend="ital">Danish
                            Antiquities on the Pagan Danes’ Disdain of Death</hi>). This work
                         achieved European-wide fame and became one of the most frequently used
                        sources for information  on the heroic warrior mentality of the
                        Scandinavians and, by extension, the pre-Christian Germanic  world.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Edda. Poetic and Prose</label>. The <hi rend="ital">Poetic Edda</hi>,
                        also known as the <hi rend="ital">Elder Edda</hi>, refers to the collection
                        of  probably pre-Christian poems compiled about 1270. The poems fall
                        into two groups: heroic lays  and mythological lays. The latter group
                        comprises the <hi rend="ital">Völsunga saga</hi>, a history of the
                        Norse gods  from creation to apocalypse, and the <hi rend="ital">Hávamál</hi>, the words of the High One (Odin). In the
                        eighteenth  and nineteenth centuries, this collection was sometimes
                        called <hi rend="ital">Saemund’s Edda</hi>, as it was wrongly 
                        attributed to one Saemund Sigfusson, a writer of the twelfth century.</item>
            <item>The <hi rend="ital">Prose Edda</hi> was written by the Icelander Snorri
                        Sturluson about 1220. It is divided into a  prologue and three parts:
                        the <hi rend="ital">Gylfaginning</hi>, a series of mythological stories told
                        in the form of a  dialogue; the <hi rend="ital">Skáldskaparmál</hi>, in which Snorri illustrates the
                        rules of skaldic verse, while retelling  many myths and legends; and
                        the <hi rend="ital">Háttatal</hi>, a long poem, in which each strophe
                        exemplifies a Norse  metre.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Frea/Frigg</label>. The wife of Odin and goddess of fertility. She
                        often represented as the grieving mother  of Balder, the dying god.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Hel</label>. Both the name of the underworld and the goddess who ruled
                        it. In the Romantic period,  English writers often used the name Hela
                        for the cruel mistress, to distinguish her from her cold  underworld,
                        Hel. From her waist down Hel was rotting flesh. Hel, the location, was where
                        those  who died of sickness or old age would go. The description of
                        this place as surrounded by high walls  and a gate, within which hunger
                        and starvation rule, is found in Snorri Sturluson’s <hi rend="ital">Gylfaginning</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Jotun (Old Norse <hi rend="ital">Jötunn</hi>)</label>. Member
                        of the race of giants, enemies of the gods.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Loki/Loke/Lok</label>. Represented in Norse mythology as a mischievous
                        trickster figure, and sometimes  god of evil. He was the father of
                        Fenrir, the Midgard’s serpent, and Hel. He contrived the death of
                         Odin’s much-loved son Balder and was punished for it by being
                        bound to a rock with chains  until Ragnarök, when he will break
                        free and fight against the Æsir.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Odin</label>. Woden or Wotan in English tradition. He is the principal
                        god in Norse mythology, a deity of  battle, magic, poetic inspiration,
                        and the dead. His name probably meant “wild” or
                        “furious”. He  inspired the feared berserkers, warriors
                        who rushed naked into the midst of battle, inebriated with  fury.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Mead</label>. Drink made by fermenting a mixture of honey and water.
                        In <hi rend="ital">Valhalla</hi>, it is served to the  warriors, when
                        they rest after a long day of fighting. The leaves of the tree
                        Læraðr is eaten by the  goat Heiðrún, which
                        in turn produces mead.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Paul-Henri Mallet (1730–1807)</label>. Geneavean professor in
                        Copenhagen. His two books of interest  are <hi rend="ital">Introduction
                            a l’histoire du Danemarch</hi> (1755, 2<hi rendition="#sup">nd</hi> ed. 1763), a history of the Old North; and 
                        <hi rend="ital">Monuments de la mythologie et de la poesie des Celtes, et
                            particulierement des anciens  Scandinaves</hi> (1756), a
                        translation of Scandinavian legends and Norse literature into a major modern
                         European language for the first time. These were commissioned by the
                        Danish government.  Mallet’s works were translated into the
                        two-volume <hi rend="ital">Northern Antiquities: Or, a Description of the
                             Manners, Customs, Religion and Laws of the Ancient Danes, and
                            Other Northern Nations;  Including Those of Our Own Saxon
                            Ancestors</hi> (1770) by Thomas Percy.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Niflheim</label>. The underworld of eternal cold, darkness and mist.
                        It was the place to which those who  did not die a heroic death on the
                        battlefield would go. It was ruled over by the goddess Hel.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Norns</label>. (Old Norse <hi rend="ital">Nornir</hi>). The three
                        virgin goddesses of destiny (Urd or Urdar, Verdandi, and  Skuld), who
                        sit by the well of fate at the base of the world tree Yggdrasil, where they
                        spin the web  of fate.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Ragnarök</label>. The “End of the Gods”. The
                        original Old Norse form is <hi rend="ital">ragna rök</hi>, from <hi rend="ital">ragna</hi> “of the  gods” and <hi rend="ital">rök</hi> “destined end”, but the
                        variant <hi rend="ital">Ragna rökr</hi> (<hi rend="ital">rökr</hi> “twilight”), which occurs in the 
                        <hi rend="ital">Prose Edda</hi>, has given the often-used translation
                        “twilight of the gods”. In Norse mythology, it is a 
                        final battle between the gods and the powers of evil. According to the myth,
                        the beginning of the  end would be signalled by men fighting each
                        other, fathers killing their sons. A three-year  winter (Fimvulvetr)
                        would then ensue. The wolf, Skoll, would swallow the sun. The wolf Fenrir
                        and  bound Loki would break their bonds. Natural disasters will abound.
                        It is foretold in legend that  Heimdall, the guardian of the
                        Æsir, will sound the Gjallarhorn, alerting the gods to the onset of
                        the  final battle against evil. A major figure on the side of evil is
                        the Giant Sutr, who will fight with his  flaming sword. In this battle,
                        most of the Æsir will die. But out of Ragnarök, a new world
                        will be  born. A new sun will take the place of the old and some gods
                        will return to the ruined Asgard, led  by the resurrected Balder, the
                        best and most beloved of gods.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Raven banner (in Old Norse <hi rend="ital">Hrafnsmerki</hi>)</label>.
                        A flag reported to have been used by Vikings at the  time of their
                        conquests. It was triangular, with a rounded outside edge. It was possibly a
                        symbol  of Odin, who is often depicted with two ravens (Hugin and
                        Munin) and may have served to gain his  favour in war. This type of
                        banner is mentioned in the <hi rend="ital">Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</hi> (<hi rend="ital">sub anno</hi> 878) and a  number of other English
                        sources.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Skald/Scald/Scalder</label>. An Old Norse word for a poet, usually
                        applied to a court poet or bard of the  period from the ninth century
                        to the thirteenth. The skald was a composer and reciter of poems 
                        honouring heroes and their deeds. The accomplishment of poetic composition
                        was counted among  the <hi rend="ital">íþróttir</hi> (“skills”,
                        “art”) suitable for a warrior.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Skuld</label>. See <hi rend="ital">Norns</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Snorri Sturluson (1179–1241)</label>. Icelandic historian and
                        poet, who was a leading figure of medieval  Icelandic literature. He
                        wrote the mythological <hi rend="ital">Prose Edda</hi> and the <hi rend="ital">Heimskringla</hi>, a history of the  kings of Norway
                        from mythical times to the year 1177. He wanted to preserve the stories and
                         methods of skaldic and Eddic poetry for his contemporary Icelandic
                        poets.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Thor.</label> The god of sky and thunder, who was responsible for law
                        and order in the world of humans.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Torfæus, Thormodus (Þormóður Torfason)
                            (1636–1719)</label>. Icelandic historian. Author of <hi rend="ital">Historia  Rerum Norvegicarum</hi> (four volumes, 1711).
                        This Latin history of Norway covers the very earliest  of time to 1387.
                        It contained much historical information on the Old Norse kings.
                        Torfæus uses a  number of saga manuscripts as sources.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Valhalla</label>. Literally, “hall of the slain”. To be
                        rewarded a place here was a privilege reserved for  warriors who fell
                        heroically in battle. In the <hi rend="ital">Gylfaginning</hi> section of
                        the <hi rend="ital">Prose Edda</hi> (c. 1220), the  Icelandic historian
                        and writer Snorri Sturluson created a vigorous image of this place. It was
                         depicted as a glittering palace of spears and a ceiling of shields,
                        presided over by Odin. Fallen  warriors battled each day in endless
                        preparation for Ragnarök, after which they retire for festivities,
                         where drink and mead were provided afresh each night, served by
                        Valkyries</item>
            <item>
               <label>Valkyries.</label> Odin’s twelve handmaids who conducted the
                        slain warriors which they picked from the  battlefield to Valhalla. The
                        Old Norse <hi rend="ital">Valkyrja</hi> is literally “chooser of the
                        slain”. The Valkyries are  fate-weavers and therefore approach
                        the role of the Norse Norns, who rule the destiny of men. From  the
                        surviving body of poetry, it is sometimes difficult to maintain a hard
                        distinction between the two  species of female deities (<hi rend="ital">dísir</hi>). This is why the Valkyries are
                        “weavers” of fates in Thomas Gray’s  adaptation
                        “The Fatal Sisters”.</item>
            <item>
               <label>Völva</label>. A prophetess, seeress. In Old Norse society, a
                        female practitioner of magic divination and  the foretelling of events.
                        According to the myth of Odin, which several Romantic writers took up, 
                        this god called up a seeress from the dead, who told him how the world would
                        end.</item></list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>