<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
            <title type="subordinate">Robert Hole</title>
            <editor>
               <name>Robert W. Rix</name>
            </editor>
            <editor role="editor">Robert W. Rix</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="nines">rce1016</idno>
            <idno type="edition">Richard_Hole</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                    Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                        forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Extract from <title>Arthur; or, the Northern Enchantment. A Poetical Romance, in Seven Books</title>
                  </title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Robert</forename>
                        <surname>Hole</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
                  <title level="m" type="subordinate">Themes in British Literature,
                            1760–1830</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Robert W.</forename>
                        <surname>Rix</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                                Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used for titles.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                        on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5 #g27"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <date>2011-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>xslt transforms</item>
               <item>change from APEX to RC TEI encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:id="book">
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <anchor xml:id="intro"/>
            <head>Richard Hole (1746–1803)</head>
            <p>Richard Hole was a graduate from Oxford University, who considered a military
                        career, but was  eventually ordained in the Church of England. He held
                        the curacy of Sowton, and later Buckerell,  both near Exeter. He
                        contributed to several periodicals, such as the <hi rend="ital">Monthly
                            Review, British  Magazine</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, and, most notably, a series of
                        satirical dialogues to the 
                        <hi rend="ital">London Magazine</hi> during 1782. In 1789, Hole published a
                        paraphrase of a passage from <hi rend="ital">Njals saga</hi>,  which he
                        entitled “The Tomb of Gunnar”. The source was a Latin
                        translation by Thomas Bartholin.  In Hole’s adaptation, Gunnar,
                        a famous warrior of outstanding prowess, awakes in his tomb to raise  a
                        “loud-resounding song”. When Hogner, Gunnar’s son,
                        arrives with his friend Sarhedine (versions  of the Saga-names <hi rend="ital">Högni</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Skarpheðinn</hi>) to investigate, Gunnar delivers a poetic
                        clarion call to  martial fortitude: “Unmanly flight the brave
                        despise/ Conquest of death is the warrior’s prize!”<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">“The
                                Tomb of Gunnar, Imitated from an Ancient Islandic Fragment,
                                preserved by Bartholin”, <hi rend="ital">Gentleman’s
                                    Magazine</hi>
                                 (October 1789): 937.</note> The  reason for
                        Hole’s interest, given his later poetic focus on heroic romance,
                        seems to be the  dramatization of how valiant virtues of the past may
                        be communicated through poetry to a new age.</p>
            <p>Hole was a founding member of a literary society at Exeter, whose members
                        included Richard  Polwhele, Hugh Downman, and William Jackson. Hole
                        wrote a number of Miltonic odes that  appeared in the society’s
                        publication <hi rend="ital">Poems Chiefly by Gentlemen of Devonshire and
                            Cornwall</hi>
                         (1792). This also included a new version of “The Tomb of
                        Gunnar”, which was printed alongside a  number of other Norse
                        translations concerned with the heroic (including Regnar’s Death
                        Song). The  collection was partly a response to the debates over the
                        French Revolution; and the Norse poems  were surrounded by several
                        patriotic and alarmist pieces. The collection was edited by Richard 
                        Polwhele, who would later emerge as a prolific anti-Jacobin.</p>
            <p>Hole’s major work, <hi rend="ital">Arthur, or, The Northern
                            Enchantments</hi>, is a romance epic in seven books,  written in
                        imitation of both Ariosto and Ossian. It is an Arthuriad, focussing on how
                        Arthur’s  Britons encountered the invading Saxons and
                        Scandinavians in the fifth century. An essential part  of the action
                        concerns the magician Merlin’s daughter, who is betrothed to Arthur.
                        However,  Hengist, the legendary leader of the Germanic invasion,
                        according to the Venerable Bede, also  woos her. However, Anglo-Saxon
                        practices are confounded with Scandinavian ideals of the Viking  age.
                        Hole further assumes that Scandinavians were part of the invasion force,
                        placing the Danish  leader Valdemar as a cohort of Hengist (perhaps
                        inspired by <ref target="./Macpherson.html">James Macpherson’s</ref> description of  Anglo-Saxon
                        culture through the use of examples taken from Old Norse literature in <hi rend="ital">An  Introduction to the History of Great Britain and
                            Ireland</hi> (1771; rev. ed, 1772, 1773). However, in  the
                        scholarly preface to <hi rend="ital">Arthur</hi>, Hole repeats the argument
                        made by Thomas Percy that the medieval  romance tradition originated in
                        Scandinavia: the ideals of chivalry and Scandinavian manners were 
                        “really and originally the same”.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">Hole, <hi rend="ital">Arthur</hi>, pp. xi–xii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hole’s romance is an examination of early heroism in Britain. He shows
                        how the Anglo-  Saxon/Scandinavian warriors were motivated by their
                        superstition: the conviction of heavenly  rewards for the fallen
                        warrior and the fear of a terrible abode for those who die an unheroic
                        death.  The poem is awash with references to magic and incantations,
                        pitting Merlin against Urda, the  Norse goddess of fate, who assists
                        Hengist and Valdemar. Much Gothic horror emerges from the  use of
                        magic.</p>
            <p>The extract below is taken from Book four of the poem, in which Valdemar,
                        king of Denmark,  and the northern chieftains are feasting in Calisle,
                        when Urda adopts the form of Odin and appears  to them. She exhorts the
                        Scandinavian warriors to show the death-defying courage for which they 
                        were known and march against the Britons, who are marching towards them.</p>
            <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">***</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poetry">
            <anchor xml:id="text"/>
            <head>From Book four of <hi rend="ital">Arthur; or, the Northern Enchantment. A
                            Poetical Romance</hi> (1789)</head>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>In Carlile’s lofty hall, in festive state,</l>
               <l>The Dacian monarch<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">
                      Dacia = medieval term for Denmark.
                                    The king is Valdemar</note> mid his heroes sate.</l>
               <l>In Hengist’s absence, such the king’s commands,</l>
               <l>Th’ appointed leader of the Northern bands.</l>
               <l>Ill-brook’d by Hacon, grown in combats grey,</l>
               <l>Norway’s dread lord, beneath whose iron sway</l>
               <l>E’en distant Thule groan’d, and lands unknown</l>
               <l>To fame, that stretch beneath the frigid zone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Sullen and stern he marks the genial rites;</l>
               <l>The music charms not, nor the feast delights.</l>
               <l>Sweno in silent grief his father view’d,</l>
               <l>A generous youth with milder thoughts endued;</l>
               <l>And lovely as the rosy morn that streams</l>
               <l>Thro vernal showers its joy-diffusing beams:</l>
               <l>Whose voice when untam’d passions sway’d his soul</l>
               <l>Alone could sooth his woes, or rage controul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>The goblet circles; the resounding lyre,</l>
               <l>And lofty strain heroic thoughts inspire.</l>
               <l>Some vaunt their high exploits in former wars:</l>
               <l>Some shew their batter’d shields, and deep-trenched scars:</l>
               <l>In brutal riot some the hours employ,</l>
               <l>And all is dissonance, and barbarous joy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Sudden, dark clouds the rafter’d dome
                            o’ercast;</l>
               <l>Upwards they turn their anxious eyes aghast:</l>
               <l>And thro’ the quick disparting shades behold</l>
               <l>Dread Odin, seated on his throne of gold.</l>
               <l>Black vapors, such as clothe the wintry night,</l>
               <l>His foot-stool form’d; a meteor’s vivid light</l>
               <l>His brows encircled: radiant arms he wore,</l>
               <l>And shook his flaming lance distain’d with gore,</l>
               <l>Loud as when thunder roars he silence broke –</l>
               <l>The vast dome trembled as the phantom spoke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>“Offspring of heroes! fam’d in fields of
                            fight,</l>
               <l>“Who sport in danger, and in death delight,</l>
               <l>“Docs this become you, sons of battle! say,</l>
               <l>“To wear in shameful sloth the hours away?</l>
               <l>“Is this a time to feast in bower or hall,</l>
               <l>“When foes advancing to the combat call?</l>
               <l>“The host you deem’d beneath the roaring main</l>
               <l>“O’erwhelm’d, defies you to the lifted plain.</l>
               <l>“The cloud of war on Cambria’s height impends</l>
               <l>“No more, but darkly-lowering hither bends.</l>
               <l>“Awake, arise, and in your might confide!</l>
               <l>“Rush on, and let destruction be your guide!</l>
               <l>“Think on your fathers’ fame, your own renown,</l>
               <l>“My favour, who with joys perpetual crown</l>
               <l>“The chiefs, who boldly in the combat fall,</l>
               <l>“And guide their spirits to my lofty hall,</l>
               <l>“O’er-arch’d with golden shields, whose dazzling
                  blaze<note place="foot" resp="author" type="original">
                                     Hole’s note: “The Scandinavian
                                    Valhalla, like the Mahometan Paradise, was supposed to have been
                                    roofed with  shields. The Valkeries were employed by Odin
                                    to choose in battle these who were to perish, and like the
                                    Houries to wait  on the selected heroes. These
                                    ‘Posters of the sea and land” have been confounded
                                    by other writers, as well as  Shakespeare, with the
                                    northern Parcæ or <hi rend="ital">Destinies</hi>: but the
                                    latter, according to, Scandinavian mythology, had their 
                                    abode near the great ash Ygdrasil in Asgard, or <hi rend="ital">city of the gods</hi>. Skulda only, the youngest of them,
                                    is mentioned in the  Edda, as accompanying the Valkeries,
                                    when encased in fulfilling the commands of Odin. From these
                                    beautiful  Divinities, so they were once esteemed, who
                                    bestrode the “sightless coursers of the air,’ was
                                    most probably derived in  subsequent times (with grief be
                                    it spoken) the degrading idea of witches riding upon
                                    broomsticks. At least, so soon as  Christianity began to
                                    prevail, severe edicts were promulgated in different kingdoms
                                    against those who travelled through  the air in the
                                    night-time. The belief in such nocturnal flight, scarcely yet
                                    exploded among our country people, was the  fashionable
                                    creed in the days of James the First
                                …”.</note>
               </l>
               <l>“Exceeds the mid-day sun’s unclouded rays.</l>
               <l>“There shall each hero share, a welcome guest,</l>
               <l>“The foaming goblet, and perpetual feast.</l>
               <l>“Again their souls with martial fire shall burn,</l>
               <l>“And host conflicting adverse host o’erturn:</l>
               <l>“While bright Valkeries, blue-eyed nymphs shall crown</l>
               <l>“With plausive smiles their actions of renown.</l>
               <l>“Be conquest yours, and fame’s unfading wreath,</l>
               <l>“Or, more than victory, a glorious death!”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>This said, the dark’ning cloud, the
                            meteor’s glare</l>
               <l>And stately form dissolves, and melts in air.</l>
               <l>“Be all our warriors summon’d to the field!</l>
               <l>“Cried Valdemar, and struck his echoing shield:</l>
               <l>“On every height your banners wide unfold!</l>
               <l>“At morn we march; and let the sun behold,</l>
               <l>“As in the purpled East he rises bright,</l>
               <l>“Our arms of splendor emulate his light!”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>“Tho’ Valdemar’s proud banners
                            brave the skies</l>
               <l>“Beneath his sway we march not; Hacon cries.</l>
               <l>“Know, tho’ a God commands, the soul is free,</l>
               <l>“To mortal power we scorn to bend the knee,</l>
               <l>“Or yield subjection—no, were Hengift here,</l>
               <l>“Whose distrust I admire, and fame revere,</l>
               <l>“Thus had I spoke: nor deem my words, O king!</l>
               <l>“From mean distrust, or canker’d envy spring.</l>
               <l>“To lead the Danes, the Saxon bands, be thine;</l>
               <l>“So Hengist will’d, but Norway’s sons are mine.</l>
               <l>“Resolv’d as brave allies your cause to own,</l>
               <l>“And no superior but their king alone.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Cerdic and Ida, Saxons far renown’d,</l>
               <l>Upstarting at the word, indignant frown’d.</l>
               <l>In fiercer wrath the Dacian chieftains rise;</l>
               <l>Biorno, Grimal, roll their silent eyes,</l>
               <l>As secretly they grasp the ready blade,</l>
               <l>On their lov’d lord. He, doubtful, long survey’d</l>
               <l>His haughty rival; but reflection quell’d</l>
               <l>The vengeful thoughts that in his bosom swell’d,</l>
               <l>“If Hacon at our rule, he cried, repine,</l>
               <l>“Be his apart to lead Norwegian line.</l>
               <l>“Brave are thy warriors, and a foe draws nigh,</l>
               <l>“Who soon their prowess will severely try.</l>
               <l>“Then, generous emulation be our aim,</l>
               <l>“Best to deserve, and win the meed of fame!”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Performing barbarous rites, a gloomy band,</l>
               <l>The priests all night before their altars stand.</l>
               <l>Meanwhile, in cadence low, or choral chime,</l>
               <l>The bards alternate wake the Runic rhyme,<note place="foot" resp="author" type="original">Hole’s note:
                                    “The invention of letters is attributed to Odin, and in
                                    the Edda of Sæmund Frode, he is called the ‘fire
                                    of  spells.’ In an old poem entitled the Runic
                                    Chapter, or the Magic of Odin. (Mallet V. 2.) he boasts that by
                                    the use of the  Runic characters, and power of poetical
                                    numbers, he could raise the dead, and produce the most strange
                                    and miraculous  effects.—These characters, it may be
                                    supposed, were merely the common letters of the Gothic alphabet,
                                    and represented  by those few who could write and read, as
                                    possessing a mysterious nature and hidden virtue their barbarous
                                     countrymen. Sheringham asserts, that after the
                                    introduction of Christianity, its zealous converts not only
                                    destroyed a  great number of these pretended charms, but
                                    defaced many records and monumental inscriptions, by which means
                                    the  history of the Goths has been irreparably injured.
                                    Many of the lower class of people still attribute a hidden
                                    virtue to  amulets and magical inscriptions; an opinion
                                    doubtless derived from our Gothic forefathers. In progress of
                                    time the less  they were understood, the more mysterious
                                    and terrible they appeared to be; and the old mode of writing
                                    was called,  and now is, by many who little apprehend its
                                    origin, <hi rend="ital">casting a
                                figure</hi>”.</note>
               </l>
               <l>With mystic import fraught: but chief to thee,</l>
               <l>Swells the full peal of mingled harmony,</l>
               <l>Dread god of battle! so they fondly deem,</l>
               <l>Bewilder’d, lost in error’s fatal dream.</l>
               <l>Now, a vain shadow, and an empty name,</l>
               <l>Is he, who foremost trod the fields of fame.</l>
               <l>Not his the form that struck their wond’ring sight,</l>
               <l>Urda that form assum’d thro’ magic sleight.</l>
               <l>And whilst their rugged altars stream with gore,</l>
               <l>And their wild cries the hapless victims pour;</l>
               <l>Whilst loft in trance extatic seems the seer,</l>
               <l>Whose words as heaven’s high dictates they revere,</l>
               <l>Urda his foul with high-wrought frenzy fires,</l>
               <l>And fate’s ambiguous oracles inspires.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>“Sons of the North! ignoble fear despise;</l>
               <l>“Propitious smiles the god who rules the skies:</l>
               <l>“And, as the wild winds, mingling in their course,</l>
               <l>“O’erturn the forest with united force;</l>
               <l>“Your strength united shall dismay the foe;</l>
               <l>“And lay the towering ranks of battle low.</l>
               <l>“Unwonted fear shall seize the hostile band,</l>
               <l>“And the pois’d lance drop from the valiant hand.</l>
               <l>“Unless your heroes first in arms renwn’d,</l>
               <l>“Plant in each other’s breasted deadly wound;</l>
               <l>“Arthur shall ne’er the British throne ascend;</l>
               <l>“But all his dream of pride in ruin end.”</l>
               <l>He ceas’d; convulsions shook his lab’ring
                            frame,</l>
               <l>And his red eye-balls gleam’d with living flame;*</l>
               <l>Then, as th’ inspiring fiend forsook his breast,</l>
               <l>He sunk unconscious in the arms of rest.</l>
               <l>With loud acclaim the priests and minstrel train,</l>
               <l>The presage hail, and pour the suppliant strain.</l>
               <l>“Hear, mighty father of thy battle! hear,</l>
               <l>“Lift thy broad buckler, shake the flashing spear</l>
               <l>“With wrath’s dark cloud thy aweful brows invest,</l>
               <l>“And scatter terror from thy nodding crest!</l>
               <l>“The foes shall fink beneath the dreadful sight,</l>
               <l>“And ghastly horror seize them in the fight.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Faint streaks of light shoot thro’ the eastern
                            skies,</l>
               <l>And wrapt in mist the distant mountains rise.</l>
               <l>As round their hollow oak bees swarming play,</l>
               <l>When the sun downward shoots his fervid ray,</l>
               <l>Athwart, direct, along the echoing plain</l>
               <l>In wild confusion pour the martial train;</l>
               <l>Till rang’d in order by their leader’s care,</l>
               <l>The clarion founds, and onward rolls the war.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>In two black columns their destructive way</l>
               <l>They bend; like clouds in summer’s sultry day:</l>
               <l>Each in his womb the lurking thunder hides,</l>
               <l>And waving lightnings edge their sable sides.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>In Nubia’s desarts, by th’ attractive
                            beam</l>
               <l>Of heaven exhal’d, as poisonous vapours steam,</l>
               <l>Ascend the skies, and from their flagging wings</l>
               <l>Shake pestilence, and death’s pernicious flings</l>
               <l>Such havoc marks their course; by sword, by fire,</l>
               <l>The land lies waste, and man and beast expire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Where Deva’s streams the Cestrian plains
                            divide,</l>
               <l>Hacon and Denmark’s lord, on either fide,</l>
               <l>High-towering in their battle’s front, pursu’d</l>
               <l>Their rapid way: at length the warriors view’d</l>
               <l>The distant heights in clouds of dust array’d,</l>
               <l>And arms faint-gleaming thro’ the rolling shade.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>“Behold, fierce Hacon cried, behold our foes!</l>
               <l>“(Whilst in his soul the martial transport rose)</l>
               <l>“To rage unbounded give the loosen’d rein!</l>
               <l>“Banquet your hungry falchions on the slain!</l>
               <l>“Impel, as meteors cleave the vault of night,</l>
               <l>“A radiant fliower! yourfliafts’ deftrucive flight!</l>
               <l>“In British blood the vengeful spear embrue,</l>
               <l>“And give the sacrifice to Odin due!”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Fired by their monarch’s words, his daring
                            train</l>
               <l>Advanc’d impetuous o’er the founding plain.</l>
               <l>As Valdemar their rapid march beheld,</l>
               <l>Athwart the current swiftly he impell’d</l>
               <l>His bounding steed; the furious king addrest,</l>
               <l>And thus the ardour of his soul represt.</l>
               <l>“If terror-struck yon warriors shun’d the fight,</l>
               <l>“It then were fit to urge their shameful flight;</l>
               <l>“But lo! defiance stern their battle wears:</l>
               <l>“Still, as of old, amid the shock of spears,</l>
               <l>“On highest deeds resolv’d is Britain’s train,</l>
               <l>“To die or conquer—fame to give or gain.</l>
               <l>“Then, let us wait till morn the skies illume,</l>
               <l>“To prove our matchless force, and seal their doom.</l>
               <l>“For see, the sun descending from his height,</l>
               <l>“Discloses many a gulf of dazzling light</l>
               <l>“Thro’ black, obstructing clouds that westward rise;</l>
               <l>“And now in sanguine radiance cloaths the skies.</l>
               <l>“A dreadful omen of the coming day</l>
               <l>“To Britain’s race. Soon o’er their destin’d
                            prey</l>
               <l>“The birds of heaven shall shake their founding wings,</l>
               <l>“Exulting—the gaunt wolf shall feast on kings.</l>
               <l>“’Tis ours, let dastards veil their acts in night,</l>
               <l>“To claim the sun a witness to our might.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Hacon assents: heaven’s setting splendors
                            gild</l>
               <l>The snow-white tents.—Thus scatter’d o’er the
                            field,</l>
               <l>Appears the fleecy flock at even tide,</l>
               <l>Recumbent by the fountain’s rushy fide.</l>
               <l>Not thrice an arrow’s flight across the plain</l>
               <l>Approach the vanguard of the hostile train.</l>
               <l>Their cornets found; their fiery coursers neigh,</l>
               <l>And high in air their waving banners play.</l>
            </lg>
            <p rend="noCount">END OF BOOK FOURTH.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bib">
            <p rend="noCount">Source: Richard Hole, <title>Arthur; or, the Northern Enchantment. A
                Poetical Romance, in Seven Books</title> (London: G. G. J.  and J.
                Robinson, 1789), 117–31.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>