<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
            <title type="subordinate">Thomas Gray</title>
            <editor>
               <name>Robert W. Rix</name>
            </editor>
            <editor role="editor">Robert W. Rix</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor,</resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="nines">rce1021</idno>
            <idno type="edition">Thomas_Gray</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                    Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                        notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
                        forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">“The Fatal Sisters”, “The Descent of Odin”</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Thomas</forename>
                        <surname>Gray</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" type="main">Norse Romanticism: </title>
                  <title level="m" type="subordinate">Themes in British Literature,
                            1760–1830</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Robert W.</forename>
                        <surname>Rix</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
                                Maryland</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011-11-01">November 1, 2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>APEX used utf-8 codes for quotation marks, hyphens, and all special characters; except in the introduction, "hi rend="ital" has been used for titles.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smcap" scheme="css">font-variant:small-caps;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
                      xml:id="genre">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
                        on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5 #g27"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <date>2011-11-01</date>
            <list>
               <item>xslt transforms</item>
               <item>change from APEX to RC TEI encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:id="book">
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <anchor xml:id="intro"/>
            <head>Thomas Gray (1716–1771)</head>
            <p>Thomas Gray was one of the most influential and popular poets of the
                        eighteenth century. He first  achieved success in 1751 with the
                        publication of “Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard”. Gray
                        is  connected with the poetry of sensibility and seen as a precursor
                        for many of the developments that  would lead to the flowering of
                        Romanticism. Gray was also a scholar, who took an interest in both  Old
                        Norse and Celtic traditions. However, the two Icelandic poems included here
                        were translated  into English via Latin versions. Gray composed his
                        translations in 1761, but they would await  publication until the
                        bookseller Robert Dodsley included them in the 1768 edition of Gray’s
                            <hi rend="ital">Poems</hi>.</p>
            <p>In a short “Advertisement” prefacing the poems, Gray explains
                        that the odes were intended to  illustrate Norse verse as an early
                        influence on English poetry:</p>
            <q>The Author once had thoughts (in concert with a Friend) of giving <hi rend="ital">the History of English Poetry:</hi>
                         In the Introduction to it he meant to have produced some specimens of
                        the Style that reigned in  ancient times among the neighbouring
                        nations, or those who had subdued the greater part of this  Island, and
                        were our Progenitors: the following three Imitations made a part of them. He
                        has  long since drop’d his design, especially after he had
                        heard, that it was already in the hands of a  Person well qualified to
                        do it justice, both by his taste, and his researches into antiquity.</q>
            <p>The history of English poetry was planned with the minor poet <ref tagrget="./Mason.html">William
                            Mason</ref> (the “Friend”  referred to above), but it
                        was never completed. The “Person” mentioned in the last line
                        is the poet  and antiquary Thomas Warton (1728–1790), to whom
                        Gray sent his notes, after he decided to  abandon the project. Warton
                        published his <hi rend="ital">History of English Poetry in three volumes
                            between</hi>
                         1774 and 1781. In the preface to the first volume, Warton refers to
                        Gray’s aborted plans.</p>
            <p>The scholarly value of the odes, as representative of the Norse
               “style” influencing the development of English verse, is vitiated by the fact that both pieces are imaginative recreations
                         rather than translations (“The Fatal Sisters” more so
                        than “The Descent of Odin”). Evidently,  Gray’s
                        re-imagining of these poems suited eighteenth-century preoccupation with the
                        Gothic and  superstitious, and they became enormously popular. The odes
                        were often reprinted, cited, imitated  and even parodied.</p>
            <p>The Norse original of <hi rend="ital">The Fatal Sisters. An Ode</hi> is found
                        in chapter 157 of <hi rend="ital">Njáls saga</hi> (13<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi>
                         century). The poem relates to the Battle of Clontarff, near Dublin in
                        1014. It centres on the image of  the Valkyries, who are singing about
                        the outcome of this battle. The song is recorded by a passer-  by.</p>
            <p>The original is known as <hi rend="ital">Darraðarljóð</hi> (“Lay of Darts”).
                        Through metaphoric association, the  Valkyries’ weaving and
                        cutting of human lives on the loom of fate is compared to the web of 
                        arrows in the air over the battlefield. The type of loom referred to in the
                        poem used a movable rod  connected with loops to the back threads; this
                        rod is called <hi rend="ital">skapt</hi>, which is the word also used for
                         the pole of a spear or other weapon (as in ON <hi rend="ital">spjótskapt</hi>, “spear-shaft”). In fact, the poem
                        is a major  documentary source for information about weaving in
                            Scandinavia.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1">
                                 See Jenny Jochens, <hi rend="ital">Women in Old Norse
                                    Society</hi> (Ithaca, NY: London: Cornell University Press
                                1995), 136–7.  The poem describes a standing loom
                                consisting of two posts on top of which rests a crossbeam. Threads
                                were weighted at  the bottom with stones or other heavy
                                objects.</note> But Gray is primarily  interested in its
                        imaginative effects and the horrific image of female deities weaving a cloth
                        from  human intestines on a loom weighted by human heads.</p>
            <p>An undated entry in Gray’s Commonplace Book, entitled
                        “Gothic”, refers to the poem as “The  Song of the
                        Weird Sisters, or Valkyries”.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">See William Powell Jones, <hi rend="ital">Thomas Gray. Scholar</hi> [1937] (repr. New York:
                                Russell &amp; Russell, 1964), 103.</note> Shakespeare critics
                        of the eighteenth century asserted that  the “weird
                        Sisters” in <hi rend="ital">Macbeth</hi> were based on Scottish
                        folklore; in turn this was a corrupt remnant  of Old Norse religion
                        (parts of lowland Scotland had been occupied by Vikings).<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">Shakespeare’s
                                early eighteenth-century editor Lewis Theobald had identified
                                Shakespeare’s Weird Sisters with “the  Fates of
                                the northern nations; the three hand maids of <hi rend="ital">Odin</hi>” in his edition of 1726. This assertion was
                                repeated by  William Warburton in his edition of
                                Shakespeare’s works (1747).</note> Shakespeare’s
                         “weird sisters” play an important role in deciding the
                        fortunes of the agents in the play.  Furthermore, the English <hi rend="ital">weird</hi> is cognate of the Old Norse <hi rend="ital">urðr</hi> (“fate”). Although Gray does not 
                        mention it, the purported link between the Norse “fatal
                        sisters” and Shakespeare’s witches was  certainly a
                        reason for including this poem as an example of early influence on the
                        development of  English literary history.</p>
            <p>Gray’s version is a rather free paraphrase of the original. Some lines
                        bear no relationship to the  Latin text, from which he worked. The
                        first atmospheric stanza, for example, has no equivalent in  the
                        source. At other times, Gray can be seen to intensify the descriptions of
                        the original. To mention  just one example, the line: “Gored
                        with many a gaping wound” (l. 42) adds colour to the simple 
                        description of being shot to death by arrows, where the Latin source simply
                        has <hi rend="ital">sagittis occubuit  comes</hi> (“from arrows
                        the Earl is dead”). Furthermore, Gray liberally interpolates
                        adjectives such as  “griesly”, “gasping”,
                        and “trembling” throughout. For comparison, Gray’s
                        Latin source text and the  Icelandic original can be seen here.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">The poem was
                                first translated in Thomas Bartholin’s <hi rend="ital">Antiquitatum Danicarum De Causis Contemptae A Danis Adhuc 
                                    Gentilibus Mortis</hi> (Copenhagen, 1689), 617–24. It was
                                later reproduced in Thormodus Torfæus’s <hi rend="ital">Orcades Seu Rerum  Orcadensium Historiae</hi>
                                (Copenhagen, 1697), 36–8. Bartholin’s Latin text
                                reads:<lg type="verse">
                     <l>Late diffunditur</l>
                     <l>Ante stragem futuram</l>
                     <l>Sagittarum nubes:</l>
                     <l>Depluit sanguis:</l>
                     <l>Iam hastis applicatur</l>
                     <l rend="noCount">Cineracea</l>
                     <l>Tela virorum</l>
                     <l>Quam amicae texunt</l>
                     <l>Rubro subtegmine [i.q. subtemine.</l>
                     <l>Randveri mortis.</l>
                     <l>Texitur haec Tela</l>
                     <l>Intestinis humanis,</l>
                     <l>Staminique stricte alligantur</l>
                     <l>Capita humana,</l>
                     <l>Sunt sanguine roratae</l>
                     <l>Hastae pro Insilibus</l>
                     <l>Textoria Instrumenta ferrea</l>
                     <l>Ac Sagittae pro Radiis:</l>
                     <l>Densabimus Gladiis</l>
                     <l>Hanc Victoriae Telam.</l>
                     <l>Prodeunt ad texendum Hilda</l>
                     <l>Et Hiorthrimula,</l>
                     <l>Sargrida et Swipula</l>
                     <l>Cum strictis Gladiis;</l>
                     <l>Hastile frangetur,</l>
                     <l>Scutum diffindetur,</l>
                     <l rend="noCount">Ensisque</l>
                     <l>Clypeo illidetur.</l>
                     <l>Texamus, texamus</l>
                     <l>Telam Darradar!</l>
                     <l>Hunc (Gladium) Rex Juvenis</l>
                     <l>Prius possidebat.</l>
                     <l>Prodeamus,</l>
                     <l>Et Cohortes entremus</l>
                     <l>Ubi nostri Amici</l>
                     <l>Armis dimicant!</l>
                     <l>Texamus, texamus</l>
                     <l>Telam Darradi;</l>
                     <l>Et Regi deinde</l>
                     <l>Deinde adhaereamus!</l>
                     <l>Ibi videbant</l>
                     <l>Sanguine rorata scuta</l>
                     <l>Gunna et Gondula</l>
                     <l>Quae Regem tutabantur.</l>
                     <l>Texamus, texamus</l>
                     <l>Telam Darradi!</l>
                     <l>Ubi Arma concrepant</l>
                     <l>Bellacium Virorum</l>
                     <l>Non sinamus eum</l>
                     <l>Vita privari:</l>
                     <l>Habent Valkyriae</l>
                     <l>Csedis potestatem.</l>
                     <l>Illi Populi terras regent</l>
                     <l>Qui deserta Promontoria</l>
                     <l>Antea incolebant.</l>
                     <l>Dico potenti Regi</l>
                     <l>Mortem imminere</l>
                     <l>Jam Sagittis occubuit Comes:</l>
                     <l>Et Hibernis</l>
                     <l>Dolor accidet,</l>
                     <l>Qui nunquam</l>
                     <l>Apud Viros delebitur.</l>
                     <l>Jam Tela texta est.</l>
                     <l>Campus vero (Sanguine) roratus:</l>
                     <l>Terras percurret</l>
                     <l>Conflictus Militum.</l>
                     <l>Nunc horrendum est</l>
                     <l>Circumspicere</l>
                     <l>Cum Sanguinea Nubes</l>
                     <l>Per Aera volitet:</l>
                     <l>Tingetur Aer</l>
                     <l>Sanguine Virorum,</l>
                     <l>Antequam Vaticinia nostra</l>
                     <l>Omnia corruent.</l>
                     <l>Bene canimus</l>
                     <l>De Rege juvene,</l>
                     <l>Victoriae carmina multa:</l>
                     <l>Bene sit nobis canentibus!</l>
                     <l>Discat autem ille</l>
                     <l>Qui auscultat</l>
                     <l>Bellica Carmina multa</l>
                     <l>Et Viris referat.</l>
                     <l>Equitemus in Equis</l>
                     <l>Quoniam efferimus gladios strictos</l>
                     <l>Ex hoc loco.</l>
                  </lg>The original Icelandic text is here transcribed (from <hi rend="ital">Íslendínga sögur</hi>, vol. 4. <hi rend="ital">Njála</hi> [Copenhagen: S. L. Möllers
                                 bogtrykkeri,  1875], 899–900].<lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>1.</label> Vítt er orpit</l>
                     <l>fyrir valfalli</l>
                     <l>rifs reiðiský,</l>
                     <l>rignir blóði ;</l>
                     <l>nú er fyrir geirum</l>
                     <l>grár upp kominn</l>
                     <l>vefr verþjóðar,</l>
                     <l>er þær vinur fylla</l>
                     <l>rauðum vepti</l>
                     <l>Randvés bana.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>2.</label> Sjá er orpinn vefr</l>
                     <l>ýta þörmum</l>
                     <l>ok harðkléaðr</l>
                     <l>höfðum manna ;</l>
                     <l>eru dreyrrekin</l>
                     <l>dörr at sköptum,</l>
                     <l>járnvarðr yllir,</l>
                     <l>en örum hrælaðr ;</l>
                     <l>skulum slá sverðum</l>
                     <l>sigrvef þenna.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>3.</label> Gengr Hildr vefa</l>
                     <l>ok Hjörþrimul,</l>
                     <l>Sanngríðr, Svipul</l>
                     <l>sverðum tognum;</l>
                     <l>skapt mun gnesta,</l>
                     <l>skjöldr mun bresta,</l>
                     <l>mun hjálmgagarr</l>
                     <l>í hlíf koma.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>4.</label> Vindum, vindum</l>
                     <l>vef darraðar,</l>
                     <l>þann er ungr konungr</l>
                     <l>átti fyrri!</l>
                     <l>Fram skulum ganga</l>
                     <l>ok í fólk vaða,</l>
                     <l>þar er vinir várir</l>
                     <l>vápnum skipta.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>5.</label> Vindum, vindum</l>
                     <l>vef darraðar</l>
                     <l>ok siklingi</l>
                     <l>síðan fylgjum!</l>
                     <l>Þar sjá bragna</l>
                     <l>blóðgar randir</l>
                     <l>Guðr ok Göndul,</l>
                     <l>er grami hlífðu.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>6.</label> Vindum, vindum</l>
                     <l>vef darraðar,</l>
                     <l>þars er vé vaða</l>
                     <l>vígra manna!</l>
                     <l>Látum eigi</l>
                     <l>líf hans farask ;</l>
                     <l>eigu valkyrjur</l>
                     <l>vals of kosti.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>7.</label> Þeir munu lýðir</l>
                     <l>löndum ráða,</l>
                     <l>er útskaga</l>
                     <l>áðr of byggðu ;</l>
                     <l>kveð ek ríkum gram</l>
                     <l>ráðinn dauða ;</l>
                     <l>nú er fyrir oddum</l>
                     <l>jarlmaðr hniginn.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>8.</label> Ok munu Írar</l>
                     <l>angr um bíða,</l>
                     <l>þat er aldri mun</l>
                     <l>ýtum fyrnask.</l>
                     <l>Nú er vefr ofinn,</l>
                     <l>en völlr roðinn ;</l>
                     <l>munu um lönd fara</l>
                     <l>læspjöll gota.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>9.</label> Nú er ógurligt</l>
                     <l>um at lítask,</l>
                     <l>er dreyrug ský</l>
                     <l>dregr með himni ;</l>
                     <l>mun lopt litat</l>
                     <l>lýða blóði,</l>
                     <l>es sóknvarðar</l>
                     <l>syngja kunnu.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>10.</label> Vel kváðu vér</l>
                     <l>um konung ungan</l>
                     <l>sigrhljóða fjölð,</l>
                     <l>syngjum heilar!</l>
                     <l>en hinn nemi,</l>
                     <l>er heyrir á</l>
                     <l>geirfljóða hljóð,</l>
                     <l>ok gumum segi.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>
                        <label>11.</label> Ríðum hestum</l>
                     <l>hart út berum</l>
                     <l>brugðnum sverðum</l>
                     <l>á brott heðan.</l>
                  </lg>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p rend="noCount" rendition="#center">***</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <anchor xml:id="text"/>
            <head>The Fatal Sisters. An Ode (1768)</head>
            <p rend="noCount">(From the Norse-Tongue,)</p>
            <p rend="noCount">IN THE <hi rend="ital">ORCADES</hi> of THORMODUS TORFÆUS;
                        HAFNIÆ, 1697, Folio: and also  in BARTHOLINUS.</p>
            <p rend="noCount">VITT ER ORPIT FYRIR VALFALLI, &amp;c.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">The full sentence reads: <hi rend="ital">Vitt er orpit fyr valfalli/ rifs
                                    rei[th]i-ský</hi>. It is difficult to do justice to this
                                in English  translation: “Wide stretched is the pendant
                                cloud (<hi rend="ital">reiði</hi>-, passive, “held
                                suspended”) on the crossbeam (<hi rend="ital">rifr</hi>),
                                blood rains  down”. The “cloud” is the
                                image used about the threads suspended on the loom’s
                                crossbeams.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the Eleventh Century <hi rend="ital">Sigurd</hi>, Earl of the
                        Orkney-Islands, went with a fleet of ships and a  considerable body of
                        troops into Ireland, to the assistance of <hi rend="ital">Sictrygg with the
                            silken beard</hi>, who was then  making war on his father-in-law
                        Brian, King of Dublin; the Earl and all his forces were cut to pieces, 
                        and <hi rend="ital">Sictryg</hi> was in danger of a total defeat; but the
                        enemy had a greater loss by the death of <hi rend="ital">Brian</hi>, their
                         King, who fell in the action.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6">
                   The Battle of Clontarf took place on
                                April 23, 1014, when the forces of Brian Boru, High King of the
                                Irish met with  the armies led by the King of Leinster,
                                Máel Mórda mac Murchada, joined by Viking mercenaries.
                                Brian’s forces  marched into Leinster to quench the
                                rebellion. Máel Mórda sent his cousin Sigtrygg
                                Silkbeard, the Viking king of  Dublin, to find help overseas.
                                Sigtrygg enlisted the support of the Earl of Orkney, Sigurd
                                Lodvesson, as well as the  leader of the Isle of Man, Brodir.
                                In the battle, Brian’s forces were victorious, but Brian
                                himself was killed by  Norsemen who were fleeing the battle but
                                stumbled upon his tent.</note> On Christmas-day, (the day of the
                            battle,)<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">
                                 Torfæus makes it clear that the battle occurred
                                on Good Friday (<hi rend="ital">eodem die passionis dominicae</hi>),
                                i.e. April 23, 1014.</note> a native of <hi rend="ital">Caithness</hi> in Scotland  saw at a distance a number of persons
                        on horseback riding full speed towards a hill, and seeming to  enter
                        into it. Curiosity led him to follow them, till looking through an opening
                        in the rocks<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">
                             The cave is Gray’s invention; the original refers
                                to <hi rend="ital">dyngja</hi>, which simply means a bower, or a
                                place where women’s  work is done.</note> he saw
                         twelve gigantic figures resembling women: they were all employed about
                        a loom; and as they  wove they sung the following dreadful song: which,
                        when they had finished, they tore the web into twelve pieces,  and
                        (each taking her portion) galloped six to the north and as many to the
                        south.</p>
            <p>Note: The <hi rend="ital">Valkyriur</hi> were female divinities, servants of
                            <hi rend="ital">Odin</hi> (or <hi rend="ital">Woden</hi> ) in the Gothic
                        mythology. Their  name signifies <hi rend="ital">Choosers of the
                            Slain</hi>. They were mounted on swift horses, with drawn swords in
                        their  hands; and in the throng selected such as were destined to
                        slaughter, and conducted them to <hi rend="ital">Valkalla</hi>,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">This is a
                                typo for <hi rend="ital">Valhalla</hi> (“hall of the
                                slain”). The <hi rend="ital">OED</hi> records this as the
                                first occurrence of the word in English, so  the publisher or
                                printer may have misspelled an unfamiliar term.</note>
                         the hall of Odin, or paradise of the Brave; where they attended the
                        banquet, and served the departed  Heroes with horns of mead and
                        ale.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Now the storm begins to lower,</l>
               <l>(Haste, the loom of Hell prepare,)</l>
               <l>Iron-sleet of arrowy shower<note place="foot" resp="author" type="original">*
                                    [Gray’s Note:]  How quick they wheel’d; and
                                    flying, behind them shotSharp sleet of arrowy showers.
                                        <hi rend="ital">Milton</hi>’<hi rend="ital">s Par.
                                        Regained</hi> [III, 324].</note>
               </l>
               <l>Hurtles in the darkened air<note place="foot" resp="author" type="original">[Gray’s Note:] The
                                    noise of battle hurtled in the air. <hi rend="ital">Shakesp</hi>. <hi rend="ital">Jul. Cæsar</hi> [II,
                                        ii].<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="12">
                         Gray introduces deliberate
                                            echoes of Milton and Shakespeare, which can be seen as
                                            an argument for the influence of  Norse verse on
                                            later English literary tradition. This was, after all,
                                            how he wanted to present the odes in his projected 
                                            history of English poetry.</note>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Glittering lances are the loom, 5 <num n="5" rend="right">5</num>
               </l>
               <l>Where the dusky warp we strain,</l>
               <l>Weaving many a soldier’s doom,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="ital">Orkney</hi>’s woe and <hi rend="ital">Randver’</hi>s bane.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="13">The original phrase in this
                                    line reads <hi rend="ital">vinur… Randvés
                                        bana</hi> (the friends of Randver’s slayer). That
                                    this is a kenning for  the Valkyries cannot be doubted.
                                    Several editors and commentators have accepted the suggestion of
                                    the Norse scholar  Sophus Bugge (“Nordiske
                                    Runeindskrifter”, <hi rend="ital">Aarbøger for
                                        nordisk oldkyndighed og historie</hi> [1899], 253–4),
                                    who  suggested a reference to the son of the Gothic king
                                    Ermanaric (<hi rend="ital">Jörmunrekkr</hi>), well-known
                                    from Norse legends.  Ermanaric had Randver executed out of
                                    jealousy on the advice of his counsellor Bikki. Bugge sees Bikki
                                    as a  personification of Odin, on analogy with Odin having
                                    donned other such disguises. However, there are others named
                                     Randver known from Norse tradition, including the son of
                                    Valdarr in <hi rend="ital">Hervarar Saga</hi>, who is said to
                                    have fallen in  England (ch. 16). It is uncertain who
                                    exactly is meant in this line; the MS text may be corrupt. Gray
                                    makes sense of the  line by adding Sigurd, Earl of Orkney
                                    as a parallel, thus indicating that Randver was someone who fell
                                    in the Battle of  Clontarff.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>See the grisly texture grow,</l>
               <l>(’Tis of human entrails made,) 10 <num n="10" rend="right">10</num>
               </l>
               <l>And the weights that play below,</l>
               <l>Each a gasping Warriour’s head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Shafts for shuttles, dipt in gore,</l>
               <l>Shoot the trembling cords along.</l>
               <l>Sword, that once a Monarch bore, 15 <num n="15" rend="right">15</num>
               </l>
               <l>Keep the tissue close and strong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>
                  <hi rend="ital">Mista</hi>, black, terrific maid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="ital">Sangrida</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">Hilda</hi>
                  <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="14">
                                    Valkyries. In the Icelandic original, they are <hi rend="ital">Hildr</hi>, <hi rend="ital">Hjörþrimul</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="ital">Sanngríðr</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Svipul</hi>. Gray leaves out the awkwardly 
                                    named <hi rend="ital">Hiorthrimula</hi>, which appears in his
                                    Latin sources, replacing her with the much more menacing
                                    sounding <hi rend="ital">Mista</hi>.  Gray found this name
                                    in Bartholin’s translation of a stanza of <hi rend="ital">Grímnismál</hi>, a poem from the <hi rend="ital">Poetic Edda</hi>, where it  occurs in the
                                    list of names of <hi rend="ital">valkyrjur</hi>. The Old Norse
                                    form in Bartholin’s text is <hi rend="ital">Mist</hi> (p.
                                    554).</note>, see,</l>
               <l>Join the wayward work to aid;</l>
               <l>‘Tis the woof of victory. 20 <num n="20" rend="right">20</num>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Ere the ruddy sun be set,</l>
               <l>Pikes must shiver, javelins sing,</l>
               <l>Blade with clattering buckler meet,</l>
               <l>Hauberk<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="15">
                             A shirt of mail armour.</note> crash, and
                            helmet ring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>(Weave the crimson web of war)<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="16">
                      In the poem “The
                                    Bard”, first published 1757, Gray uses the line
                                    “Weave the warp and weave the woof” (l.
                                49).</note> 25 <num n="25" rend="right">25</num>
               </l>
               <l>Let us go, and let us fly</l>
               <l>Where our friends the conflict share,</l>
               <l>Where they triumph, where they die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>As the paths of fate we tread,</l>
               <l>Wading thro’ th’ ensanguined field: 30 <num n="30" rend="right">30</num>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi rend="ital">Gondula</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Geira</hi>,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="17">
                                    Valkyries. In the Icelandic original named as <hi rend="ital">Göndul</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Guðr</hi>.</note> spread</l>
               <l>O’er the youthful King your shield.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>We the reins to slaughter give,</l>
               <l>Ours to kill, and ours to spare:</l>
               <l>Spite the dangers he shall live. 35 <num n="35" rend="right">35</num>
               </l>
               <l>(Weave the crimson web of war.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>They, whom once the desert-beach</l>
               <l>Pent within its bleak domain,</l>
               <l>Soon their ample sway shall stretch</l>
               <l>O’er the plenty of the plain. 40 <num n="40" rend="right">40</num>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Low the dauntless earl is laid,</l>
               <l>Gored with many a gaping wound;</l>
               <l>Fate demands a nobler head;</l>
               <l>Soon a king shall bite the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Long his loss shall Eirin<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="18">
                      Poetical name for
                                Ireland.</note> weep 45 <num n="45" rend="right">45</num>
               </l>
               <l>Ne’er again his likeness see;</l>
               <l>Long her strains in sorrow steep,</l>
               <l>Strains of immortality!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Horror covers all the heath,</l>
               <l>Clouds of carnage blot the sun. 50 <num n="50" rend="right">50</num>
               </l>
               <l>Sisters, weave the web of death;</l>
               <l>Sisters, cease, the work is done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Hail the task, and hail the hands!</l>
               <l>Songs of joy and triumph sing!</l>
               <l>Joy to the victorious bands; 55 <num n="55" rend="right">55</num>
               </l>
               <l>Triumph to the younger King.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="19">
                      The young king seems to refer to
                                    Siggtryg, but it was the aging king Brian (born in 941, and thus
                                    73 years of age)  who was victorious. It has therefore been
                                    suggested that the poem incorporated into <hi rend="ital">Njals
                                        Saga</hi> in fact refers to a Viking  victory of 919;
                                    see Russell Poole, <hi rend="ital">Viking Poems on War and
                                        Peace</hi> (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1991),
                                    120–  25. In Gray’s preface, the discrepancy
                                    is dealt with, or perhaps glossed over, by mentioning
                                    Brian’s near defeat and his  death.</note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Mortal, thou that hear’st the tale,</l>
               <l>Learn the tenour of our song.</l>
               <l>Scotland, thro’ each winding vale</l>
               <l>Far and wide the notes prolong. 60 <num n="60" rend="right">60</num>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Sisters, hence with spurs of speed:</l>
               <l>Each her thundering faulchion wield;</l>
               <l>Each bestride her sable steed.</l>
               <l>Hurry, hurry to the field!</l>
            </lg>
            <p rend="noCount">Source: <hi rend="ital">Poems by Mr. Gray, A New Edition</hi> (London: J.
            Dodsley, 1768), 73–84.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <anchor xml:id="text1"/>
            <head>The Descent of Odin (1768)</head>
            <p>The second of Gray’s Norse odes is based on the poem known as <hi rend="ital">Baldrs draumar</hi> (“Balder’s 
                        Dreams”), which is also called <hi rend="ital">Vegtamskviða</hi> (“The Lay of the Wayfarer”) in
                        some of the late  manuscripts where it is preserved. The original is
                        included in the <hi rend="ital">Eddica minora</hi>, poems relating to 
                        <hi rend="ital">Poetic Edda</hi>, but not in the Codex Regius, which
                        contained the canon of the tradition.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="20"> Gray’s source for the
                                poem was chapter two of Bartholin’s text (p.
                        632).</note>
            </p>
            <p>The background of the story is not fully explained in the poem, but readers
                        could read about its  tragic circumstances in Paul-Henri
                        Mallet’s work. To summarize briefly, Balder, the son of Odin 
                        and Frigg, is told in his dreams that he will soon die. The other gods
                        therefore send Frigg to exact  an oath from all gods, living beings,
                        plants and stone, not to do Balder harm. However, she forgets  the
                        mistletoe. The trickster Loki takes advantage of this oversight and makes an
                        arrow from  mistletoe, which he gives to the blind Hödr
                        (Gray’s “Hoder”), Baldr’s brother. Unknowingly,
                        Hödr  kills Baldr. Odin begot Vali on the giantess Rind[a] to
                        revenge his dead son. Vali grew to be man in  just one day and killed
                        Hödr.</p>
            <p>The poem takes place after the dreams. Gray omits the first four lines, which
                        tells of the gods  holding a council in which they decide to find out
                        about Baldr’s fate. Odin dons the disguise of the  traveller
                        Vegtam (literally, “Way-tamer”) in order to awaken a <hi rend="ital">völva</hi> from her grave. The <hi rend="ital">völva</hi>
                         could see into the future (hence, Gray’s translation
                        “prophetess”), and the idea was to trick her into 
                        revealing the portents of Balder’s visions. Odin makes the
                        re-animated <hi rend="ital">völva</hi> answer a series of 
                        questions and thereby learns of Balder’s imminent death and how it
                        will be revenged. For reasons  no longer understood, Odin’s
                        fourth question reveals his identity and the seeress bids him to leave,
                         refusing to disclose any further information. Nonetheless, she alludes
                        to the events that will take  place at the end of the world: <hi rend="ital">Ragnarök</hi>.</p>
            <p>The poem contained many of the themes that would become familiar in
                        Norse-inflected poetry  during the Romantic era: the descent to the
                        underworld, the waking of the dead, the use of magic  incantations
                        etc.</p>
        
         <div type="poetry">
            
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Uprose the King of Men<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="21">
                      A name for Odin.</note> with
                            speed</l>
               <l>And saddled straight his coal-black steed:<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="22"> Sleipnir,
                                    Odin’s eight-legged horse.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Down the yawning steep he rode,</l>
               <l>That leads to HELA’S drear abode.</l>
               <l>Him the Dog of Darkness<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="23">
                      Garm (which has the meaning of
                                    “howl”), a gigantic hound guarding the cave
                                    Gnipahellir (the “yawning steep” of the  next
                                    line), where one found Gjöll, the entry to the world of
                                    the dead. Gray’s elaborate description of the hound is
                                    not in  the original, but contributes to the horror of the
                                    scene.</note> spied, 5 <num n="5" rend="right">5</num>
               </l>
               <l>His shaggy throat he open’d wide,</l>
               <l>While from his jaws with carnage fill’d,</l>
               <l>Foam and human gore distill’d,</l>
               <l>Hoarse he bays with hideous din,</l>
               <l>Eyes that glow, and fangs, that grin: 10 <num n="10" rend="right">10</num>
               </l>
               <l>And long pursues, with fruitless yell,</l>
               <l>The Father of the powerful spell.</l>
               <l>Onward still his way he takes,</l>
               <l>(The groaning earth beneath him shakes,)</l>
               <l>Till full before his fearless eyes 15 <num n="15" rend="right">15</num>
               </l>
               <l>The portals nine of hell arise.</l>
               <l>Right against the eastern gate,</l>
               <l>By the moss-grown pile he sate;</l>
               <l>Where long of yore to sleep was laid</l>
               <l>The dust of the prophetic maid. 20 <num n="20" rend="right">20</num>
               </l>
               <l>Facing to the northern clime,</l>
               <l>Thrice he trac’d the runic rhyme,</l>
               <l>Thrice pronounc’d in accents dread,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="24"> The repetition of
                                    a magic incantation three times is not in the original, but
                                    refers to folklore tradition, which was  believed to
                                    contain traces of the pagan religion once practiced in the
                                    British Isles.</note>
               </l>
               <l>The thrilling verse that wakes the Dead;</l>
               <l>Till from out the hollow ground 25 <num n="25" rend="right">25</num>
               </l>
               <l>Slowly breath’d a sullen sound.</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr. [Prophetess]<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="25">
                      The original manuscript source has
                                    no superscriptions indicating the speakers.</note>
               </speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>What call unknown, what charms presume</l>
                  <l>To break the quiet of the tomb?</l>
                  <l>Who thus afflicts my troubled sprite,</l>
                  <l>And drags me from the realms of night? 30 <num n="30" rend="right">30</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>Long on these mould’ring bones have beat</l>
                  <l>The winter’s snow the summer’s heat,</l>
                  <l>The drenching dews and driving rain!</l>
                  <l>Let me, let me sleep again.</l>
                  <l>Who is he, with voice unblest, 35 <num n="35" rend="right">35</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>That calls me from the bed of rest?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. [Odin]</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>A traveller to thee unknown,</l>
                  <l>Is he that calls, a Warriour’s Son.</l>
                  <l>Thou the deeds of light shalt know;</l>
                  <l>Tell me what is done below, 40 <num n="40" rend="right">40</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>For whom yon glitt’ring board is spread,</l>
                  <l>Drest for whom yon golden bed.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Mantling in the goblet see</l>
                  <l>The pure bev’rage of the bee,<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="26"> Mead; see
                                        Glossary.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>O’er it hangs the shield of gold; 45 <num n="45" rend="right">45</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>‘Tis the drink of <hi rend="ital">Balder</hi> bold:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="ital">Balder</hi>’s head to death is
                                giv’n.</l>
                  <l>Pain can reach the sons of Heav’n!</l>
                  <l>Unwilling I my lips unclose:</l>
                  <l>Leave me leave, me to repose. 50 <num n="50" rend="right">50</num>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Once again my call obey.</l>
                  <l>Prophetess, arise and say,</l>
                  <l>What dangers <hi rend="ital">Odin</hi>’s Child await,</l>
                  <l>Who the Author of his fate.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>In <hi rend="ital">Hoder</hi>’s hand the hero’s doom;
                                55 <num n="55" rend="right">55</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>His Brother sends him to the tomb.</l>
                  <l>Now my weary lips I close:</l>
                  <l>Leave me, leave me to repose.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Prophetess, my spell obey,</l>
                  <l>Once again arise, and say, 60 <num n="60" rend="right">60</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who th’ avenger of his guilt,</l>
                  <l>By whom shall <hi rend="ital">Hoder</hi>’s blood be spilt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>In the caverns of the west,</l>
                  <l>By <hi rend="ital">Odin</hi>’s fierce embrace comprest,</l>
                  <l>A wond’rous boy shall <hi rend="ital">Rinda</hi> bear, 65 <num n="65" rend="right">65</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who ne’er shall comb his raven-hair,</l>
                  <l>Nor wash his visage in the stream,</l>
                  <l>Nor see the sun’s departing beam;</l>
                  <l>Till he on <hi rend="ital">Hoder</hi>’s corse shall smile</l>
                  <l>Flaming on the fun’ral pile.<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="27"> The reference
                                        is to Vali, who Odin begot with the sole purpose of having
                                        him revenge the death of Balder. Vali grew  to
                                        adulthood in one day. This is why he does not have time for
                                        the activities listed in this stanza.</note> 70 <num n="70" rend="right">70</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now my weary lips I close:</l>
                  <l>Leave me, leave me to repose.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Yet a while my call obey.</l>
                  <l>Prophetess, awake, and say,</l>
                  <l>What Virgins<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="28">
                         These are the “billow
                                        maidens”, also known as Ægir’s
                                        daughters, the personification of natural forces, whose
                                        grief  will be so intense that it causes tempestuous
                                        weather.</note> these, in speechless woe, 75 <num n="75" rend="right">75</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>That bend to earth their solemn brow,</l>
                  <l>That their flaxen tresses tear,</l>
                  <l>And snowy veils that float in air.</l>
                  <l>Tell me, whence their sorrows rose:</l>
                  <l>Then I leave thee to repose. 80 <num n="80" rend="right">80</num>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Ha! no Traveller art thou,</l>
                  <l>King of Men, I know thee now,</l>
                  <l>Mightiest of a mighty line —</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>No boding Maid of skill divine</l>
                  <l>Art thou nor Prophetess of good; 85 <num n="85" rend="right">85</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>But Mother of the giant-brood!<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="29"> Apparently, the
                                        völva is a giant, and thus an enemy of Odin’s
                                        Æsir, which explains why he must don the disguise of
                                        a  mortal to extract information from
                                her.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Hie thee hence, and boast at home,</l>
                  <l>That never shall Enquirer come</l>
                  <l>To break my iron-sleep again;</l>
                  <l>Till <hi rend="ital">Lok</hi> has burst his tenfold chain<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="30">
                                        For his deceit which led to the killing of Balder, Loki was
                                        bound underground by adamantine chains. In another 
                                        version of the story, his chains are made from the
                                        intestines of his son. Loki will break these chains at the
                                        day of  Ragnarök.</note>. 90 <num n="90" rend="right">90</num>
                  </l>
                  <l>Never, till substantial Night</l>
                  <l>Has reassum’d her ancient right;</l>
                  <l>Till wrapt in flames in ruin hurl’d,</l>
                  <l>Sinks the fabric of the world.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="bib">
            <p  rend="noCount">Source: <title>Poems by Mr. Gray, A New Edition</title> (London: J.
            Dodsley, 1768), 85–96.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>