<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
               <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>General Editor, </resp>
               <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2013-05-30</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno type="nines">rce283</idno>
            <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.about</idno>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
            <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-05-30">May 30, 2013</date>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Lynda Pratt</author>
                  <title>General Introduction</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. </title>
                  <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
                  <author>
                     <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
                  </author>
                  <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
               <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Southey’s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
               <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
               <category xml:id="g1">
                  <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g2">
                  <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g3">
                  <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g4">
                  <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g5">
                  <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g7">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g6">
                  <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g8">
                  <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g9">
                  <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g10">
                  <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g11">
                  <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g12">
                  <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g13">
                  <catDesc>History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g14">
                  <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g15">
                  <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g16">
                  <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g17">
                  <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g18">
                  <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g19">
                  <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g20">
                  <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g21">
                  <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g22">
                  <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g23">
                  <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g24">
                  <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g25">
                  <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g26">
                  <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g27">
                  <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g28">
                  <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g29">
                  <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g30">
                  <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g31">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g32">
                  <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g33">
                  <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="g34">
                  <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
               <category xml:id="people">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
               <category xml:id="places">
                  <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef target="#g21" scheme="#genre"/>
            <catRef target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"/>
            <catRef target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"/>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change n="10" when="2013-05-30" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="9" when="2013-02-15" who="LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming after additions up to Part 4</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="8" when="2011-08-15" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="7" when="2011-07-06" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="6" when="2011-03-20" who="#AB">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>corrections from proofing</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="5" when="2011-02-21" who="#AB">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>Part II added</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="4" when="2009-03-10" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="3" when="2009-03-02" who="#AB">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>corrections from proofing</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="2" when="2009-02-20" who="#LM">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
            <list>
               <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
            </list>
         </change>
         <change n="1" when="2009-02-20" who="#AB">
            <label>Changed by</label>
            <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
            <list>
               <item>TEI Encoding</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="paratext">
            <head>About this Edition</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Editorial Methodology</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> is divided into eight Parts: I: 1791-1797, II:1798-1803, III:1804-09,
               IV:1810-15, V:1816-21, VI:1822-27, VII:1828-33, VIII:1833-39. </p>
            <p>The General Introduction outlines the project’s research context. In addition, each individual Part has a brief introductory essay. </p>
            <p>Throughout the edition, letters are presented in chronological order, each letter being assigned its own number. Any letters that have
               been located after the first publication of an individual Part of the edition are inserted at their appropriate chronological point and
               given a suffix number (e.g. .1,.2): see, for example, Letter 1889.1. Previously unpublished letters have all been newly transcribed
               from the autograph manuscript, when that survives. In cases where the letter now exists only in a manuscript transcript in another
               hand, copy-text is taken from the transcript and this is recorded in the editorial headnote. Where letters have been previously
               published, we have returned to and transcribed the original manuscript when it survives. In cases where we have been unable to locate
               the manuscript of a published letter, copy-text is taken, without emendation, from the published version and this is recorded in the
               editorial headnote. There are two instances where a previously published version of a letter is fuller than the surviving manuscript.
               In these an edited, annotated transcript of the manuscript version has been placed within the main run of letters (see Letters 46 and
               147), and the text of the longer, previously published version in Appendix 1.</p>
            <p>We have followed the editors of the letters of Mark Twain and adopted a ‘plain text’ methodology in order to produce a text that is
               more quickly intelligible to the reader but that also represents, as closely as our digitised transcriptions can, the original
               holograph letters.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">For a full explication of ‘plain text’ see ‘Guide to Editorial Practice,
                  (MTDP 00005).’ In Mark Twain Project Online. Berkeley, Los Angeles, London: University of California Press. 2007. <ref
                     target="http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/MTDP00005.xml;style=letterletter;brand=mtp"
                     >&lt;http://www.marktwainproject.org/xtf/view?docId=letters/MTDP00005.xml;style=letterletter;brand=mtp&gt;</ref>, accessed
                  2014-12-19.</note> Our aim is to allow the reader to get as close as possible to what Southey wrote and thus to provide an insight
               into the creative processes that underpinned his letter writing. This is particularly important now, when the older idea of Southey as
               someone who wrote with ease and never blotted a line or deleted a word is being challenged by new textual and critical scholarship. All
               letters are transcribed in full and editorial intervention in the text has been kept to a minimum. Southey’s original spelling, and
               mis-spelling, grammar, punctuation and any slips of his pen have been retained. Deletions are indicated by striking through the
               cancelled word or phrase, but without any attempt to indicate the heaviness of the deletion: e.g. ‘<del>he said</del>’. In those cases
               where Southey changed his mind and wrote over his original thought, we have put his final version in the text of the letter and
               indicated the original words or characters in an endnote. Throughout the text, ‘x’ is used to indicate an illegible character: e.g. ‘he
               xxid’. Underlining is indicated by italics: e.g. ‘<hi rend="ital">he</hi> said’. The exception to this rule is where Southey used
               underlining not for emphasis but to indicate an abbreviation written in superscript: eg. ‘D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>’ rather than ‘Doctor’
               or ‘Dr’. This was something Southey did occasionally and irregularly, particularly on address leaves. It is not possible to code a
               character or set of characters in both underline or italic and superscript, so in these cases we have silently regularised his practice
               and presented all his superscript abbreviations, both underlined or not, in superscript: e.g. ‘M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith said’.
               Editorial [...] within the text of an individual letter are used to indicate issues relating to the manuscript: a tear, cut, missing
               section or area obscured by a seal mark or blot, or a substantial section of a letter in the hand of a co-correspondent. See, for
               example, Letter 56, co-written with Grosvenor Charles Bedford. Editorial &#123;...&#125; are used to indicate an authorial insertion of
               text above or below the line. </p>
            <p>We have retained Southey’s paragraphing but have not otherwise replicated the lineage of prose, the pagination, the hand, or any other
               physical features of his letters that it is clear Southey did not invest with any meaning. Throughout the edition, words split in the
               text of an individual letter by the end of a line or a page have been silently emended to reflect Southey’s customary spelling: eg.
               ‘mis-/ chief’ has been emended to ‘mischief’ in our text. In the case of poems included by Southey in his letters, we have retained the
               lineage and stanza breaks, with the exception of lines and stanzas that run onto the following line or page of the manuscript. In these
               cases, the run over word or line/s has been silently incorporated into the preceding part of the line or stanza as it is clear that the
               break had no meaning to Southey and was dictated purely by the spatial constraints of the manuscript page.</p>
            <p>Each letter has an editorial headnote. This records the location of the manuscript, if it has survived, and describes its physical
               characteristics, using the following abbreviations:</p>
            <p>ALS: autograph letter signed</p>
            <p>AL: autograph letter, without signature</p>
            <p>(A)LS: more than 50% of the manuscript in a hand other than Southey’s</p>
            <p>TR = survives as a transcript in another hand</p>
            <p>TS = survives as a typescript</p>
            <p>p. = numbers of pages of the letter containing script, including the address leaf, when this has survived</p>
            <p>(c) = letter transcribed and checked from a digital scan, photograph or photocopy of the manuscript</p>
            <p>The headnote also notes any previous instances of publication and deals with other relevant issues, such as endorsements, watermarks,
               postmarks, franks, stamps and dating. This edition provides important new information about when many of Southey’s letters were
               actually written, and re-dates letters that have been misdated or misleadingly dated by previous editors. For example, Southey’s
               earliest correspondence is here demonstrated to date to late 1791, rather than 1790 as claimed by John Wood Warter. The following
               conventions have been observed in dating individual letters: [...] is used in headnotes to indicate an editorial dating; ‘c.’ to
               indicate a dating taken from the postmark or from internal evidence within an individual letter; ‘before’ is used either when a letter
               contains an authorial date, but there is evidence within the letter that it was begun before that time, or when an endorsement on the
               letter indicates its date of receipt; ‘after’ is used when a letter contains an authorial date, but there is evidence within the letter
               that it was continued after that time; ‘?’ is used to indicate a dating about which there remains some uncertainty.</p>
            <p>Detailed information about Southey’s correspondents, along with other important figures in his letters, can be found in the
               ‘Biographies’ section. Each entry in this section also contains a list of letters to and list of letters about the person it deals
               with. People mentioned in the ‘Biographies’ section are hyperlinked from the text of individual letters, but are only hyperlinked from
               editorial endnotes when their identity needs further clarification than that supplied by the letter text. Information about where
               Southey lived, locations he was associated with, and the homes of friends he visited is provided in the ‘Places’ section of this
               edition and hyperlinked from the texts of individual letters. </p>
            <p>Editorial notes to the text are used to clarify references to persons, books, places, and events within the main body of each
               individual letter. They also identify quotations and provide translations of foreign language material. A ‘Chronology’ covers key
               events in Southey’s life. ‘Indices of People and Letters’ organise Southey’s correspondence by, respectively, the individual to whom a
               letter is addressed and the person or persons mentioned in it. The links in the ‘Primary Navigation’ bar, on the left-hand side of the
               page, allow navigation across difference sections of the edition. The ‘Search’ facility allows the reader to perform dedicated word or
               phrase searches both across the entire edition (including the editorial apparatus) or within a particular part of it.</p>

            <p>All transcriptions and editorial materials are checked by the editor or editors of that particular part of the edition and by at least
               one other member of the editorial team. After xml encoding and transformation, each Part of edition is proofed online by its editor or
               editors, who also check the index and search engine. The editor, or editors, also ensure any corrections are implemented before the
               text is made publicly available. After publication, any corrections or comments should be directed to Lynda Pratt from whom a copy of
               the current version of the correction file is also available on request.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">People</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lynda Pratt is Professor of Modern Literature and Director of the Centre for Regional Literature and Culture at the University of
               Nottingham. She has published widely on Southey and his circle. She was general editor of <title level="m">Robert Southey: Poetical
                  Works, 1793-1810</title>, 5 vols (2004) and is co-general editor, with Tim Fulford, of <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later
                  Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>, 4 vols (Pickering and Chatto, 2012). Her edited collection <title level="m">Robert Southey and
                  the Contexts of English Romanticism</title> was published in 2006.</p>
            <p>Tim Fulford is a Professor of English at De Montford University. He has published several monographs in which Southey features, most
               recently <title level="m">Romantic Indians</title> (2006). He edited <title level="m">Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, vol. 3 of <title
                  level="m">Robert Southey: Poetical Works, 1793-1810</title> (2004) and is co-general editor, with Lynda Pratt, of <title level="m"
                  >Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. Fulford and Pratt’s edition the <title level="m">Collected Letters of
                  Robert Bloomfield and his Circle</title> is also online at <title level="m">Romantic Circles</title>
            </p>
            <p>Ian Packer is Reader in History at the University of Lincoln. His publications include <title level="m">The Letters of Arnold
                  Stephenson Rowntree to Mary Katherine Rowntree</title> (Cambridge 2002). He has published widely on political and religious history
               and was an editor on <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. </p>
            <p>Carol Bolton is Senior Lecturer in English at Loughborough University. Her monograph <title level="m">Writing the Empire: Robert
                  Southey and Romantic Colonialism</title> was published in 2007. She has published widely on Romantic period writing and was an
               editor on <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. </p>
            <p>W. A. Speck is Emeritus Professor of History at the University of Leeds and was a Special Professor in the School of English Studies at
               the University of Nottingham. His <title level="m">Robert Southey: Entire Man of Letters</title> was published by Yale University Press
               in 2006.</p>
            <p>Averill Buchanan was an AHRC-funded research fellow on <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title>, based at the
               University of Nottingham. She completed an AHRC-funded PhD at Queen’s University Belfast in 2004 on the Anglo-Irish writer Mary Tighe.
               Her monograph <title level="m">Mary Blachford Tighe: The Irish Psyche</title> was published by Cambridge Scholars Publishing in
               2011.</p>
            <p>Sam Ward was an AHRC-funded research fellow on <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title>, based at the
               University of Nottingham. He completed an AHRC-funded PhD at Nottingham Trent University in 2006. He has published peer-reviewed essays
               on John Clare John and Robert Bloomfield. His research interests also include James Montgomery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Contact</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The editors welcome comments and corrections. Please contact:</p>
            <p>Lynda Pratt: <ref target="mailto:lynda.pratt@nottingham.ac.uk">Lynda.Pratt@nottingham.ac.uk</ref>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Permissions</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The editors thank the following for permission to reproduce manuscripts in their collections: </p>
            <p>North America</p>
            <p>The Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley; Beinecke Library, Yale University; The Berg Collection of English and
               American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Private Collection of Fred Burwick; The
               Trustees of the Boston Public Library, Rare Books; Brown University Library; Special Collections Department, Bryn Mawr College Library;
               The Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University in the City of New York; The Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections,
               Cornell University Library; Duke University Library; The Fales Library, New York University; Special Collections, The John Hopkins
               University; Harry Ransom Center, University of Texas, Austin; Hispanic Society of America, New York; Houghton Library, Harvard
               University; Historical Society of Pennsylvania; Huntington Library, San Marino; Special Collections, University of Iowa Libraries, Iowa
               City, Iowa; the Library, Lehigh University; The Lilly Library, Indiana University; Special Collections, University of Kentucky
               Libraries; Massachusetts Historical Society; Autograph Letter Collection, Rare Books and Special Collections, McGill University
               Library; Morgan Library, New York; Morristown National Historical Park; New York Public Library (General Manuscript collection);
               Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library; the Library, Pennsylvania State University; Department of Rare Books and Special
               Collections, Princeton University Library; Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries,
               University of Rochester; Spencer Library, University of Kansas; Department of Special Collections, Stanford University Libraries;
               Tulane University Library; Victoria University Library, Toronto; the Library, Washington University in St Louis; the Wilson Library,
               University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, University of California,
               Los Angeles.</p>
            <p>United Kingdom </p>
            <p>Department of Manuscripts and Special Collections, University of Birmingham; Bodleian Library, University of Oxford; Bristol City
               Library, Bristol; British Library, London; Brotherton Library, Leeds University; The Principal and Fellows of Newnham College,
               Cambridge; the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Harrowby Manuscript Trust; Keswick Museum and Art Gallery,
               Keswick; Lancashire Archives; Liverpool City Library, Liverpool; Liverpool Record Office; Department of Manuscripts and Special
               Collections, University of Liverpool; City of London Corporation, London Metropolitan Archives; the University of Manchester; the
               Mitchell Library, Glasgow; the National Art Library, Victoria and Albert Museum, London; National Library of Scotland, Edinburgh;
               National Library of Wales, Aberystwyth; the Librarian, Robinson Library, Newcastle University; Newstead Abbey, Nottinghamshire;
               Department of Manuscripts and Special Collections, University of Nottingham; the Provost and Fellows of Oriel College, Oxford; The
               Royal Institution of Great Britain; Samuel Johnson Birthplace Museum, Lichfield; University of Sheffield Library; Somerset Record
               Office; Staffordshire Record Office; Sterling Library, Senate House, University of London; University College London Library, Special
               Collections; West Sussex Record Office; West Yorkshire Archive Service; the Governing Body, Westminster School; Dr Williams’s Library,
               London; Wisbech and Fenland Museum; The Wordsworth Trust, Dove Cottage, Grasmere.</p>
            <p>Europe</p>
            <p>Biblioteca Pública de Évora; Universiteitsbibliotheek, Ghent.</p>
            <p>The editors are extremely grateful to the family of the late Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick Jnr for granting us permission to quote from
               his unpublished doctoral thesis ‘The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826’ (Harvard, 1967).</p>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Conditions of Use, Permission for Reprinting, and Guidelines for Citation</hi></p>

            <p>For the edition’s Conditions of Use please follow this link:</p>
            <p><ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/pubinfo/conditions.html">http://www.rc.umd.edu/pubinfo/conditions.html</ref></p>

            <p>For further information about Permission for Reprinting Romantic Circles Materials, including materials from <title>The Collected
                  Letters of Robert Southey</title>, please follow this link:</p>
            <p><ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/about/reprint-permissions">http://www.rc.umd.edu/about/reprint-permissions</ref></p>

            <p>Guidelines for Citation of the edition can be found here:</p>
            <p><ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/pubinfo/citation.html">http://www.rc.umd.edu/pubinfo/citation.html</ref></p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> has been made possible by the generosity, help and support of a number
               of individuals and institutions.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The general editors thank the Arts and Humanities Research Council for a Resource Enhancement award. Lynda Pratt would
               like to thank the Arts and Humanities Research Council for a Research Leave grant; the Leverhulme Trust for a Research Fellowship; the
               British Academy for a Small Research grant; the Beinecke Library, Yale University, for an Osborn fellowship; the Huntington Library,
               San Marino, for a Michael Connell fellowship; the Friends of Princeton University library for a research grant; and the Harry Ransom
               Humanities Research Centre, University of Texas, Austin, for a research fellowship. Tim Fulford would like to thank the Leverhulme
               Trust for a Research Fellowship and the British Academy for a Small Research Grant. Carol Bolton wishes to thank the British Academy
               for a Small Research Grant. The general editors also thank the following for their financial support: the Aurelius Charitable Trust,
               the Charlotte Bonham Carter Charitable Trust, the John S. Cohen Foundation, the Gladys Krieble Delmas Foundation, the Gibbs Trust,
               Bristol, the Mercers Charitable Foundation, and the Thriplow Charitable Trust.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">
               <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> has also benefited from grants from the School of English, University
               of Nottingham; Humanities Research Centre, University of Nottingham; the Humanities and Social Sciences Strategic Research Fund,
               University of Nottingham; the English Department, Nottingham Trent University; the University of Lincoln; Loughborough University.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The editorial team are indebted to the following individuals for their advice, support and assistance in completing
                  <title level="m">Part One</title> of this edition: Frances Banks, Anthony Bowen, Averill Buchanan, Maria Castanheira, David
               Eastwood, Parvin Fatemi, Caroline Franklin, Michael J. Franklin, Lynne Hapgood, Laura Mandell, Tilar J. Mazzeo, Souvik Mukherjee, Mike
               Quilligan, Dave Rettenmaier, Nicholas Roe, Diego Saglia, Bill Speck, Sam Ward, Susan J. Wolfson, David Worrall, Duncan Wu and Nahem
               Yousaf.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">In addition to the above, the editorial team are extremely grateful to the following for advice and assistance in
               completing <title>Part Two</title> and <title>Part Four</title> of this edition: Richard Butterwick, Michael Eberle-Sinatra, Jason
               Koenig, Joanna Martin, Bill Overton, Nicola Royan, Lucia Scigliano Suarez, Douglass H. Thomson, Timothy D. Whelan, and Edward
               Yescombe.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">In addition to the above, the editors of <title>Part Three</title> thank the following for their assistance: Kerri
               Andrews, Joselyn Almeida-Beveridge, John Bolton, Julia S. Carlson, Pamela Clemit, Ashley Cross, and Elaine Hobby. The editors are most
               grateful to Marilyn Gaull for her support, and to Michael Nash for his invaluable advice on naval matters in <hi rend="ital">Part
                  Three</hi> and <hi rend="ital">Part Four</hi>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The editors of <hi rend="ital">Part Five</hi> in addition to the above are grateful to: David Fairer, Philippa Hoskin,
               Sara Slinn, Jane Stabler.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">About the Design</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This electronic edition was TEI-encoded by Averill Buchanan under the supervision of Laura Mandell and her team at Miami University of
               Ohio, and with the assistance of David Rettenmaier and Mike Quilligan at the University of Maryland. Buchanan used the new Word Macros
               tool developed at Miami University by Holly Connor and Jerry Gannod in order to learn TEI encoding. Mandell transformed the TEI files
               into HTML by using modified versions of the transforms provided by the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org">TEI</ref>. Dave Rettenmaier
               and Mike Qulligan designed the splash pages, banners, etc., comprising the HTML design. The HTML pages do not use frames but rather
               make extensive use of tables and stylesheets for layout and presentation. The site works best when viewed with Mozilla Firefox v. 3,
               Netscape 4.0, Internet Explorer 4.0, or higher, or a comparable browser; earlier browsers may not display everything properly.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
