<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">frank27.v2.notes</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2009-04-01">May 1, 2009</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a">NOTES to Volume II</title>
						<author>
							<persName>Curran, Stuart</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<editor>Curran, Stuart</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date>2009-05-01</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g12" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="3" when="2009-05-01" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-05-01" who="#DR">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2009-05-01" who="#MQ">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<head>NOTES TO VOLUME II</head>

			<div type="appCharsB">
				<list type="simple">
					<item n="1">
						<term target="#abhorred">abhorred devil</term> The repetitiousness of Victor's diction—it was "abhorred monster!" at the
						beginning of this interview (II:2:8)—seems fitting in circumstances where so many mirrored prisms are being deployed
						simultaneously by Mary Shelley. </item>
					<item n="2">
						<term target="#abject">the submission of abject slavery </term> This is a phrase that will resonate through the final third of
						the novel as the Creature and Victor Frankenstein vie for mastery over the other's will. Although fundamentally psychological
						in its formulation, the contention, as this phrase stresses, carries political overtones as well. </item>
					<item n="3">
						<term target="#adam">like Adam </term> Although the Creature here alludes to Adam's instruction by Raphael, which occupies the
						central third of Milton's epic, the imprecation on his creator that follows in the next paragraph bears comparison with the
						fallen Adam's indictment of God and lament that he was ever born (X.720ff). Like Adam, although physically he does not bear
						the imprint of his Creator, the Creature is indissolubly bound to Victor Frankenstein, as is indicated by his frequent
						unconscious doublings in language or gesture. </item>
					<item n="4">
						<term target="#aduty">a duty</term> As he has before, Alphonse Frankenstein raises before Victor the notion of duty as a
						contractual obligation between individual and family or state (I:1:1, I:3:10). </item>
					<item n="5">
						<term target="#affect">the affections of a sensitive being </term> This antiquated terminology bears pausing over. "Sensitive"
						in this context implies both "vitality, "human feeling," and an "independent will." The reciprocity of sensitive beings is the
						foundation of all social interchange; thus, the key to creating a society. </item>
					<item n="6">
						<term target="#affright">disgust and affright </term> The explicitly sensual terms with which the Creature characterizes
						Caroline Frankenstein, unknown to him the mother of his creator-father, recalls his reaction to the first sight of Safie
						(II:5:4 and note). Clearly, Safie is in his mind when the paragraph ends with the anticipated aversion of a beautiful woman to
						his form. </item>
					<item n="7">
						<term target="#again">again, with a lessened form</term> That is, the moon has disappeared totally, then has just reappeared
						in its new phase: so, a period of two weeks has elapsed. </item>
					<item n="8">
						<term target="#agentle">A gentle light </term>
						<p>The moon, which appears from details that follow in the narrative to be in its full phase. It is so bright, in Victor's
							narrative of the night of the Creature's birth, that "it forced its way through the window-shutters" (I:4:3), allowing him
							sufficient light to discern the features of the Creature as he opened the bed curtains to discover Victor. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="9">
						<term target="#ahell">a hell of intense tortures</term> Again, the stress is on hell as a mental state that Victor bears
						within himself. As demonstrated earlier at I:4:5 (and note) and I:7:30 (and note), Victor's internalization of the pangs of
						hell-fire is a clear allusion to the misery of Milton's Satan in Paradise Lost, especially IV.66-75. </item>
					<item n="10">
						<term target="#aiguille">aiguilles</term> Literally needles: the term applies to the smaller pinnacles that rise in the
						periphery of Mont Blanc. </item>
					<item n="11">
						<term target="#alady">a lady </term> With the arrival of this enigmatic stranger Mary Shelley essentially completes the cast
						of characters—which is to say, the balance of human and social elements—that compose her novel. That Safie is herself an
						outsider makes her curiously similar to the Creature who observes her entrance on the scene. </item>
					<item n="12">
						<term target="#alblast">All was blasted</term>

						<p>The language seems intended to invoke the "blasted stump" (I:1:22 and note) that is left after lightning strikes the tree
							near Bellerive, a manifestation of the power of the "vital fluid," electricity, that can at once create and destroy. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="13">
						<term target="#aleague">A league</term>
						<p>The Oxford English Dictionary defines this unit of measurement as follows: </p>
						<p>LEAGUE: </p>
						<p> league lig, sb.1 Forms: 4-5 leghe, 4-6 lege, leuge, (4 lewge, 5 lewke, leuke, leeke), 5-6 leege, 6 legge, le(a)que, Sc.
							lig, 6-7 leag(e, 6- league. Late ME. leuge, lege, leghe, etc., ad. late L. leuga, leuca (= late Gr. leu'gh, leu'kh),
							according to Hesychius and Jordanes a Gaulish word; hence OFr. liue, liwe (mod.Fr. lieue), Pr. lega, legua, Cat. llegua,
							Sp. legua, Pg. legoa, Ital. lega.</p>
						<p> a. An itinerary measure of distance, varying in different countries, but usually estimated roughly at about 3 miles; app.
							never in regular use in England, but often occurring in poetical or rhetorical statements of distance.</p>
						<p>MARINE LEAGUE</p>
						<p>marine league: a unit of distance = 3 nautical miles or 3041 fathoms. Although the league appears never to have been an
							English measure, leuca occurs somewhat frequently in Anglo-Latin law-books (Bracton, Fleta, etc.); it is disputed whether
							in these works it means one mile or two.</p>

					</item>
					<item n="14">
						<term target="#allbound">All bounds of moderation</term>
						<p>Although Victor had earlier moralized against letting the pursuit of knowledge run away with one's sober judgment (I:3:12),
							here he portrays himself as indulging his hatred with the kind of impulsiveness and lack of restraint he had displayed in
							Ingolstadt. It is clear that what Alphonse Frankenstein had termed "immoderate grief" three paragraphs earlier (II:1:3) is
							not Victor's problem. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="15">
						<term target="#allpleas">All pleasures . . . life</term>
						<p>This is a remarkable sentence, redolent of all of Victor's earlier obsessiveness but now transposed into a kind of
							psychotic state. It is surely tied to earlier questions about the unhealthy products of the human imagination. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="16">
						<term target="#allthe">all the light I enjoyed came through the stye</term>
						<p>This is not easy to visualize, but Mary Shelley twice emphasizes the presence of this stye. She appears to do so for
							several interrelated reasons: in order to have a natural bulwark against the Creature's being detected by the cottagers;
							to place the Creature symbolically as close to the natural order as to human beings; and to reveal, against our visceral
							repugnance at the accompanying noise and stench (if the De Lacey household had been able to afford to keep a herd of
							swine), the level of subsistence to which necessity has reduced this being after six weeks or so of his existence. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="17">
						<term target="#alone">I am alone, and miserable</term>
						<p>In the 1818 edition the last noun of Volume 1, in Victor's narration, is "misery" (I:7:33), and the second volume opens on
							a scene in which he draws further into himself and his despair (II:1:1). Given the technical mastery of Frankenstein, it
							is thus perhaps only to be expected that the Creature's autobiographical account should conclude with the Creature in the
							exact condition of his Creator, sharing an existential misery compounded of solitude and guilt. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="18">
						<term target="#america">I will go . . . America</term>
						<p>Although there was relatively little Swiss (or German) emigration to the New World by the time this novel was written,
							there was of course a great amount of it from the country in which Frankenstein was published. Indeed, Percy Bysshe
							Shelley's grandfather had been born in the British Colonies of North America (in Passaic, New Jersey), whence he
							reimmigrated to Great Britain. The closest parallel for the Creature's plan, and probably one that would be uppermost in
							the minds of a contemporary reader, was the British penal colony established in 1788 at Botany Bay in Australia. There
							hardened convicts were transported so as to rid honest citizens from their threat to the common welfare. Over time, of
							course, these outcasts "civilized" a new continent. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="19">
						<term target="#anger">anger and hatred</term>
						<p>It may be difficult for the reader to suspend prior knowledge of the plot at this point and recall that Victor's one
							sighting of his Creature in the vicinity of Geneva does not constitute proof that he has done anything transgressive, let
							alone has accomplished the murder of William and the framing of Justine. Given what Victor actually knows of his Creature,
							this first greeting of him would seem to testify to a psychological disturbance, if not a real derangement. Certainly, he
							does not treat him as the prodigal son returning to his rightful father. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="20">
						<term target="#anticip">anticipations of joy</term>
						<p>The diction seems deliberately intended to evoke the end of Chapter 5 of Volume 1, where a full year later Victor and
							Clerval return from their walking tour around Ingolstadt—"with feelings of unbridled joy" (I:5:19)— to be greeted by a
							letter from Victor's father announcing the death of his brother William. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="21">
						<term target="#appear">appearance, different from any I had ever before seen</term>
						<p>The Creature had, of course, seen Victor before, but it was by dim moonlight, with Victor first in bed, then rushing
							hastily from the room (I:4:3). This is his first conscious encounter with another human being, whose mundane business is
							wholly disrupted by this unanticipated and sublime intrusion. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="22">
						<term target="#arbiters">arbiters of my future destiny</term>
						<p>The Creature's sense of his destiny stands in marked contrast to Victor's. Whereas the scientist sees himself as passively
							compelled by his destiny within an obsessive solitude, whether in his experiments with the principle of life or, later, in
							pursuit of the being that is its result, the Creature conceives of himself instinctively within a domesticated social
							context where he will be guided by others toward his self-realization. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="23">
						<term target="#archen">my arch-enemy, because my creator</term>
						<p>In Paradise Lost Satan bears this designation (I.81)—or is named Arch-foe (VI.259)—but it is ironically reversed here to
							apply to the figure who stands in place of God. Yet, to contemplate the phrase in isolation is to discern serious
							implications about the relation between sire and scion of a type that have greatly concerned modern psychoanalytic
							discourse. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="24">
						<term target="#ardently">I ardently desired</term>
						<p>Here the Creature joins the other principal male figures of the novel in the diction of burning intellectual ambition,
							repeating the phrasing earlier uttered by Walton and by Victor Frankenstein: see I:L3:1 and I:2:7.</p>

					</item>
					<item n="25">
						<term target="#artlang">the art of language</term>
						<p>Although Mary Shelley in this chapter seems deliberately to be emphasizing the Creature's "ardour" to place it within the
							context of the ambitions driving both Walton and Victor Frankenstein (see paragraph 9 above and note), she is effectively
							contrasting them. In the Creature's education language has a moral function, allowing communication among beings and
							operating as an instrument by which they may think and feel in common. True sympathy, the object of his utmost desire, is
							thus dependent upon language. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="26">
						<term target="#arve">the river Arve</term>
						<p>The Arve is fed by the glacier called the Mer de Glace (Sea of Ice), where the remaining chapters of Volume 2 will take
							place: the river descends from the mountain through the Chamounix Valley, turns to the east, and joins the Rhone river in
							its progress toward Lyons. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="27">
						<term target="#arveiron">the Arveiron</term>
						<p>The Arveiron is a glacial tributary the Shelleys visited on their excursion to Mont Blanc. Their visit is described in the
							account headed July 24 in Letter 4 of A History of a Six Weeks' Tour. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="28">
						<term target="#asbelong">as belonging to another earth, the habitations of another race of beings</term>
						<p>The simile is telling here. We will discover in the next chapter that the Alps can, indeed, support another "race" of
							beings. Yet, however much human imagination may discern in these altitudes the possibility of a transcendence of the human
							condition, neither a human nor another kind of being can effectually manage to do so. Moreover, "another race" of beings,
							if brought down from an imaginary conception to the solid ground of normative human existence would be considered, like
							Victor's Creature, alien and hounded from human society. The conflict between the unrestricted imagination and human
							society is total. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="29">
						<term target="#aspan">as Pandæmonium appeared</term>
						<p>This is the Creature's second knowing reference to Milton's Paradise Lost (see I.670ff. and X.418ff.): the first was when
							he remarked that Victor, in creating him, had cast him as Satan rather than Adam (II:2:11). The oddity of these learned
							citations goes unremarked for now, but will be explained five chapters later (II:7:7). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="30">
						<term target="#assdog">The ass and the lap-dog</term>
						<p>This fable is told by both Aesop and his French follower, Jean de la Fontaine (1621-1695), in his Fables. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="31">
						<term target="#atdistan">at a distance</term>
						<p>Even in social circumstances like this family outing Victor's separation of himself from his companions is conspicuous. The
							extreme variability of his movements here seems intended to remind us of his condition when he welcomed Clerval to
							Ingolstadt (I:4:12), hysterical and on the verge of a nervous breakdown. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="32">
						<term target="#autumn">late in autumn</term>
						<p>The creature leaves the ruins of the De Lacey cottage about a year after he arrived to take refuge there. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="33">
						<term target="#avalanch">the rumbling thunder of the falling avelânche</term>
						<p>The Shelleys witnessed such an avalanche on their excursion to Chamonix: see Letter 4 of A History of a Six Weeks' Tour,
							where the diction is very close to that of this passage. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="34">
						<term target="#awallet">a wallet</term>
						<p>This is a tote-sack or shoulder bag. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="35">
						<term target="#barerock">bare perpendicular rock</term>

						<p>Victor stands below the Aiguille du Dru (12,320 feet).</p>
						<p>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="../Gifs/dru.gif"/>
							</figure>
						</p>
						<p>From Walter Woodburn Hyde, "The Ascent of Mont Blanc," in National Geographic, 24:8 (1913), 861-942. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="36">
						<term target="#beast">I was like a wild beast</term>
						<p>The language once again affirms the Creature's affinity with nature and natural forces: his atavistic rage is a sublime
							emotional storm. Yet, we should recall, the same is true of that of the exemplary polished gentleman, Felix, at the end of
							the previous chapter (II:7:38). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="37">
						<term target="#beautif">beautiful</term>
						<p>The beautiful, in this formulation, would seem to be a characteristic understood only within a human context. That is to
							say, until the Creature can identify himself with human concerns and human emotions, he cannot distinguish the beautiful.
							The corollary of this, however, may not be so honorific to humanity. The birds with whom the creature first identified in
							paragraph four above seem wholly unconcerned with the sublime; but all humans are terrified of it and flee. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="38">
						<term target="#beauty">I beheld a countenance of angelic beauty</term>
						<p>We have no comparable description of Elizabeth Lavenza from Victor, whose appreciation of her virtues overshadows the few
							physical details he gives of her upon his return to his family at the end of of the first volume (I:6:40). In the
							unself-conscious innocence of the Creature, in contrast, not only do we realize that he has a nuanced appreciation for the
							beautiful, but we also comprehend that strong romantic desire—not a subject in which Victor seems particularly adept—is an
							aspect of his makeup, perhaps to be considered normal for a human being, but in the Creature's circumstances deeply
							problematical. Mary Shelley's delicate handling of the Creature's awakening to desire is an index of the complexity with
							which she endows his character. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="39">
						<term target="#beforsun">before the sun</term>
						<p>As the month is December, the sun in this fairly northern latitude would rise relatively late, at some time around 8 a.m. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="40">
						<term target="#begone">Begone, vile insect! or rather stay, that I may trample you to dust</term>
						<p>The language here has embarrassed some readers, but perhaps it is intended to be an embarrassment, all hot air and
							vaunting, ineffectual before the power that animates the eight-foot Creature. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="41">
						<term target="#being">being</term>
						<p>Victor unconsciously repeats the neutral language with which the Creature concludes his narrative ("This being you must
							create"). Within a few paragraphs, however, he will return to his usual store of epithets. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="42">
						<term target="#beneintn">benevolent intentions</term>
						<p>It is fair to say that Victor's intentions almost always outstrip his ability to realize them. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="43">
						<term target="#benev">benevolence</term>
						<p>It is a remarkable achievement of Mary Shelley's that by this point in the Creature's narrative, this word (and its
							derivatives) have become fully ironized. Continually repeated as it is (see, for instance, II:7:2 and II:7:9), this
							Enlightenment concept stands in a kind of verbal isolation, unsupported by any examples that might convince us of its
							dynamic, positive value, or even (outside the Creature's own actions) that active benevolence exists. Thus the Creature's
							ironic conclusion seems altogether appropriate. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="44">
						<term target="#benev2">benevolence</term>
						<p>In this paragraph the Creature skillfully assembles the conclusions to be abstracted from his treatment by the cottagers,
							touching on each of the themes so woven through the fabric of his discourse. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="45">
						<term target="#benevole">benevolent dispositions</term>
						<p>The Creature has been repeating this adjective (and the noun "benevolence") in seeming insistence on the unquestionable
							virtues of the cottagers. Now, the intrusion of the ensuing phrase ("I persuaded myself") and a next sentence in the form
							of a question artfully raises the doubts his narrative has suspended. The entire paragraph, indeed, evokes a litany of the
							high ideals of Enlightenment virtue gleaned by the Creature from his reading and quietly interrogates their efficacy for
							"a wretched outcast." </p>

					</item>
					<item n="46">
						<term target="#berries">berries, nuts, and roots</term>
						<p>Although it might seem eccentric to some readers, a crucial aspect of the Creature's bonding with the De Lacey family comes
							from the shared benevolence they practice to the natural world. Their mutual vegetarian nourishment is stressed in these
							adjacent paragraphs. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="47">
						<term target="#bestowed">Why . . . so wantonly bestowed</term>
						<p>This is the third time this phrasing has been heard in the volume. The first is at its very beginning where Victor
							confesses that he "ardently wished to extinguish that life which [he] had so thoughtlessly bestowed" (II:1:6). The second
							occurence takes place during the encounter on the Mer de Glace, where under the intensity of the experience Victor adds to
							his weight of guilt, vowing to "extinguish the spark that I so negligently bestowed" (II:2:8). The Creature thus taunts
							Victor with his own words and desires, but stresses the character of the negligence involved: his life, he asserts, has
							been "wantonly bestowed," which returns him to his earlier line of attack: "How dare you sport thus with life?" (II:2:7). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="48">
						<term target="#books">books</term>
						<p>The novel's continuing self-reflexiveness is quietly underscored here, but so is the idea of a personal library. A further
							step in the Creature's education and his exploration of his identity, reading books, rather than just overhearing them
							being read, frees him from another's tutelage, increasing his own sense of responsibility and maturity. Whether such books
							can make him happier is another question entirely. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="49">
						<term target="#bound">bound by ties</term>
						<p>As Alphonse Frankenstein continually speaks from the vantage of patriarch of the family, asserting an almost tribal sense
							of bonded attachment, so the Creature confronts Victor with his unique equivalence to those blood-ties, a bond Victor has
							from the first spurned. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="50">
						<term target="#burning">burning passion</term>
						<p>There is an unmistakeable erotic charge to the language of these paragraphs, but it is almost metaphysical in its
							conception. The Creature suggests that the rage awakened within him, which is fired by his rejection and desperate
							solitude, can only be slaked by being converted into a psychologically and socially constructive alternative, which is to
							say love. There are ramifications here as well for the "ardent" pursuits of both Walton and Victor Frankenstein. </p>
						<p>Although the notion of channeling libidinous forces into socially beneficial relationships might be thought particularly
							suited to a woman's perspective on modern culture, the conventions of the age kept most women authors from a direct
							engagement with issues of sexuality and its repression or displacement. A notable exception is Mary Wollstonecraft. Here
							one senses a true family resemblance. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="51">
						<term target="#burstall">burst all bounds of reason</term>
						<p>The Creature unconsciously echoes the very language Victor (II:1:6 and note) had used to express his violent aversion to
							him earlier in the chapter before their encounter in the mountains. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="52">
						<term target="#bythesun">by the sun . . . heaven</term>
						<p>Given the richness of context provided by Milton's representation of the Judeo-Christian Genesis in Paradise Lost, one
							cannot miss the alternate model being provided by the Creature, a pantheism rooted in nature. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="53">
						<term target="#cause">cause should produce such opposite effects</term>
						<p>Twice in the paragraph stressing the word "cause," the Creature learns that pleasure and pain proceed from the same force,
							a considerable development in his education and mental sophistication. If this is the groundwork of morality, however, it
							is important to recognize that it shares a common bond, as the earlier quotation from Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Mutability"
							may remind us, with the scientific systems that form so conspicuous a context for the novel (see II:2:3 and note). There
							are other elements emphasized in the novel that likewise exist on a neutral ground that can result in either good or ill:
							curiosity is an obvious case in point (II:2:16). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="54">
						<term target="#causfear">I will cause fear</term>
						<p>In this phrase the Creature encapsulates what will become the dynamic force of the third volume, an intense desire turned
							inside out and thus ironized, so that hatred is pursued with the single-minded obsession of passionate love. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="55">
						<term target="#cenis">across Mont Cenis</term>
						<p>This was the easiest route into Italy, across southeastern France from Chambery to Turin in northwestern Italy. The Mont
							Cenis Pass rises to only 6825 feet. This was Napoleon's invasion route to Italy in 1796, and thereafter the post-road was
							improved to allow uninterrupted traffic between the two countries. It was this road, indeed, that the Shelleys themselves
							would take shiortly after publication of the novel, in March 1818, on their trip to Italy. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="56">
						<term target="#chain">the chain . . . excluded</term>
						<p>The reference seems again to be to Paradise Lost (IV.49-53), and specifically to Satan's attempt to break the chain with
							which God links all his creatures in an eternal sharing of selves. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="57">
						<term target="#companio">his companion</term>
						<p>Felix's companion is the owner of the house, who holds as security a quarter-year deposit that because of his abrupt
							departure Felix will have to forfeit. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="58">
						<term target="#compass">thy compassion</term>
						<p>In effect, the Creature asks Victor to look the other way and listen to his story. We will recognize the similarity of this
							plea to that made to the blind De Lacey when the Creature first attempts to establish human community later in the volume
							(II:7:15). Throughout Frankenstein sound, rather than sight, is the means by which human sympathy is evoked. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="59">
						<term target="#compass3">compassion</term>
						<p>An appeal to justice must necessarily depend on compassion, fellow-feeling. This is the only occasion in the Creature's
							existence where, even momentarily, he has been accorded what we assume to be that fundamental right of human beings. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="60">
						<term target="#condemn">He was tried, and condemned to death</term>
						<p>This is, it should be obvious, the novel's second such condemnation of an innocent victim after a summary trial. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="61">
						<term target="#controul">I did not strive to controul them</term>
						<p>The power of the Creature's rage is shocking, perhaps as well to himself after having spent an entire year in isolation and
							under a regimen of strict and carefully enforced self-control. The infinitive, however, reminds us how severely that
							control has been earlier exercised by him. It might likewise call to mind the lack of restraint with which Victor
							Frankenstein pursued the researches that resulted in the Creature's birth (I:3:3). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="62">
						<term target="#converse">conversed with my family</term>
						<p>Such incongruity of tone can have its value (though Mary Shelley did decide in the third edition to remove the family
							presence altogether from Victor's excursion to Mont Blanc). We will shortly be reminded that there is another part of
							Victor's family he has assiduously avoided and to whom, unlike his conventional family, he has given no solicitude
							whatsoever. The oddity of tone here, quickly rectified by the gloomy weather of the next morning, almost unconsciously
							prepares us for the conversation so feared and so long postponed but now, given the state of Victor's psychological
							condition, clearly urgent. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="63">
						<term target="#cottager">names of the cottagers</term>
						<p>The naming of the cottagers depends not just on their individual identities but also on their family, i.e., their social,
							relations. That they thus have several different names, depending on which aspect is being emphasized, constitutes a new
							level of awareness on the Creature's part. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="64">
						<term target="#countena">his countenance bespoke bitter anguish, combined with disdain and malignity</term>
						<p>The nouns here are all associated with Satan and the Satanic in Paradise Lost: e.g. "anguish" (II.568; VI.340); "disdain"
							(I.98; II.680; V.666); "malign" (III.553; IV.503; VII.189). And yet, the framing language forces us to consider
							perspective: "bespoke" is not the same as "constitutes" in its implicit representation of reality; and if Victor, even as
							he articulates it, openly remarks that he "scarcely observed this," where, then, might his terms come from? As we will
							learn from the Creature himself (II:7:7), it is easy to insert oneself (or others) into the mythic texture of Paradise
							Lost: thus it might appear, as it were, that Victor does so first, here defining the Creature as Satanic not from sharp
							empirical observation but from literary—that is to say, cultural—convention. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="65">
						<term target="#create">you must create</term>
						<p>The change in verb form to a command is rhetorically powerful, but it also signals a shift in, broadly speaking, the
							political dynamics of the novel. Victor's power, a symbolic extension of that of his father and family, is no longer
							absolute, but can be successfully challenged by the figure who stands in the position of his son and who can command
							superior strength and tenacity. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="66">
						<term target="#creatsen">a creature of fine sensations</term>
						<p>Along with his acknowledgement of justice, Victor appears at last to have recognized what a masterpiece of work he created
							only to abandon. Even if he is not reminded of his original ambition to create "a new species," we certainly may be (see
							I:3:8). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="67">
						<term target="#cursed">Cursed (although I curse myself) be the hands that formed you</term>
						<p>Under the creature's unrelenting accusation, the self-destructive nature of Victor's hatred and its manifestation in the
							Creature-as-double are here at last openly admitted by him. Percy Bysshe Shelley will use the same formula a year later in
							writing the first act of Prometheus Unbound, where Prometheus summons the Phantasm of Jupiter, the specter of his enemy,
							to repeat the self-enchaining curse Prometheus had once pronounced upon Jupiter (see 1.258). There, too, the strong echoes
							of Paradise Lost suggest a reading of God and Satan in the manner represented in his "Defence of Poetry," as
							co-complicitous doubles. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="68">
						<term target="#cursed2">Cursed, cursed creator!</term>
						<p>This chapter begins with a remarkable series of linguistic echoes in which the Creature echoes the language of Victor
							Frankenstein, in part to indicate that comparable experiences have produced comparable misery, but also to underscore the
							affinity of creator and creation. The first element is this imprecation, a repetition of the curse Victor pronounced on
							himself at their meeting on the Mer de Glace (II:2:14 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="69">
						<term target="#dante">Dante's iron . . . hypocrites</term>
						<p>The reference is to Inferno 23.58ff. Here at the end of the volume we are recalled to the "hell of intense tortures" with
							which it began (II:1:1). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="70">
						<term target="#dareyou">dare you sport thus with life</term>
						<p>The moral power of this verb stands out against Victor's ineffectual name-calling, reminding us that in some sense
							"curiosity" (a word with considerable resonance in the first volume) is sport, as are all open-ended intellectual
							endeavors associated with the imagination. The pejorative sense of the word as used here against Victor is, appropriately,
							the sense invoked by Victor himself in silently indicting the Creature during the trial of Justine (I:7:11). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="71">
						<term target="#dayuse">daily usefulness, without which no man is fit for society</term>
						<p>Unlike his son (or, for that matter, Robert Walton), Alphonse Frankenstein shares Justine Moritz's sense, uttered as her
							last words (I:7:31 and note), of the value embodied in a humble, quotidian usefulness. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="72">
						<term target="#declared">I declared everlasting war . . . me</term>
						<p>The emphasis here is on the psychology of alienation, as centered in the antagonism between Satan and God in Paradise Lost
							(I.105-24). There, as Mary Shelley interprets the emotional dynamics, a cycle of destruction results from God's rejection
							of Satan. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="73">
						<term target="#deepdark">deep, dark, death-like solitude</term>

						<p>The language seems intended to invoke both hell and the grave as being synonymous with Victor's sense of himself, in the
							previous paragraph, as an "evil spirit." Behind this language a reader may sense the solitude of Coleridge's Ancient
							Mariner, won by Life-in-Death and obsessively reenacting his guilt. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="74">
						<term target="#deeprev">a deep and deadly revenge</term>
						<p>On an uncomplicated psychological plane Mary Shelley is representing the simple dynamics of the Creature's alienation. With
							no other presence to balance or feel for this injustice, in his solitude he works himself into a confirmed opposition to
							the world that has rejected and threatened him. The Enlightenment virtues of benevolence and sympathy, were they ever to
							be encountered by the Creature, would by their very nature undercut his introverted and exclusionary mental state and
							enforce a social communion. Once again, as in Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Alastor; or, the Spirit of Solitude," published in
							March 1816, we recognize that solitude constitutes an evil spirit leading one to ill. The opening paragraph of Volume 2,
							in which Victor Frankenstein reveals himself similarly introverted and plotting revenge as a means of assuaging his
							self-hatred is, indeed, an appropriate introduction to this dynamic that arches across the volume (see II:1:1 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="75">
						<term target="#deformed">one as deformed . . . deny herself to me</term>
						<p>As at the beginning of this chapter, so at its end the Creature is willing to repress his own desires to accord with the
							normative expectations of humanity. Although human beings cannot endure his sight, he will inure himself to make ugliness
							aesethetically acceptable to his eyes. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="76">
						<term target="#delacey">the family of De Lacey</term>
						<p>The marmoreal cast of this sentence throws the emphasis on the family unit. Whereas before the Creature had seen a
							patriarchal family as nurturing civilized values (II:7:6), here he has reason to interpret it from a contrasting
							perspective, as harboring the equivalent of ethnic prejudices on a small, tightly formed, and exclusionary scale. With
							that perspective in mind one might return to the family unit that Victor Frankenstein left a few hours back to consider
							how little different is its underlying ethos (II:1:3). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="77">
						<term target="#delicate">Felix was too delicate to accept this offer</term>
						<p>There is a marked similarity here between the sense of honor of Felix and that of Alphonse Frankenstein after rescuing the
							daughter of his old friend Beaufort from poverty (I:1:5). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="78">
						<term target="#delights">Chief delights</term>
						<p>The Creature implicitly reaffirms his part in a natural order and his own affinity with nature. Once again, we are reminded
							that in his composition there are non-human creaturely attributes (see I:3:9 and note) that fit him for the wild. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="79">
						<term target="#deprived">deprived of his wealth and rank</term>
						<p>Given the nature of the injustice visited upon Felix and his family, it is especially fitting that Volney's Ruins should
							form the basic educational text in the cottage. We should recall that it is from that book that the Creature learns, and
							Felix and Safie are bitterly reminded, of the necessities of wealth and rank (II:5:16). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="80">
						<term target="#descend">I believe, descended</term>
						<p>Victor's workshop, he reported earlier (I:3:9), was a cell at the top of the house, separated in a complex way from the
							main part of the edifice. Presumably, the bedchamber to which he fled at the awakening of the Creature (I:4:3) was on a
							floor below. There the Creature wandered and awoke Victor who then in terror plunged outside. By some means unknown to
							Victor and unremembered by the Creature, the newly created being made his way from the house to the streets outside the
							courtyard, where Victor spent the night, and thence into the countryside surrounding Ingolstadt, where at last he fell
							asleep. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="81">
						<term target="#desert">desert mountains and dreary glaciers are my refuge</term>
						<p>"Desert" here means "of the wilderness" (cf. III:3:1 and note). This account, then, exactly fulfills the prescription
							innocently thought by Victor as he approached the alpine range, that these mountains might be "the habitations of another
							race of beings" (II:1:12). Since Mont Blanc was first scaled only in 1786, the fact that the Creature has taken up his
							abode there indicates just how superior to conventional human endurance Victor has made him. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="82">
						<term target="#deserved">deserved better treatment</term>
						<p>This would appear a premonition of the Creature's own experience with the De Lacey family. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="83">
						<term target="#desire">the greater became my desire</term>
						<p>The Creature's intensity, like the suddenness of his admiration for Safie (II:5:4 and note), has the ring of adolescence to
							it. It is not, then, utterly surprising that it should remind us of the diction of the two "ardent" men whose youthful
							discourse we have already overheard: Walton (see I:L1:2 and I:L2:2) and Victor Frankenstein (see I:2:7, I:3:1, and I:3:6).
							Burning desire is a characteristic all three share. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="84">
						<term target="#desolate">my desolate state</term>
						<p>Desolation is, indeed, the appropriate term for a condition in which the Creature is so alienated from his original state
							that he feels the rebirth of spring as an ironic counterforce to his internal degeneration. Mary Shelley carefully marks
							the inherent "unnaturalness" and thus self-destructiveness of such a psychological condition. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="85">
						<term target="#detest">a destable monster</term>
						<p>None of the cottagers, of course, has as yet to lay sight on the Creature. It is a mark of how self-alienated his education
							has made him that he can presume such a reaction without having to put it to the test. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="86">
						<term target="#devcott">the devoted cottage</term>
						<p>That is, reserved for destruction, the same usage as in the encounter with Victor on the Mer de Glace (II:2:11 and note.) </p>

					</item>
					<item n="87">
						<term target="#devil">Devil!</term>
						<p>This is the first word that Victor utters to his Creature. Perhaps, as the allusions to Satan in the previous paragraph
							suggest, it is already in his mind. But, there is a dimension to this epithet beyond its effectiveness as an index to
							Victor's mental state, a timeless and mythic dimension. Although rigorously suppressed wherever organized Christendom
							extended its arms into secular society, the writings of heretical theology, particularly from Gnostic sects, continually
							revert to the concurrence of creation and the fall as two aspects of a single event. Thus to create is to cast out, on a
							universal level as well as, literally so, in childbirth. The cast-off in this case functions as Satan in a dual sense—as a
							disrupter of the putative unity of God and his coextensive creation, and—from the Hebrew root—as the accuser, who here
							immediately upbraids Victor Frankenstein for not doing his duty by his creature.</p>
						<p>Note how carefully Milton embeds this coincidence, without heretically stressing a linkage, in the moment where God divides
							himself so as to function on a second level, as a Creative Word, the Logos that will render God's conceptual blueprint for
							the universe into a workable reality (Paradise Lost, V.594-617). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="88">
						<term target="#devoted">my devoted head</term>
						<p>Johnson's 1755 Dictionary offers us the appropriate definitions for this period, definitions virtually lost to modern
							English usage:</p>
						<p> To addict; to give up to ill.<lb/> To curse; to execrate; to doom to destruction.</p>
						<p>For the second meaning Johnson helpfully cites the Satanic legions in Paradise Lost, V.890.</p>
						<p>The phrase "devoted head" is so common a usage as to appear to be a customary eighteenth-century idiom.</p>

					</item>
					<item n="89">
						<term target="#doomed">doomed to waste his powers for . . . few</term>
						<p>This suggests a different kind of determinism from that continually evoked by Victor Frankenstein, a social and economic
							form of destiny, what Marx was to denominate as wage slavery. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="90">
						<term target="#dream">But it was all a dream</term>
						<p>As the preceding paragraphs have made clear, the more the Creature reads the more he becomes conscious of alternate plot
							possibilities, of disparities between the worlds conjured up by desire and the imagination and the inescapable reality of
							his condition. Rather than find solace in his imaginative life, he experiences an increasing desperation. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="91">
						<term target="#dressed">they dressed</term>
						<p>Compare to II:3:7 and note. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="92">
						<term target="#drewtear">they at once drew tears of sorrow and delight from my eyes</term>
						<p>This is only the second occasion in which the Creature has shed tears, the other being on the first night of his existence
							(II:3:2). Yet how different is this repetition, another sign of the growing refinement of his emotional life. His
							oxymoronic response to music (and perhaps to Safie as well) is a further example of how his education proceeds by
							encompassing opposites (see II:3:6 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="93">
						<term target="#earth">Oh, earth!</term>
						<p>A curious, unusual vocative, but one indicating the Creature's continual association with natural forces. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="94">
						<term target="#enemies">enemies</term>
						<p>Victor directly rejects the Creature's overture and vow not to be set in opposition. To Victor, whose rejection of his
							Creature has hardened into a way of life, there is no alternative to such opposition. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="95">
						<term target="#enkindle">enkindled</term>
						<p>The diction reminds us of the numerous uses of "ardent" and its derivatives (from Latin ardere, 'to burn': see definitions)
							in Volume 1: see I:3:1 for instance, and note. Out in the world rather than confined to a hovel, the Creature's capacity
							for ardor carries dangerous implications. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="96">
						<term target="#entered">entered the valley</term>

						<p> Nineteenth-century travelers entering the valley of Chamonix. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="97">
						<term target="#epithets">loaded me with epithets</term>
						<p>That it is to stop a child's naming that impels the Creature almost accidentally to kill him is significant in several
							ways. Most importantly, the Creature is existentially unnamed, lacking an identity that denominates a particularized
							selfhood and a socialized connectedness, the sort of implicit identity by which William himself immediately commands
							authority. It was Victor Frankenstein's initial duty as his creator to accord him that name but he fled from the
							responsibility. Thus, everywhere else in the novel, with Victor from his distance actively participating in the process,
							the Creature is identified, not by a name but through epithets, as being outside a human sphere. In a symbolic sense at
							least, William dies for his naming, for taking on a function only his brother has the right to perform. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="98">
						<term target="#evil">I looked . . . evil</term>
						<p>The "as yet" introduces an ominous tone into this account, but it also reminds us that the Creature as a voyeur hiding from
							the world, experiences that world only vicariously. That his retreat is fragile and his faith in the future tentative are
							all that he can be sure of. Elizabeth Lavenza, expressing a similarly impossible desire to escape the world, had
							articulated similar sentiments at the beginning of this volume (II:1:9). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="99">
						<term target="#evilpass">your evil passions</term>
						<p>Victor, with something like a Genevan Calvinist's sense of original sin, cannot bring himself to think of his Creature as
							created without internal flaw. What we hear in his phrase is the language of depravity, which is not an element that ever
							informs the Creature's narrative of his life. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="100">
						<term target="#evilspir">an evil spirit</term>

						<p>Mary Shelley seems deliberately to invoke the terms of Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Alastor: or, the Spirit of Solitude,"
							published in March 1816 a few months before the summer trip to Geneva. The title was suggested by their friend Thomas Love
							Peacock, poet and novelist, and an autodidact in classical Greek, who conveyed to Percy Bysshe Shelley the aptness of
							using the Greek word for a kakodaimon, "alastor," as the governing term for his poem. The word kakodaimon translates
							exactly into the "evil spirit" invoked here by Victor Frankenstein, and its association with solitude is manifest in these
							circumstances as well. At the same time, a sensitive reader cannot help observing the likeness of this term to the diction
							Victor commonly uses to describe his Creature, which he now, without recognizing the similarity, applies to himself. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="101">
						<term target="#excess">excess of misery</term>
						<p>Although we are apparently returned here to Alphonse Frankenstein's worries over "immoderate grief" with which the volume
							began (II:1:3). We are reminded both that "misery" is the last noun of Volume 1 and that the Creature ended his account of
							his life with the declaration of his own misery (see II:8:36 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="102">
						<term target="#exhort">the exhortations of her father</term>
						<p>Mary Shelley's insistence on the deference of daughters to fathers might be logically connected with her dedication of this
							novel to her own father; at the same time, it is rather at odds with her mother's views, and particularly with her running
							argument against Rousseau's views on female education in Book 5 of her Vindication of the Rights of Woman. What is odd in
							the present case is the fact that Felix does not mirror Agatha's reaction. His stance suggests something of the distance
							between son and father already accentuated in the case of Victor and Alphonse Frankenstein. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="103">
						<term target="#exile">a perpetual exile</term>
						<p>The status of persona non grata, if somewhat unusual, was certainly not unheard of in France either before, or after, the
							Revolution. Napoleon, in fact, became famous for sending those who displeased him into exile. With one of these, Germaine
							de Staël, he got more than he bargained for: resentful of her criticism of his authoritarian rule, he banished her forever
							from French dominions, whereupon she set out on a long tour of Europe, speaking out against the Emperor of France and
							attracting legions of admirers wherever she went. One reason that she established herself at Coppet and gathered around
							her a set of pan-European intellectuals was that she could not return to Paris. Mary Shelley, in the ambience of Geneva in
							the summer of 1816, would have well aware of this record. Madame de Staël's last book, published posthumously in 1820, was
							called Ten Years of Exile. Whether Napoleon was afforded a copy on St. Helena, his island of exile in the middle of the
							Atlantic Ocean, is unlikely. Nonetheless, Germaine de Staël decidedly had the last laugh. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="104">
						<term target="#falofsnw">fall of snow had taken place</term>
						<p>It would appear that a month or more has passed since the Creature's birth, and with autumn's end he is experiencing the
							decrease of nature's bounty. We are now in December, and early signs of winter have appeared. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="105">
						<term target="#feelings">feelings which . . . have made me what I am</term>
						<p>Up to now the Creature has been remarking seasonal changes and their reflection in the landscape. Here, suddenly, the sense
							of internal divorce and self-alienation already present in the previous chapter (II:4:4, II:4:13) opens out into a split
							between past and present selves equivalent, as the emphatic language might suggest, to Adam's fall from paradise. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="106">
						<term target="#feltcold">I felt cold also</term>
						<p>Victor Frankenstein has already supplied additional details to elucidate the weather being experienced here. The Creature,
							he recounts, was born "on a dreary night of November," and the next morning dawned "dismal and wet," with rain pouring
							"from a black and comfortless sky" (I:4:6). Although, if we then follow the Creature's account, it subsequently cleared
							sufficiently for the light to seem oppressive to him, later that night, the time to which he is referring in his
							narrative, it reverted to a seasonably cold temperature. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="107">
						<term target="#fiend">the fiend that lurked in my heart</term>
						<p>As with the double resonance of "wretch" at the end of the previous paragraph, here Victor applies to himself the term he
							had used to refer to the Creature three paragraphs earlier. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="108">
						<term target="#fiend1">the fiend with an air of exultation</term>
						<p>Nothing in the Creature's statements in the previous paragraph—particularly given the stark alternatives he lays before
							Victor at its end—suggests that he is exulting at this point. Rather, the remark along with the epithet convey Victor's
							intrinsic sense of superiority and of his right to wield a power capable of affording satisfaction to an underling.
							Whatever Victor may regard as "the duties of a creator," they do not yet forestall him from calling his creature a "fiend"
							and regarding him as "odious." </p>

					</item>
					<item n="109">
						<term target="#fiend2">fiend</term>
						<p>At the beginning of the chapter he bore the neutral term "being"; but, as Victor indulges his rage, so the Creature's
							identity changes for him as well. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="110">
						<term target="#first">first . . . kindness</term>
						<p>What the Creature does not know is that this will also be the last such expression of kindess directed to him. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="111">
						<term target="#fool">I was a fool</term>
						<p>This calm reconsideration of his actions attests to the analytical capacities of the Creature and pictures him once again
							as superior to those who spurn him. On a darker side, it also exhibits him in the process of internalizing himself as
							Other and of reifying a concept of normative reality in which he lacks any secure place. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="112">
						<term target="#forcesol">forced solitude</term>
						<p>Where Victor hedges, the Creature counters: as "evil passions" the phrase Victor employed four paragraphs before, will
							disappear within an ambience of sympathy, so (as "vices") they are the product of solitude. Again, we hear the resonance
							of the title of Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Alastor; or, the Spirit of Solitude," published a few months before Frankenstein
							was begun (see II:8:21 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="113">
						<term target="#french">are you French</term>
						<p>In ordinary circumstances this would not seem so absurd a question. The fact that the Creature lacks a national identity,
							however, throws into relief how deeply embedded are national prejudices even among the enlightened. We have already
							witnessed in the French reaction to Safie's father (II:6:3) and in his abuse of Felix's kindness (II:6:12) how
							mean-spiritedness is served by national identity. Part of Volney's aim in Les Ruines is to eradicate such defining
							ideological concepts. That the Creature is thus born without them indicates his superiority and, ironically, is a further
							example of how he does not fit into normative human society. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="114">
						<term target="#friend">a feeling and kind friend</term>
						<p>Up to this point all the expression of sympathy has come as a surmise of the Creature's about the cottagers. This assertion
							reminds us that for something like a year the Creature has intervened actively to assist the cottagers in their daily
							existence. His fellow-feeling has, indeed, extended into kind actions on their behalf. The heavy irony behind this scene
							is that all the Enlightenment virtues the Creature has presumed to be attributes of the cottagers have been employed by
							him on a daily basis. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="115">
						<term target="#frstflow">the first little white flower</term>
						<p>The snowdrop, a common subject of poems on fragile beauty and mutability, often associated with young women, in the late
							eighteenth century. Like the crocus, the snowdrop blooms in late winter. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="116">
						<term target="#gnashing">gnashing of teeth</term>
						<p>In his pain and anger the Creature imitates the actions of Victor Frankenstein twice noted in the first volume (I:L4:10 and
							note; I:7:27 and note) and again at the beginning of the second (II:1:6 and note). The Creature will again be portrayed as
							gnashing his teeth in the third volume (III:3:13). The prototype for this behaviour remains the Satan of Milton's Paradise
							Lost, VI.340. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="117">
						<term target="#goalone">I determined to go alone</term>
						<p>It is of some use to the design of Frankenstein that Victor go onto the Mer de Glace by himself. At the same time, his
							rationale, that another human being would "destroy" what he considers its "solitary grandeur," is characteristic of his
							constitutional withdrawal into a contemplative introversion. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="118">
						<term target="#godlike">a godlike science</term>
						<p>This seems another connection with legendary associations of Prometheus. In Percy Shelley's Prometheus Unbound, Asia, the
							Titan's consort, credits him with responsibity for our access to language: "He gave man speech, and speech created
							thought,/ Which is the measure of the universe" (II.iv.72-73). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="119">
						<term target="#goodspir">good spirit</term>
						<p>The Creature's inherent generosity earns him this appellation, which is an ironic reversal of that used by Victor
							Frankenstein to describe himself in the introductory paragraph of Volume 2. There he conceives himself as wandering like
							"an evil spirit" (II:1:1). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="120">
						<term target="#goodwill">the good-will . . . De Lacey</term>
						<p>Although De Lacey's blindness allows the Creature unmediated access to him, another reason he approaches the elder man is
							his instinctive veneration for those older than he, a transference from the respect he would have accorded Victor
							Frankenstein. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="121">
						<term target="#gowithout">I determined to go without a guide</term>
						<p>It is of some use to the design of Frankenstein that Victor go onto the Mer de Glace by himself. At the same time, his
							rationale, that another human being would "destroy" what he considers its "solitary grandeur," is characteristic of his
							constitutional withdrawal into a contemplative introversion. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="122">
						<term target="#greater">the greater part of his property</term>
						<p>Obviously, Safie is also a part of the Turk's property and is expected to be part of the final shipment of his goods home.
							Four paragraphs earlier, we recall, the De Laceys have had their entire fortune confiscated by the state for abetting the
							Turk's escape. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="123">
						<term target="#greedily">I greedily devoured the remnants</term>
						<p>Although on the face of it this appears like stealing, the Creature makes no distinction between this human fare and the
							other bounty of the earth on which he has been living. His unconscious socialism is surely a deliberate ploy of Mary
							Shelley's, reflecting a general family political viewpoint. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="124">
						<term target="#guilty">The guilty are allowed, by human laws, bloody as they may be, to speak in their own defence before they
							are condemned</term>

						<p>Unknowingly yet shrewdly, throughout this speech the Creature touches Victor Frankenstein on his most sensitive moral
							points. Watching Justine condemned for a crime for which he held himself responsible, Victor was (and continues to be)
							racked by a sense of injustice. Yet, in condemning the Creature, he is just as guilty of fundamental injustice as had been
							the Genevan magistracy. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="125">
						<term target="#hasten">I now hasten</term>
						<p>The last plot line of the novel, that involving the Arabian Safie, is introduced at this significant point of the
							narrative, the central chapter of the work as published in 1818. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="126">
						<term target="#hateful">Hateful day when I received life</term>

						<p>The Creature, cursing both his own creation and his Creator, tellingly echoes Victor's own imprecation on himself uttered
							several hours earlier (see II:2:14 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="127">
						<term target="#heart">my heart was heavy</term>
						<p>This is an artistically crafted interval during which Mary Shelley deftly brings Victor back to the center of her novel as
							a moral being. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="128">
						<term target="#hearts">the hearts . . . charity</term>
						<p>This a sentiment born of Enlightenment optimism that Mary Shelley would have heard echoed in her father's home as well as
							in the one she established with Percy Bysshe Shelley. It is based on a sense of the shared values of the human community.
							For it to be discovered a falsehood would profoundly affect normative ethical premises. The very blandness of this
							discourse testifies to our comfortable assurances and prepares the way for a devastating reversal of them. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="129">
						<term target="#hellish">hellish triumph</term>
						<p>The Creature has internalized the dynamics of Paradise Lost, setting himself as a reactionary force to undo the world of
							his creator. That such desolation, rather than a triumph, is inherently defeating and involves the undoing of his self is
							well understood by Mary Shelley, yet to be learned by the Creature. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="130">
						<term target="#hellwith">I, like the arch fiend, bore a hell within me</term>
						<p>His limited reading immediately calls to his mind the mythic model for his profound alienation, Milton's Satan,
							establishing a new line of psychological congruence between the tormented Creature and Victor Frankenstein, who used the
							identical expression at the end of Volume I (Chapter 8 in the 1831 edition): see I:7:30 and note. Victor also makes
							similar statements in I:4:5 and II:1:1 (and note). The allusion is to Satan's soliloquy upon Mount Niphates: Paradise
							Lost, IV.75. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="131">
						<term target="#hethus">He thus began his tale</term>
						<p>We enter here into a third level of narrative, one that is embedded within Victor Frankenstein's autobiography, which is
							itself being transcribed by Walton each night of its recounting for his sister's future perusal. Issues of the authority
							and even the reliability of any particular level of the narrative thus abound and have raised serious debate in the
							critical literature on the novel. As the Creature twice in these two paragraphs speaks of his "tale," so Victor refers to
							his narrative as a "tale" as well (see I:L4:30 and I:3:13). The underlying question is how true is any tale. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="132">
						<term target="#hideous">Hideous monster!</term>
						<p>The combination of terms here may be accidental, but is wonderfully encapsulating of the dynamics of the novel thus far.
							The Creature is denominated an Other even as the fixed point for comparison is lodged in the established, public figure of
							Alphonse Frankenstein, who, from the point of view of his sons (and of himself) is never capable of being viewed in the
							light of alterity. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="133">
						<term target="#hiseyes">he placed his hands before his eyes</term>
						<p>This instinctive gesture is part of a pattern across the novel in which those with sight must technically blind themselves
							in order to endure the presence of the Creature: see I:4:3 and note. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="134">
						<term target="#hisson">His son was bred in the service of his country</term>
						<p>This could mean, narrowly, that Felix had been educated for the French diplomatic corps or, more broadly, to function in
							the upper levels of the government bureaucracy. Whatever the case, there is a clear link between his family and
							expectations and those of Victor Frankenstein, whose father and forefathers, from a strong sense of civic duty, have held
							positions of public trust in Geneva. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="135">
						<term target="#howmove">How can I move thee</term>
						<p>As Victor is self-conscious about the shape and impact of his narrative (see I:7:13 and note), so is his Creature. His
							question also curiously echoes Justine Moritz's recognition that facts alone are not sufficient to exonerate her (I:7:5
							and note); if she is to establish her claim to innocence she must move her auditors. Aside from such thematic continuities
							within the novel, this issue is likewise very much alive in the poetry that Percy Shelley was writing contemporaneously,
							particularly in The Revolt of Islam, where Cythna's eloquence is an important element in spreading political and cultural
							enlightenment: see particularly Canto 8. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="136">
						<term target="#hut">the hut upon the mountain</term>
						<p>Mary Shelley knows from experience of what she writes. There were actually two such huts on Montanvert above the Sea of
							Ice, one made of wood and erected by an Englishman named Blair in 1779, and the other of stone constructed by a Frenchmen,
							Desportes, in the year 1795 (Charles Edward Mathews, The Annals of Mont Blanc [Boston: L.C. Page, 1900]).</p>

					</item>
					<item n="137">
						<term target="#ialone">am I not alone, miserably alone?</term>
						<p>Not only does the Creature's terrible solitude remind us of the mental isolation into which Victor Frankenstein finds
							himself plunged, but it also takes us back to the original scene in which this narrative is being recited, upon a ship in
							the midst of the Arctic Ocean, remote from either land or other human beings. As in Walton's letters (Letter I and Letter
							II), so here one cannot fail to hear the echo of Coleridge's "Rime of the Ancient Mariner": "Alone, alone, all, all
							alone,/ Alone on a wide wide sea!" (line 232-3). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="138">
						<term target="#iard2">I ardently desired to understand them</term>
						<p>As earlier in his ruminations about language acquisition (II:4:9), the Creature unconsciously adopts the exact phrasing of
							Victor Frankenstein (I:2:7) as he looks forward to his education at Ingolstadt. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="139">
						<term target="#iardent">I ardently wished to extinguish that life</term>

						<p>Heavy irony attends this choice of diction. Not only are we reminded of the "ardent" desire with which, when young, Victor
							(I:2:7) (and Walton—I:L1:2) eagerly pursued scientific knowledge, but we can associate with that innocent desire the more
							complicated ardency driving Victor obsessively toward the scientific breakthrough that was the birth of this Creature: see
							I:3:1 and note. This is the point in the novel when the language of intense love first is used to embody the designs of a
							passionate hatred. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="140">
						<term target="#iexclaim">I exclaimed</term>
						<p>It is a curious coincidence that the last time Victor called upon the heavens (I:6:22) he instantly beheld his Creature. If
							Mary Shelley intended to signify something through this coincidence, she certainly left no hint, and it has not been
							explained by commentators. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="141">
						<term target="#ignashed">I gnashed my teeth</term>
						<p>The same characteristic has been the subject of our recent focus, as Victor's anguished frustration in Justine's prison
							cell issues in this extraordinary physical reaction (I:7:27). Earlier we witnessed the same phenomenon when Victor was
							brought aboard Walton's ship (I:L4:10 and note), which, since it is an event almost contemporary with his present
							narrative account must give us a sense of how habitual this reaction has become; also how revelatory of psychological (and
							moral) disturbance it is. Two other characters engage in the same passionate behavior: the Creature (III:3:13) and
							Milton's Satan. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="142">
						<term target="#imagine">the imagination</term>

						<p>As has already been evident in earlier chapters, in Mary Shelley's perspective the imagination is a power at once of great
							dynamic force and ethically neutral in its operations, leading to good or evil ends depending on the psychological
							framework in which it exists. The darker side of this mental attribute has been especially invoked as events in the novel
							have taken a tragic turn: see, for instance, I:3:7 and note, I:4:18 and note, I:6:27 and note. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="143">
						<term target="#immense">immense mountains and precipices</term>
						<p>The reader observes a carefully registered journey from the beautiful into the sublime, from what Elizabeth has proposed as
							a domestic enclosure, warding off the unimaginable and protecting the family unit from threat, into another confrontation,
							at least for Victor, with elemental nature, with destruction and with fresh creation. The transitional point of this rite
							of passage is marked by the village of St. Martin in the Shelleys' account of their excursion to Chamonix in History of a
							Six Weeks' Tour. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="144">
						<term target="#imperfct">an imperfect and solitary being</term>
						<p>The Creature's enforced loneliness has been physically brought home to him, but that he should already conceive of himself
							at this early stage of his experience as flawed seems to involve progress through social rejection to a new and not
							exactly liberating stage of self-consciousness. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="145">
						<term target="#improved">I improved more rapidly</term>
						<p>This is a nice detail in itself but not wholly devoid of further import. However boastful the Creature may be about his
							advancement, the important point, and one that has been slowly dawning on the reader, is that he is extremely intelligent.
							Like his "father," he is superior to his fellow-students (I:3:2). With his great stature, his exquisitely fine feelings,
							and his mental quickness, he should have been equipped, in Victor's early aspiration, to be a "new species" (I:3:8) of
							superhuman being. Instead, he has been spurned. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="146">
						<term target="#impulses">If our impulses were confined to hunger, thirst, and desire, we might be nearly free</term>
						<p>Although Victor cannot know yet what is fully involved in his philosophical opinings, the questions of what constitutes
							human identity and how humans may be free will turn out to be major concerns of this second volume of the novel. As with
							the previous sentence, Victor is here in the process of unconsciously setting the stage for a major development in his
							education. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="147">
						<term target="#inclemen">the inclemency of the season, and still more from the barbarity of man</term>
						<p>The Creature, who appears to educate himself by a process of progressive binary distinctions, here broaches his master
							categories, nature and humanity, both of them, given the season of his birth and the shock of his first human encounters,
							seemingly inhospitable to him. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="148">
						<term target="#increase">Increase of knowledge . . . was</term>
						<p>The Creature once again echoes the opening soliloquy of Byron's Manfred (1817) (see II:5:18 for the earlier instance). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="149">
						<term target="#inhabits">the hapless fate of its original inhabitants</term>
						<p>The Creature and Safie alike bemoan the conquering of native Americans of both the Northern and Southern hemispheres by the
							various European imperial powers, who in many cases reduced the natives to a condition of slavery. The Creature's
							emotional identification with their fate is unself-conscious at this point, but the progress of his education is leading
							him to understand an fundamental similarity with their abjectness (see, for instance, II:9:5 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="150">
						<term target="#injust">injustice</term>
						<p>There is a qualitative difference between this sense of injustice and what the Creature has felt earlier. Here, after doing
							a good deed, he has been been judged undesirable in a preemptive manner and physically punished. Thus, what festers
							mentally as well as physically is that a simple action to save a life has been met with a violent, life-threatening
							reaction from the larger society of human beings. He feels no longer merely rejected by this world but actively menaced. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="151">
						<term target="#insanity">a kind of insanity</term>
						<p>Victor will exactly echo this language at the very end of Volume 2 (Chapter 17 in the 1831 edition), in II:9:23. </p>
						<p> As he is superior to other human beings in stature and endurance, and finely tuned both emotionally and intellectually,
							perhaps we should not be surprised at the sublimity of the Creature's emotional outburst. Or, at least we should be no
							more surprised than we are at the inarticulate ranting of Victor Frankenstein when they meet on the Mer de Glace (II:2:6)
							or at the fury of Felix De Lacey (II:7:38), both of whom are the products of cultivated families and refined educations. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="152">
						<term target="#instinct">instinctively, finding myself so desolate</term>
						<p>In contrast to Victor, who through his intellectual obsession at Ingolstadt virtually sequestered himself from both family
							and associates, the Creature, born into a natural humanity, feels oppressed by his solitude. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="153">
						<term target="#instruct">She instructed her daughter . . . religion</term>
						<p>As with the condescension to Justine's Catholicism (I:5:6, I:7:21), this ostensible religious bias needs to be placed
							within the conventions of English publishing and religious attitudes. It is unlikely that Mary Shelley herself subscribes
							to them. Indeed, if in this chapter one reads in the attitudes of Turks to women some sense of reflection on contemporary
							English attitudes, then, Mary Shelley would appear to be playing something of her mother's game. And the mother-daughter
							relationship here certainly testifies to that which Mary Shelley derived from the frequent perusal of her mother's
							writings, an inculcation of ideals of independence on which, like, Safie she was not afraid to act. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="154">
						<term target="#instrumt">an instrument</term>
						<p>This will be named as a guitar (II:5:3), when the Creature is sufficently educated in human ways to know the word for it. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="155">
						<term target="#intercha">interchange of kindness</term>
						<p>That the Creature's argument is wholly based on Englightenment premises about the function of virtue makes them practically
							irresistible. Here he invokes the golden rule as the single desire of his existence. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="156">
						<term target="#iought">I ought to be thy Adam; but I am rather the fallen angel, whom thou drivest from joy for no misdeed</term>
						<p>The Creature delivers a sudden telescoping and radical interpretation of the mythic text that stands behind this entire
							narrative, Milton's Paradise Lost. The point behind the Creature's distinction is that Adam fell by knowingly commiting a
							sinful deed, whereas Satan, in contrast, in this reading was intended to fall from heaven as an intrinsic part of the
							conception of God's new creation. Most readers of Milton's epic would not countenance a reading of Satan as more sinned
							against than sinning, but it is the general interpretation that Percy Bysshe Shelley offers in the famous passage of his
							"Defence of Poetry" devoted to the poem. Since that document dates from 1821, five years after the beginning of
							Frankenstein, however well it glosses the antagonism of Victor and his Creature, it ought not to be read in retrospect as
							explaining this usage. One might, however, wish to argue that the representation in Mary Shelley's novel either influenced
							her husband's interpretation or was worked out as a reading in tandem with him. Whatever the case, the emphasis is
							unmistakeable here, that the Creature sees himself as like Satan, "irrevocably excluded" from bliss, which—although Milton
							(in Satan's soliloquy on Mount Niphates, IV.32ff.) tries to finesse the issue—is how received theology forced him to
							represent the fallen archangel in his epic. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="157">
						<term target="#ipersuad">I persuaded myself</term>

						<p> Whatever self-examination Victor undertakes, he cannot appear to see what the reader does, that the same habitual
							obsessiveness regulates his thoughts, turned now, not on a scientific experiment, but on the inner landscape of the mind
							over which he pores with a customarily intense scrutiny. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="158">
						<term target="#ireliev">Thus I relieve thee</term>
						<p>Although the Creature here gains the bitter satisfaction of forcing Victor to confront his own responsibility for having
							created a being of such surpassing ugliness that he himself cannot bear his sight, at the same time this aggressive
							gesture imposes the threat of his great physical power upon his weaker creator. It sharply emphasizes the aesthetic
							problem he poses for human beings; but this gesture does not by any means seem limited solely to that end. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="159">
						<term target="#isatdown">I sat down and wept</term>
						<p>As in the infant grin with which the Creature greeted Victor after his birth (I:4:3) here again we are suddenly reminded
							that he is a newborn, signalling his wants by crying. But, cast off by his creator and forced to make his way into the
							world in utter solitude, his wants are so enormous that here we are perhaps intended by the similarity of diction to
							recall the timbres of one of the most famous songs of exile (Psalm 137) in the Western tradition. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="160">
						<term target="#isoard">I so ardently desire</term>
						<p>The same phrasing was used by the Creature to describe his obsession with learning to speak (see II:4:9). After all the
							variants on the term, applied to and linking the intellectual passions of Walton, Victor, and the Creature, the reader is
							hardly prepared to encounter it here in its primary sense, as an expression of uninhibited and undeflected sexual
							instinct. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="161">
						<term target="#italian">the Italian state which they inhabited</term>
						<p>From 1796, when Napoleon invaded Italy until 1814 when he was exiled to Elba, in fact, most of Italy was either under the
							rule or the strong influence of France, and with the restoration of the old monarchies in 1815, although the politics
							decidedly changed, the French influence on Italy remained strong. Whether it would in either case have involved
							extradition from Livorno of a non-French national might be questionable, but the Turk's fears are not entirely groundless. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="162">
						<term target="#ivowed">I vowed eternal hatred . . . mankind</term>
						<p>This is actually the second such vow. The first, uttered after being driven from the De Lacey's cottage (paragraph 3 above
							above and note) was, upon sober (and mistaken) self-reflection, withdrawn. This time the Creature will carry out his
							threat. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="163">
						<term target="#iwasapor">I was a poor, helpless, miserable wretch</term>
						<p>With telling artistic assurance Mary Shelley has the Creature, who up to this point has referred to himself only by
							personal pronouns, name himself with the same word originally used by Victor, "wretch" (I:4:3). Here, however, he defines
							himself as what King Lear calls "the thing itself . . . unaccommodated man" (III.iv.100). Perhaps, indeed, Mary Shelley
							means us to hear in the insistent repetition of the word "wretch" the memorable accents of that unsceptered, sorrowing
							monarch: </p> Poor naked wretches, whereso'er you are,<lb/> That bide the pelting of this pitiless storm,<lb/> How shall
						your houseless heads and unfed sides,<lb/> Your loop'd and window'd raggedness, defend you<lb/> From seasons such as these? O,
						I have ta'en<lb/> Too little care of this! Take physic, pomp;<lb/> Expose thyself to feel what wretches feel,<lb/> That thou
						mayst shake the superflux to them,<lb/> And show the heavens more just.<lb/> —III.iv.28-36 </item>
					<item n="164">
						<term target="#iwasbene">I was benevolent</term>
						<p>The Creature repeats his claim, which amounts to his saying that, like Adam, he was created free of original sin. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="165">
						<term target="#iwillkeep">I will keep no terms</term>

						<p>That is, he will not abide by rules of combat stipulated by human beings. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="166">
						<term target="#iwished">I wished to avoid him</term>
						<p>Here, as elsewhere in the novel, we sense some strain in Victor's relationship with his strict father. Usually it is marked
							by his being recalled by a paternal admonition to obligations that he has not met: see, for instance, I:3:10 and note;
							I:3:12 and note. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="167">
						<term target="#journal">your journal</term>
						<p>Evidently the journal is written in French, and it suggests that Victor's claim to Walton that he had thought his creation
							beautiful until it was infused with life (I:4:2 and note) to some extent masked his original feelings. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="168">
						<term target="#journey">journey</term>

						<p>This is the route from Geneva to Chamonix represented in the standard nineteenth-century British guidebook to the region. </p>
						<p>
							<figure>
								<graphic url="../Gifs/gencham.gif"/>
							</figure>
						</p>
						<p>From Edward Whymper, Chamonix and the Range of Mont Blanc (London: John Murray, 1896).</p>

					</item>
					<item n="169">
						<term target="#judge">judge . . . misfortunes</term>
						<p>Behind this utterance, one can hear what is truly the locus classicus, the classic statement, of how one is impelled by
							exile to provide sympathetic assistance to other exiles, that of Dido before the shipwrecked Aeneas: "Non ignari mali,
							miseris succerere disco—Not ignorant of evils myself, I learn to succor the miserable" (Aeneid, I.630). Without question
							Mary Shelley's educated readers would have heard the resonance of this Latin tag, an allusion few women novelists of this
							time would have had sufficient classical training to make. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="170">
						<term target="#justice">justice</term>
						<p>By this point in the novel, after two trials and an education in ancient and modern political science, this word may be
							thought to carry large public as well as private associations. But in this context they are theological as well, invoking
							the notion of a theodicy (from Greek theou dike), a justification of God, which is Milton's announced purpose for Paradise
							Lost: that is, to "justify the ways of God to men" (I.26). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="171">
						<term target="#justice2">justice</term>
						<p>Perhaps the Creature comprehends that is he talking to a person from a long line of civic magistrates, or perhaps his plea
							has simply been predicated on their shared Enlightenment discourse. Whatever the case, in his long narration he has
							consistently been touching on the nerve from which he at last gets a response. For the first time in his dealings with the
							Creature, from the original thought of his creation down to this moment of moral decision, Victor acknowledges an abstract
							concept of the justice owed him. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="172">
						<term target="#justice3">justice</term>
						<p>This phrase is ambiguous: "fellow-creatures" in this contexts appears to be limited to his family and friends. Later,
							Victor will revert to what he owes the human race as a separate entity from the Creature, and justice will be construed
							quite differently. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="173">
						<term target="#kindinsa">a kind of insanity</term>
						<p>These exact words were uttered in the previous chapter when the Creature described burning down the De Lacey's cottage
							(II:8:13 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="174">
						<term target="#kindness">This trait of kindness</term>
						<p>In the ongoing education of the Creature this is the point at which he is first able to conceptualize that refinement of
							affection that constitutes kindness. As with much of the ongoing development of his awareness, there is an ironic
							undertone here, however, since he will never experience the sort of solicitude that, despite his poverty and blindness, is
							the elder De Lacey's daily expectation and comfort. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="175">
						<term target="#kindsymp">I required kindness and sympathy</term>
						<p>As was the case three paragraphs earlier, here the Creature evokes essential Enlightenment values, twice privileging the
							notion of sympathy, but the affirmations are so hedged as to be ominous. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="176">
						<term target="#knowfeel">I know, I feel</term>
						<p>A highly resonant shift of language. Elizabeth is forced back on intuition in the same manner as Victor had been on his
							return to Geneva (I:6:25). Given the miscarriage of justice perpetrated by those who convicted Justine on the basis of
							circumstantial logic, Elizabeth's intuitive knowledge of the heart seems a preferable means by which to organize—or to
							transcend—social institutions. And yet, the contrasting case of Victor's passion for revenge would suggest how
							unpredictable, and even dangerous, such a course might be. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="177">
						<term target="#knowledg">Of what a strange nature is knowledge!</term>
						<p>Again, the Creature uncannily picks up on the timbres of Victor's meditations. Compare, for instance, the first paragraph
							of this second volume (II:1:1), where Victor reviews what he considers is a "blasted" existence. There his remorse (note)
							has much the same deleterious and lasting effect that the Creature here attributes to knowledge. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="178">
						<term target="#lang2">the language of the country</term>
						<p>That is, the language spoken is German, not the French used by the De Laceys and the Creature. This relapse appears to bear
							a symbolic connotation, as the Creature, who had seen his efforts to acquire language as the key to his being accepted
							within human society, is suddenly plunged once again into linguistic incomprehension. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="179">
						<term target="#langimpr">She and I rapidly improved in the knowledge of language</term>
						<p>Although the tonality is subtle, the Creature's education along with Safie seems to have a bonding effect, increasing his
							original attachment to her. In two months' time the linguistic disadvantage that is a shared mark of their alienation is
							assuaged, preparing them simultaneously for what should be a full social integration. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="180">
						<term target="#language">written in the language</term>
						<p>These works are written, respectively, in Renaissance English, classical Latin, and modern German. Fortunately for the
							Creature, they have all been translated into French, which is of course the language the Creature has acquired through the
							De Laceys. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="181">
						<term target="#lefthome">I suddenly left my home</term>

						<p>This is the major departure from the 1818 text, indicative of Mary Shelley's wish to keep her novel concentrated not on
							Victor's family relations, but, instead, on the sense of abject isolation he bears in his psyche. Most critics who have
							compared the texts prefer the appropriateness of this extensive shift of focus. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="182">
						<term target="#leghorn">Leghorn</term>
						<p>Livorno, in Italian. Leghorn was the major port of Tuscany, with a large and thriving English community of traders; hence
							the anglicized name. It would be a logical refuge for someone looking to book passage to the eastern Mediterranean. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="183">
						<term target="#lessons">the lessons . . . sanguinary laws of man</term>
						<p>The Creature means that the story of Felix's efforts on behalf of Safie's father and the ruination suffered by the De
							Laceys as a result have taught him how to manipulate the judicial system. Thus, his framing of Justine Moritz is
							deliberate. There is a further sense in which he has also framed the magistrate Alphonse Frankenstein to become
							complicitous in a grave injustice, but that solid upright citizen is never aware of it.</p>
						<p> A particularly brutal aspect of the "sanguinary laws of man" that the Creature did not learn from Felix but has discovered
							on his own is how to victimize women. In the 1831 text (II:16:35) Mary Shelley stresses that Justine is framed because she
							represents the type of Safie who fled in fear from his presence. In the revised text, then, the planting of the picture is
							a symbolic form of rape. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="184">
						<term target="#letustry">let us try our strength in a fight</term>
						<p>If the scene were less highly charged emotionally, this repeated challenge would bear comic undertones. That Mary Shelley
							would run the risk of so undermining the solemn tone of this exchange must indicate how important it was in her mind to
							exhibit Victor falling back upon a conventional posture of masculinist belligerence. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="185">
						<term target="#likehim">like him, when I viewed</term>
						<p>See Paradise Lost, IV.358-92 and IV.505-35, for the psychological effects felt by Satan as a voyeur surreptitiously
							watching Adam and Eve in Paradise. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="186">
						<term target="#loveand">love and humanity</term>
						<p>The Creature insists upon his full humanity, also upon his fellow-feeling as a human being. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="187">
						<term target="#loveresp">love and respect</term>
						<p>Although it may be a relatively small point, nonetheless it is worth observing how differently the underlying patriarchal
							structure operates in the De Lacey household from that to be discerned among the Frankensteins. At the same time, the
							mutual love of the De Lacey family, with its emphasis on the sufficiency of the domestic affections, repeats motifs from
							the early chapters of Victor's narration (see, for instance, I:3:12 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="188">
						<term target="#mademewr">You have made me wretched beyond expression</term>
						<p>Fittingly, as the curse Victor visits upon himself acknowledges his doubling in his Creature, so here he essentially
							repeats the formulation—"miserable beyond all living things"—that the Creature uttered in the second sentence of their
							colloquy (II:2:7). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="189">
						<term target="#mahomet">forbidden to the female followers of Mahomet</term>
						<p>This is the strongest feminist statement in a novel that seems obsessed with masculine perspectives. Yet, embedded in the
							core narrative, it may in some sense be intended to radiate out through the other narrative lines, informing other
							episodes of the novel with the ambitions of a liberated woman.</p>
						<p> See Mary Wollstonecraft's Vindication of the Rights of Woman 2.2. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="190">
						<term target="#makemysf">make myself useful</term>
						<p>Justine's last injunction to Elizabeth—"Live, and be happy, and make others so" (I:7:31) resonates as well for Victor,
							except that he is unable yet to see that his withdrawal from basic human interaction, whether at Ingolstadt or after his
							return to Geneva, has been the very act that has forestalled a true utility to his fellow beings. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="191">
						<term target="#manbase">so vicious and base</term>
						<p>The Creature's education in and through the simultaneity of contraries (see II:3:6 and note) leads him to a large political
							and social realm that is difficult for him to assess. He is hardly the first to have such a reaction. This sentence
							resonates with the same sense of frustration with the contradictions of the human condition expressed by Byron's Manfred
							(Manfred was begun in the summer of 1816) in a similar Alpine setting to that in which the Creature speaks. </p>
						<p>          Beautiful!<lb/> How beautiful is all this visible world!<lb/> How glorious in its action and itself;<lb/> But we,
							who name ourselves its sovereigns, we,<lb/> Half deity, half dust, alike unfit<lb/> To sink or soar, with our mix'd
							essence make<lb/> A conflict of its elements, and breathe<lb/> The breath of degradation and of pride,<lb/> Contending
							with low wants and lofty will<lb/> Till our mortality predominates,<lb/> And men are—what they name not to
							themselves,<lb/> And trust not to each other. <lb/> —I.ii.36-47 </p>

					</item>
					<item n="192">
						<term target="#manboast">why does man boast of sensibilities superior to those apparent in the brute</term>
						<p>Readers might think of this sentence as heavily ironic, given the encounter that is immediately to ensue. Yet, it may be
							intended to operate on a subtler level than just that of forcing us and Victor to contemplate the truth of his relations
							with his Creature. It is almost as if Victor's mental state, once he has been transposed into the sublime, has transformed
							him, preparing him, unlike other members of his family, to look full into the face of brute nature and experience at once
							its otherness and its symbiosis with humanity. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="193">
						<term target="#manyhour">many hours upon the water</term>

						<p>Percy Bysshe Shelley was passionately fond of boats. During the previous summer, which he and Mary spent at Marlow near
							Windsor, he would drift in a small boat on the Thames while he wrote. Mary, Claire, and he had a boat on Lake Geneva
							during the 1816 summer, in which they sailed out most evenings. Later in the summer Byron and Shelley undertook a two-week
							excursion by boat around the lake stopping at the various sites of interest reachable from its shores. During this venture
							Mary Shelley stayed home to look after her infant boy and write. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="194">
						<term target="#meanly">meanly dressed</term>
						<p>This is intended as an indication of poverty not class. The Creature in these paragraphs, adjusting to his first
							observation of human beings and their social codes, reveals himself to be a quick study. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="195">
						<term target="#meetwith">meet with sympathy</term>
						<p>The Creature is an adept rhetorician, countering Victor's supposition about his original sin with a strict causality: evil
							passions arise solely from a lack of sympathy. The argument between them is scarcely academic, since these are the grounds
							over which western criminology has been suspended for centuries. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="196">
						<term target="#misbeynd">miserable beyond all living things</term>
						<p>Following his reappropriation of "wretch," the Creature picks up on this derogatory term just employed by Victor and
							transforms its signification. In effect, it is recast as a term demanding the sympathy of any humane being, whether Victor
							or the reader. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="197">
						<term target="#miser">miserable, unhappy wretch</term>
						<p>The Creature echoes his memories of his first day of existence (II:3:1), which may suggest that, however much he has
							learned since, his essential condition as existential being has not changed in the least. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="198">
						<term target="#miserabl">miserable head</term>
						<p>In her customary way Mary Shelley plays on two meanings of the word. Victor uses it in a derogatory manner, denoting the
							creature as inferior, but will be answered with its meaning transformed as the Creature begins to recount his life of
							misery. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="199">
						<term target="#misery">misery made me a fiend</term>
						<p>The Creature picks up the name Victor has just hurled at him and subtly recasts its point. From the first Victor has looked
							upon his Creature as essentially depraved, that is to say, evil in his very nature. The same issue hovers over the
							treatment of Justine Moritz, particularly by members of the Frankenstein household, in Chapters 6 and 7 of Volume 1. The
							Creature's rejoinder is constructivist: which is to say, that a sentient being is molded by material conditions. It is a
							position stoutly argued by William Godwin throughout Political Justice (1793). In terms of contemporary criticism of
							Frankenstein, this issue has a high visibility in all gender criticism. Beyond literary criticism per se, the terms in
							which the novel casts this debate are highly resonant for modern social and critical theory. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="200">
						<term target="#mixture">a mixture of pain and pleasure</term>
						<p>This is a step in the Creature's education, related to his encountering pain and pleasure from a single source in fire
							(paragraph 6 above), by which he learns the complex doubleness of emotional experience. Such ambivalent emotions, it is
							safe to say, were unknown in prelapsarian Eden. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="201">
						<term target="#monster2">monster</term>
						<p>Like his brother, William immediately names the Creature as an outcast. If we take the issue of family relationship
							seriously, however, we must realize that the Creature is actually young William's nephew. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="202">
						<term target="#monsters">monsters thirsting for each other's blood</term>
						<p>The echo here is pronounced. Only two paragraphs earlier Victor had recounted his fear "lest the monster whom I had created
							should perpetrate some new wickedness." In Elizabeth's perspective, on the other hand, there is no alien being to consider
							as a scapegoat and in whom to localize and therefore objectify evil. Instead, the potentiality for monstrousness exists in
							all human hearts, and in their collective aggregate that is human society, as Justine's fate demonstrates, this
							monstrousness can be institutionalized as an underlying, unrecognized and therefore dangerous formation. In other words,
							the monstrous is not external but within. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="203">
						<term target="#montanv">the summit of Montanvert</term>
						<p>Montanvert is a subsidiary height of 6303 feet situated to the north of Mont Blanc. It rises above the Mer de Glace and by
							the later eighteenth century had become the tourist perspective of choice on this natural phenomenon. The Shelleys visited
							the Sea of Ice in a driving rain on 24 July 1816, then returned in better weather the next day, leaving an account of
							their experiences in Letter 4 of A History of a Six Weeks' Tour. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="204">
						<term target="#moons">the space of several revolutions of the moon</term>
						<p>That is to say, several months. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="205">
						<term target="#moving">the more moving part of my story</term>
						<p>Like his Creator, the Creature is highly conscious of rhetorical effect. By this locution he may mean that he will now
							explain the ways in which his emotional involvement with the cottagers intensified, but he is also setting a signpost for
							our own engagement as readers with his text, as Victor has done before him (I:3:13) and will again attempt to do after
							completing his narrative (III:Walton:4). Through his contemplation of his effect, he raises anew the questions concerning
							truth and eloquence that are never far from from the novel's surface. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="206">
						<term target="#multipli">multiplicity of sensations</term>
						<p>Mary Shelley posits the Lockean notion that at first one's natural condition is that of synaesthesia, an indiscriminate
							intermingling of sense experience: only when the intellect begins consciously to analyze sensory data are they broken down
							according to the five diverse senses. The physiological basis for this development had been posited in the mid-eighteenth
							century by the French materialist philosopher Condillac, in his Traité des sensations. </p>
						<p>Deliberate synaesthesia is an artistic ploy often to be found among the English Romantic poets, in none more than Percy
							Bysshe Shelley: see, for instance, his poem of 1818, "Lines Written among the Euganean Hills," esp. line 285 ff. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="207">
						<term target="#multitud">If the multitude of mankind knew of my existence, they would do as you do, and arm themselves for my
							destruction</term>

						<p>Thus, the Creature explicitly remarks what the experience of Justine's trial and execution had conveyed to Elizabeth, that
							men are universally "monsters thirsting for . . . blood" (II:1:8). This is exactly antipathetic to the tenets of
							disinterested benevolence Godwin had championed in his public writings (see Political Justice Book IV, Chapter 8 and
							elsewhere in that treatise) and in the instruction of his children. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="208">
						<term target="#mutabili">mutability</term>
						<p>The third and fourth stanzas of Percy Bysshe Shelley's poem, "Mutability," published in the Alastor volume in March 1816.</p>
						<p> The fairly conventional notions of her husband's poem seem at first to have little direct linkage with the circumstances
							into which Mary Shelley has thrust Victor at this juncture. But if one looks back over the landscape of the first volume,
							the operations of mutability as a force of destruction are everywhere evident—from the fearsome movements of sea and ice
							in Walton's letters, to the sudden deaths in the Frankenstein and Moritz households, to the unmerited reversal of
							Justine's fortunes. But mutability is also the very stuff of life. Perhaps then, most of all, the subject of the poem
							applies to the scientific paradigms that govern the development of the volume—in ancient alchemy (from the various
							transmutations it would apply to base metals to its search for a means of suspending mutability itself in the elixir of
							life); or in modern chemistry, which increasingly saw organic changes in terms of chemical transformations; or in
							contemporary electrical theory, where dialectical tensions between opposing poles were held responsible for the essential
							energy of life. A later poem of Percy Bysshe Shelley confronts these ambivalences more subtly and more directly, embedding
							them in a single symbolic force that is at one and same time both "Creator and Destroyer," the "Ode to the West Wind,"
							written in 1819. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="209">
						<term target="#mutual">mutual bonds</term>
						<p>Here one begins to get a glimmer of the impact of Safie's arrival on the Creature's thoughts, as he ponders his own need
							for a mutuality of feeling. The novel powerfully demonstrates that where there are not such mutual bonds, a form of
							bondage is substituted instead. Neither Victor nor his Creature is able to break away from the other, even if all that
							holds them together is their antagonism. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="210">
						<term target="#mycreatr">my creator, detest and spurn me, thy creature</term>
						<p>The Creature's logic is direct and unambiguous, starting from a premise of obligation that Victor had totally expunged from
							his mind. Continuing the process by which he picks up on Victor's language and wholly recontextualizes it, now he asserts
							his right to be considered in the place of Adam, not, as Victor had tried to cast him in the previous paragraph, as Satan. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="211">
						<term target="#myfate">which would decide my fate</term>
						<p>The Creature's growing obsession with revealing himself to the cottagers may lack an external instrumentation, but
							otherwise is of a piece with other obsessions in the novel, both those of Walton and of Victor Frankenstein. His casting
							his future in terms of destiny likewise echoes the discourse of the novel's other protagonists. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="212">
						<term target="#myfather">my father</term>
						<p>The Creature at last names Victor as father, forcing upon his unwilling head the entire range of cultural and literary
							associations that from his limited experience the term might carry. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="213">
						<term target="#myform">my form is a filthy type of your's</term>
						<p>There are occasions in this novel where the subtlety of the verbal patterning may leave readers shaking their heads. The
							Creature, alluding to the journal in which Victor describes the process of his creation, appears deliberately to echo the
							ugly language with which Victor had earlier, in marked aversion, recounted that experience to Walton. We are thus to
							suppose that Victor has been reusing phrases from that journal in his narrative. For his "workshop of filthy creation,"
							see I:3:9 and note. For his further reference to the Creature as "the wretch, the filthy dæmon, to whom I had given life,"
							see I:6:22. At the end of this interview Victor will revert to the adjective to characterize him once again (II:9:12), and
							the word then appears in the penultimate sentence of the 1818 volume translated into nightmarish proportions (II:9:23). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="214">
						<term target="#myimag">my imagination</term>
						<p>At first sight this appears to be an evocation of the imagination more in line with the normative practices of British
							Romanticism than earlier ones have been: the Creature in his isolation takes refuge in an innocent, even utopian world of
							his own making, one provided by the creative power of his imagination. This characteristic, almost more than any other so
							far encountered in his educational process, testifies to his fully human sensibility. From a more analytical perspective,
							however, such a refuge of the creative imagination shares the main attributes of Victor's introverted retreat at
							Ingolstadt, even to the point of opening the way to a sudden, disastrous reversal. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="215">
						<term target="#mywife">My wife</term>
						<p>Felix and Safie have never been married, but neither, for that matter, were Mary Godwin and Percy Shelley when they lived
							together at Geneva in the summer of 1816. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="216">
						<term target="#names">I discovered the names</term>
						<p>The first definitions are of discrete things, which happen also to be the necessities of life. The Creature's education
							places him in the condition of Adam, who named the animals of Eden. See Genesis 2:18-20: </p>
						<p>Then the LORD God said, "It is not good that the man should be alone; I will make him a helper fit for him."</p>
						<p>So out of the ground the LORD God formed every beast of the field and every bird of the air, and brought them to the man to
							see what he would call them; and whatever the man called every living creature, that was its name.</p>
						<p>The man gave names to all cattle, and to the birds of the air, and to every beast of the field; but for the man there was
							not found a helper fit for him.</p>
						<p>The last phrase of the Genesis text we will soon see applies to the Creature as much as it does to all of God's creation. </p>
						<p>Milton's litany of the creatures whom Adam named comes in his account of the Creation in Paradise Lost, Book VII, 493ff. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="217">
						<term target="#nature">nature</term>
						<p>The Creature responds to spring with the same "sentiments of joy and affection" (I:4:19) experienced simultaneously by
							Victor in his convalescence at Ingolstadt. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="218">
						<term target="#nocommun">There can be no community between you and me</term>
						<p>Although Victor is thinking solely in personal terms, Johnson's 1755 Dictionary emphasizes in a valuable way the social,
							and particularly the political, dimensions of this noun. Given the fact that the novel will soon move directly to include
							such a framework of human institutions, it is important to recognize that the Creature's perspective on such diction might
							be quite different from, perhaps even more knowing than, Victor's. </p>
						<p> 1. The commonwealth; the body politick.<lb/> 2. Common possession; the state contrary to property or appropriation.<lb/>
							3. Frequency, commonness.</p>

					</item>
					<item n="219">
						<term target="#nolang">no language can describe</term>

						<p>Although the phrase appears essentially innocent, yet it illustrates how constantly self-reflexiveness about the nature of
							language and communication troubles the author -- or both these authors, Victor Frankenstein and Mary Shelley. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="220">
						<term target="#nolonger">no longer that happy creature</term>

						<p>Elizabeth's sudden plunge into a maturity born of despondency was indicated in the last chapter of Volume 1 (I:7:25). Not
							events per se, but their impact on characters' perceptions give Mary Shelley's novel its dynamic momentum. In this focus
							on the integrity of mental phenomena for good or ill—concerns likewise at this time governing the productions of both Lord
							Byron (Manfred) and Percy Bysshe Shelley ("Mont Blanc" and Prometheus Unbound)—one senses Mary Shelley's equal
							participation in the intellectual vibrancy of that 1816 summer. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="221">
						<term target="#noonelov">No one could love a child more than I loved your brother</term>

						<p>For all Alphonse's attempt to console Victor, his being exactly wrong about the source of Victor's grief must be indicative
							of some narrowness or shortsightedness of his own. His son William is his only concern, and he assumes the same family
							priorities for Victor; but Victor knows that Justine has been murdered, too, and that more than tribal loyalty is at
							stake. That the father's commitment to the "public situations" (I:1:1) in which he has passed his mature years extends so
							little into actual social benevolence must in some sense affect how we take his counsel and assess his notion of virtue. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="222">
						<term target="#nopower">no power</term>
						<p>Victor's habitual passivity reasserts itself with a sharp irony that reminds one of the physical deterioration he suffered
							in giving life to his creation (I:3:9). His argument is that the Creature, empowered by Victor with life, has so used that
							power that it has robbed Victor of his own ability to act independently. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="223">
						<term target="#noright">I had no right to claim their sympathies</term>

						<p>Given the novel's insistence on sympathy as an essential moral attribute of an individual human being and a just society,
							Victor's drawing away so wholly from normative family intercourse is an alarming event. That he is scarcely able to speak
							to his family suggests a psychological condition that in modern parlance would seem to border on psychosis. It is ironic
							that the Creature's passionate demand for an end to his solitude should result in Victor's own recoil into a solitude
							almost as utter and just as fraught with danger to himself and to others. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="224">
						<term target="#notconsnt">I could not consent to the death of any human being</term>
						<p>As this sentence might suggest, Mary Shelley was opposed to all forms of capital punishment, a sentiment she shared with
							her father and husband. Perhaps, the true significance of this statement, however, is the contrast it offers to the
							violent retribution Victor would inflict on the Creature, whom, we must remember, he has as yet no evidence whatsoever to
							connect with the murder of William or the framing of Justine. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="225">
						<term target="#notenter">I dared not enter it</term>
						<p>If it occurs to a reader to wonder why the De Lacey family did not hear of such a fearsome apparition in the nearby
							village, the reason is that they are, in their poverty and separation, self-sufficient. They have no money to spend in
							that German community and are likewise isolated from it by the fact that they appear to speak only French. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="226">
						<term target="#notonly">not only you and your family, but thousands of others, shall be swallowed up in the whirlwinds of its
							rage</term>

						<p>This is an open threat of mass destruction, the second such intimation of the violence to which the Creature will resort if
							he is provoked: see II:2:7. Although its unethical dimensions cannot be ignored, one should again remark how aptly
							congruent is the amoral power Percy Bysshe Shelley saw embodied in Mont Blanc itself: see Shelley's "Mont Blanc," lines
							107-20. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="227">
						<term target="#nottempt">I will not be tempted to set myself in opposition to thee</term>
						<p>It is significant that the Creature is the one to try to break the impasse between himself and Victor, likewise that he
							understands the fateful ethical consequences of the antagonistic course to which Victor has set himself. The primary verb
							of this sentence ("tempt") assumes free will and moral responsibility as premises for all human action, premises that
							Victor repeatedly endeavors to deny. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="228">
						<term target="#nourish">I do not destroy the lamb and the kid . . . nourishment</term>
						<p>The Creature, pressing his advantage, reminds Victor that the "new species" he has created is herbivore and therefore in
							essence essentially non-violent. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="229">
						<term target="#nowfound">I now found that I could wander on at liberty</term>
						<p>Inside Victor's house the Creature had to negotiate around walls and through doors. Outside he has no such obstacles. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="230">
						<term target="#numa">Numa</term>
						<p>Numa Pompilius, legendary second king of infant Rome, and Lycurgus, legendary lawgiver of Sparta in the ninth century B.C.,
							are compared as founding fathers in parallel accounts by Plutarch. It is possible that the particular emphasis of these
							Lives contributes to the Creature's decision, as it were, to become a founding father himself. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="231">
						<term target="#nursed">Safie nursed her</term>
						<p>Like Caroline Beaufort Frankenstein (I:1:4, I:2:2) and Justine Moritz (I:5:5), not to forget Clerval (I:4:17) and Walton
							(I:L4:10), Safie demonstrates her solicitude and common humanity through nursing. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="232">
						<term target="#obnox">he became obnoxious to the government</term>
						<p>However obnoxious the Turk will himself appear within this account, the stress here is on an arbitrary exercise of
							tyrannical state power over an individual's civil rights. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="233">
						<term target="#offals">the offals</term>
						<p>Refuse left over from a meal: given the Creature's fastidious vegetarianism, these would seem to be part of the "roots and
							nuts" he goes on to mention as part of his fare. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="234">
						<term target="#ogre">You are an ogre</term>
						<p>The seven-year old William seems to be drawing his points of reference from reading fairy tales and romances. This is of a
							piece with the experiences of the older members of the household when they were his age, particularly Henry Clerval, who
							wrote a fairy tale at the age of nine and was passionately fond of romances (see I:1:11). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="235">
						<term target="#ohheat">Oh that I had forever remained . . . heat</term>
						<p>Here the Creature unconsciously echoes the sentiments of Victor Frankenstein ("if our impulses were confined to hunger,
							thirst, and desire, we might be nearly free") from earlier the same morning of their conversation (II:2:3). That the
							Creature speaks of heat where Victor uses "desire" reflects his very first conscious experiences (II:3:3, II:3:6), but
							desire is also at this point very much on his mind, as the ensuing paragraphs will stress. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="236">
						<term target="#ohstars">Oh! stars, and clouds, and winds</term>
						<p>It is one thing for the Creature to utter a pantheistic oath (previous paragraph), but to put a second immediately into the
							mouth of Victor is to emphasize that where man plays God, he has no other deity to whom to turn to right his injustices
							but himself. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="237">
						<term target="#oldman">The old man took no notice</term>
						<p>The elder De Lacey, we will soon learn, is blind. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="238">
						<term target="#omnipot">a power as mighty as Omnipotence</term>
						<p>To a later reader accustomed to the 1818 edition or to the customary biographical terrain of Mary Shelley's family
							associations, these phrases come with a sense almost of shock. Even within the terms set by the novel itself they do not
							seem to ring true to the general distance kept thus far between the characters and conventional religious expression. The
							reader has the choice of construing this interpolation as a sign of a shift in Mary Shelley's rhetorical palette to
							accommodate an early Victorian religious sensibility (which has been asserted by some critics). On the other hand, this
							could be interpreted instead as an attempt on her part to prepare us for the deep, if primitive, religious faith that will
							eventually be invoked by Victor to sanction his single-minded pursuit of revenge against his Creature. In other words, not
							all rhetorical alterations portend changes in the author's own opinions. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="239">
						<term target="#omnipote">an omnipotent God warring with his creatures</term>

						<p>The war of gods and titans first recounted in Hesiod's Theogony is likewise such a heavenly battle: it was won by Jupiter
							only after Prometheus came over to the side of the gods on the strength of Jupiter's promise to ameliorate the human
							condition, a promise he later betrayed. Percy Bysshe Shelley develops this scenario in Asia's long recital of the
							legendary history in Prometheus Unbound, II.iv.32ff. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="240">
						<term target="#oneyear">an entire revolution</term>
						<p>In other words, the Creature is now a year old. During this revolution of the year he has learned to speak and read French,
							has read four books and an account of his creation, and has awakened to intellectual and emotional desire. The anniversary
							of his creation suggests to him that he is now ready to start out on life. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="241">
						<term target="#opencoun">open country</term>
						<p>The supposition is that the Creature has been able to remain within the general confines of woodlands during this three-day
							passage. Now, he comes out into the open—which is to say, into arable ground. Unwittingly, he is stumbling upon his first
							contacts with human society. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="242">
						<term target="#original">the original æra of my being</term>
						<p>To compare the creature's sense of his original identity with that contained in the opening sentence (I:1:1) of Victor
							Frankenstein's narrative is to mark a dramatic contrast in self-conception and cultural endowment. Also, as has often been
							noted, a second and striking context exists between these first memories and those of Adam in representing himself to the
							Archangel Raphael in Paradise Lost (VIII.250-96). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="243">
						<term target="#other">Other lessons were impressed upon me even more deeply</term>
						<p>The various relations of intercourse within normative family structures are a new category of experience that the creature
							studies without being able to enact. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="244">
						<term target="#ourhouse">our house at Belrive</term>
						<p>It was here, at the family's country house, that Victor had witnessed lightning strike the ancient oak when he was fifteen
							(I:1:22). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="245">
						<term target="#paradise">a paradise</term>
						<p>Mary Shelley manages a quiet pathos from the simple satisfactions that for the new Adam constitute Eden. The reader may at
							this point reflect, in contrast to the epithets by which Victor has abused the Creature for a number of chapters in
							succession, how naturally drawn to human society he is. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="246">
						<term target="#pardon">Pardon this intrusion</term>
						<p>These are the first words that the Creature has ever uttered. As with the unexpected control of his opening remark to
							Victor (II:2:7), one is taken aback by their sophistication. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="247">
						<term target="#partly">partly urged by curiosity</term>
						<p>"Partly from curiosity" Victor wandered into Professor Waldman's lecture and thence into the scientific career that
							culminated in the birth of his Creature (I:2:14). As this instance may indicate, the import of this essential human
							attribute for good and bad—other examples will be found in I:L1:2, I:L4:11, I:L4:31, I:1:22, and I:7:1—has been emphasized
							throughout the first volume of Frankenstein. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="248">
						<term target="#pastmem">the past was blotted from my memory</term>
						<p>This spring appears to wipe the slate clean for Victor in Ingolstadt as well (I:4:19). For the Creature, no less than for
							Victor Frankenstein, however, the past cannot be so easily forgotten. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="249">
						<term target="#path">the path of my departure was free</term>
						<p>The Creature here quotes back to Victor a line from Percy Shelley's "Mutability" that Victor had mused over that morning in
							ascending Montanvert (II:2:3). Although this does stretch the imagination, it is indisputably another instance of the
							mirror effects we discern in the relations of Creator and Creature. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="250">
						<term target="#patriarc">the patriarchal lives of my protectors</term>
						<p>That is, a family where seniority is honored for its wisdom and the generations respect and support each other provides a
							model for a civilized community. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="251">
						<term target="#pines">pines</term>
						<p>Although we have no guide to Mary Shelley's thought processes as she wrote this passage, it is probable that the stanza
							from Percy Shelley's poetry she quotes at the end of the paragraph caused her to think of another from the volume in which
							it was published (or the causality might have been reversed, with that other passage first coming to mind and prompting
							the remembrance of this stanza): whatever the case, this description of mountain conifers strongly resembles the desolate
							final scene, actually drawn from Shelley's experiences in Wales before he met Mary, of his poem "Alastor" (see lines
							550-70). An early sketch of this same subject is contained in a poem in the early notebook known as the Esdaile Notebook,
							a poem Shelley wrote in 1811 and never published, called after its first line "Dark spirit of the desart rude." </p>
						<p>On the other hand, the scenery of Switzerland, far more sublime than that of Wales, afforded ample opportunity for Mary
							Shelley to observe the desolation that alpine storms and glacial movement could visit on the pine forests of the
							mountains. There is a description of such shattered trees in Letter 4 of A History of Six Weeks' Tour. Byron offers
							another such passage in the second scene of Manfred, I.ii.66-74, which, though begun later than Frankenstein, indicates at
							many points a common conceptual origin. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="252">
						<term target="#pl">Paradise Lost</term>
						<p>Paradise Lost, John Milton's epic poem, was originally published in 1667 in ten books, then revised by its author into the
							twelve-book form in which we read it today shortly before his death in 1674. Containing the major creation myth of modern
							Europe, its impact on Frankenstein is major and discernible from beginning to end. In the immediate context of the
							Creature's discovery rather than of Mary Shelley's intertextual conception of her novel, however, what is most significant
							is how he reads the epic as a key to his self-understanding, even perhaps his self-fashioning. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="253">
						<term target="#plenty">a greater degree of plenty</term>
						<p>It would appear that Safie has sold some of the jewelry with which she left Livorno (II:6:19). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="254">
						<term target="#plutarch">Plutarch's Lives</term>
						<p>Plutarch's Lives of the Noble Grecians and Romans are sometimes known as "Parallel Lives" because of the author's method of
							presenting a prominent Greek and Roman in tandem, then comparing their achievements.</p>
						<p>Rousseau testifies to the importance of the Lives in his early education in Confessions, book I. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="255">
						<term target="#poorgirl">the poor girl died</term>
						<p>Like the deaths of Justine's siblings (see I:5:6 and note), this is an intrusion not necessary to the plot, but
							underscoring the tentative nature of the human condition and the threats to happiness to be remarked everywhere in this
							novel. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="256">
						<term target="#poorwret">poor wretch</term>
						<p>Again (see paragraph 2 above), the Creature names himself by the same word (although it here carries a different
							connotation) that Victor first uses in I:3:2. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="257">
						<term target="#port">portmanteau</term>
						<p>A large carrying-case with two compartments, what in modern English is called a suit-carrier. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="258">
						<term target="#poverty">poverty</term>
						<p>That the root cause of the family's sorrow is not exile nor even a personal loss, but rather an economic condition, carries
							radical political overtones of a type that a later generation would call Marxist. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="259">
						<term target="#property">I possessed no money . . . property</term>
						<p>In England at this time a man without property had no vote: thus the very idea of citizenship, of having a "stake" in the
							system, was tied to possession of property. Of course, as the Creature will learn in the subsequent chapter, both Safie
							and the De Laceys as exiles are also excluded from this polity, but they have family or friends to rely on for support. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="260">
						<term target="#protect">my protectors</term>
						<p>This is subtly touching diction: the Creature has convinced himself that he has mistaken the De Laceys and recasts them in
							the role in which for many months he had conceived them to act: see II:5:22 for his recognition that he has invented this
							appellation. The De Laceys, of course, have never consciously done the Creature any good whatsoever. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="261">
						<term target="#provtrue">they will prove the truth of my tale</term>
						<p>Again, the creature seems to echo Victor Frankenstein (though, since Victor's narrative to Walton postdates the Creature's
							by several years it is actually he who is engaged in echoing). Wherever in the narrative nesting we look to find a
							foundation for its truth, we discover both Victor and the Creature seeking to establish the evidence that will verify
							their accounts and using almost identical language to do so. One may thus compare this utterance with those of Victor to
							Walton at the beginning (I:L4:30 and note) and end (III:Walton:2) of his narrative. That the "evidence" comes from the
							centrally embedded narrative, the story of Safie, is thus taken to lend credibility to all narrative strands that subsume
							it. But, of course, these putative copies of letters depend entirely on the Creature's word for their authenticity: so
							there is actually no documentary foundation whatsoever for the "truth" of any of these fictions. Still, it is indicative
							that Victor Frankenstein produces the letters to convince Walton of his veracity (III:Walton:2). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="262">
						<term target="#quickly">quickly . . . ice</term>
						<p>The phrasing essentially repeats the language of the Creature's disappearance across the Arctic ice in Walton's fourth
							letter (see I:L4:3). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="263">
						<term target="#rage">I could no longer suppress the rage</term>
						<p>Victor pointedly indulges unbridled emotions with the same abandon we witnessed overcome the Creature in the previous
							chapter (II:8:1, II:8:12). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="264">
						<term target="#rank">rank, descent, and noble blood</term>
						<p>Mary Shelley had herself to have been highly conscious of these attributes. Byron, even if he inherited his title almost by
							accident, was a member of the House of Lords and was always addressed as Lord Byron by the Shelleys. Percy Bysshe Shelley,
							although somewhat down the hierarchical list of aristocracy, was the elder son of a baronet and would therefore have
							expected to inherit the title of his father, Sir Timothy Shelley. His family had an illustrious "descent," with Sir Philip
							Sidney being among his ancestors. On the other side, however, neither William Godwin nor Mary Wollstonecraft had any
							pretensions to lineage, and as middle-class radicals they were committed to a classless society without false hierarchies. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="265">
						<term target="#rather">rather the vast river of ice</term>
						<p>The correction reminds us that this glacier is itself in motion, simultaneously accumulating new mass and at its lower edge
							melting, a pure example of the universal mutability proclaimed in the poem just cited. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="266">
						<term target="#reflect">to reflect</term>
						<p>These reflections are of a very different character from earlier occasions where Victor has used the term, so much so that
							a reader may feel some sense of disquiet over his presumption in at last assuming the Olympian detachment of supervisory
							deity or parent. Perhaps judgment on this level requires condescension, but the timbres of Victor's father seem to
							resonate across this paragraph. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="267">
						<term target="#relation">I have no relation or friend upon earth</term>
						<p>A remarkable difference exists, we must realize with something of a jolt, between the Creature's silent meditations in his
							hovel and the sudden intrusion of a public utterance of his conclusions from them. Insofar as it is hard for any reader to
							conceive of such sentences as these ever being uttered by an actual human being, it testifies to the unique existential
							extremity of the case he poses. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="268">
						<term target="#resolved">resolved . . . remain quietly in my hovel</term>
						<p>The Creature innocently echoes the language of Victor Frankenstein when he first conjectured who was the murderer of his
							brother, one of the number of signs of their unconscious affinity (I:6:28). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="269">
						<term target="#revenge">revenge</term>
						<p>With characteristic understatement, Mary Shelley places the two cousins in total contrast: Elizabeth through her sympathy
							attempting to assuage the pain Victor feels, and Victor consumed by his hatred. As the reader would anticipate, it is
							Elizabeth who makes the social gesture, "taking [Victor's] hand," and Victor who retreats into self-accusation. As a
							tableau vivant this is a very illuminating scene. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="270">
						<term target="#right">as a right</term>
						<p>This is a distinction worth pondering. In general terms throughout the novel we have been allowed to relax in the notion of
							sympathy as a private, even domestic virtue, commensurate with compassion and affection. Questions of justice have been
							largely raised within public arenas or as involving the legal rights of individuals. Here, however, the larger issues of
							late Enlightenment democratic enfranchisement merge with private desire, as to an important degree they also do in the
							Constitution of the United States of America (1787), particularly as amended by the Bill of Rights (1789), or the
							Declaration of Rights of the French Constituent Assembly (1789) or that proposed by Maximilien Robespierre (1793) or,
							indeed, the radical Declaration of Rights written by the young agitator Percy Bysshe Shelley for distribution among the
							Irish in 1812. Sympathy thus has a political component to it. In the Creature's formulation God, or one who would assume
							the supreme powers of God, implicitly has an obligation to foster the "pursuit of happiness" of a creation or subject. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="271">
						<term target="#rootsand">roots and plants</term>
						<p>The De Lacey household also observes vegetarian principles, which, one assumes, is why, luckily for the Creature, the
							pig-stye lies empty. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="272">
						<term target="#ruins">Ruins of Empire</term>
						<p>Les Ruines, ou méditations sur les révolutions des empires (1791) by Constantin François Chasseboeuf, comte de Volney
							(1757-1820) is one of the geniunely radical documents produced in the early years of the French Revolution, a work that
							severely critiques all the reigning ideologies of the world—whether political or theological—and proposes their abolition.
							That the Creature should get his principal education into the institutions of modern culture from such a profoundly
							antiestablishment work must have a significant influence on his own subsequent distaste for human culture. But there is an
							ironic side to it as well, for Volney's attempt to create the blueprint for the new revolutionary man here falls on the
							ears of a uniquely revolutionary and wholly dispossessed individual. The first English translation of Les Ruines,
							published as The Ruins, or a Survey of the Revolutions of Empires (London: Joseph Johnson, 1792) was done by Godwin's
							close friend James Marshall. Volney himself thought the translation too tame and in 1802 oversaw a new English version
							published in Paris, which was reprinted frequently and became the standard conduit for his ideas throughout the
							English-speaking world. Among those strongly effected by it was Percy Bysshe Shelley, whose Queen Mab shows considerable
							debt to its ideas. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="273">
						<term target="#safcott">Safie . . . cottage</term>
						<p>That the enterprizing Safie, who has managed to travel from Constantinople to Paris, then to central Italy, and from there
							to this rural section of south-central Germany, is so horrified attests to the intensity of fear aroused by the sight of
							the Creature. That she deserts the entire family at this moment of crisis testifies to a primal, irrational sense of
							self-preservation that is distinctly unGodwinian and stands as an ironic counterstatement to all the Enlightenment ideals
							so accentuated in the paragraphs leading up to this denouement. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="274">
						<term target="#safiearr">Safie arrived from Constantinople</term>
						<p>Although Mary Shelley puts no extra emphasis on this point, still it is significant that Safie, a woman with ambition and a
							mind of her own, is up to this point the best-traveled figure in the novel. On some level of consciousness Mary Shelley
							must be aware of her implicit links to Cythna, the liberated feminist heroine of Percy Shelley's contemporary Revolt of
							Islam, published simultaneously with Frankenstein in 1818. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="275">
						<term target="#satan">Satan</term>
						<p>The resemblance to Satan stems at first from the Creature's sense of having no place in the universe, of being designed for
							alienation in the fulfillment of the Genesis. This is, indeed, the ground upon which his colloquy with Victor Frankenstein
							began: see II:2:7 and note. The Satanic prototype will extend, however, to the point of having external not simply
							psychological ramifications: as Satan's only acts are reactions, attempts to undo the perfection of God's universe, so the
							Creature will claim Victor's attention by destroying what he most values. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="276">
						<term target="#scilett">science of letters</term>
						<p>However important language is as an instrument to knowledge of the world and the self, its compression to coherent meaning
							in literature is what affords the Creature his true education. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="277">
						<term target="#seaofice">sea of ice</term>
						<p>The Mer de Glace, the great glacier decending from Mont Blanc: a popular tourist site in 1816, when the Shelley party
							visited it that July, described in A History of a Six Weeks' Tour, Letter IV. It was taken to be the very epitome of
							Nature's sublime (and perhaps antihuman) power. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="278">
						<term target="#seek">seek the old man . . . win him to my party</term>
						<p>This not only makes sense in the context of the De Laceys' civilized demeanor, which for many months now has served as the
							Creature's behavioral model, but also specifically in respect to the elder De Lacey's explicit understanding of the
							dynamics of alienation just witnessed in the Creature's night-time rampage. The use of political terminology reminds us of
							the Creature's reading matter (particularly of the education furnished him by Volney's Ruines), but also suggests that he
							still thinks it possible to negotiate a place for himself within the human polity. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="279">
						<term target="#self">something out of self</term>
						<p>The Creature refers to the numerous philosophical speculations of Werter. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="280">
						<term target="#selfdec">self-deceit</term>
						<p>The self-deceit is, indeed, painful, since in his continual awareness that there is no reality underlying his imaginings,
							the Creature testifies to the split existence in which he lives. Here, the imagination is decidedly not a boon. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="281">
						<term target="#senses">the human senses are insurmountable barriers</term>
						<p>Whether or not this must necessarily be the case, it is a premise of Mary Shelley's novel that normative aesthetic
							categories are, indeed, the instrument for ostracizing the Creature from all human society. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="282">
						<term target="#sensgult">sense of guilt</term>

						<p>As is manifest in the previous chapter (see I:7:13 and note), for Victor remorse has a physical and mental effect akin to
							that of poison. Already worn down constitutionally, Victor will feel its debilitating effects from this point forward. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="283">
						<term target="#several">several hours</term>
						<p>If he departed the hut at noon, then the Creature would have had some five hours to travel further before dusk fell. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="284">
						<term target="#shecott">she was neither understood by, or herself understood, the cottagers</term>
						<p>Although this is an important plot device by which the Creature is allowed to advance in his education, it is more than
							simply that. What the Creature in his enforced solitude thought of as a "godlike science" (II:4:9) and "the art of
							language" (II:4:18) is an acquisition essential for his claim to true humanness. As Safie is enfolded by the De Lacey
							family through acquiring their language, so, the Creature hopes, he can likewise break down the barriers of Otherness in
							which he is compelled to live. If language has up to now been used as an instrument for his self-knowledge (note), with
							Safie's arrival it will become the actual means by which he will endeavor to secure a place in a human community. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="285">
						<term target="#sheseemd">She seemed pleased</term>
						<p>Poverty-stricken though they are, they have managed to replace the loaf of bread purloined by the Creature that morning
							(paragraph 13 above). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="286">
						<term target="#shldmake">I should make use of the same instructions to the same end</term>
						<p>The crucial place of language in the Creature's education and in his growing sense of identity is a significant sign of the
							importance Mary Shelley attaches to it as a professional writer and, however herself inexperienced at the age she began
							the novel, as the child, wife, and associate of other major authors of the age. And yet it is always shadowed by the dark
							irony of another "monster" accorded the use of language, Shakespeare's Caliban, who tells Miranda: "You taught me
							language, and my profit on't/ Is, I know how to curse" (The Tempest, I.ii.363-64). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="287">
						<term target="#shutting">the shutting of the gates</term>

						<p>The shutting of these gates at the time of Victor's return to his family home (I:6:19), it will be remembered, allowed for
							his midnight sighting of his Creature. The same precaution also necessitated Justine Moritz's passing the fateful night of
							William Frankenstein's death in a barn in the environs of Geneva (I:7:6). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="288">
						<term target="#sight">sight tremendous and abhorred</term>
						<p>Although the rhetoric is overloaded, one should not miss the significance of the Creature's being first defined as the
							actual embodiment of the sublime landscape out of which he emerges. Taller and stronger than any normal human being and
							created out of the essential dynamic forces of nature, he seems deliberately to embody the Power that Percy Bysshe Shelley
							located in the mountain itself: </p>
						<p> . . . awful scene,<lb/> Where Power in likeness of the Arve comes down<lb/> From the ice-gulfs that gird his secret
							throne,<lb/> Bursting through these dark mountains like the flame<lb/> Of lightning through the tempest.<lb/>("Mont
							Blanc," 15-19)</p>

					</item>
					<item n="289">
						<term target="#siroc">siroc</term>
						<p>A sirocco is a dry hot wind from Africa that descends upon Mediterranean countries from the south. It is scarcely
							appropriate to the region of Mont Blanc, but, if one reads the reference generically to a violent storm, that is probably
							all that Victor means. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="290">
						<term target="#slave">made a slave by the Turks</term>
						<p>Since the issue of enslavement arises in a number of contexts in the novel, this instance of it in the innermost narrative
							should not go unnoticed. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="291">
						<term target="#society">women were allowed to take a rank in society</term>
						<p>Muslim women of the period were kept sequestered from the outside world and in the high ranks of Ottoman culture were kept
							in harems. Safie wishes to have the freedom of movement and independence of mind putatively enjoyed by women in Western
							societies. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="292">
						<term target="#softtear">Soft tears</term>
						<p>The freshness of the Creature's emotional response to nature and to beauty, which operates as a signal testimony to his
							unambiguous humanity and his inner capaciousness, carries an increasingly ironic import where no one else will acknowledge
							his claims to be human. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="293">
						<term target="#solemn">He made a solemn vow . . . means</term>
						<p>Felix's daring to right an injustice in which he is in no way personally involved, and to do so by himself transgressing
							legal strictures, in retrospect recalls to us the contrasting silence and inaction of Victor Frankenstein and the bland
							acquiescence of his father before the similar injustice of Justine's condemnation. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="294">
						<term target="#solemnit">a scene of wonderful solemnity</term>
						<p>In returning us to the sublime Alpine landscape in which she sets the second volume of her novel, Mary Shelley makes us
							realize how deeply internalized as psychological reality, for both Victor and his Creature, its sublimity has become. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="295">
						<term target="#solitary">solitary and detested</term>
						<p>In his brief course of reading the Creature has encountered a surprising number of examples of alienation, martyrdom, and
							victimization. These are states, however uneviable they may be, that at least testify to social and political
							relationships. His solitude, in contrast, has been utter. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="296">
						<term target="#solon">Solon</term>
						<p>A famous early Athenian poet and author of its constitution, Solon is credited with the maxim, "Count no man happy until he
							is dead." His life appears in Plutarch.</p>
						<p>Romulus and Theseus are also the subject of comparative treatment but, unlike the first three figures mentioned by the
							Creature, one that is essentially negative. Romulus murdered his brother, Theseus his father, and both were likewise
							violent toward women. The Creature thus testifies to his essentially pacific nature and his admiration for gentle and
							socially conscious figures. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="297">
						<term target="#somethng">something out a drawer</term>
						<p>All women, no matter their class, in the eighteenth century were expected to do embroidery, called "work," while otherwise
							unoccupied. It would seem so natural to Mary Shelley's readership that she would have no need to name the occupation. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="298">
						<term target="#sorrow">sorrow only increased with knowledge</term>
						<p>A second echo of Byron's Manfred (1817) in this chapter: </p>
						<p>Sorrow is knowledge: they who know the most<lb/> Must mourn the deepest o'er the fatal truth,<lb/> The tree of Knowledge is
							not that of Life. <lb/> —1.1.10-12 </p>

					</item>
					<item n="299">
						<term target="#sportive">the sportiveness of infancy</term>
						<p>William Frankenstein is some seven years old. Infancy thus here means "childhood." </p>

					</item>
					<item n="300">
						<term target="#starwood">stars of pale radiance among the moonlight woods</term>
						<p>The Creature's imagery tends to be poetic and generally, as is the case here or in his description of Safie's singing three
							paragraphs before, where he compares her to a nightingale, his imagery is drawn from nature. In his temperament he seems,
							interestingly, to be something of a cross between Elizabeth, with her love of nature, and Clerval, with his refined poetic
							sensibility. Victor, of course, does not intrude upon the narrative he is recounting to note such linkages nor, indeed,
							the irony of the internal delicacy of the figure he so brutishly names. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="301">
						<term target="#steps">And now . . . whither should I bend my steps?</term>
						<p>The reference is to the famous last lines of Paradise Lost in which Adam and Eve forever depart Eden (XII.646-49). That the
							Creature speaks in these elegiac tones suggests that, for him, this is the moment in which he can no longer define
							himself, as he did in his appeal to the elder De Lacey (II:7:26), as a being of innocent and benevolent disposition. A
							second Adam, he has experienced his fall. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="302">
						<term target="#stifle">I tried to stifle these sensations</term>
						<p>The issue of self-control that has been an undercurrent throughout this volume here near its end surfaces as an important
							component of its pattern of complex ambivalences. Even as such discipline appears a principal aim of the emphasis on
							education, it also directly counters the natural values elsewhere generally honored. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="303">
						<term target="#strange">the strange system of human society</term>
						<p>However unthreatening such language may sound today, in 1818, with England racked by unrest and governed by reactionaries,
							these were what we might today call fighting words. They certainly signaled the anonymous author's radical sympathies to
							readers—and reviewers. This is the point in the novel where discerning readers, not knowing who the author was, would
							comprehend the significance of the dedication to William Godwin, whose Enquiry Concerning Political Justice of 1793
							remained the most radical analysis of "the strange system of human society" for the generation of his daughter. This work,
							rather than the more tempered redaction of 1798, when the extreme antiestablishment perspective of the original might have
							been taken for treason, in many respects underlies the Creature's sense of alienation, his understanding of the structured
							injustice that allows him no place in human society, and his recognition of endemic restraints upon individual
							self-fulfillment. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="304">
						<term target="#suchlove">such lovely creatures</term>
						<p>However this veneration of an ideal to which he might aspire testifies to the underlying human sensibility of the Creature,
							the awareness to which his logic carries him, that he is not part of the human family, places it within another and more
							pernicious construction. In effect, he is internalizing a sense of profound alienation, becoming the Other that society
							would make him. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="305">
						<term target="#suchwret">such a wretch</term>
						<p>The reiteration of this epithet, which has been applied to Justine (see I:7:29 and note) but also, in the sense that
							Elizabeth here means, to Victor (I:7:33 and note) as well as, from the first, his Creature, allows Elizabeth's unknowing
							accentuation of the word to bear an explosive charge. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="306">
						<term target="#sufficen">sufficient</term>
						<p>East of Eden a bare sufficiency may be all one can ask for: the Creature's experiences test just how much -- or little --
							that may be. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="307">
						<term target="#supplic">Adam's supplication</term>
						<p>The Creature refers to Adam's almost instant demand of God after his creation that he be given a mate (VIII.357-451). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="308">
						<term target="#supreme">the supreme and magnificent Mont Blanc</term>
						<p>The diction here is quite similar to that of Percy Shelley in "Mont Blanc," lines 60-66, the poem he wrote from the
							experience of visiting these scenes with Mary in the summer of 1816. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="309">
						<term target="#survive">surviving brother</term>

						<p>Victor refers to Ernest, now 17 years old. That he thinks it his duty to "protect" his father and brother has an ironic
							edge to it, since his own continuing presence and actions are what pose the immediate threat to their well-being. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="310">
						<term target="#sympath">I sympathized</term>
						<p>In accordance with Enlightenment social thought, notably the writings of the Earl of Shaftesbury and his many followers,
							sympathy is the means by which the Creature becomes educated both physically and morally. It has a dual private and public
							dimension, making the Creature aspire to higher personal goals, as well as fostering in him a desire for civilized human
							relations. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="311">
						<term target="#sympath2">I sympathized</term>
						<p>Although the later writings of Percy Bysshe Shelley cannot be cited as indicating his influence here, still his Defence of
							Poetry is continually concerned with the moral impact of literature on its readers. There is one passage, in particular,
							that appears to gloss the psychological operations the Creature is experiencing in this first endeavor to enlarge his
							existence through books: "The great instrument of moral good is the imagination. . ." </p>

					</item>
					<item n="312">
						<term target="#sympnec">sympathies necessary for my being</term>
						<p>The Creature's experiences have given a nuanced sense of the meaning of sympathy. It is not a superficial kindness or
							momentary expression of compassion, but an essential aspect of what it is to live as a human being, a necessity. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="313">
						<term target="#syndic">My papa is a Syndic</term>
						<p>The capacity to name, or abuse by naming—and to judge, or misjudge—are intimately allied throughout this novel. This is
							even truer of the stance one takes to the object of naming and judging. As William confidently assures the Creature, his
							father has been accorded the power to punish by this society: William adopts the same tone and attitude of natural
							superiority. Perhaps it was implictly present from the family expectations underscored in the first sentence of Victor's
							narrative (I:1:1) as well. Given the emotional chords that have resonated from William's death for eleven chapters and the
							epithets with which he has been honored ("little darling William" by Elizabeth [I:5:7], "that sweet child . . . who was so
							gentle, yet so gay" by Alphonse [I:6:3], "dear angel" by Victor [I:6:25]), his sheer childish nastiness surprizes us and,
							though it does not justify his murder, makes the Creature's bumbling attempt to quiet him comprehensible. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="314">
						<term target="#tapers">tapers</term>
						<p>A family reduced to this level of poverty would be unlikely to afford candles, which, generally speaking, in the eighteenth
							century were among household luxuries. A peasant in the northern part of Europe would be most likely to burn rush—dried
							reeds—for light. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="315">
						<term target="#tears">What did their tears imply?</term>
						<p>The logic of desire is played out through this paragraph to such an extent that, in the abstract at least, the answer to
							the question is already implicit in the disparity the Creature feels between himself and the De Lacey household. The
							thirst for perfection and incumbent awareness of personal inadequacy is a theme often encountered in the poetry of Lord
							Byron (e.g. Childe Harold's Pilgrimage Canto 4, 122ff.) and Percy Bysshe Shelley (e.g. "Lines Written among the Euganean
							Hills") during this period. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="316">
						<term target="#tempted">tempted to plunge into the silent lake</term>

						<p>In a boating accident during the summer Percy Bysshe Shelley, who could not swim, fell overboard and sank to the bottom of
							Lake Geneva, from which he had to be rescued. Speculative biography has discovered an urge toward suicide in the event and
							has connected it with these ruminations of Victor's. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="317">
						<term target="#terms">signification of those terms</term>
						<p>Here one senses the imprint of Godwin's method of progressively discriminating the necessary components of abstract ethical
							concepts. Virtue, and to a less degree vice, are repeatedly used as markers for social justice in the Enquiry concerning
							Political Justice, whose extended title continues as "and Its Influence on General Virtue and Happiness." Particular
							attention is paid to these concepts in Book I, Chapter 3 ("The Moral Characters of Men Originate in their Perceptions"),
							Book 4, Chapter 6 ("Inferences from the Doctrine of Necessity"), Book 4, Chapter 8 ("Of the Principle of Virtue"), Book 4,
							Chapter 9 ("Of the Tendency of Virtue"), and Book 5, Chapter 2 ("Of Education"). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="318">
						<term target="#thatcoul">that could not be</term>

						<p>This phrase carries a significant freight. Although it might be read as one more occasion in which Victor yields up his
							distinctive identity, substituting an obscure destiny in the process of fulfillment for his innate responsibility for
							events, in fact this necessity is driven by his own remorse, which is so acute that it can never be assuaged. Although he
							seems unaware of what he is doing, he is actually claiming responsibility for that destiny. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="319">
						<term target="#thaweful">the awful and majestic in nature</term>
						<p>The modern descriptive term for Victor's experience would be awesome. Although he dwells on how satisfying is this kind of
							response to nature (and in the third edition it is particularly accentuated), it is probably so because of its reliable
							alterity from his own situation. In a few paragraphs, with startling irony, he will have that dependability rudely broken,
							and the sublime will come directly home to the human who, thinking to master it, had fled from its tremendous power. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="320">
						<term target="#thedutys">the duties of a creator towards his creature</term>
						<p>This recognition confirms how tellingly on the mark the Creature had been in earlier confronting Victor with the habitual
							language of his father (II:2:7 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="321">
						<term target="#thefiend">the fiend</term>

						<p>This is a new term for the Creature, in its extremity indicating how far beyond "all bounds of moderation" (as Victor puts
							it in the next paragraph) his hatred has carried him. He will repeat it, virtually like a mantra, in that ensuing
							paragraph. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="322">
						<term target="#themonst">the monster</term>

						<p>Although Victor continually flagellates himself for the deaths of William and Justine, yet the hardening of his language as
							a means of self-exculpation and displacing his guilt continues. As he interchanges "fiend" and "monster," he combines the
							diabolic and the unnatural to objectify and distance his Creature from the norms he accords his family. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="323">
						<term target="#thewret">the wretch</term>
						<p>Victor reverts, as if by instinct (or psychological regression), to the nomenclature in which he first invested his
							Creature on that dreary November night some twenty-one months earlier when he brought him to life: see I:4:2-3 and note.</p>

					</item>
					<item n="324">
						<term target="#theyshar">they shall share my wretchedness</term>

						<p>Since this noun and its derivatives tolls like a bell through the novel after it is first used by Victor to name the
							Creature (I:4:3), there is a very real sense, on a linguisitic plane, in which the condition is already broadly shared. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="325">
						<term target="#thisfreq">This frequently took place</term>
						<p>It is now early spring, the first spring for the Creature, and he observes its characteristics without any previous example
							for comparison. The reader, however, already has experienced Victor's transports over this "divine spring" (see I:4:19 and
							note) in the first volume of the novel. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="326">
						<term target="#thlatter">the latter, however, I did not like</term>
						<p>Not only a vegetarian, the Creature is likewise naturally (like the Shelley household in general) averse to alcohol. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="327">
						<term target="#thought">I thought him as beautiful as the stranger</term>
						<p>The additional element that Safie brings to the emotional dynamics by which the Creature learns what it is to enjoy a full
							humanity is erotic love. That Felix responds so wholly to her presence as to seem physically transfigured perhaps
							underscores the emphasis the Creature will hereafter place upon the creation of a mate that may, he might hope, in some
							small part have a similar effect on him. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="328">
						<term target="#thyjust">thy justice</term>
						<p>The terminology here has a curiously political edge to it, particularly so after we have witnessed the demonstration of
							social injustice in the final chapters of Volume 1. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="329">
						<term target="#todress">to dress my food</term>
						<p>An archaic usage, meaning to prepare or cook: only the nominative form—"dressing"—is still retained in English with this
							original import. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="330">
						<term target="#tortures">the tortures of hell</term>
						<p>As earlier, Victor's histrionic sputtering, even as it testifies at once to the explosion of long repressed emotion and to
							his incapacity to handle the situation with which he is suddenly confronted, is also revelatory on a conceptual level. His
							mind is totally bound by the binary opposition of God and Satan in which he assumes not just creative godhead but also the
							right of judgment and particularly that of damnation, appointing this "fiend" and "devil" to the "tortures of hell." </p>

					</item>
					<item n="331">
						<term target="#toutter">to utter sounds</term>
						<p>Only at this point, at the end of the chapter, do we become aware that the Creature has, up to now, no ability to relate
							linguistically, that he is still operating on the non-verbal level of the sparrows and thrushes whose sounds he first
							discriminated (paragraph 4 above). Although presumably the De Lacey family speaks during the ongoing business of the day,
							except for the "few sounds" (paragraph 14 above) that were uttered by the young man outside the cottage and by the old man
							when his music elicited tears, this account is, as it were, rendered against a backdrop of total silence except for the
							interlude of music. Mary Shelley's artistic refinement in rendering this silence intensifies, in contrast, the importance
							of words and of communication for the world of her novel. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="332">
						<term target="#towards">towards the setting sun</term>
						<p>The Creature travels west for three full days. Given his stature and endurance, one would assume this would allow him to
							cover a large tract of south-central Germany. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="333">
						<term target="#transpor">in a transport of fury</term>
						<p>This phrase stands with a startling contradictory purity against the elder De Lacey's amiable platitudes concerning
							"brotherly love" (paragraph 25 above). Even worse, it undercuts all the ideals for which Felix has stood as well as the
							intellectual command by which he has restored his family's happiness and tranquillity. In a pinch Volney's ideal of an
							open, accepting humanity gives way to an unthinking recidivism, a protective and brutal tribalism, a masculinist
							belligerence, that is the moral equivalent of war. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="334">
						<term target="#trees">trees broken and strewed on the ground</term>
						<p>Compare Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Mont Blanc," lines 104-14. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="335">
						<term target="#tremendo">the tremendous and ever-moving glacier</term>
						<p>That is, the Mer de Glace, the Sea of Ice, which is the horizontal glacial field fed by three glaciers (including
							Montanvert) on the sides of Mont Blanc. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="336">
						<term target="#trial">the trial</term>
						<p>Although only mentioned here in passing, this is the novel's third unjust trial. All its circumstances—from involvement of
							the elder De Lacey and Agatha, who had no part in Felix's machinations, to the five-month pre-trial incarceration, to the
							confiscation of the family fortune and their banishment—suggest an arbitrary and tyrannical abuse of power by the state. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="337">
						<term target="#truehist">a true history</term>
						<p>The Creature has not yet learned the concept of fictionality: from his naive perspective all narratives are alike dutiful
							representations of reality. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="338">
						<term target="#twinklin">the eternal twinkling of the stars weighed upon me</term>
						<p>The sense of the momentous responsibility he has assumed seems for the moment to have made Victor into a new being. In a
							curious way, by recognizing what it is to be God, he becomes more like the sober and fearful Adam setting out from Eden at
							the end of Paradise Lost, a moral being for whom, as the Creature himself has acknowledged in reference to Byron's Manfred
							(II:5:18 and note, II:7:10 and note), knowledge is commensurate with sorrow. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="339">
						<term target="#uncouth">uncouth and inarticulate sounds</term>
						<p>This is the Creature's first sense of how he appears as a figure within a natural order. It is not a pleasant discovery to
							find oneself a discordant presence, but, as the ensuing paragraph relates, a kind of natural logic helps this eight-foot
							anomalous being not to feel himself divorced from the natural order. On the contrary, he seems instinctively able to
							recognize his affinity with it, even down to what he shares with beings as tiny as sparrows. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="340">
						<term target="#unfeelin">Unfeeling, heartless creator!</term>
						<p>This is not the first time that Victor has been thought "heartless": he levels the charge at his own behavior after
							Clerval's arrival in Ingolstadt (I:4:13 and note). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="341">
						<term target="#united">his daughter should be united to a Christian</term>
						<p>Himself victimized on account of his religion (II:6:3), the wily Turk is as bigoted as those who persecute him. He is
							likewise a type of Turkish villain frequently found on the early nineteenth-century stage, in England and across Europe,
							so there is another level of bigotry being appealed to here as well. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="342">
						<term target="#unlike">unlike what I have since found cottagers and farm-house servants to be</term>

						<p>As with her earlier treatment of Justine Moritz, Mary Shelley seems unable to keep a certain class bias from entering her
							discourse. In the case of Alphonse Frankenstein (I:6:36 and note) this may be something of a key to his character; but the
							Creature's emphasis on gentility after six weeks of existence might seem ill-conceived to some readers. It would appear,
							however, that the author is trying to suggest the Creature's own natural gentility rather than an innate snobbery in him. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="343">
						<term target="#unsymp">unsympathized with</term>
						<p>He means this in a literal sense: there is no one who feels with or for him, who accepts him as a fellow human being. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="344">
						<term target="#vacancy">blind vacancy</term>
						<p>The last word of Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Mont Blanc" is vacancy. In that poem the mountain is a "blank" slate upon which
							the mind writes the nature of reality. The present scene, we must recall, takes place not in the hovel attached to the De
							Lacey cottage, but rather in a hut above the Sea of Ice on Mont Blanc. It is here, fittingly, that the Creature, another
							blank slate, lives removed from humanity and where he appeals to his creator for identity, to be written upon. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="345">
						<term target="#valley">the valley of Chamounix</term>
						<p>Properly Chamonix, this valley lies in France at the northern approach to Mont Blanc. Mary and Percy Bysshe Shelley, along
							with Claire Clairmont, made an excursion to this valley of almost a week from 21 to 27 July, 1816, while Mary was deep in
							the writing of her novel. A long description of the excursion, written by Shelley to Thomas Love Peacock, was included in
							A History of a Six Weeks' Tour (see Letter 4). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="346">
						<term target="#vegetabl">vegetables in the gardens</term>
						<p>The season is yet early enough that the produce of late-autumn is still growing even with an early snowfall. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="347">
						<term target="#verybare">very bare of furniture</term>
						<p>Like Agatha's dress in the previous paragraph, this is another sign of poverty, but it is likewise an indication of how
							close to subsistence exists this entire family. In this they share the condition of the Creature who attaches himself to
							them partly on the basis of their simplicity of manners and means. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="348">
						<term target="#viewpool">when I viewed myself in a transparent pool</term>
						<p>With pointed economy Mary Shelley returns to the context of Paradise Lost, once again to emphasize the disparity between
							God's accomplishment and that of Victor Frankenstein. This time it is centered in the figure of Eve, who is transfixed by
							her beauty when, newly born, she happens to catch sight of her perfect form mirrored in a pool (IV.449-88). In both the
							novel and epic, though the effect is differently pointed in each, we read ironically against Ovid's account of the myth of
							Narcissus in Book III of the Metamorphoses. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="349">
						<term target="#violent">violent gesticulations</term>
						<p>Although the Creature cannot interpret the subject of this conversation, the gestures should be sufficient for his
							comprehension. They mime the reaction he elicits in all human beings. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="350">
						<term target="#violent2">violently</term>
						<p>A few paragraphs before, the Creature was reintroduced to human society through observing "violent gesticulations." Now
							Felix is seized by what is clearly an instinctive and uncontrollable violence. This is the same youth who, inspired by the
							most noble motives, has been habitually called "gentle" by the Creature in earlier chapters. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="351">
						<term target="#virtue">that . . . virtue</term>
						<p>These lines, repeated by the Creature to Victor, apply directly to his conduct, indicting his lack of both foresight and
							responsibility. They are also sadly ominous of the further degree of alienation faced by the Creature if this present
							mission fails. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="352">
						<term target="#virtues">the virtues that I once possessed</term>
						<p>The Creature acknowledges his fall from an original state of grace: "virtues" seems to be deliberately Miltonic diction,
							invoking Satan and Adam (and Eve). The Biblical context aside, this claim to a prelapsarian perfection is intended to
							remind Victor of his own high ambition (see I:3:8) and to affirm how well, on an internal if not external plane, it was
							realized. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="353">
						<term target="#wanderng">wandering beggars</term>
						<p>This is the Creature's first observation of human society rather than the life of nature, and it does not exactly accord
							with our normative sense of the civilized. Yet, a wandering beggar himself, he accepts this without wondering why it
							should be, leaving that question to the logical instincts of a reader with greater command over social institutions. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="354">
						<term target="#wanton">wantonness of power</term>
						<p>The Creature knows about the effects of unchecked power through the account of Safie's father's persecution (II:6:3) and
							the De Laceys' ruination (II:6:14), and he may have gleaned something of its underlying assumptions from William
							Frankenstein's instinctive reliance on his father's ability to punish arbitrarily (see II:8:27 and note). Yet, it is to
							Victor that the Creature speaks, and, since he has used a derivative of "wantonness" in his earlier condemnation (II:8:1
							and note), it is perhaps to that particularized sense of irresponsibility that he reverts here. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="355">
						<term target="#wasbene">I was benevolent</term>
						<p>This appears a deliberate echo of Victor's self-exculpating claim, "I had begun life with benevolent intentions," in the
							opening paragraph of this second volume. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="356">
						<term target="#wasmonst">Was I then a monster</term>
						<p>Even to be able to ask the question suggests the extremity of alienation in which the Creature exists and the extent to
							which he internalizes the values by which normative human culture rejects him. The "then" is a significant index of the
							force of logic that excludes the Creature from a recognizable place in the world. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="357">
						<term target="#weighed">weighed down by horror and despair</term>
						<p>The phrase echoes words used in the third sentence of this chapter, suggesting that for Victor there is no imaginable
							change in his condition. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="358">
						<term target="#werter">Sorrows of Werter</term>
						<p>Die Leiden des Jungen Werthers (The Sorrows of the Young Werter) by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749-1832) was originally
							published anonymously in Leipzig in 1774. Almost instantly it became a best seller, catapulting its young and unknown
							author into fame and a major literary career that would span more than half a century. By the end of the decade the novel
							had been translated into the other European languages, attaining a pan-European success that continued well into the
							nineteenth century: as late as 1892 it afforded Jules Massenet one of his greatest musical triumphs at the Paris Opera.</p>
						<p>The first French translation was published in 1777 as the work of C. Aubry, a pseudonym for Friedrich Wilhelm Karl, Graf
							von Schmettau (1742-1806), and it was frequently reprinted in that language. The first English version, by Daniel Malthus,
							was published in 1779 as The Sorrows of Werter, using the French text, rather than Goethe's original, as its base. </p>
						<p>The novel coincided with what has come to be known as the Age of Sensibility, whose flames it helped to fan. It is an
							epistolary novel, told in Werther's voice and from his perspective, and there is little in the way of plot. Charlotte, the
							oldest of six children, is left an orphan by the sudden death of her mother, and she marries the sensible, if somewhat
							plodding, Albert as a means of holding the family together. Onto the scene comes the young student Werther who is
							befriended by the couple but then falls passionately in love with Lotte. His infatuation progressively deepens to a point
							of desperation in which he commits suicide. The novel was said to be responsible for making suicide fashionable among the
							young men of Europe.</p>
						<p>What the Creature responds to are less the episodes of the plot or even the dynamics of infatuation than the sense of moral
							emptiness that Werther finds in the world and from which he turns for refuge to the somewhat maternal Lotte. Precociously
							intellectual with a late-adolescent intensity, Werther too seeks to understand his identity and to discover his place in a
							middle-class milieu that cares for little that is not prudent and sensible, the world represented by Albert. In reference
							to the particular dynamics of Mary Shelley's novel, this milieu would appear very much on the order of the temperate Swiss
							world of Alphonse Frankenstein and Henry Clerval's father. Thus, curiously enough, the novel establishes a link to
							Goethe's fiction both through the intense self-questioning and bleak alienation of the Creature as well as the obsessive
							behavior of his creator Victor Frankenstein, who also turns away from the commonplace Geneva expectations in which he was
							raised to fathom a new mode of being. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="359">
						<term target="#wertplut">I learned . . . thoughts</term>
						<p>The Creature turns from Goethe's novel of isolated sensibility, where he sees his own reflection (and we to some extent see
							Victor's) to contemplate the public and civic models of Plutarch's biographical accounts, engaging a world of social
							interaction and nation-building of which he has no experience whatsoever. Thus the accounts draw him forth from his own
							isolation to imagine a larger cultural sphere of action in which he might participate. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="360">
						<term target="#weshall">we shall be monsters . . . world</term>
						<p>That the Creature proposes to make a virtue out of necessity and embrace his alienation as a mode of existence indicates
							what two years of experience have cost him. The pathos of this declaration does not call attention to itself, but is all
							the more affecting. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="361">
						<term target="#whatcand">what can disturb our tranquillity</term>
						<p>Elizabeth's faith that a retreat from the world would allow the two of them a relief from the buffeting of experience is
							understandable, if sadly ill-placed. The ensuing chapters seem deliberately designed to test this hope both in their
							exemplary tale of a collective retreat (involving not just the DeLacey's and Safie, but the Creature as well) and in the
							very fact that, themselves taking place in an almost inaccessible retreat, they present Victor Frankenstein with a moral
							crisis of a kind he has never known and is unprepared for. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="362">
						<term target="#whatdest">what . . . destination?</term>
						<p>These might be said to be the root questions of all philosophy. They are in a substantial way the end toward which the
							progressive education of the Creature has been tending. That they are unanswerable has larger implications than for just
							him. They contribute to the exploratory tonalities of a novel that resists easy answers and unambiguous truths. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="363">
						<term target="#whenfals">when falsehood can look so like the truth</term>
						<p>Elizabeth's comparative innocence does not allow her the larger perspective held by the reader, who might want to apply the
							force of these words to the accruing series of contrasts between herself and Victor being offered by this paragraph. In
							his lack of candor, justice, and sympathy, Victor appears specifically to negate the virtues of Elizabeth, who stands here
							as something of an emblem for truth itself. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="364">
						<term target="#whnbecam">I was in reality the monster that I am</term>
						<p>A lengthy pattern of self-analysis and attendant self-alienation is implicit in this passage. The Creature's divorce from
							himself is linked to the imagery of doubling throughout the novel. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="365">
						<term target="#windings">continual and short windings</term>
						<p>American usage would substitute the word "switchbacks" for this locution today. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="366">
						<term target="#without">without bounds</term>
						<p>The repetition of "boundless" language from the previous chapter (see II:1:6 and note) emphasizes the point that Victor is,
							as ever, too "ardent," unable to moderate or even control his reaction. Whereas some earlier critics wished to enforce a
							facile dichotomy between Victor as rationalist and his Creature as the exemplar of sensibility, a passage like this
							reminds us of how little power Victor's capacity for abstraction actually has over the broad field of his mind.</p>
						<p> The Creature, as his narrative unfolds, will likewise represent himself through similar language as he experiences what he
							conceives to be a betrayal by his "adopted" family, the De Laceys. At that moment (II:8:12) in his recital he seems
							unconscious of the close similarity between the two of them. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="367">
						<term target="#wobeing">without being able as yet to understand or apply them</term>
						<p>That the Creature has as yet no notion of how words that define feelings can be applied suggests that the next stage of his
							education must be metaphysical, involving an understanding of the self and an exploration of self-consciousness. For him
							this will necessarily entail what Byron called "Consciousness awaking to her woes" (Childe Harold's Pilgrimage 1.941: st.
							92). </p>

					</item>
					<item n="368">
						<term target="#wretchd">the wretched</term>
						<p>"Wretch" is the first term Victor applies to his Creature (I:4:3), as well as his appellation for him at his reappearance
							in this chapter. It is apt that the creature thus picks up this resonant word and by shifting its form alters its meaning.
							For her debut as a novelist Mary Shelley adopts a daring and difficult but brilliantly successful strategy, keeping the
							Creature out of sight for most of Volume I while Victor heaps terms of abuse on his felt presence and renders him for the
							reader the monster he is wont to call him. The urbane calm of the Creature's opening statement, "I expected this
							reception," is a startling reminder of just how much Victor, in his narration of his story, has skewed the perspective on
							its events. In effect, the Creature takes the opportunity of his finally being heard to rename, to reconceptualize,
							himself. And the reader is left hanging in doubt—perhaps, even distrust—about rendering a verdict from having listened
							only to one side of the case. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="369">
						<term target="#youacuse">You accuse me of murder; and yet you would, with a satisfied conscience, destroy your own creature</term>

						<p> As the Creature's terms have just implicitly placed Victor Frankenstein with the judges who have wrongfully condemned
							Justine Moritz to death, so here, he recognizes that Victor's easy willingness to commit murder, broached in the preceding
							chapter (II:1:6) and reiterated to the Creature himself (II:2:6), places him on the same moral plane as the being he
							accuses of having committed murder. If Victor does not yet recognize his identity with his creation, the Creature's plea
							is reinforcing their "ties" on every level possible. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="370">
						<term target="#yourduty">your duty</term>
						<p>Alphonse Frankenstein has so chastized Victor over his slippery sense of his family obligations that he ought to experience
							some confusion to hear his father's words echoed from the mouth of his Creature. In a world about to be turned
							upside-down, it would not be surprising if Victor's putative son were not in some odd sense to assume the role of his
							father. </p>

					</item>
					<item n="371">
						<term target="#youwrong">You are in the wrong</term>
						<p>No one, not even his father, ever speaks to Victor so forthrightly or with such categorical moral language. The diction
							picks up on the issue of what is a "right" from two paragraphs before. </p>

					</item>
				</list>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
