<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Introduction: Sound Studies in Romanticism </title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Michele Speitz</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-04-18</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                   <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                   <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                   <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                   <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.soundstudies.intro</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">soundstudies</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Introduction: Sound Studies in Romanticism
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Michele</forename>
                                <surname>Speitz</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/soundstudies/praxis.2023.soundstudies.intro"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Sound Studies: Recording Romantic Relationality</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-04-10">April 18, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                   <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                   <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                   <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                   <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                   <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                   <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                   <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                   <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                   <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                   <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>04.18.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Introduction: Sound Studies in Romanticism</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Michele Speitz</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Furman University</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
              <p>This collection takes up two interrelated questions. One, how might the
                interdisciplinary field of sound studies change the way we engage with Romantic
                literature? Two, how can sound studies foment broader inquiries into a range of
                Romanticisms not exclusive to British Romanticism? Inspired by such thinking, the
                essays gathered here attest to how sound studies can uncover a multisensorial
                Romanticism steeped in narratives of experiential history not limited to Romantic
                literatures of just one place or people or time. As questions of multisensory
                meaning and experience arise as a red thread running across the volume, attendant
                questions pertaining to the stakes of human relationality both in a social sense and
                an environmental one become impossible to ignore. The volume stands as a fresh
                complement to 2008 <hi rend="italic">Praxis</hi> volume edited by Susan J. Wolfson
                and titled “<ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/index.html"
                    >Soundings of Things Done”: The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear
                    and Era</ref>. While those generative essays deal chiefly with “the sounding
                sense of Romantic poetry, both thematically (a poetics of sound) and
                sensually/phonically (the poetry of sound and the sound of poetry),” this volume
                studies sound through a wider cross-section of Romantic genres. This includes not
                poetry alone but also periodicals, drama, and the novel as well as governmental,
                musical, and scientific literature (1). And whereas the previous volume foregrounds
                Wordsworthian poetics and a smaller subset of authors of British Romanticism, these
                essays increase their reach to include a wider array of writers, German Romanticism,
                and extra-Romantic historical and contemporary documents on sound, voice, and
                song.</p>
                
          <p>This collection, then, begins to open up larger conversations for scholars and
                readers of Romantic-era literature and culture such that they might consider a wider
                assortment of representations of sounds, silences, voices, calls, quietudes,
                volumes, modes of listening, sensing, and interpreting sonic experiences, including
                human and nonhuman sound-bound relations. By so doing—in some small yet important
                way—these essays herald Dylan Robinson’s recent call to acknowledge “how writing
                allows certain moments of sonic experience to be heard while foreclosing upon
                others” and how a person’s “positionality guides the way [they] listen” (1). There
                is a politics to how we make sense of sound, how we mark sonic experiences, how we
                record practices of listening, voicing, sounding, hearing—as Steingo and Sykes
                remind us, nearly two decades ago Jonathan Sterne noted in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Audible Past</hi> “that, in the West, the ‘differences between hearing and
                seeing’ … [are] <hi rend="italic">ideologically loaded</hi> (2 original
                emphasis).</p>
                
          <p>Sterne’s iconic essay, “Sonic Imagination” from <hi rend="italic">The Sound Studies
                    Reader</hi> (2012), defines sound studies as an interdisciplinary project “that
                takes sound as its analytical point of departure or arrival” (2). To “<hi
                    rend="italic">think sonically</hi>” entails “analyzing both sonic practices and
                the discourses and institutions that describe them” (2). The task of the critic of
                sound studies, then, is to “redescribe what sound does in the human world, and what
                humans do in the sonic world,” to “always go beyond … common-sense categories” to
                uncover “what we don’t already know” (2). In keeping with Sterne’s definition, the
                essays appearing here attune readers to Romantic representations of human sonic
                worlds as well as more-than-human sonic worlds to underscore the key parts played
                therein by sound. Across the whole, the volume experiments with making sense of
                Romantic literature by way of sound studies. Consequently, and as this volume’s
                readers will learn for themselves, every one of these essays features questions of
                relationality. In this sense, the volume coheres in the manner of a chorus uniting
                voices of all sorts that in this instance cannot but sing of relationality because
                sound does not exist in a vacuum and because its histories are more contingently
                experiential than broadly universal. </p>
                
         <p>Each author demonstrates how sound studies alerts us to key dimensions of Romantic
                literatures and cultures that we didn’t already know. The collection moves from
                rethinking modes of lyric listening to discovering the role that sonic thinking and
                feeling plays in conceptualizing the Romantic power of the imagination. It registers
                the ways in which sonic terror operates in the gothic novel. It broadcasts how
                understanding sound not only in a narrow auditory sense but as a relational
                multisensory experience enables us to reconceive Romanticism’s models of
                epistemology, ecology, and aesthetics. Sound studies makes it impossible to <hi
                    rend="italic">un</hi>hear Romantic literature’s preoccupation with ways of
                knowing and feeling that couple together this sensory mode with that, ultimately
                complicating simplistic accounts of the imperial, oppressive primacy of the
                visual.</p>
                
          <p>In homage to the original <hi rend="italic">Praxis</hi> volume on sound and its
                nuanced discussions of British Romantic lyric in particular, this volume’s opening
                essays stage a veritable dialogue on representations of sound in Samuel Taylor
                Coleridge’s classic poem “Frost at Midnight.” Mina Gorji’s and Elizabeth Weybright’s
                respective treatments of one poem, Coleridge’s “Frost at Midnight”(c. 1798),
                showcase how reading Romantic poetry in light of the sound studies turn can yield
                profuse interpretive futures for studies in Romanticism. </p>
                
          <p>Gorji’s “Lyric Listening” inquires into the place of sound and volume as well as
                listening – or the lack thereof - in lyric studies. Using Coleridge’s poem and lyric
                theory as key points of departure, Gorji notes how the word
                <hi rend="italic">volume </hi>“acquired an acoustic register in
                the late eighteenth century” and explains that the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>’s
                first recorded use of the term bearing this new meaning is attributed to Byron’s
                <hi rend="italic">Werner </hi>(1822). Gorji contends
                that while “Frost at Midnight” does not use the term <hi rend="italic">volume</hi>
                itself, the poem bespeaks a Coleridgean “preoccup[ation] with how to represent
                sounds and especially volume, and that his imaginative interest in acoustics and in
                musical forms and notation informed the way he shaped sound into both aural patterns
                and visual language in his poetry." </p>
                
          <p>Gorji questions how lyric poetry might serve as “a container for sound” or as an
                “expression of volume” through a richly contextualized interpretation of “Frost at
                Midnight.” The essay grapples with how the poem “records a playful exploration of
                dynamics and of the various ways (graphic, rhythmic, linguistic and as an effect of
                tempo) in which sound and quiet could be represented to both eye and ear in the
                poem." Extending Susan Wolfson’s essay in particular from the previous
                <hi rend="italic">Praxis </hi>volume on sound, Gorji thickens
                her consideration of “Frost at Midnight” with other contemporary and later lyric
                poetry to offer “the state of listening, hearkening” after “something” as <hi
                    rend="italic">the</hi> “poetic state” of Romantic lyric. Gorji gives readers new
                ways to think about “the significance of silence and quiet in Coleridge’s poems, and
                in Romantic lyric more widely,” with the essay ultimately calling for a “new kind of
                listening” and pushing “Lyric Studies [to expand] the range and frequency of its
                listening.”</p>
                
          <p>Gorji’s work on Coleridge dovetails with Elizabeth Weybright’s “Unquiet
                Romanticism,” which likewise engages with “Frost at Midnight” and Wolfson’s
                “Sounding Romantic.” Yet Weybright’s approach departs from Gorji’s by offering a
                comparative reading of the poem that takes into account related representations of
                sound—and furthermore, noise—in Wordsworth’s
                <hi rend="italic">Prelude </hi>and Percy Shelley’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Mont Blanc.</hi> Weybright’s essay demonstrates how “Romantic
                literary representations of listening present noise as an underpinning of
                phenomenological experience and audition” (23). Noise, as Romantic literature frames
                it, is “as an essential (sometimes involuntary) activity through which human
                subjects enter into self-reflective reciprocity with elements of their social and
                natural worlds” (23). In this sense, noise is defined as a dynamic interaction, one
                prompting humanity to recognize itself as always already in necessary dialogue with
                the cultural and natural worlds within which they reside. Building on influential
                theorizations of noise, sound, and silence penned by the likes of Jacques Attali,
                John Cage, Michael Chion, Jean-Luc Nancy, David Novak, Jonathan Sterne, Shelley
                Trower, Salomé Voegelin, and more, Weybright’s contribution to this volume
                resoundingly testifies to the rich upwellings of thought that arise from a
                conceptual terrain sensitive to both sound studies and studies of Romanticism. </p>
                
          <p>Rather than reading “Frost at Midnight” from a musical perspective akin to Gorji’s
                project, Weybright centers her inquiry into Romantic lyric poetry around the
                question of “how sounds … far removed from anything like musical organization (or
                even the categories of tonal sound available at the turn of the nineteenth century)
                might be generative points of contact between the creative mind and the phenomenal
                world” (6-7). For Weybright, figurations of “‘quiet’ things made ‘unquiet’” become
                central to understanding sound as it relates to models of subjectivity in Romantic
                lyric, particularly as Romantic poets’ “approaches to quietly noisy sounds … refuse
                absolute epistemological or symbolic stability” (2, 3). Weybright argues “that for
                the Romantics, listening to unquiet noise is often both an active ‘straining’ to
                place oneself as a creative agent in relation to the world and—somewhat
                paradoxically—a compelled state of receptive embodiment” where noise is not
                understood “as a one-dimensionally overwhelming, distracting or painful thing, but
                rather was an ambiguous, sometimes baffling, and sometimes imaginatively provocative
                presence” (3, 4). </p>
                
          <p>David Sigler’s essay dismantles the binary that counterpoises sound against vision.
                In “The sound of the gaze in Ann Radcliffe’s <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian
                    Romance</hi>” Sigler troubles the simplistic formula that takes sound as the
                bearer of mystery and vision as the bringer of knowledge. In the end, Sigler
                deconstructs the gaze-as-bad/sound-as-good dichotomy extant within Radcliffe
                criticism, Gothic Studies, and Romantic Studies more generally. The essay notes that
                in Radcliff’s novel, “sound … asks to be seen” and “show[s] vision to be an aspect
                of sound,” all of which allows Sigler to unearth “the psychic consequences of that
                sensory entanglement” (1, 4). It is less that we cannot know sound in Sigler’s
                analysis of Radcliff’s gothic novel, and more that - like desire - sound yields an
                “excess of signification” that could never be fully determined. Thereby sound
                harbors the power to terrify with its potential to lead us into spaces of the
                unknown and indeterminate. Sigler’s approach pairs sound studies with psychoanalysis
                to demonstrate that by “thinking about sound through epistemologies of vision,
                Radcliff could respond to contemporary debates about gender, class, and privilege”
                (3). That is, sound has the capacity to play such a role in the novel precisely
                because “sound (including music, noise, and silence) had an important visual
                component in the eighteenth-century English culture, especially for the construction
                of gender” (4).</p>
                
          <p>Sigler’s analysis of
                <hi rend="italic">A Sicilian Romance </hi>confirms that
                “Radcliff hears lack as a positive presence in its own right, consistently crossing
                the visual and sonic registers to highlight a multisensory ambiguity” (28).
                Intriguingly, by thinking with sound studies approaches, Sigler unearths how
                “Radcliff subjects her characters to a sonic voyeurism that exceeds Foucauldian and
                Sartrean models of the gaze” (28). The essay offers a fresh understanding of the
                novel by conveying how “Radcliff challenges emergent visual epistemologies of the
                eighteenth century and reorganizes prevailing patterns of Enlightenment
                subjectivity” (28). Through a compelling assessment of the sonic contexts within
                which Radcliff’s characters are placed, Sigler stresses how “lack, in [Radcliff’s]
                account, is not something missing but something present and resonant” (28). 
            </p>
                
          <p>Joel Faflak’s contribution, “Shelley’s Sound Body,” turns upon questions of voice,
                vocal expression, and listening in Percy Shelley’s lyrical drama
                <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound </hi>to confront the ways
                in which sound challenges sense making even as it is derived of the senses. Faflak’s
                project “explore[s an] incompossibility between voice and the said” in Shelley’s
                lines (1). Akin to Sigler’s work, Faflak acknowledges that “Romanticism inherits
                from the Enlightenment a preoccupation with sight, visuality, and the gaze as both
                formative and troubling forms of how an emergent modernity increasingly comes to
                apprehend the world” (2). But at the same time, Faflak underscores that “in its
                preoccupation with voice and sound, however, Romanticism explores what this
                apprehension misses” (2). More to the point, Romanticism’s debates around voice and
                sound foreground compelling questions of human potential and right action, where the
                very act of listening assumes a political edge and bears great ontological weight.
                Such debates held across Romantic literature announce “that human potential ‘does
                not [necessarily] solidify in an object of fetish reverence’—the kind of reverence
                that [in <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound</hi>] guarantees tyranny as a symbol
                and method of prescribing what humans and thus the human itself can and should be”
                (2).</p>
                
         <p>For Faflak, “sound in Shelley’s poem seems to be merely the medium” but in a sort of
                Kittleresque fashion “at the same time [sound] facilitates a mode of relationality
                that is the matrix of meaning itself without making meaning present” (23). Because
                sound acts as both medium and never-fully-present message in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Prometheus Unbound</hi>, “sound insists on its own opacity,” and thus Shelley’s
                thinking chimes with Édourard Glissant’s when the latter writes of “the ‘errantry’
                of ‘Totality’s imaginary [which] allows the detours that lead away from anything
                totalitarian’” (23). Faflak argues that
                <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound </hi>“asks us to listen
                without prejudice, as if that is ever possible” since counter to any “illusions of
                transparency … listening requires the implicit acknowledgement that we can never
                truly understand what we are listening for” (24). In keeping with this ethos, though
                the poem directs readers to listen as an intrinsic good and goes so far as to devote
                the “fourth Act [to] a staging of the act of listening itself … the poem doesn’t
                tell us what to listen <hi rend="italic">for</hi>” (25, author’s emphasis). Instead,
                and in light of its prescription to listen,
                <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound </hi>scripts for its
                readers yet another unpredictable scene, a scene to be played out beyond the pages
                of the poem: “confronted by the nothingness of sound from which meaning can or might
                or might not come, we are nonetheless compelled to speak again” (25).</p>
                
         <p>Offering the collection’s closing argument, Gabriel Stephen Trop surveys significant
                works of German Romanticism to discuss how within this body of literature sounding
                objects figure “a metaphysical drama in acoustic form” (2). Beginning with the
                examples of the clock and the wind that famously open Novalis' novel
                <hi rend="italic">Heinrich von Ofterdingen </hi>(1802), Trop
                insists that readers not “reduce [such] objects, in traditional terms, to the
                function of setting—to background conditions against which an event takes place”
                (2). Instead, Trop argues, “they indicate tensions in the dynamic from which
                entities emerge, the domain the Romantics and post-Kantian philosophers called the
                    <hi rend="italic">unconditioned </hi>(<hi rend="italic">das
                    Unbedingte</hi>): the absolute as that to which no conditions can be attached”
                (2). As Trop notes, whereas “the window is typically a privileged speculative site,
                the opening onto a space at once visual and visionary, in Novalis “the first sensory
                organ to register the drama of the unconditioned in this instance is the ear” (2).
                The essay finds that within various works of German Romanticism “it is not just that sound indicates the absolute as that
                    which is unconditioned, but that it constructs the real as a material-ideal
                    system in the process of turning against itself, moving amidst the peaks and
                    troughs of waves, perpetually unconditioning itself and carrying all beings
                    along in its wake” (33). In this sense, then, a larger implication of Trop’s
                    project is that sound carries us all in its wake.</p>
                
          <p>Across an ambitious yet careful analysis of sound in key works of German Romanticism,
                Trop emphasizes how such texts articulate “the irreducible gap between real and
                ideal as the basis for a diabolic and extra-normative generativity” (3). Trop
                engages with not just Novalis’ novel but also his “scientific and philosophical
                fragments,” Shelling’s take on “sonority” from the <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of
                    Music</hi>, Ørsted’s discussions of “sound as shock,” Ritter’s conception of
                sound “as an electrical virtuality of figuration,” Eichendorff’s “lyrical equation
                of contemplation with intoxication through the concept of rustling, <hi
                    rend="italic">Rauschen,</hi>” as well as E. T. A. Hoffmann’s “electrical-musical
                aesthetics” (3). In these respective treatments of sound each work testifies to how
                “Material vibrations, waves, oscillations, collisions—all taking place below the
                threshold of conscious perception—can be amplified in Romantic thought into
                larger-scale domains: from language to the soul, from acoustics to physiology, from
                wave oscillations to the modification of human sensuous capacities” (2). The essay
                    uncovers how “sound discloses fundamental ontology as an oscillation of the real, the real <hi rend="italic">as </hi>
                    oscillation: a trembling of things that moves through all
                    individuated forms, material and spiritual” (33). Trop grapples with how “the
                    most intimate experiences of the world become the most alien” as the German
                    Romantics he studies undertake “their speculative philosophical and aesthetic
                    experiments with sound” (33). By these lights “we see that it is not sufficient
                    for the German Romantics to describe sound and its material or ideal basis;
                    rather, the latent dynamics emergent from the speculative and aesthetic
                    encounter with sound must be redirected back into the world: as an art of
                    unconditioning” (33).</p>
                
          <p>To round out the introduction by voicing one of the volume’s largest implications
                that might otherwise go unsung, I’ll turn once again to Sterne’s field-defining work
                on sound studies from <hi rend="italic">The Audible Past</hi>. There Sterne makes
                quick work of dispelling a persistent myth: that the telegraph, telephone,
                phonograph, and radio irrevocably altered “the nature, meaning, and practices of
                sound in the late nineteenth century” (1). Sterne calls out seductive narratives
                such as these for being “incomplete” given that “[m]any of the practices, ideas, and
                constructs associated with sound-reproduction technologies predated the machines
                themselves” (1). Extending Sterne’s thinking, I offer the lines of Romantic
                literature studied here and elsewhere as a valuable record of eighteenth- and
                nineteenth-century soundways. Romanticism’s literary records predate the likes of
                the telegraph or the radio and so comprise a sound-reproducing technology bearing
                sonic cultures and sonic histories and sonic theories. These are cultures,
                histories, and theories that are at risk of going unheard if we were to fail to take
                the time now to turn their pages, to tune in, and listen to them. </p></div>
            
            <div type="citation">
                <head>Works Cited</head>
           
                
           
          <bibl>Robinson, Dylan. <hi rend="italic">Hungry
                    Listening: Resonant Theory for Indigenous Sound Studies</hi>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
                2020.</bibl>
                
          <bibl>Steingo, Gavin, and Jim Sykes. “Introduction: Remapping
                    Sound Studies in the Global South.” In <hi rend="italic"
                    >Remapping Sound
                    Studies</hi>, edited by Gavin Steingo and Jim Sykes, 1–36. Duke University Press, 2019. <ref
                    target="https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctv125jhsq.4"
                    >https://doi.org/10.2307/j.ctv125jhsq.4</ref>.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>Sterne, Jonathan. <hi rend="italic">The
                    Audible Past: Cultural Origins of Sound Reproduction</hi>. Durham: Duke University Press, 2003.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>---. “Sonic
                    Imaginations.” In
                    <hi rend="italic">The Sound Studies Reader</hi>, edited by Jonathan Sterne, 1-17.
                    London and New York: Routledge, 2012.</bibl>
                
          <bibl>Wolfson, Susan J. “‘Soundings of Things Done’: The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear and Era,” <hi
                    rend="italic">Romantic Circles Praxis
                    Series</hi>, 2008. <ref
                    target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/index.html"
                    >https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/index.html</ref>.</bibl>
                
           <bibl>---. “Sounding Romantic: The Sound of Sound” In “‘Soundings of Things Done’: The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear and Era,” edited by Susan J. Wolfson, 1-33. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles Praxis
                    Series, 2008. </hi><ref
                    target="https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/wolfson/wolfson.html"
                    >https://romantic-circles.org/praxis/soundings/wolfson/wolfson.html</ref>.</bibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>