<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Shelley's Sound Body</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Joel Faflak</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-04-14</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.sound.faflak</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">praxis</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Shelley's Sound Body
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Joel</forename>
                                <surname>Faflak</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/sound/praxis.2023.sound.faflak"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Sound Studies: Recording Romantic Relationality </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-02-21">April 14, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>04.14.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Shelley's Sound Body <note place="foot" resp="author"> I thank
                    Michele Speitz for her timely suggestions, incisive editing, and kind invitation
                    to contribute in the first place.</note></head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Joel Faflak</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Western University</affiliation>
                </byline>
            
            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">For Ross, who listened, and heard, like no
                    other.</hi></p>
                
            <p>Nothing will come of nothing; speak again.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    William Shakespeare,<hi rend="italic">King Lear</hi>, ed. Stanley Wells (Oxford:
                    Oxford World Classics, 2000), Act One, Scene One, line 99.</note></p>
                
            <p>-- <hi rend="italic">King Lear</hi></p>
                
            <p>Listen Without Prejudice.<note place="foot" resp="author"> George Michael,<hi
                        rend="italic">Listen Without Prejudice, Volume I</hi> (Columbia Records,
                    1990). </note></p>
                
            <p>-- George Michael</p>
                
            <p>Can we ever hear the sound of our own voice? When as a child I was asked by my
                mother, “Do you hear yourself?!”, I would think to myself, “Well, no. But you do. Or
                do you?” Mladen Dolar calls the voice “the material support of bringing about
                meaning, yet it does not contribute to it itself. It is, rather, something like the
                vanishing mediator” that “makes the utterance possible, but . . . disappears in
                    it.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Mladen Dolar,<hi rend="italic">A
                        Voice and Nothing More</hi> (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2006), 15.</note>
                What “persists,” Dolar argues, is the “object voice,” which “does not go up in smoke
                in the conveyance of meaning, and does not solidify in an object of fetish
                    reverence.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Dolar, 4.</note> Hence a
                paradox: although “voices are the very texture of the social, as well as the
                intimate kernel of subjectivity,” the voice “is <hi rend="italic">what does not
                    contribute to making sense.</hi>”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Dolar,
                    14, 15 (original emphasis).</note> Voice “is the material element recalcitrant
                to meaning,” for “if we speak in order to say something, then the voice is precisely
                that which cannot be said.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Dolar,
                    15.</note> I want to explore this incommensurability between voice and the said
                in Percy Shelley’s lyrical drama, <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound </hi>(1820).
                If the materiality of voice and sound mediates and grounds meaning and the human,
                more often than not in Romantic verse (think of Keats’ nightingale) they remain
                “recalcitrant to meaning,” opening a fissure within human being. This vanishing
                potential makes transformation possible while at the same time challenging notions
                of “a unified self-representation.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Tilottama Rajan, “’The Web of Human Things’: Narrative and Identity in<hi
                        rend="italic">Alastor</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">New Romanticisms: Theory
                        and Critical Practice</hi>, ed. David L. Clark and Donald C. Goellnicht
                    (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1994), 87.</note> Examining the moment in
                    <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi> when Walton hears “the sound as of a human
                voice” that announces the creature’s presence, David Clark asks, “Would a human
                voice be thinkable if not for hearing it <hi rend="italic">differentially
                </hi>through the other?”, as when a sound recording of our voice confronts us with
                its “machinic life”:
                
            <quote>The difference between a human voice and the likeness of a human voice reproduces a
                difference within the human voice, making it originarily a likeness of itself: here
                ‘voice’ stands as a figure for the way in which the human appears <hi rend="italic"
                    >to </hi>itself and <hi rend="italic">for </hi>itself, that is, <hi
                    rend="italic">monstrates</hi>, stands out, shows, or portends. In other words,
                the ‘human voice’ is the figure for the human’s marking of itself <hi rend="italic"
                    >as </hi>human, and thus its re-marking.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    David L. Clark, “Last Words: Voice, Gesture, and the Remains of<hi rend="italic"
                        >Frankenstein</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein in Theory</hi>, ed.
                    Orrin N. C. Wang (New York: Bloomsbury, 2020), 18, 22, 19.</note></quote>
                
            Romanticism inherits from the Enlightenment a preoccupation with sight, visuality,
                and the gaze as both formative and troubling forms of how an emergent modernity
                increasingly comes to apprehend the world. In its preoccupation with voice and
                sound, however, Romanticism explores what this apprehension misses as that which
                necessarily <hi rend="italic">remains </hi>missing such that human potential “does
                not solidify in an object of fetish reverence” – the kind of reverence that
                guarantees Jupiter’s tyranny as a symbol and method of prescribing what humans and
                thus the human itself can and should be.</p>
                
            <p>In Act One of Shelley’s poem, Prometheus implores the Earth and her elements to
                recall to him the “many-voiced Echoes” (1.60)<note place="foot"
                    resp="author"> All references to Shelley’s writing are from<hi rend="italic">Shelley’s
                        Poetry and Prose, </hi>ed. Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat, 2<hi
                        rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. (New York: W. W. Norton, 2002); cited by title, act,
                    scene, and/or line number for poetry and page number for prose.</note> of his
                curse against Jupiter, who has pinned Prometheus to a rock in the Indian Caucasus
                for daring to defy the tyrant’s authority. Whatever plot the poem has, this, as well
                as the transforming energy of Asia’s desire, constitutes its single driver, apart
                from its concrete result, relegated to a stage direction at the opening of Act
                Three, Scene Three: “Hercules unbinds Prometheus, who descends” (259). But the poem
                enacts no straightforward feat of recall. For one thing, Shelley’s is not “the
                individual Mind that keeps her own / Inviolate retirement,”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> William Wordsworth, Preface to<hi rend="italic">The
                        Excursion</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Poetical Works</hi>, ed. Thomas
                    Hutchinson; rev. ed. Ernest de Selincourt (Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                    1988), lines<hi rend="italic"> </hi>19-20.</note> grounded in its ability to
                reclaim the past within the present and thus gain purchase on the future. Shelley
                draws his imagery “from the operations of the human mind” (Preface to <hi
                    rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound</hi>, 207) as a reflection of “different
                modifications of the one mind” (“On Life,” 508). But whereas for an earlier
                criticism the “one mind” signalled a movement from Shelley’s early skepticism toward
                the metaphysics of “postmortal transcendence,”<note place="foot"
                    resp="author"> Earl Wasserman,<hi rend="italic">Shelley: A Critical Reading
                    </hi>(Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1971), ix.</note> so much of
                his verse explores a mind rarely at one with itself. Symptomatic of this unbound and
                unbinding nature is the fact that Prometheus’ curse has gone viral in the
                environment. There it remains, ready to haunt, if not return, a “voice” which is
                both “contagion to the world” (2.3.10) and “an awakening sound” (3.3.14). That the
                Mountains, Springs, Air, and Whirlwinds echo back the “dread words” (1.99) of the
                curse indicates a rather more distributed cognition.<note 
                    place="foot" n="13"> This term is usually attributed to Edwin Hutchins, a
                    general signifier for cognition as both embodied and an extension of our lived
                    environments, hence my use of sound as the matrix of a viral terrain. See Edwin
                        Hutchins,<hi rend="italic">Cognition in the Wild </hi>(Cambridge, MA: MIT
                    Press, 1995). See also David J. Chalmers, <hi rend="italic">The Conscious Mind:
                        In Search of a Fundamental Theory </hi>(Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                    1996); and Andy Clark, <hi rend="italic">Supersizing the Mind: Embodiment,
                        Action, and Cognitive Extension</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                    2011). </note> Recalling the curse itself is beside the point, for “words are
                quick and vain” (1.303). What matters instead is “the voice / Which [Prometheus]
                gave forth” (1.112-13). He has less forgotten the curse than he wants to recall the
                sound of his – its – defiance at the moment of its saying. But again, this is not
                merely to summon the voice of this defiance. More complexly, it is both to express
                and to register the autonomous affect of resistance as the vanishing mediator of any
                attempt to renovate a devastated world.</p>
                
            <p>Hence to recall the curse is not to return to any origin or first principle in order
                to advance toward some eventual or anticipated <hi rend="italic">telos</hi>. The
                poem’s complex movement back to its own future, its relentless pursuit of “the
                gigantic shadows which futurity casts upon the present” (<hi rend="italic">A Defence
                    of Poetry</hi>, 535), tracks the primal scene of an experience that can never be
                recalled but that remains as the habitual performance of its absence. As Fred Moten
                argues, “It’s the ongoing repression of the primal scene of subjection that one
                wants to guard against and linger in. . . . the <hi rend="italic">conjunction
                </hi>of reproduction and disappearance is performance’s condition of possibility,
                its ontology and its mode of production.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Fred Moten,<hi rend="italic">In the Break: The Aesthetics of the Black Radical
                        Tradition</hi> (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2003), 5.</note>
                In this delicate balance between submitting again to the sound of punishment and
                keeping alive the voice of resistance, what, then, does Prometheus hear, or want to
                hear, or need to hear? Something to do with the sound <hi rend="italic">of
                    </hi>sound,<note place="foot" resp="author"> I borrow this phrase from
                    Susan J. Wolfson, “Introduction,” in<hi rend="italic">‘Soundings of Things
                        Done’: The Poetry and Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear and Era</hi>, ed.
                    Susan J. Wolfson, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles Praxis</hi> (April 2008):
                    par. 3.</note> the activity of its occurrence, provides the answer, which is why
                echoes come to signify at once the failure of recall and its insistent possibility.
                In Shelley’s lyrical drama, a voice, like Echo herself, is nothing more than sound
                cursed to repeat what it hears, wasted by the desire she can never express for the
                astonishing beauty of another she can never have. But unlike Narcissus’ perpetually
                redirected inwardness, that the voice is nothing more means it also has the queerly
                powerful potential to release itself from the gaze of the other. </p>
                
            <p>Eventually I want to argue that this potential resides with the capacity to listen
                and to be heard as nearly impossible markers of what it means to be human. Listening
                is the literal act of a possible communication between individuals. Yet at the same
                time speaking with and to others is less to listen for and hear the content of what
                is being said, the grounding of a human relationality, than it is to register what
                risks getting lost in translation. Listening is facilitated by the materiality of
                sound, but it transpires as and results in the immaterial or ideational affect and
                effect of what is possibly being heard. We can, that is, differentiate between
                hearing and listening. To hear and be heard is to indicate a certain transmission of
                meaning. To listen is to remain open to the possibility <hi rend="italic">of
                </hi>meaning, not as its crystallization but as what cannot be conscripted into
                meaning, as what takes us always already beyond ourselves. Prometheus listens more
                than hears and listens for more than he hears. In doing so, listening moves the poem
                perpetually along the non-human trajectory of what Chris Washington calls
                Romanticism’s post-apocalyptic future.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See
                    Chris Washington,<hi rend="italic">Romantic Revelations: Visions of
                        Post-Apocalyptic Life and Hope in the Anthropocene</hi> (Toronto: University
                    of Toronto Press, 2019).</note>
            </p>
            
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>II.</head>
                
            
            <p>At the opening of Act One, Prometheus asks the Earth, “have not the mountains felt?”
                (1.24), “yon Heaven – the all-beholding Sun, / Has it not seen?” and “The Sea, in
                storm or calm / Heaven’s ever-changing Shadow, spread below – / Have its deaf waves
                not heard my agony?” (1.26-29). Feeling, sight, sound. The poem seems to avoid
                prioritizing one over the other, though it’s not as simple as that. When he
                encounters the Furies Mercury sends to harrow his soul, Prometheus states, “Whilst I
                behold such execrable shapes, / Methinks I grow like what I contemplate / And laugh
                and stare in loathsome sympathy” (1.449-51). Here the ominous fixity of the gaze
                orchestrates the scene of Romantic sympathy. The Furies anatomize what Panthea calls
                “A woeful sight – a youth / With patient looks nailed to a crucifix” (584-85). This
                image marks the nightmare of iconography and thus of the visual to supersede and
                thus oppress all other senses. Or as Blake writes in <hi rend="italic">The Marriage
                    of Heaven and Hell </hi>(1790-1793), “man has closed himself up, till he sees
                all things thro’ narrow chinks of his cavern.”<note place="foot"
                    resp="author"> William Blake,<hi rend="italic">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake,
                    </hi>rev.ed, ed. David V. Erdman (New York: Anchor, 1988), plate 14.</note> In
                    <hi rend="italic">Letters on Natural Magic</hi>, David Brewster argues that
                “This wonderful organ [the eye] may be considered as the sentinel which guards the
                pass between the worlds of matter and spirit. . . . The eye is consequently the
                principal seat of the supernatural.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> David
                        Brewster,<hi rend="italic">Letters on Natural Magic, Addressed to Sir Walter
                        Scott</hi> (London: John Murray, 1832), 10.</note> The statement suggests by
                the time of the First Reform Bill the enduring post-Enlightenment hegemony of the
                visual. Yet one of Brewster’s examples is the Spectre of the Brocken, an atmospheric
                phenomenon by which our shadows, cast upon mist, both magnify and distort the human
                form. The Spectre reflects the spectral nature of vision itself, the way in which
                reality passes into consciousness via a logic beyond comprehension, like the
                hallucinatory doubles of James Hogg’s <hi rend="italic">Private Memoirs and
                    Confessions of a Justified Sinner </hi>(1824) or Thomas De Quincey’s opium
                fantasias. </p>
                
            <p>In Shelley’s poem the Sea challenges the Sun’s “all-beholding” pre-eminence of the
                visual as the mirror or “ever-changing Shadow” of Heaven “spread below,” where
                Prometheus’ “agony” falls on “deaf” ears. Glen O’Malley has explored this
                transitional space between sight and sound as part of Shelley’s synesthetic
                aesthetic. Synaesthesia suggests how the neuronal pathways of the poem’s sensorium –
                the “vitally metaphorical” way in which the transferences of figurative language
                embody a poem’s experience as it unfolds <hi rend="italic">in medias res</hi> –
                produce a kind of involuntary interconnectedness in which subjects hear sight or see
                    sound.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Glen O’Malley,<hi
                        rend="italic">Shelley and Synesthesia </hi>(Evanston, IL: Northwestern UP,
                    1964). William Keach calls Shelley’s style “the work of an artist whose sense of
                    the unique and unrealized potential in language was held in unstable suspension
                    with his sense of its resistances and limitations.” William Keach, <hi
                        rend="italic">Shelley’s Style </hi> (xvi).</note> Such capacity radicalizes
                the perceptual juxtapositions of what Blake calls the “Ratio of the five
                    senses.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Blake,<hi rend="italic">The
                        Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, plate 14.</note> At the same time, as a
                synaesthete will tell you, all senses firing involuntarily at once brings its own
                form of hell, a kind of perceptual deluge that overwhelms and suspends the self, as
                if to open a fissure within human being. Addressing the capacity of images to compel
                and fascinate our notice, W. J. T. Mitchell asks “What do pictures want?”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> See W. J. T. Mitchell, <hi rend="italic"
                            >What Do Pictures Want? The Lives and Loves of Images </hi>(Chicago:
                        University of Chicago Press, 2005).</note> Asking how and why the visual
                arrests our attention is to account for the lack that mobilizes this mutual desire
                in the first place, one for which neither we nor the picture can account. In a
                similar way, Shelley’s poem both desires and demands our attention without any
                guarantee that we will be able to make sense of its felt environment. </p>
                
            <p>The poem thus implicitly differentiates between making sense and the making <hi
                    rend="italic">of </hi>sense, between what we imagine the result of sense-making
                to mean and the perceptual actions that make meaning possible in the first place,
                but on which we can gain no objective purchase. Sound signals this paradoxical
                embeddedness, what in a somewhat different context Jacques Lacan calls the
                “filigree” in which we “feel the presence of the gaze” even when “any representation
                of the human figure is absent.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Jacques
                        Lacan,<hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book XI: The Four
                        Fundamental Concepts of Psychoanalysis, </hi>ed. Jacques-Alain Miller,
                    trans. Alan Sheridan (New York: W. W. Norton, 1981), 101.</note> Put another
                way, sound in <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound </hi>confronts us with a
                subjectivity without subjects, what one might call a transferential subject or
                subject <hi rend="italic">of </hi>transference. And in this sense, sound suggests a
                mode of survival that survives the visual. At the end of Act Three the Spirit of the
                Earth recounts to Asia that he has heard the “voice to be accomplished” as a “long
                long sound, as it would never end” (3.4.57). In Act One Ione asks where the Chorus
                of Spirits that bring the sound of the future from “the dim caves of human thought”
                (1.658) have “fled” (1.801). Panthea replies: “Only a sense / Remains of them, like
                the Omnipotence / Of music when the inspired voice and lute / Languish, ere yet the
                responses are mute” (1.802-5). Something about the loss of sound registers as the
                enduring sound of loss, the ineluctable transference between invincibility and
                expiration. Or as Jean-Luc Nancy writes,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>the “visual persists
                until its disappearance,” while “the sonorous appears and fades away into its
                    permanence.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Jean-Luc Nancy,<hi
                        rend="italic">Listening</hi>, trans. Charlotte Mandell (New York: Fordham
                    University Press, 2007), 2.</note></p>
                
            <p>The resonantly disastrous sonic effects of Prometheus’ curse denude the earth and
                dehumanize its inhabitants. They also indicate what Steve Goodman calls “the less
                anthropocentric <hi rend="italic">environmentality </hi>or <hi rend="italic">ecology
                    of vibrational effects</hi>”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Steve
                        Goodman,<hi rend="italic">Sonic Warfare: Sound, Affect, and the Ecology of
                        Fear</hi> (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2010), xviii (original
                    emphasis).</note> that will be the poem’s final vision and celebration of a kind
                of post- or para-human life. In Act Three Earth feels these effects as a “touch”
                that “runs down / Even to the adamantine central gloom / Along those marble nerves”
                (3.3.85-87). At first, however, the sound of Prometheus’ curse seems to echo
                Jupiter’s oppression, resonating as a sound within Jupiter’s hearing that confirms
                his power. The “Mountains” and “ice Springs” “vibrated to hear” Prometheus’ curse
                “and then crept / Shuddering through India” (63-65). The sound of the curse was like
                that of an “Earthquake’s couch” over which the Mountains “stood,” and like “men
                convulsed with fears / We trembled in our multitude” (1.75-77). This traumatic sonic
                vibration registers as the involuntary and inarticulate affective vocabulary of
                groans: “rending groan” (1.85), “the groans of pining slaves” (1.128), “groans and
                blood” (1.332), “groans half heard, and blood untasted” (1.529), “low yet dreadful
                groan” (1.578). As Panthea says, revisiting the effects of Jupiter’s curse on earth
                and throughout history, “those groans are grief enough” (1.593). They manifest what
                Goodman calls “sonic warfare.” In 2005 the Israeli military used “sound bombs” in
                the Gaza Strip, “the high-volume, deep-frequency effect of low-flying jets traveling
                faster than the speed of sound.” The “objective was to weaken the morale of a
                civilian population by creating a climate of fear through a threat that was
                preferably nonlethal yet possibly as unsettling as an actual attack.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman, xiii-xiv.</note> Such a traumatic
                deployment indicates how “sound can modulate mood,” for the “intense vibration
                literally threatens not just the traumatized emotional disposition and physiology of
                the population, but also the very structure of the built environment.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman, xiv.</note> Part of Prometheus’
                desire to recall his curse against Jupiter in Act One, then, is to risk
                re-instantiating voice and sound for their purely material and thus violent effect
                and affect.</p>
                
            <p>Yet Prometheus short-circuits this “affectively contagious radiation of sonic
                    events”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman, xix.</note> in order
                to re-sound sound as the potentiality of a less traumatizing experience. He thus
                pushes against the deployment of sonic trauma as the “<hi rend="italic">activity of
                    the future in the present,</hi> and therefore a portal into the operative logic
                of fear within the emergent paradigm of preemptive power,” what Brian Massumi calls
                the future affect of terror.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman, xviii
                    (original emphasis). See Brian Massumi,“The Future Birth of the Affective Fact:
                    The Political Ontology of Threat,” in <hi rend="italic">The Affect Theory
                        Reader</hi>, ed. Melissa Gregg and Gregory J. Seigworth (Durham, NC: Duke
                    University Press, 2010), 52–70.</note> The last Fury says, “Blood thou canst
                see, and fire; and canst hear groans: / Worse things unheard, unseen, remaind
                behind” (1.617-18). If the sound of grief is felt along the pulses, it also heralds
                another “unheard, unseen” materiality that here signals an ominous future but, as we
                later see, is also a redemptive sonic possibility. The Fury’s negative formation
                embeds its inverse as the “happy sounds” of Earth that remain to this point like the
                “inarticulate people of the dead” (1.188, 183). Asking to hear the sound of the
                voice he “gave forth,” Prometheus hears “an awful whisper” that “rises up,” the
                “inorganic voice” of a “Spirit” that Prometheus feels “art moving near” (1.132-36).
                That this voice is “scarce like sound” (1.133) suggests the weakening resonance of
                Prometheus’s curse that he would re-amplify in order to dismiss. Yet the phrasing
                also indicates a potentiality that “connects every separate entity in the cosmos,
                organic or inorganic.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman, xiv.</note>
                This “production, transmission, and mutation of affective tonality” signals a
                “non-representational ontology of vibrational force,”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman, xv.</note> not sound’s representation <hi
                    rend="italic">as </hi>sound but its dynamic motion through time and space. As
                avatars carrying the sonic effect of this movement to Asia in Act Two, Ione and
                Panthea see the voice as “A Shape, a throng of sounds” (1.226). But this “Shape” is
                at the same time “awful <hi rend="italic">like</hi> the sound” (1.233; emphasis
                added), indicating a metonymic or sideways movement or force that the Phantasm of
                Jupiter hears as “unaccustomed sounds . . . hovering on my lips” (1.242-43), as if
                to anticipate their decentering power to overthrow the tyrant. More pointedly,
                Prometheus in turn hears the voice of the Phantasm as “empty” (1.249), as if to
                signal it as now void of meaning, just as Prometheus, upon hearing the curse,
                famously responds, “It doth repent me: words are quick and vain” (1.1.303).</p>
                
            <p>But “empty” also foreshadows within the plenitude of sound the vanishing mediator of
                voice that is, as Dolar notes, the matrix of sound itself, one that by Act Four will
                drown out all other voices. Tellingly, when the Fury finally vanishes and the
                “sights with which [Jupiter] torturest gird [Prometheus’] soul / With new endurance”
                (1.643-44), Prometheus then says, “There are two woes: / To speak and to behold;
                thou spare me one” (1.646-47). This spared woe I take to be the sound of words
                themselves. Earlier Prometheus says, pondering the sacrificial image or “emblem” he
                might become to “heap / Thousand-fold torment” (1.595-96) on humankind, “Thy name I
                will not speak, / It hath become a curse” (1.603-5). He is thus spared succumbing to
                the fixed sound of his original curse, so that its traumatic sonic effects can be
                released into its more productive vibratory movement. At this point the Earth calls
                upon a chorus of spirits to voice what “they behold / Beyond that twilight realm, as
                in a glass” (1.661-62), but a glass darkly that is the mirror stage of sound through
                which Prometheus and Asia will pass. And what they bear/speak is the sound of “The
                future” (1.663): “One sound – above, around, / One sound beneath, around, above /
                Was moving” (1.703-5). Through this medium, as Ione states, “despair” is “Mingled
                with love, and then dissolved in sound,” which in turn stops up words altogether. As
                Panthea responds, “Canst thou speak, sister? all my words are drowned” (1.758), and
                the Spirits having fled, they hear “Only a sense” of their presence, but one that
                “Like echoes through long caverns, wind and roll” (1.806). Here the echoes that
                earlier in the Act threatened to die out now resonate with a startling and complex
                materiality as sound bends (“wind and roll”) through a space that is at once
                physical, natural, psychological, spiritual, and cosmic.</p>
                
            <p>This resonance, at once material and metaphysical, drives Act Two. Here Asia, long
                parted from Prometheus in the Indian Caucasus, now occupies the “scene of her sad
                exile” (1.827), patiently awaiting his return. Yet their impending reunion, meant to
                signal the rebirth of the world released from the effects of Jupiter’s curse, is
                less the <hi rend="italic">hieros gamos </hi>of two identities than their mutual
                submersion in sound as their very mode of being. Panthea enters with the knowledge
                of two dreams, the sound of which carries her and Asia to the realm of Demogorgon.
                One heralds the imminent liberation of Prometheus from Jupiter’s tyranny, a gradual
                transformation Panthea witnesses while asleep in Ione’s arms in Act One, enacted in
                Act Three’s stage direction. That dream carries Panthea in Act Two as “the wind /
                Which fails beneath the music that I bear” (2.1.50-51), which is the “wordless
                converse” (2.1.52) already transpiring between Asia and Prometheus since Act One.
                Asia reads the psychic interiority of Prometheus in Panthea’s face, now a site of
                potential recognition and communication between Asia and Prometheus: “Lift up thine
                eyes, / And let me read thy dream” (2.2.55-56).<note place="foot"
                   resp="author"> For Rajan these scenes construct a dialogic “model” that presents
                    “reading as a psychological and not just a semiological process” (<hi
                        rend="italic">The Supplement of Reading: Figures of Understanding in
                        Romantic Theory and Practice</hi> [Ithaca, NY: Cornell University Press,
                    1990], 308).</note> Finding Panthea’s “words / Are as the air. I feel them not”
                (2.1.109), Asia then implores her to “lift / Thine eyes that I may read his written
                soul!” (2.1.109-10). Yet their transference suggests neither entrapment within the
                gaze of the visual nor the prison house of language; instead it does the felt work
                of reading through the medium of sound. The Norton Editors tell us that Panthea’s
                second dream – which, tellingly, she “remember[s] not” (2.1.610) – is of “the Spirit
                of Hours that are to usher in the fall of Jupiter and the release of Prometheus, and
                to the course of necessity” (238n2). I would argue that the purpose of this second
                dream is to manifest sound as what “has no hidden face; it is all in front, in back,
                and outside inside, <hi rend="italic">inside-out</hi> in relation to the most
                general logic of presence as appearing, as phenomenality or as manifestation, and
                thus as the visible face of a presence subsisting in self.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Nancy, 13-14.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>This subjectivity without subjects gradually emerges as the poem’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >modus operandi</hi>. The second Dream tells Asia and Panthea to “Follow,
                follow!” (2.1.132), then “disappears” (2.132) and “passes now into [the] mind”
                (2.133) of Panthea, who echoes its sound: “<hi rend="italic">O follow, follow!</hi>”
                (2.141). As Panthea speaks the sound of her “words / Fill, pause by pause [Asia’s]
                own forgotten sleep / With shapes” (2.141-43) that in turn echo the Dream’s sound at
                lines 153 (“<hi rend="italic">Follow, O follow!</hi>”), 159 (“<hi rend="italic">O
                    follow, follow, follow me!</hi>”), and 162 (“<hi rend="italic">follow,
                    follow</hi>”), what she hears as the “clinging music” of “Low, sweet, faint
                sounds, like the farewell of ghosts” (2.1.157, 158). This <hi rend="italic"
                    >menage-a-trois </hi>of sound signifies the tangled transference between
                Panthea, Asia, and Prometheus that then resounds in the Echo of the Dream – “Follow,
                follow!” (2.1.162) – and yet again in “<hi rend="italic">unseen</hi>” Echoes who
                announce, “Echoes we – listen! / We cannot stay / As dew-stars glisten / Then fade
                away” (2.1.166-69). Here, as throughout the poem, Shelley’s syntax is maddeningly
                opaque. Although sound cannot be seen, it nonetheless announces its presence “as the
                visible face of a presence subsisting in self.” Like Heideggerian<hi rend="italic"
                    >Schein, </hi>in which<hi rend="italic"> </hi>being is at once revelatory and
                illusory, it <hi rend="italic">appears</hi>, as in the phrase “We are echoes,” a
                performative speech act that implores Asia and Panthea to “listen” before this
                presence fades. At the same time, the echoes carry the sounds of this listening and
                thus do the work of listening itself. As Asia and Panthea approach Demogorgon’s
                realm, they hear a sound that “Satiates the listening wind, continuous, vast, /
                Awful as silence” (2.3.35-36). We might ask how wind can listen, but then we need to
                ask what a sound might be with no wind to carry – to hear – it? </p>
                
            <p>At the end of Act Two, after her descent to the Cave of Demogorgon, where she finds
                that “the deep truth is imageless” (2.4.116), Asia, hearing only the sound of her
                thought echoed back by Demogorgon, is told instead simply to “Behold!” (2.4.128).
                The exclamation is less an injunction to <hi rend="italic">see </hi>than to <hi
                    rend="italic">feel </hi>and thus <hi rend="italic">hear </hi>what the future
                holds. Or rather, if it is to see, it’s to see what cannot be seen, to see the sound
                of the future as the picture of what sound might look like. The Spirit of the Hour
                arrives to transport Asia to her reunion with Prometheus in Act Three. Seeing the
                change in Asia’s presence, Panthea cannot “endure the radiance of [her] beauty”
                (2.5.17-18), like the synaesthete unable to withstand all senses firing at will: “I
                feel, but see thee not” (2.5.17). Yet at the same time this perceptual crisis
                heralds the emergence of a greater immersive sonic environment, the “sounds i’ the
                air which speak the love / Of all articulate beings” (2.5.35-36) and sing of Asia as
                the “Life of Life” (2.5.48) and “Child of Light” (2.5.54). Immersed in this music,
                Panthea experiences the abandonment of and by sight as the pre-existing condition
                for transformation by the feeling of sound: “all feel, yet see thee never / As I
                feel now, lost forever!” (2.5.64-65). At this point Asia, “by the instinct of sweet
                Music driven” in the “enchanted Boat” of her “desire” (2.5.90, 72, 94), is carried
                to the poem’s primal scene, as it were, of its sonic imagination<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> This is Jonathan Sterne’s “deliberately synaesthetic
                    neologism” to “denote a quality of mind, but not a totality of mind” that is
                    “guided by an orienting curiosity.” “Sonic imaginations are [thus] necessarily
                    plural, recursive, reflexive, driven to represent, refigure and redescribe.”
                    Jonathan Sterne, “Sonic Imaginations,” in<hi rend="italic">The Sound Studies
                        Reader</hi>, ed. Jonathan Sterne (New York: Routledge, 2012), 5, 9, 6, 5.
                </note>: 
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l> My soul is an enchanted boat</l>
            <l> Which, like a sleeping swan, doth float</l>
            <l>Upon the silver saves of they sweet singing . . .</l>
            <l> It seems to float ever – forever –</l>
            <l> Upon that many winding River</l>
            <l> Between mountains, woods, abysses,</l>
            <l> A Paradise of wildernesses,</l>
            <l>Till like one in slumber bound</l>
            <l>Borne to the Ocean, I float down, around,</l>
            <l>Into a Sea profound, of ever-spreading sound. (2.5.72-74, 78-84)</l>
                </lg>
                    
            Drowning, not waving, suggests a loss (“lost forever”) that is at the same time
                suspension and buoyancy (“It seems to float ever – forever”).<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> On Shelley’s use of metonymy and similitude (“seems,”
                    “like”), see Julie Carlson “Like love: The feel of Shelley’s similes.”<hi
                        rend="italic">Romanticism and the Emotions</hi>, ed. Joel Faflak and Richard
                    C. Sha (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014), 76-97.</note> This life
                    <hi rend="italic">of </hi>sound marks the relation of Being insofar, as Éduoard
                Glissant notes, “Relation is safe from the idea of Being.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Édouard Glissant,<hi rend="italic">Poetics of
                    Relation</hi>, trans. Betsy Wing (Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press,
                    1997), 185.</note> To wave would be to signal from the depths of being, what
                Glissant calls a “poetics of depth,” “like depth psychology.”<note 
                    place="foot" n="36"> Glissant, 24.</note> Such depth signals a knowledge that
                can be plumbed, exteriorized from the subject, “dispossessing it of the sovereign
                subject (requiring the knowledge – the gaze, or the hearing – of another) then
                surrendering it to this subject (speaking ‘in’ the structures of any expressed
                    knowledge).”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Glissant, 24.</note> To
                drown, on the other hand, is to surrender yet not to submit.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>III.</head>
                
            <p>In Act Three Ione announces both what sound prophecies and the sound <hi
                    rend="italic">of </hi>prophecy itself. Implored by Prometheus, she takes “that
                curved shell, which Proteus old / Made Asia’s nuptial boon, breathing within it / A
                voice to be accomplished” (3.3.65-67), as if the sound emanates at once from Ione’s
                breath <hi rend="italic">and</hi> autonomously from the shell itself. Similarly, the
                resulting “sound must be at once both sweet and strange” (3.3.75), familiar and
                alien, one whose timbre is pitched ambiguously between present and future as well as
                past. “Must” signals variously as ‘it must be this way,’ ‘it must take this form,’
                but also it ‘must already be this way,’ at once given, imperative, and
                prognostication. As Prometheus announces, Ione will “chant fragments of sea-music”
                (3.3.27) that signal a “Mutability” from which “man” cannot “hide” (3.3.25), while
                Asia and Prometheus, “unchanged,” “will sit and talk of time and change / As the
                world ebbs and flows” (3.3.23-24). Moreover, they shall “Weave harmonies divine yet
                ever new, / From difference sweet where discord cannot be” (3.3.38-39). This vision
                is of things “though unimagined, yet to be” (3.3.56). This “voice to be
                accomplished” suggests a blank utopian future that might never be realized, a
                sterile ‘no-place’ of only ever potential action. But it also suggests Frederic
                Jameson’s reading of utopia as an “imaginary enclave within the real social space,”
                one whose “very possibility . . . is itself the result of spatial and social
                differentiation” born of two “contradictory features.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Frederic Jameson,<hi rend="italic">Archaeologies of the
                        Future: The Desire Called Utopia and Other Science Fictions</hi> (New York:
                    Verso, 2005), 15.</note> This “pocket of stasis within the ferment and rushing
                forces of social change” is the product of the agitations of transitional historical
                moments, like the effects of Jupiter’s tyranny or Prometheus’ curse. But it also
                marks a “distance . . . from practical politics, on the basis of a zone of the
                social totality which seems eternal and unchangeable,” like the cave to which
                Prometheus and Asia repair at the end of Act Three.</p>
                
            <p>We can thus read Jameson’s two “contradictory features” in terms of how <hi
                    rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound</hi> wrestles with the uncanny connection
                between tyranny/oppression and liberation/transformation. The poem’s utopianism only
                makes sense by virtue of its emergence both within and apart from the space of
                discord that is the occasion of Prometheus wanting to remember his curse against
                Jupiter in the first place. Yet this paradox, as I have explored it to this point,
                is to map a space of listening negotiation based, not in “discord” but in a
                “difference” that does not at the same time produce identity. Just at the moment
                that the Chorus of Spirits announces the song of the Promethean in Act Four, the
                Chorus of Hours, whose temporality signals the movement of social transition,
                announces, “Break the dance, and scatter the song; / Let some depart and some
                remain” (4.159-60). As Kandice Chuh notes, borrowing from Fred Moten, this ‘break’
                in sound, which is also an invitation “‘into the break,’” indicates a “radical
                aesthetics that undermines the privileged position of visual representation and its
                attendant processes of subjectification/subjection.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Kandice Chuh,<hi rend="italic">The Difference Aesthetics
                        Makes: On the Humanities “After Man” </hi>(Durham, NC: Duke University
                    Press, 2019), 61.</note> As Ione says to Panthea, “Even whilst we speak / New
                notes arise . . . What is that awful sound?” (4.184-85). Like Demogorgon’s realm,
                “Awful as silence,” this sound cannot be understood or turned into meaning. Instead
                it must be felt as part of the subject’s immersion in the matrix of her own coming
                to being. </p>
                
            <p>This absorption is less to trap the subject between oppression and transformation,
                which Shelley seems to recognize as an unavoidable capture, than it is to mark a
                “pocket of stasis” in which a subjectivity without subjects registers a rather more
                fluid and dynamic possibility. At this point Ione and Panthea “Listen” for “The
                Ocean-like inchantment of strong sound / Which flows intenser, keener, deeper yet /
                Under the ground and through the windless air” (4.203-5). This tonal motion heralds
                the “Two visions of strange radiance” (4.202) whose “path of melody” (4.198) carries
                the “lovely grief” of “sweet sad thoughts” (4.201). Again, the ambiguity of
                Shelley’s phrasing indicates the lived experience of listening itself as both active
                attunement and submission to the act of listening. As the Earth says when in Act
                Three Prometheus heralds the “thunder mingled with clear echoes,” “I hear – I feel”
                (3.3.84). Sound and voice but more importantly <hi rend="italic">listening </hi>to
                either indicates a sensory intake that is itself constitutive of the poem’s
                revolutionary movement. This agitation within the social space of a world reeling
                from both the tyrant’s oppression and defeat that instantiates the very moment of
                political practice itself as a lived utopian gesture. As Chuh notes, “sound can
                interrupt the social order more immediately, perhaps more effectively, than can
                visual representation.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Chuh, 61.</note>
                Such disruptive potential also speaks to the fact that Shelley’s text seems more
                than aware of itself <hi rend="italic">as </hi>sound, more importantly an aesthetics
                of “sound, as sound.” Put another way, one engages in listening yet can never
                anticipate what will be heard. As Glissant states, “The power to experience the
                shock of elsewhere is what distinguishes the poet.”<note place="foot"
                    resp="author"> Glissant, 29-30.</note> And what will be heard, once materialized as
                sound, immediately vanishes into the sonorousness of this materialization. </p>
                
            <p>It’s not the case, then, that sound takes priority over sight. Instead, “listening .
                . . is the sense that touches upon and stimulates at once all bodily senses, as well
                as that other sense-making faculty that has been variously called ‘mind,’ ‘spirit,’
                or ‘soul.’”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Adrienne Janus, “Listening:
                    Jean-Luc Nancy and the ‘Anti-Ocular’ Turn in Continental Philosophy and Critical
                        Theory,”<hi rend="italic">Comparative Literature </hi>63:2 (2018):
                    189.</note> For “to listen is both to engage in proprioceptive self-reflection
                and to be drawn towards other sounding bodies whose resonances both penetrate and
                envelope the listener.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Janus, 189.</note>
                One might say all of Act One, indeed the entire poem, is engaged in active listening
                for the synaesthetic good vibrations that signal “the new world of man” that, as the
                Chorus of Spirits and Hours in Act Four foretell, “shall be called the Promethean”
                (4.158). This “awakening sound” “shall be / As thunder mingled with clear echoes”
                (3.3.81-82), yet not in the sense that the echoes themselves provide a clarity of
                sound for they are “mingled” with the sound of the thunder itself. The poem attends
                to a rather more complex “loud and whirlwind harmony” (4.237) that is “the deep
                music of the rolling world / Kindling within the strings of the waved air / Æolian
                modulations” (4.186-88). Listening, that is to say, is neither an easy nor isolated
                and solitary task. As Ione says in Act Four, one must “Listen too, / How every pause
                is filled with under-notes, / Clear, silver, icy, keen, awakening tones / Which
                pierce the sense and live within the soul / As the sharp stars pierce Winter’s
                chrystal air / And gaze upon themselves within the sea” (4.188-93). Goodman speaks
                of the “unactualized nexus of rhythms and frequencies within audible
                    bandwidths,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman, xx.</note> like
                the unheard melodies resonating from Keats’ Grecian urn. Goodman calls this the “<hi
                    rend="italic">not yet audible</hi>” or “<hi rend="italic">unsound,</hi>” silence
                as “sound in potential, unactualized.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Goodman, 191.</note> An as yet unactualized potential both of and within sound
                at the same time constitutes the sonic’s capacity for mobilizing, orchestrating, and
                reorganizing pluralistic and relational rather than totalizing or atomizing
                environments.</p>
                
            <p>Listening thus constitutes the profoundly political dimension of Shelley’s text as a
                gesture beyond the political. In <hi rend="italic">Noise</hi>: <hi rend="italic">The
                    Political Economy of Music</hi>, Jacques Attali unfolds a cultural
                historiography of music as the prophetic herald of change, “a way of perceiving the
                world” and a “tool of understanding,”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Jacques Attali,<hi rend="italic">Noise: The Political Economy of Music</hi>,
                    trans. Brian Massumi (Minneapolis: Minnesota University Press, 1985), 4.</note>
                what Shelley in “Ode to a West Wind” calls “The trumpet of a prophecy” (69). Music
                is the orchestration of sound as noise: “With noise is born disorder and its
                opposite: the world. With music is born power and its opposite: subversion.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Attali, 6.</note> As the political
                unconscious of music, noise is an especially potent idea in a world of capital and
                the fetishization of music as commodity and spectacle, in a “society of repetition
                in which nothing will happen anymore,”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Attali, 5.</note> the prospect of a recursive and redundant historical progress
                Shelley will confront in his last poem, <hi rend="italic">The Triumph of Life</hi>.
                Theodor Adorno associates this fetishization with the “pseudoactivity” and
                “deconcentration” of an “atomized” or “regression of listening,” which misses
                hearing “the possibility of a different and oppositional music” and collapses the
                differentiating force of sound into a mere diversion from the autocracy of
                    sameness.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Theodor Adorno, “On the
                    Fetish-Character in Music and the Regression of Listening,” in<hi rend="italic"
                        >The Essential Frankfurt School Reader</hi>, ed. Andrew Arato and Eike
                    Gebhardt (New York: Continuum, 1985), 283, 288, 289, 286, 286.</note> Instead,
                “concentrated listening,” in Attali’s terms, “heralds the emergence of a formidable
                subversion, one leading to a radically new organization never yet theorized, of
                which self-management is but a distant echo.”<note place="foot"
                   resp="author"> Adorno, 288; Attali, 5.</note> Within this unstable economy of sound the
                various forms of listening as “eavesdropping, censorship recording, and
                surveillance, are weapons of power” that sustain the “dreams of political scientists
                and the fantasies of men in power: to listen, to memorize – this is the ability to
                interpret and control history.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Attali,
                    7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Jupiter’s tyranny is sustained by his capacity to incite hate in those he oppresses;
                their curse against him is a sign of his power <hi rend="italic">to</hi> oppress. He
                listens for it; he yearns to hear it, though like Oedipus confronted by Tiresias, he
                cannot hear what is being said. When the Car of the Hour bearing Demogorgon arrives
                at the opening of Act Three, Jupiter demands, “Awful Shape, what art thou? Speak!”
                (3.1.51). Demogorgon responds, “Eternity – demand no direr name” (3.1.52), which
                short circuits the master/slave dialectic whose words no longer have power as both
                “conqueror and the conquered” sink “into the bottomless void” (3.1.78, 76). This
                pointed, almost traumatically abbreviated exchange symbolizes the absurdly fragile
                nature of power and its ideological labour. Like Dorothy in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Wizard of Oz </hi>pulling aside the Wizard’s curtain to reveal the farce of a
                utopian wish that has misguided her journey toward a future divorced from reality,
                the scene performs in political time the paradox of what in Act Two the empty throne
                in Demogorgon’s cave stages in metaphysical time: the effects of power are
                all-too-real, but power itself functions in a vacuum. At this point we realize what
                makes Prometheus’ desire to hear the curse repeated, only to refute its words, so
                potent (again, as Prometheus earlier notes, “how vain is talk”). This is to bring
                the two “contradictory features” of Frederic Jameson’s understanding of utopia into
                sharp relief as a potentiality at once embedded within yet separate from the very
                sociopolitical and historical reality that makes it possible. Prometheus invokes the
                words themselves not even to refute, but merely to dismiss their power as
                “unregarded now” (3.4.179) in order simultaneously to mark and to efface their
                potency. Put another way, because Prometheus refuses to memorize the curse, he
                signals instead another form of active listening to the sound of music and the music
                of sound.</p>
                
            <p>As Panthea enters bringing news of Prometheus’ transformation, Asia asks, apparently
                rhetorically, “hear I not / The Æolian music of her sea-green plumes / Winnowing the
                crimson dawn?” (2.1.25-27). The phrasing at once affirms and renders ambiguous the
                potentiality of sound, a hypostasis that may or may not transpire. In a seminal
                essay D. J. Hughes explored the poem’s potentiality as its means of “cleansing the
                ontological situation, restoring our sense of the potential, turning, through a
                series of verbal strategies, the actual back upon itself,” such that the “world at
                the end of the poem is a virtual one, with the seeds of decline checked, themselves
                remaining in potency.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> D. J. Hughes,
                    “Potentiality in <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound,</hi>” <hi
                        rend="italic">Studies in Romanticism </hi> 2.2 (Winter, 1963): 108.</note> We need to be
                skeptical of Hughes’ positivity, however. As Timothy Webb is careful to note,
                “[w]hether we enact and perpetuate a Promethean revolution depends on us; we have
                the opportunity to move in either direction.”<note place="foot"
                    resp="author"> Timothy Webb, “The Unascended Heaven: Negatives in<hi rend="italic"
                        >Prometheus Unbound,</hi>” in <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s Poetry and
                        Prose</hi>, 708.</note> Although Shelley partly intended his poem to
                complete the mythic arc of Aeschylus’ unfinished Promethean trilogy, in <hi
                    rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound </hi>Shelley leaves the myth incomplete in an
                “attempt[ ] to realize the potential of a tale<hi rend="italic">untold.</hi>”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Webb, 711.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Untelling and the untold resonate with the notion of the narrator’s “thoughts which
                must remain untold” in Shelley’s final poem (21). Again, that word “must” troubles
                us. Leaving something “untold” points to a deliberate self-suppression.
                Acknowledging “thoughts” to which the subject has no access is another matter. This
                is to confront us with modernity’s pursuit of the unthought, what is at once
                “exterior” and “indispensable to [man],” the “shadow cast by man as he emerged in
                the field of knowledge” and “the blind stain by which it is possible to know him” as
                we find ourselves “straining to catch its endless murmur.”<note 
                    place="foot" resp="author"> Michel Foucault,<hi rend="italic">The Order of Things</hi>:
                        <hi rend="italic">An Archaeology of the Human Sciences </hi>(New York:
                    Routledge, 2002), 356.</note> Like the unthought, Lacan describes “the real” as
                “what,” within the “the feeling of reality,” “resists symbolisation absolutely,” at
                which point we encounter “the pressing manifestation of an unreal, hallucinatory
                    reality.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Jacques Lacan,<hi
                        rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan: Book I, Freud’s Papers on
                        Technique, 1953-1954, </hi>ed. Jacques-Alain Miller, trans. John Forrester
                    (New York: W. W. Norton, 1991), 66, 67.</note> Rather differently for Foucault,
                however, the unthought constitutes “a certain mode of action,” the “perilous
                    act,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Foucault, 357.</note> of a
                possible “symbolisation.” We might say, then, that Prometheus, as the avatar of
                Shelley’s most difficult poem, figures the “perilous act” of listening for this
                “endless murmur.” But to listen is not necessarily to capture the meaning of what it
                hears. This would be, as Foucault says of “the phenomenological project,” to
                “resolve[ ] itself into a description . . . of actual experience, and into an
                ontology of the unthought that automatically short-circuits the primacy of the ‘I
                    think.’”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Foucault, 355.</note> To track
                the interminable process – murmur – of thought itself in the process of thinking the
                unthought, which is to unthink thought itself in the process of its formation, an
                unthinking that is, paradoxically, constitutive of thought and being in the first
                place. As Michele Speitz explores in Wordsworth’s verse, echoes and murmurs trade on
                “loss and rupture,” not as a counterpose to its restorative nature, but by
                “revealing . . . the epitaphic nature of sound itself.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Michele Speitz, “The Wordsworthian Acoustic Imagination,
                    Sonic Recursions, and ‘that dying murmur,’”<hi rend="italic">SEL</hi> 55.3
                    (Summer 2015): 621, 622.</note> As part of his poetry’s “acoustic imaginary,”
                they register within “poetry’s inexorably elegiac acoustic remains” its “promise of
                a sometimes vaguely discernible, sometimes illegible yet still audible collective
                foundation” and thus “draw out a recursive wave of the otherwise broken sonic life
                of the individuated living being.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Speitz,
                    622, 641, 642. Whereas Speitz is talking about the possibility of an
                    “individuated” Wordsworthian subject, I would argue that Shelley’s poem moves us
                    far beyond any sense of such individuation.</note> The sense of thought as
                thoughts themselves vanish “Remains” as the materiality of thought itself in the
                process of its manifestation. Or as Forest Pyle writes of what Jerrold Hogle calls
                Shelley’s process, “if an aesthetic experience makes us feel <hi rend="italic">as if
                </hi>we are gaining knowledge, then when the experience of a radical aestheticism
                ‘bursts’ upon us, it makes us feel as if we knew anything or, perhaps, <hi
                    rend="italic">anything else but this</hi>.”<note place="foot"
                    resp="author" > Forest Pyle,<hi rend="italic">Art’s Undoing: In the Wake of a Radical
                        Aestheticism</hi> (New York: Fordham University Press, 2014), 10. See
                    Jerrold E. Hogle, <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s Process: Radical Transference and
                        the Development of His Major Works </hi>(New York: Oxford University Press,
                    1988). Hogle reads the nomadic principle of Shelley's aesthetic as “a rootless
                    passage between different formations,” a “primordial, preconscious shift,
                    intimated in the movement of perception, feeling, and language, always already
                    becoming a different enactment of itself at another time and in conjunction with
                    other elements” (15). For Hogle, Shelley’s Prometheus represents “the
                    transitional and disruptive actions of the Titan in his previous [mythic]
                    forms,” which “shifts make him very nearly the activity of transference
                    incarnate” (172). In my reading sound both enacts and undoes this
                    process.</note> In this way listening signifies listening for what can never be
                heard as the constitutive act and moment of listening itself.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
            <head>IV.</head>
            <p>Asking if one can talk of a “<hi rend="italic">visual sound</hi>,” Nancy goes on tosay, “perhaps it is necessary that sense not be content to make sense (or to be <hi
                    rend="italic">logos</hi>), but that it wants also to resound.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Nancy, 3, 6.</note> He calls this the “corp
                sonore” as resonant and listening body “that includes, but is not limited to, the
                human body as matrix of resonance.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Janus,
                    191.</note> In this way listening is at once temporal – “embodied time” – and
                spatial – the <hi rend="italic">renvoi </hi>or “offering and returning of resonance
                sense as sonorous presence.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Janus, 193,
                    194.</note> Sound thus also has a materiality that emanates from, extends, and
                in turn affects bodies <hi rend="italic">as </hi>bodies of sound. Moreover, it
                evokes a self that manifests outside of “dichotomies traditionally associated with
                subjectivity: presence-absence, surface-depth. Rather, this self – as the space of
                the ‘corps sonore’ (sonorous or resonant body) through which and around which the
                    <hi rend="italic">renvoi </hi>of sense takes place – has to be described
                according to a qualitative continuum between diminuendo and crescendo, soft and
                hard, higher or lower frequencies, expansive and contracting volumes.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Janus, 194.</note> As Thomas Christensen
                notes, the term comes from Jean-Phillippe Rameau, eighteenth-century French composer
                and musical theorist: “The <hi rend="italic">corps sonore </hi>. . . was Rameau’s
                term for any vibrating system such as a vibrating string which emitted harmonic
                partials above its fundamental frequency.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Thomas Christensen, “Eighteenth-Century Science and the ‘Corps Sonore’: The
                    Scientific Background to Rameau’s ‘Principle of Harmony,”<hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Music Theory</hi> 31.1 (Spring 1987): 24.</note> This sonorous
                subject – really more of a resonant subjectivity – is also a “listening subject, if
                it is a subject at all,” that “tends to dissolve, to fuse with and absorb all those
                elements of self and world that might otherwise be termed ‘objects.’”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Janus, 194.</note> This listening subject at
                once emanates from and constitutes the warp and woof of sound, as when in Act Four
                the Chorus of Spirits and Hours move to “weave the web of the mystic measure”
                (4.129), such that the “Spirits of the human mind” are “wrapt in sweet sound’”
                (4.81-82). </p>
                
            <p>Nancy’s idea of resonance informs transactions of meaning in Shelley’s lyrical drama,
                which give equal priority to the visual and the auditory as forms of restraint and
                release, a way of visualizing sound that does not reify its meaning. Differentiating
                narrative from lyric in Romantic writing, Tilottama Rajan argues that the former
                evokes a “kind of mirror stage in which the [latter's] search for a unified
                self-representation is enacted and called into question,” “the displacement of the
                self into an objective world that will disclose it as other than itself.”<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> Rajan, “’The Web of Things,’” 87, 90.</note>
                Karen Weisman associates this de-idealized lyric utterance with transference, which
                is “never ‘what’ is heard [but] . . . <hi rend="italic">how</hi> hearing is
                    experienced.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Karen Weisman,
                    “Romanticism, Kant, and the Prehistory of Psychoanalysis,” Modern Language
                    Association Convention, Washington, DC (December 1996), 6.</note> Through this
                process both analyst and analysand are “seek[ing] to hear the fragments of
                [hearing’s] dispersed body.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Weisman,
                    8.</note> Here Weiskajn refers to Theodor Reik’s notion of ‘listening with a
                third ear,’ a way of thinking the unthought of ideology, of listening for both the
                oppressive and liberatory effects and potentiality of its deep resonance. Shelley’s
                “Sea profound of ever-spreading sound” thus figures a mode of critical listening,
                the mood of which is inherently revolutionary.<note place="foot"
                    resp="author"> Here I am indebted to Ryan Shuvera’s notion of listening to Indigenous
                    music as a form of conciliation rather than reconciliation, which presupposes
                    the return to some pre-existing harmony. Reconciliation entails the just state
                    as a kind of blank utopian notion that implicitly elides the situational and the
                    everyday and thus any<hi rend="italic">sense </hi>of social justice. Such a
                    utopia is distinctly at odds with the ‘sense of sound’ that makes the poem’s
                    final act such a powerfully resonant auditorium for political action. See Ryan
                    Shuvera, “Sounding Unsettlement: Rethinking Settler States of Mind and
                    Re(-)cognition through Scenes of Cross-Cultural Learning,” dissertation (London,
                    ON: Western University, 2020). See also Mark Rifkin, “Settler States of Feeling:
                    National Belonging and the Erasure of Native American Presence,” in <hi rend="italic">A Companion to American
                        Literary Studies</hi>, ed. Caroline F. Levander and Robert S. Levine
                    (Hoboken, NJ: Wiley Blackwell, 2011), 342-55.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Sound in Shelley’s poem seems to be merely the medium that carries the poem’s
                message. Yet at the same time it facilitates a mode of relationality that is the
                matrix of meaning itself without making meaning present. As such, sound insists on
                its own opacity, the “errantry” of “Totality’s imaginary [which] allows the detours
                that lead away from anything totalitarian.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                    Glissant, 18.</note> Like the work of feeling in <hi rend="italic">Prometheus
                    Unbound</hi>, as I have argued elsewhere,<note place="foot"
                    resp="author"> See Joel Faflak, “More than a Feeling:
                        Shelley’s Affect,” in <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and
                        Affect Studies</hi>, ed. Seth T. Reno, Romantic
                        Circles Praxis (May 2018), 23 pars.</note> sound is the elusive and
                ineluctable conduit of being in the poem. Its subjects remain unable to grasp its
                broader network because they exist in its midst as both its products and generators.
                Sound, like feeling, sustains the poem’s atmosphere as part of what I would call a
                global sonic ecology. This ecology indicates not just the transfer between subjects
                and the world, but the vibratory transference that is the very mode and matrix of
                their (co-)existence. Goodman notes that “<hi rend="italic">We do not yet know what
                    a sonic body can do.</hi>”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman,
                    191.</note> I wonder if Shelley does, as his <hi rend="italic">corp sonore
                </hi>is by no means <hi rend="italic">of </hi>sound mind or body, as in the
                ineffable pauses between the Maniac’s outbursts in <hi rend="italic">Julian and
                    Maddalo</hi>. Sound<hi rend="italic">ness </hi>is beside the point here,
                especially when it indicates<hi rend="italic"> </hi>the potential “colonization of
                inaudible frequencies by control.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Goodman,
                    191.</note> To riff in my own terms on Susan Wolfson’s essay for her editing of
                an earlier collection of essays on sound in Romantic poetry for this journal, the
                sound <hi rend="italic">of </hi>sound functions as its own vanishing mediator.<note
                     place="foot" resp="author"> See Susan J. Wolfson, “Sounding Romantic:
                    The Sound of Sound,”<hi rend="italic">‘Soundings of Things Done’: The Poetry and
                        Poetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear and Era</hi>, ed. Susan J. Wolfson. <hi
                        rend="italic">Romantic Circles Praxis</hi> (April 2008): 33 pars. </note> Or
                as Garret Stewart argues in his essay for the same collection, “Romantic poetry
                begins with a sigh,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Garrett Stewart,
                    “Phonemanography: Romantic to Victorian,”<hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles
                        Praxis</hi> (April 2008): par. 3.</note> the undertone or real of language
                as its latent possibility and, like Mladen Dolar’s account of the voice, the
                constitutive possibility of human sound that is at the same time incommensurable
                with the human itself. Perhaps this is why Demogorgon, implored by the Chorus of all
                voices in Act Four to “Speak” so that “thy strong words may never pass away”
                (4.553), warns us that words are only “spells by which to reassume / An empire o’er
                the disentangled Doom” (4.568-69), even as they sound and re-sound within the
                environment. As the echoes that carry Panthea and Asia to Demogorgon, “In the world
                unknown / Sleeps a voice unspoken” (2.1.190-91). Yet the sound of what remains
                unspoken <hi rend="italic">un</hi>nerves us. </p>
                
            <p>In an article for <hi rend="italic">New York Review of Books</hi> Fintan O’Toole
                notes the spirit of mourning and restoration that informed the 2020 Presidential
                race, in the Biden-Harris camp fueled by sorrow rather than anger over what has been
                lost since 2016, in the Trump-Pence camp by revisiting the nostalgia of 2016 when
                Trump (like Reagan before him) promised to return America to its former glory. In
                either case, as O’Toole rather trenchantly remarks, “the point of genuine mourning
                is that the thing you are grieving for cannot be restored. The grief is an
                acceptance that the loss is irreparable,” and so what is needed is a “hard, sad,
                relentless reckoning with the knowledge that much of what [America] has been should
                be allowed to die.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Fintan O’Toole, “Night
                    and Day,”<hi rend="italic">New York Review of Books</hi> (24 September
                    2020).</note> I take O’Toole’s Freudian primer on the psychology of our
                political moment as a reflection of Prometheus’ insistence on hearing his curse
                against Jupiter: he wants – needs – to know that it’s dead. In this case it’s not
                ocular proof, as Othello demands of Desdemona’s alleged adultery, not the verbal
                sign of the words themselves, but the sound of their rage. In this sense the curse
                itself dies, but the affective resonance that sustains its utterance doesn’t. It
                thus falls to that transformational, even transmogrifying process to carry
                Prometheus, Asia, and Co., indeed the entire cosmos, toward their collective future.
                If elections are waged and won by emotion, then we see in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Prometheus Unbound </hi>that sound literally as well as figuratively carries
                the day. The poem asks us to listen without prejudice, as if that is ever possible.
                For listening requires the implicit acknowledgement that we can never truly
                understand what we are listening for. I mean this in the sense of Glissant’s “right
                to opacity”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Glissant, 189.</note> against
                the illusions of transparency. So here's the rub: Shelley’s poem tells us how to
                listen, or at least <hi rend="italic">that </hi>we should listen, which makes of its
                fourth Act a staging of the act of listening itself, brought to a close only through
                the <hi rend="italic">deus ex machina </hi>of Demogorgon’s arrival. Beyond that,
                however, the poem doesn’t tell us what to listen <hi rend="italic">for</hi>.
                Confronted by the nothingness of sound from which meaning can or might or might not
                come, we are nonetheless compelled to speak again. Yet <hi rend="italic">what
                </hi>for? Or as I now imagine responding to my mother, “I hear you . . . I
                think.”</p>
            </div>
            </div>
        <div type="citation">
            <head>Works Cited</head>
            
            <bibl>Adorno, Theodor. “On the Fetish-Character in Music and the Regression of Listening.”
                    <hi rend="italic">The Essential Frankfurt School Reader</hi>. Ed. Andrew Arato
                and Eike Gebhardt. New York: Continuum, 1985. 270-99.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Attali, Jacques. <hi rend="italic">Noise: The Political Economy of Music</hi>. 1977.
                Trans. Brian Massumi. Minneapolis: Minnesota University Press, 1985.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Blake, William. <hi rend="italic">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake. </hi>Ed. David V.
                Erdman. Rev. ed. New York: Anchor, 1988. 33-45.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Brewster, David. <hi rend="italic">Letters on Natural Magic, Addressed to Sir Walter
                    Scott</hi>. London: John Murray, 1832.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Carlson, Julie. “Like love: The feel of Shelley’s similes.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romanticism and the Emotions</hi>. Ed. Joel Faflak and Richard C. Sha.
                Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014. 76-97.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Chalmers, David J. <hi rend="italic">The Conscious Mind: In Search of a Fundamental
                    Theory. </hi>Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1996.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Christensen, Thomas. “Eighteenth-Century Science and the ‘Corps Sonore’: The
                Scientific Background to Rameau’s ‘Principle of Harmony.” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                    of Music Theory</hi> 31.1 (Spring 1987): 23-50.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Chuh, Kandice. <hi rend="italic">The Difference Aesthetics Makes: On the Humanities
                    “After Man.” </hi>Durham, NC: Duke University Press, 2019.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Clark, Andy. <hi rend="italic">Supersizing the Mind: Embodiment, Action, and
                    Cognitive Extension</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Clark, David L. “Last Words: Voice, Gesture, and the Remains of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Frankenstein</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein in Theory</hi>. Ed. Orrin N.
                C. Wang. New York: Bloomsbury, 2020. 13-31.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Dolar, Mladen. <hi rend="italic">A Voice and Nothing More</hi>. Cambridge, MA: MIT
                biblress, 2006.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Faflak, Joel. “More than a Feeling: Shelley’s Affect.” <hi rend="italic">Romanticism
                    and Affect Studies</hi>. Ed. Seth T. Reno. Romantic Circles biblraxis. May 2018. 23
                biblars. <ref target="httbibls://romantic-circles.org/biblraxis/affect/biblraxis.2018.affect.faflak.html"
                >Romantic Circles</ref></bibl>
            
            <bibl>Foucault, Michel. <hi rend="italic">The Order of Things</hi>: <hi rend="italic">An
                    Archaeology of the Human Sciences. </hi>1966. New York: Routledge, 2002. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Glissant, Édouard. <hi rend="italic">bibloetics of Relation</hi>. Trans. Betsy Wing. Ann
                Arbor: University of Michigan biblress, 1997.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Goodman, Steve. <hi rend="italic">Sonic Warfare: Sound, Affect, and the Ecology of
                    Fear</hi>. Cambridge, MA: MIT biblress, 2010.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Hogle, Jerrold E. <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s biblrocess: Radical Transference and the
                    Develobiblment of His Major Works</hi>. New York: Oxford University biblress,
                1988.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Hutchins, Edwin. <hi rend="italic">Cognition in the Wild. </hi>Cambridge, MA: MIT
                biblress, 1995.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Hughes, D. J. “biblotentiality in <hi rend="italic">biblrometheus Unbound,</hi>” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Romanticism </hi> 2.2 (Winter, 1963): 107-126.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Jameson, Frederic. <hi rend="italic">Archaeologies of the Future: The Desire Called
                    Utobiblia and Other Science Fictions</hi>. New York: Verso, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl>Janus, Adrienne. “Listening: Jean-Luc Nancy and the ‘Anti-Ocular’ Turn in Continental
                biblhilosobiblhy and Critical Theory.” <hi rend="italic">Combiblarative Literature </hi>63:2
                (2018): 182-202. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Keach, William. <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s Style</hi>. London: Methuen, 1984.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Lacan, Jacques. <hi rend="italic">The Seminar of Jacques Lacan, Book XI: The Four
                    Fundamental Concebiblts of biblsychoanalysis. </hi>Ed. Jacques-Alain Miller. Trans.
                Alan Sheridan. New York: W. W. Norton, 1981.</bibl>
            
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">---. The Seminar of Jacques Lacan: Book I, Freud’s biblabiblers on
                    Technique, 1953-1954. </hi>Ed. Jacques-Alain Miller. Trans. John Forrester. New
                York: W. W. Norton, 1991.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Massumi, Brian. “The Future Birth of the Affective Fact: The biblolitical Ontology of
                Threat.” <hi rend="italic">The Affect Theory Reader</hi>. Ed. Melissa Gregg and
                Gregory J. Seigworth. Durham, NC: Duke University biblress, 2010. 52–70.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Michael, George. <hi rend="italic">Listen Without biblrejudice, Vol 1</hi>. Columbia
                Records, 1991. </bibl>
            
            <bibl>Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="italic">What Do biblictures Want? The Lives and Loves of
                    Images. </hi>Chicago: University of Chicago biblress, 2005.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Moten, Fred. <hi rend="italic">In the Break: The Aesthetics of the Black Radical
                    Tradition</hi>. Minneabiblolis: University of Minnesota biblress, 2003.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Nancy, Jean-Luc. <hi rend="italic">Listening</hi>. Trans. Charlotte Mandell. New
                York: Fordham University biblress, 2007.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>O’Malley, Glen. <hi rend="italic">Shelley and Synesthesia. </hi>Evanston, IL:
                Northwestern University biblress, 1964.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>O’Toole, Fintan. “Night and Day,” <hi rend="italic">New York Review of Books</hi> (24
                Sebibltember 2020) <ref  target="httbibls://www-nybooks-com.biblroxy1.lib.uwo.ca/articles/2020/09/24/joe-biden-election-night-day/">NYBooks</ref></bibl>
            
            <bibl>biblyle, Forest. <hi rend="italic">Art’s Undoing: In the Wake of a Radical
                    Aestheticism</hi>. New York: Fordham University biblress, 2014.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Rajan, Tilottama. <hi rend="italic">The Subiblbibllement of Reading: Figures of
                    Understanding in Romantic Theory and biblractice</hi>. Ithaca, NY: Cornell
                University biblress, 1990.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>---. “’The Web of Human Things’: Narrative and Identity in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Alastor</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">New Romanticisms: Theory and Critical
                    biblractice</hi>. Ed. David L. Clark and Donald C. Goellnicht. Toronto: University
                of Toronto biblress, 1994. 27-51.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Rifkin, Mark. “Settler States of Feeling: National Belonging and the Erasure of
                Native American biblresence.”<hi rend="italic">A
                    Combiblanion to American Literary Studies</hi>. Ed. Caroline
                F. Levander and Robert S. Levine. Hoboken, NJ: Wiley Blackwell, 2011. 342-55.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Shakesbibleare, William. <hi rend="italic">King Lear. </hi>Ed. Stanley Wells. Oxford
                World Classics. New York: Oxford Ubibl, 2000.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Shelley, biblercy Bysshe. <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s bibloetry and biblrose</hi>. 2<hi
                    rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. Ed. Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat. New York: W. W.
                Norton, 2002.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Shuvera, Ryan. “Sounding Unsettlement: Rethinking Settler States of Mind and
                Re(-)cognition through Scenes of Cross-Cultural Learning.” Dissertation. London, ON:
                Western University, 2020.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Sbibleitz, Michele. “The Wordsworthian Acoustic Imagination, Sonic Recursions, and ‘that
                dying murmur.’” <hi rend="italic">SEL</hi> 55.3 (Summer 2015): 621-46.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Sterne, Jonathan. “Sonic Imaginations.” <hi rend="italic">The Sound Studies
                    Reader</hi>. Ed. Jonathan Sterne. New York: Routledge, 2012. 1-17.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Stewart, Garrett. “biblhonemanograbiblhy: Romantic to Victorian.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romantic Circles biblraxis</hi>. Abiblril 2008. 69 biblars.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Washington, Chris. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Revelations: Visions of
                    biblost-Abiblocalybibltic Life and Hobible in the Anthrobiblocene</hi>. Toronto: University of
                Toronto biblress, 2019.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Wasserman, Earl. <hi rend="italic">Shelley: A Critical Reading</hi>. Baltimore: Johns
                Hobiblkins University biblress, 1971.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Webb, Timothy. “The Unascended Heaven: Negatives in <hi rend="italic">biblrometheus
                    Unbound</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s bibloetry and. biblrose,
                </hi>694-711.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Weisman, Karen. “Romanticism, Kant, and the biblrehistory of biblsychoanalysis.” Modern
                Language Association Convention. Washington, DC. December 1996.</bibl>
            <bibl>Wolfson, Susan J. “Introduction.” <hi rend="italic">‘Soundings of Things Done’: The
                    bibloetry and bibloetics of Sound in the Romantic Ear and Era</hi>. Ed. Susan J.
                Wolfson. <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles biblraxis</hi>. Abiblril 2008. 3 biblars. <ref
                    target="httbibls://romantic-circles.org/biblraxis/soundings/wolfson/wolfson_intro.html"
                >Romantic Circles</ref></bibl>
            
            <bibl>---. “Sounding Romantic: The Sound of Sound.” <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles
                    biblraxis</hi>. Abiblril 2008. 33 biblars. <ref
                    target="httbibls://romantic-circles.org/biblraxis/soundings/wolfson/wolfson.html"
                >Romantic Circles</ref></bibl>
            
            <bibl>Wordsworth, William. <hi rend="italic">bibloetical Works</hi>. Ed. Thomas Hutchinson.
                Rev. ed. Ernest de Selincourt. Oxford: Oxford University biblress, 1988.</bibl>
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
