<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1627</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2749</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1627" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1627" type="letter">
        <head>1627. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1809-05-11">11 May
                    1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Staunton upon Wye/ Hereford
                        <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery<lb />Unpublished. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I suspected that the great I. de Joanes<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Island de Joanes. Southey
                        was planning to publish a map with his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) and was using his books on South America
                        to check geographical accounts of the region.</note> in the mouth of the Maranham was made far too large in the maps, &amp;
                        Pimental<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Manoel Pimentel (1650&#8211;1719), <title>The Brazil Pilot; or, a Description of
                            the Coast of Brazil, Translated from the Portuguese of Manoel Pimentel &#8230; to which are added, Charts, of some of its most
                            Considerable Ports</title> (1809). This was no. 2331 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> confirms me
                    in this notion. This intimation I sent Arrowsmith<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aaron Arrowsmith (1750&#8211;1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>), cartographer of Soho Square, London, renowned for his 1790 large chart of the world. Among
                        Arrowsmith&#8217;s other productions were <title>A Map of America</title> (1804), which depicted North and South America. The second
                        volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1817) contained Arrowsmith&#8217;s <title>Map of Brazil and Paraguay with the
                            Adjoining Countries</title>.</note> together with a transcript of your paper. I suppose the main current of the river
                    turns the corner &amp; flows by Belem, for otherwise I do not see how the poor Friars whose adventure occasioned Teixeira&#8217;s
                    expedition could have reached that city, by abandoning themselves to the stream.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro
                        Teixeira (d. 1641) was a Portuguese explorer who became, in 1637, the first European to travel up the entire length of the
                        Amazon, an expedition which helped extend Portuguese colonial possessions there at the expense of Spain. Crist&#243;bal de Acu&#241;a
                        (1597&#8211;1676?), a member of Texeira&#8217;s expedition, published <title>Nuevo Descubrimiento del Gran R&#237;o de las Amazonas</title>
                        (1641).</note> Frightened &amp; in fact lost as they were, they must have been carried straight to the sea. &#8211; Aguirre&#8217;s
                        story<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey took from Antonio de Herrera y Tordesillas (1559&#8211;1625),
                            <title>Historia General del Mundo del Tiempo del Rey Felipe II, desde 1559 haste su Muerte</title> (1601&#8211;1612) the story
                        of the ill-fated Amazon expedition of exploration conducted by Pedro de Urs&#250;a (1526&#8211;1561) and Lope de Aguirre (c. 1510&#8211;1561).
                        However, he omitted it from his <title>History of Brazil</title> and instead published it in the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812) and then separately as <title>The Expedition of Orsua: and the Crimes of
                            Aguirre</title> (1821).</note> must be wholly omitted &amp; merely referred to in a single sentence. It is far too long to
                    be placed among the supplementary notes, &amp; the interest would be lost by any farther abbreviation, as I have already reduced
                    Pedro Simons<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Pedro Sim&#243;n (b. 1565), <title>Noticias Historiales de la Conquistas de
                            Tierra Firme en las Indias Occidentales, Primera Parte</title> (1626), no. 3787 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> narration one half at least. No account is given of the materials from which he wrote, &#8211; but Acosta<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jos&#233; de Acosta (1539&#8211;1600), a Spanish Jesuit missionary and naturalist who published
                            <title>Historia Natural y Moral de las Indias: Vida Religiosa y Civil de los Indios</title> (1590), no. 3220 in the sale
                        catalogue of his library.</note> says that a young man who was of the party became a Jesuit, &amp; had written the history of
                    what he saw, &#8211; to which history Acosta refers, &#8211; most probably <del>P Simons</del> this was P. Simons authority. I greatly regret
                    that this historian did not publish his second volume which would have comprised the conquest of the Nuevo Reyno, a most important
                    part of American history.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second part of Sim&#243;n&#8217;s history was not published until
                        1882&#8211;1892 by Medardo Rivas (1825&#8211;1901).</note> Bogota &amp; Tunju were little less civilized than Mexico &amp; Peru, yet
                    scarcely any notice is taken <del>of them</del> by later writers of them, nor of Yucatan, a country affording some very
                    extraordinary facts in the history of the progress of society. The priests in Yucatan had books of what kind Heaven knows, but
                    books they were &#8211; I suppose hieroglyphical: &amp; the arithmetic was by scores instead of tens, the only instance <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, who is very learned in these things has ever heard of.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had derived this information from Antonio de Herrera y Tordesillas (1559&#8211;1625), <title>Historia
                            General de las Indias Occidentales o de los hechos de los Castellanos en las Islas y Tierra firme del Mar Oceano</title>
                        (1728). Southey cites the passage from Herrera (4. 10. 4) in his <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (1810&#8211;1819), I, p.
                        638, giving the verdict of a &#8216;friend, better acquainted with such subjects than I am&#8217; (Rickman) that this is the earliest
                        example of &#8216;vigesimal numeration&#8217;.</note> You will see in my 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter that I have advanced, &amp;, it
                    seems to me, proved an opinion that men when once degenerated to savage have never been civilized by any other means than by a
                        priesthood.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Chapter 8 of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                            Brazil</title> (1810).</note> It is briefly stated to show why the Tupi tribes<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        An indigenous people of the Amazon.</note> were inferior to the Peruvians &amp;c. You will find the whole Chapter full of
                    curious matter, &amp; it shall be sent you with all the rest, as soon as the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is printed, &#8211; the next sheet
                    will compleat it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I forgot in my last list<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to the Herbert Hill, 2
                        May 1809, Letter 1624.</note> to include a Latin History of the Cid lately published (whether written or edited, I know not)
                    by Fr. Manuel Risco, the successor of Florez.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Enrique (or Henrique) Fl&#243;rez de Seti&#233;n y
                        Huidobro (1701&#8211;1773), a Spanish historian and author of <title>Espana Sagrada, Teatro Geografico-Historico de La Iglesia de
                            Espana</title>, a vast compilation of Spanish ecclesiastical history, of which twenty-nine volumes appeared in the
                        author&#8217;s lifetime. It was continued after his death by the Spanish historian Juan Manuel Mart&#237;nez Ugarte, known as Manuel
                        Risco (1755&#8211;1801), who published volumes 30&#8211;42 of this work. The Spanish version of Risco&#8217;s history of the Cid was published
                        as <title>La Castilla, y el mas famoso Castellano Discurso Sobre el Sitio, Nombre, Extension, Gobierno, y Condado de la
                            Antigua Castilla: Historia del Ce&#769;lebre Castellano Rodrigo Di&#769;az, Llamado Vulgarmente el Cid Campeador</title>. The
                        editors have not traced a Latin version.</note> The scarcer books in that list<del>s</del> were enumerated on a supposition
                    that the French would have thrown them into the market &#8211; the rubbish, bad as it is, will be of use, &#8211; there is no building without
                    it. It is always among rubbish that one makes discoveries. In the second Quarterly there will be a sketch of Portugueze
                        literature,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed <title>Extractos em Portuguez e em Inglez; com as
                            Palavras Portuguezas Propriamente Accentuadas, para Facilitar o Estudo d&#8217;Aquella Lingoa</title> (1808) in the
                            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (May, 1809), 268&#8211;292.</note> which <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">the
                        Editor</ref> requested of me. I shall get <del>X</del> about sixteen pounds for it, &#8211; which is <del>xxxx</del> as much again
                    as it would have brought in any other shape. &#8211; &amp; it is so mere a sketch as to forestall nothing. You will there detect my
                    ignorance of Gil Vincente,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese playwright and poet, Gil Vicente (c.1470-c.
                        1536), who produced many comedies and farces including <title>Auto da &#205;ndia</title> (1509) and <title>Farsa de In&#234;s
                            Pereira</title> (1523). Their rarity in print was caused by their suppression by the Inquisition.</note> &#8211; an author whom
                    I consider as my greatest desideratum.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere&#8217;s</ref> conduct suprizes me, &amp; I would fain persuade myself that you have
                    been misinformed, &#8211; That Mr Glasse<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Henry Glasse (1761&#8211;1809;
                        <title>DNB</title>), clergyman friend of <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s</ref> who lived
                        near Acton. Glasse, known for his short, tubby, stature, was an author and contributor to the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s
                            Magazine</title>.</note> who has a fancy for the Deanery of Hereford called upon me last year, &amp; left such a stink of
                    rose-pomatum behind him, that all my windows were thrown open for the rest of the day to purify the room. My account of him to
                        <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> in whose name he had introduced himself, was &#8211; that he was
                    aptly named Glasse, &#8211; inasmuch as you could see thro him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish to read every thing respecting Vieyra<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Jesuit missionary,
                        diplomat and preacher Antonio Vieira (1608&#8211;1697).</note> as soon as possible tho it will be better not to touch upon his
                    literary &amp; religious character in the present work. That belongs more properly to the European history. The second volume will
                    not cost me so much time as the first, for my printed authorities will speedily be reduced to R Pitta<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sebasti&#227;o da Rocha Pita (1660&#8211;1738), <title>Historia da America Portugeza, desde o anno 1500 ate o de
                            1724</title> (1730).</note> &amp; Berredo,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Bernardo Pereira de Berredo e
                        Castro (d. 1748), governor of Maranh&#227;o 1718&#8211;1722, author of <title>Annaes Historicos do Estado do Maranha&#333; de sey
                            Descivrunebtim, at&#232; 1718</title> (1749).</note> &#8211; but the first volume cannot wait for it without great loss. Arrowsmith I
                    suppose is at work upon the map. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Capt Burney</ref> will look to this, both excellent map-makers, &amp; the former taking as much interest in my work as if it
                    were his own.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>  has had no return of the disease, &amp; is no longer the little
                    Lazarus that the blister left him. His tongue however indicates fever in the morning, &amp; he is very pale &#8211; probably from the
                    violent bleeding which was necessary. We thank <ref target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> H</ref>. for her enquiries. Except this uneasiness, &#8211; which I trust will soon pass away, we are going on well.</p>
        <closer rend="indent1"> RS.</closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent2">
            <date when="1809-05-11"> May 11. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>