<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1718</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2840</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from William Knight (ed.),
                            Memorials of Coleorton, 2 vols (London, 1887).  Previously  published: William Knight (ed.),
                            Memorials of Coleorton: Being letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his sister, Southey, and Sir Walter Scott to
                            Sir George and Lady Beaumont of Coleorton, Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp.
                        86&#8211;89.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1718" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1718" type="letter">
        <head>1718. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref>, <date when="1809-12-01">1
                    December 1809</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from William Knight (ed.),
                            <title>Memorials of Coleorton</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887)<lb />Previously published: William Knight (ed.),
                            <title>Memorials of Coleorton: Being letters from Coleridge, Wordsworth and his sister, Southey, and Sir Walter Scott to
                            Sir George and Lady Beaumont of Coleorton, Leicestershire, 1803 to 1834</title>, 2 vols (London, 1887), II, pp.
                        86&#8211;89.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-12-01">Dec. 1, 1809</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am much obliged by your letter, and no otherwise sorry that your application to Lord Mulgrave<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of Mulgrave (1755&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>): First Lord of the
                        Admiralty from 1807, diplomatist and politician.</note> has been deferred than because of the circumstance which occasions the
                    delay. <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lady Mulgrave was in ill health; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 25 November
                        1809, Letter 1713.</note> On other accounts it is rather convenient that it should have been delayed, inasmuch as my brother
                    stands in a somewhat different situation. Admiral Sotheby<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby
                        (1759&#8211;1831), younger brother of the author, William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), who was Southey&#8217;s
                        acquaintance.</note> has made him Acting Commander in the Lyra brig;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Lyra</hi> was a Royal Navy Cherokee class 10-gun brig-sloop, launched in August 1808.</note> the object
                    therefore at present is to solicit a confirmation of that appointment. This I believe it is the custom of the Admiralty not to
                    grant, for the sake of preserving the patronage to itself; but if any interest can be made for an officer holding such conditional
                    rank, they take an early opportunity of promoting him, though he is set aside at first. I have therefore good hope that your kind
                    interference will be successful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has so pleasantly confuted my expectations concerning <title>The
                        Friend</title>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s periodical, <title>The Friend</title>, was published in
                        26 instalments from 1 June 1809 to 15 March 1810.</note> that I begin to look confidently forward to a continuance of his
                    exertions. He seems to be taking the advice of all his friends, and putting the reader in better humour. I hope that dreadful
                    story in the thirteenth number is not true,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The thirteenth number was dated 16 November
                        1809 and included the story of Maria Eleonora Schoning, which Coleridge claimed to have read on his visit to Germany in 1798.
                        See Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <title>The Friend; A Literary, Moral, and Political Weekly Paper</title> (London, 1809), pp.
                        194&#8211;208. See S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, pp.
                        172&#8211;183.</note> and have almost convinced myself that it is not. I remember, however, to have read of a religious madness
                    which prevailed in Denmark (I think), and not above half a century ago, precisely similar to the case in question. A set of
                    fanatics had persuaded themselves that the best way to ensure their own salvation was by committing murder, in order that they
                    might suffer death and die in a state of repentance; and they preferred children for their victims on account of their innocence.
                    It was only put a stop to by condemning them to perpetual imprisonment. I cannot recollect where I met with this fact, it is so
                    many years ago, but of it I have a full and perfect recollection; it is probably to be found in one of the earliest &#8216;Annual
                        Registers&#8217;.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The story of this sect is given in the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; in the
                            <title>Annual Register for the Year 1767</title> (1768), 164.</note> It seems to me that upon this foundation some German
                        <hi rend="ital">horrorist</hi> has made up Coleridge&#8217;s story, for however monstrous the defects of law and justice in any part
                    of Europe, it is scarcely possible that execution under such circumstances could have been ordered. Coleridge has related the
                    story very finely, but the description of Maria&#8217;s voice and countenance is too beautiful for its place; it is too much like
                    poetry. We should beware of mingling fancy with the narration of what we believe to be truth, &#8211; I mean to say of weaving it into,
                    and making it part of, the story. However true the circumstances, an air of fiction is thrown over them whenever this is done.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My poem is finished, and in course of correction and transcription for the press.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> I am on the point of beginning another upon Pelayo, the
                    father of the Spanish kings, &#8211; a subject long since chosen, but made especially interesting to me now from its applicability to
                    the existing state of Spain.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was published as <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                            Goths</title> in 1814.</note> My hope, or rather my faith, of the ultimate success of the Spaniards continues unshaken and
                    unabated, notwithstanding the imbecility of the Junta<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Junta&#8217;s unwillingness to
                        organise supplies for the British Army while urging a policy of attack led several people, including Southey, to suspect some
                        of their members of co-operating with the French.</note> (to give it no harsher name) and the miserable manner in which the
                    strength of this country has been wasted. That army which was sent to rot in the cursed islands of Walcheren<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Walcheren expedition was an unsuccessful British attempt to open another front in the
                        Netherlands in support of the Austrian Empire&#8217;s struggle with France. Approximately 40,000 soldiers with supporting horses and
                        artillery landed at Walcheren on 30 July 1809. There was little fighting but the army sustained heavy losses from sickness,
                        and in December 1809 withdrew.</note> might have exterminated every Frenchman in the Peninsula, and have given a mortal wound
                    to the Buonapartes. Even now this might be done, but I confess myself quite hopeless that anything great will be effected by the
                    present set of Ministers, or by any who are likely to supplant them. The people of England will always save themselves, even
                    though Buonaparte could bridge the Channel; but their rulers will never deliver Europe. I groan in bitterness of spirit at the
                    thought how surely and certainly it might be delivered if Peterborough<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles
                        Mordaunt, 3rd Earl of Peterborough and 1st Earl of Monmouth (1658?&#8211;1735; <title>DNB</title>), renowned for his daring tactics
                        during a British invasion of Spain in 1705.</note> or Wolfe<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Wolfe
                        (1727&#8211;1759; <title>DNB</title>), responsible for the decisive victory in 1759 that led to the British conquest of
                        Quebec.</note> or Chatham<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Pitt, 1st Earl of Chatham (1708&#8211;1778;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the minister whose policies were credited with bringing victories during the Seven Years&#8217; War.</note>
                    were among us!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our ladies<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The three sisters, <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> join with me in respects to <ref target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMary">Lady Beaumont</ref>. &#8211; Believe me, my dear Sir, very respectfully and truly yours,</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>