<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1699</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2821</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Mary Stuart (ed.), Letters from the Lake Poets, Samuel Taylor
                            Coleridge, William Wordsworth, Robert Southey, to Daniel Stuart (London, 1889), 400&#8211;404. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1699" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1699" type="letter">
        <head>1699. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Daniel Stuart</ref>, <date when="1809-10-22">22 October
                        1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Daniel Stuart Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ <del>Lilac&#8217;s
                            Boarding House</del>/ Cheltenham<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Southey October/ 1809/ Spain/ Friend<lb />MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 34046<lb />Previously published: Mary Stuart (ed.), <title>Letters from the Lake Poets, Samuel Taylor
                            Coleridge, William Wordsworth, Robert Southey, to Daniel Stuart</title> (London, 1889), 400&#8211;404. </p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-10-22">Oct. 22. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very much obliged to you for your letter. Were you near enough, there is no person living to whom I could
                    apply for advice in this undertaking with so much confidence, nor to whom I should so willingly submit my manuscript for
                        correction.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey is referring to his work for the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register</title> to which he contributed the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; for 1808&#8211;1810.</note> You will perceive that with respect
                    to the two last ministries, &amp; indeed to the whole conduct of the war, my opinions perfectly coincide with yours. &#8211; &amp; upon
                    those points on which we differ, I have expressed myself less positively, &amp; indeed almost with hesitation, in deference to
                    your judgement. <del>which</del> That letter of X. Y. is a memorable instance of political foresight:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stuart had authored several letters on the Peninsular war in the <title>Courier</title> in 1808. These took
                        issue with the negotiations and peace arguments of the Whigs and radicals. See the <title>Courier</title>, 8, 9, 26, 29
                        November (&#8216;The Campaign in Spain&#8217;); 14, 15, 16 November (&#8216;The Court of Inquiry&#8217;); 1 December (&#8216;The Apstoacy of Don Cevallos&#8217;),
                        2 December (&#8216;Apostacy of the <title>Edinburgh</title>&#8217;), and 22 December (&#8216;Spain and Revolutions&#8217;). <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> also praised these articles and responded to them with his own
                        &#8216;Letters on the Spaniards&#8217; in the <title>Courier</title> of 7, 8, 9, 15, 20, 21, 22 December 1809 and 20 January 1810. See S.
                        T. Coleridge, <title>Essays on his Times</title>, ed. David V. Erdman, 3 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1978), II, 41 and
                        44&#8211;100.</note> &#8211; I recollect it well, &amp; am sorry it is not preserved, &#8211; but the papers are consumed at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref>, &#8211; a sort of act which I have always regretted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Count de Norona who distinguished himself in Romanas army &amp; is now commanding at Coru&#241;a, published two
                    volumes of poems which I reviewed for the Critical either in 1802 or 1803.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gaspar Maria de
                        la Nava Alvarez, Conde de Norona (1760&#8211;1815), <title>Poesias</title> (1799&#8211;1800). Southey&#8217;s review appeared in <title>Critical
                            Review</title>, 36 (1802), Appendix, 538&#8211;549.</note> They are of considerable merit, &#8211; &amp; that review or a portion of
                    it, might be read with interest at present, when you want something to fill up your columns in the Courier. There is a translated
                    extract &lt;given&gt; from a mock-heroic poem which is curious as it shows his opinion of Courts, &#8211; formed no doubt from the state
                    of his own. A messenger is sent to seek for Care, &amp; according to the old notion of the moralists, goes to seek for him in
                        <del>the</del> a Palace, &#8211; but when he comes there he finds Indolence in his stead.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Norona&#8217;s mock heroic poem &#8216;La Quicayda&#8217;, extracts of which are included on pages 544&#8211;547 of Southey&#8217;s review.</note> The
                    satire is new &amp; very elegantly executed. I think if it were brought before the public now, it would place the character of the
                    nobleman very high in their esteem. The article is in one of the Appendixes &amp; you may if you think proper mention me as the
                    reputed writer of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had no conception that it could be so difficult to procure a file of papers only one year old, as it has proved
                    to be. It is a pity they should so very generally be destroyed, &amp; if they were printed in <ref target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref> form, <del>they</del> it would not be the case.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Cobbett&#8217;s weekly paper the <title>Political Register</title> which printed transcriptions of
                        parliamentary debates.</note> After a six weeks search the Star<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Star</title> was an evening daily newspaper, which began publication in 1788 under the editorship of Peter Stuart
                        (c.1760-c.1812; <title>DNB</title>).</note> has been procured for me, &#8211; &amp; the Times is &lt;now&gt; regularly sent me for
                    filing. I shall take as much time as possible, &#8211; that is to say I will not slight the work by hurrying it, &#8211; part of it I am
                    conscious cannot be done well, that is, what relates to financial &amp; commercial questions, &#8211; <del>but</del> all I can do is to
                    explain things perspicuously as far as I comprehend them &amp; pretend to nothing more. The history of Spanish affairs I shall do
                    perhaps &lt;better&gt; than any other person, bringing with me some peculiar knowledge, &amp; certainly a right spirit. For any
                        <del>things</del> &lt;hints&gt; that you can give me relating to the last or present year, &#8211; or of things as they are passing,
                    believe me I should be very thankful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Last years tragedy is about to be re-acted in Spain, &#8211; yet what great things might be done by a floating force even
                    now, ready to land wherever opportunity invited or need required them. Such a force would long ere this have cut to pieces the
                    besieging army before Gerona.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish city of Gerona had been under siege by the
                        French since 6 May 1809. After nearly seven months it finally fell on 11 December 1809.</note> That poor city will fall, after
                    the most heroic defence of modern times, but it is our fault if we do not practically assist those places which are accessible by
                    sea, whenever their hour of danger comes, &amp; there is a long line of such important posts between Barcelona &amp; Cadiz, every
                    one of which Ld Cochrane<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860;
                            <title>DNB</title>), naval officer and formerly Tom Southey&#8217;s captain. Cochrane gained renown through a campaign of daring
                        and brilliantly executed raids harassing and attacking settlements on the Spanish and French coasts.</note> or Sir Sidney
                        Smith<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The naval officer Sir William Sidney Smith (1764&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), who
                        was promoted to the rank of Admiral and received several awards for his actions in the war with France, achieving a high
                        popular reputation by 1809.</note> might render another Acre.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> In March 1799 the
                        Middle East city of Acre was besieged by the French, but a British naval flotilla under the command of Admiral Sidney Smith
                        assisted its Ottoman defenders and the siege was raised in May with Napoleon&#8217;s retreat back into Egypt. The defence of Acre
                        made Smith&#8217;s name and in September 1799 he received the thanks of both British houses of parliament for his actions.</note> I
                    do not despair of Spain, I never have despaired of it. I said both privately &amp; to the public that this spirit existed in the
                    country, when scarcely any person believed me, &amp; no symptoms had appeared, &amp; it is my firm belief that that spirit is not
                    to be subdued, tho Buonaparte may &amp; probably will overrun the country, &amp; for a time keep it down. There has been great
                    imbecillity in their Juntas and some treachery:<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Juntas unwillingness to organise
                        supplies for the British Army while urging a policy of attack led several people, including Southey, to suspect some of their
                        members of co-operating with the French.</note> &#8211; both were to be expected. The Cortes<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Cortes Generales (or &#8216;General Courts&#8217;) is the legislature of Spain.</note> would be the best remedy, &amp; the same
                    system of Deputies with the armies, armed with full power from the Cortes, which the French adopted with such success &#8211; in their
                    most perilous times. Have you seen the reviewal of Moores book in the last Quarterly?
                    &#8211; I offered to undertake it, but it was done by <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">G. Ellis</ref>, &amp; the concluding five
                    pages by <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The review by George
                        Ellis and George Canning of James Moore, <title>A Narrative of the Campaign of the British Army in Spain, Commanded by His
                            Excellency Lt. General Sir John Moore, K. B. &amp;c. authenticated by Official Papers and Original Letters</title>; <title>A few Remarks explanatory of the Motives which guided the Operations of the British Army, during the late
                            short Campaign in Spain; Observations on the Movements of the British Army in Spain, in Reply to the Statement lately
                            published by Brig. General Clinton.</title> By a British Officer; <title>Letters from Portugal and Spain &amp;c.</title>
                        By an Officer; James Wilmot Ormsby (d. 1831), <title>An Account of the Operations of the British Army &amp;c</title>; Adam Neale (1778?-1832),
                            <title>Letters from Portugal and Spain: Comprising an Account of the Operations of the Armies under their Excellencies Sir
                            Arthur Wellesley and Sir John Moore</title> (1809). Possibly Robert Ker Porter (1777&#8211;1842), <title>Letters from Portugal
                            and Spain: Written During the March of the British Troops under Sir John Moore. By an Officer</title> (1809), 203&#8211;234.</note> It is not his fault that we have so grievously mismanaged in Spain. He would have
                    done every thing, &#8211; but the arrangements in the Cabinet were made by compromises &amp; [MS torn]ssions, &#8211; &amp; the consequences
                    could not but be disgraceful &amp; ruinous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was in hopes you meant to have prest the necessity of a Court Martial upon Ld Chatham,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pitt, 2nd Earl of Chatham (1756&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), army officer and younger brother of the former
                        prime minister William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>) whose role in the ill-fated Walcheren expedition of 1809 was
                        criticised.</note> &#8211; it is only by means of the newspapers that any good can be done, from Parliament nothing is to be
                    expected in any other way than by making the public feeling act upon them thus, &amp; when the Courier goes against the Ministry,
                    it carries with it more weight than all the regular papers of opposition. Heaven help this poor country! with a power which even
                    now if <del>xxx</del> wielded with only common wisdom might change the <del>dir</del> fortune of <del>this</del> Europe &amp; the
                    World, &#8211; we experience nothing, &amp; can look for nothing but disgrace after disgrace, &amp; disaster after disaster. If we
                    balloted the whole <del>xxx</del> Empire for a Ministry the chance is that we should have a better &amp; could not have a worse,
                    than any which could at this time be formed from any party &#8211; or from all. &#8211; I see two circumstances of considerable danger, &#8211; one
                    is that any ministry will make peace for the sake of a momentary popularity; &#8211; the other that these cursed Congreve arrows will be
                    employed against our ships.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Rockets developed by Sir William Congreve, 2nd Baronet (1772
                        -1828; <title>DNB</title>) in 1804 and used to bombard Copenhagen in 1807.</note> You see the French have analysed them &#8211;
                    indeed such compositions cannot possibly long be kept secret in the present state of chemistry. When <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Mr Grenville</ref> was at the Admiralty &amp; they were first talked of, I prest this
                    danger earnestly upon my friend <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Williams Wynn</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is it too late to point out the importance of a floating force off the coast of Spain? A few such sieges as
                        Zaragoza<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> In December 1808 the Spanish town of Zaragoza was besieged (for the second
                        time that year) by the French. The siege involved ferocious street fighting, in which Spanish civilians took part. When the
                        French finally succeeded in February, 54000 people had died. For Southey&#8217;s
                        accounts see: <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 306&#8211;321; and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                            1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 508&#8211;527.</note> would waste even Buonapartes armies, &#8211; &amp; there are many other along the
                    coast which may be expected to make the same resistance, &#8211; especially if our ships were at hand to remove the <del>xxxxxx
                        xxxxx</del> &lt;women &amp; children&gt; &amp; lend assistance. <del>xxxxxx in</del> Even yet we may win the game if we play
                    it well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The last delay of the Friend was owing to a ridiculous cause. &#8211; the Rats eat up the motto at the Printers. <note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge&#8217;s periodical, <title>The Friend</title>, was published in 26 instalments from 1
                        June 1809 to 15 March 1810. The motto, from Richard Hooker (1554&#8211;1600; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Of the Lawes of
                            Ecclesiastical Politie</title> (1593&#8211;1662), appeared at the start of the ninth number dated 12 October 1809. See
                        Coleridge, <title>The Friend; A Literary, Moral, and Political Weekly Paper</title> (London, 1809), p. 129. The text is given
                        in S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and Princeton NJ, 1969), II, p.
                        122.</note> A few such numbers as the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> would win readers to it.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dated 5 October 1809, and dealing with ghosts, visions and illusions, and giving a biographical sketch of Luther. See Coleridge, <title>The Friend; A Literary, Moral, and Political Weekly Paper</title> (London,
                        1809), pp. 113&#8211;128. The text is given in S. T. Coleridge, <title>The Friend</title>, ed. Barbara E. Rooke, 2 vols (London and
                        Princeton NJ, 1969), II, pp. 110&#8211;121.</note> I am surprized a the regularity with which it has gone on, &amp; expect as well
                    as hope that it will continue.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>