<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1375</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2497</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The
                        Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 247&#8211;251..  Previously 
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 23&#8211;26.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1375" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1375" type="letter">
        <head>1375. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1807-10-26">26 October
                        1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Congreve/ Penkridge/
                        Staffordshire<lb />Postmark: [partial] KESWICK<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The
                        Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 247&#8211;251.<lb />Previously
                        published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), II,
                        pp. 23&#8211;26.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will not be very long before I shall be able to tell you something about my winter operations. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My uncle</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> were to
                    take flight from Lisbon on the 12th of this month; they will probably come in a Liverpool ship as they talk of seeing me soon, &#8211;
                    but this is only a guess. If my uncle could get a passage in a Kings ship as one of his majestys servants he meant to prefer it:
                    in that case he would come to Plymouth or Portsmouth, &amp; it would be more likely that I should meet him in London than that he
                    should come here during the winter. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> wishes me to come before Xmas, &#8211; I can do
                    my reviewing in time &amp; shall do it to be ready for any call. My movements will be in a very zig-zag line. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> wants me to stop at <ref target="places.html#Wynnstay">Wynnstay</ref> &#8211; how can
                    I cross from Shrewsbury over to your part of the world? This evening has brought me a letter from Litchfield,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Anna Seward, 25 October 1807 (letter 1376).</note> &amp; I am bound to make a
                    visit there. <ref target="people.html#SewardAnna">She</ref> is really a very staunch friend. Fellowes<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Fellowes (1771&#8211;1847), editor of <title>The Critical Review</title> from 1807&#8211;1814.</note> having become
                    joint editor of The Critical Review besought her to give him an article; to serve him she reviewed the poem of <ref target="people.html#HoggJamesEttrick">Hogg</ref> the Ettrick Shepherd,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Seward&#8217;s review
                        of James Hogg, <title>The Mountain Bard</title> appeared in <title>The Critical Review</title>, 13 (November, 1807), 237&#8211;244.
                        She criticized Southey severely for the historical inaccuracies in <title>Madoc</title>, but her praise was omitted from the
                        published article.</note> &amp; Heaven knows how, lugged in Madoc by neck and shoulders. Poor Fellowes petitioned that this
                    may be left out, in compassion to the Review, which had abused Madoc by bell book &amp; candle, &amp; must not, he says, throw off
                    all consistency at once. but he promises great civility to all my future works, &#8211; &amp; this it is likely they will meet with,
                    thro this interest. Pretty work this reviewing Senhora, I am abused because one reviewer hates <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> This was Charles Valentine
                        Le Grice (1773&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>) whose negative review of <title>Madoc</title> appeared in the <title>Critical
                            Review</title> ns 7 (1806), 72&#8211;83.</note> &amp; now am to be praised because another is a friend of Miss Sewards! &#8211; She
                    however is a good friend of mine, &amp; I am very much obliged to her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The books shall be sent you forthwith. Palmerin<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Palmerin of England; by Francisco de Moraes. Corrected by Robert Southey from the Original Portugueze</title>
                        (1807).</note> was advertised yesterday for the first time as published. &#8211; In the Athenaeum for September is a letter pointing
                    out a (real) blunder of the translator of D Manuel<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella, the
                        putative author of Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title>
                        (1807).</note> in one of his notes, written by some body who admires the book &amp; believes in its authenticity.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A letter in the September issue of the <title>Athen&#230;um</title>, 2 (1807), 242&#8211;243, corrected a
                        mistake in <title>Letters from England</title> concerning the use of the <title>Apocrypha</title> in English churches. A reply
                        appeared in the November issue (2, 555).</note> The <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Count</ref> who took his departure
                    on Sunday morning told John Fisher on his way out of town that I had a book in which his lodgings were mentioned, &amp; Aggy
                        Fisher<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> A mistake by Southey. Aggie Fisher was the wife, not the sister, of John
                        Fisher, a neighbour of <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> who had lived at Skyeside, Townend,
                        Grasmere. She died in April 1804. John&#8217;s sister, who lived with him as his housekeeper, was Molly, formerly a servant of the
                        Wordsworths. Where they lived in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is not known. Espriella stops at a cottage
                        near <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref>, and describes the making of oat bread, on the Saturday of his Lake
                        tour journal in <title>Letters from England</title>, letter 41.</note> his sister has been here today begging to see it, which
                    as his <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Sawneyship</ref> kept Espriella for the last two months at his lodgings, &amp; left
                    it there after all to be brought home when the man of the house pleases to bring it, we could not lend her. She imputes it to &#8211;
                    guess whom? &#8211; to a Turk, who, she says, lodged there once. &amp; I assure you she is expecting it with as much anxiety, as a Lady
                    of fashion looks for the description of her first court-dress in the newspaper. Were you gone before <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">Koster</ref> wrote a criticism upon this book to me, not suspecting me to be the author, but hinting to me to take the hint, invite an Italian to travel with me,
                    &amp; supply the deficiencies in D Manuel?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Peachys</ref> were gone a day before your letter arrived. <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">She</ref> desired she might stand to the unborn,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Peachey&#8217;s wife Emma became the godmother of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma Southey</ref> (b. 9 February
                        1808).</note> &#8211; a thing which I should have asked had it not been for that fear which year after year I feel at seeing her
                    depart, that she never possibly can live to return, &#8211; &amp; for which there is more cause every year than the last. There is a
                    sweetness in that womans nature which is worth all other endowments whatsoever. that sweet Island<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Derwent Island, in Derwentwater.</note> of hers always makes me melancholy when I look at it after she is
                    gone. &#8211; seven years ago I should have said so in half-a score poems, but I am now as practical a suppressor of all such
                    indulgencies of feeling as if I were a Quaker in form as well as in fact. &#8211; If the unborn be of the <hi rend="ital">weaker</hi>
                    sex her name will of course be Emma, &#8211; if he be one of the Lords of the Creation I shall name him Danvers, after the man whom I
                    suppose if it were possible to sum up such things I should be found to love best of all my friends.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, who Southey knew from childhood.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The books from London will not arrive this year.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Having decided to stay at
                            <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>, Southey had sent for his books and other belongings which were
                        scattered between friends in London and the West Country.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is in the country &amp; will not return to town till December, &#8211; of course as
                    he expects me soon, &amp; moreover as that would be a bad season for their removal, he will let them stay. &#8211; If my pension has any
                    effect upon my politics it is to make me a greater grumbler than before. I have received as yet only one quarter, &amp; that was
                    one early in April. Out of the 50 they modestly deducted 38 for fees &amp;c. Two quarters more are due, &amp; a third running on.
                    This irregularity of payment is very inconvenient to a man who has no other certain income to look to, &#8211; &amp; who has the happy
                    art of getting worse paid for every thing that he does than any living Brother of the Grey-goose quill. &#8211; The Buenos Ayres
                    business makes a pretty concluding chapter for me!! &#8211; I regard it as a good thing, were it not for the disgraceful way in which it
                    has been done. It was to be hoped that some stigma will be fixed upon Whitelocke &amp; Crawford<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir John Whitelocke (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), commander of the disastrous British attack on Buenos
                        Aires in July 1807; Brigadier-General Robert Crauford (1764&#8211;1812), participated in the failed attack.</note> But bad as this
                    is it is nothing to the everlasting &amp; ineffaceable infamy of bombarding Copenhagen.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        The English fleet had bombarded Copenhagen from 2&#8211;7 September 1807, Denmark being neutral at the time.</note> You know how
                    little I have ever feared the power of France &amp; what my feelings have been concerning invasion. They are changed since this
                    atrocious business: my faith was in God &amp; in a good cause, as much as in our human power; &#8211; but now that we have laid that
                    aside, &#8211; that we have foregone the vantage ground on which we stood, put ourselves on a level with Bonaparte, &amp; voluntarily
                    chosen to fight him with his own weapons of cruelty &amp; tyranny &amp; injustice; &#8211; in as much as I believe in God&#8217;s retributive
                    justice, do I fear for what may be the fate of this country. The curse of man is upon us, &amp; when that is the case &#8211; the curse
                    of God sooner or later follows. God help us that the main principle, the foundation &amp; mainspring of all public &amp; all
                    private morality, should still openly be set at defiance &amp; laughed to scorn! &#8211; &amp; that such miserable trash as <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Count Burnetski</ref> used to vent from a brain half filled with French morality picked up
                    in Poland &#8211; should be the creed of our ministry &#8211; &amp; our nation also! Woe be to the nation &amp; to the individual who believes
                    that any thing which is wrong can ever be expedient.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Thank you for the gold leaf<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> For tooling and lettering the bindings of Southey&#8217;s
                            books.</note> but not for the blank inclosure.</p>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-10-26">Monday Oct. 26. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>