<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1540</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2662</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30927.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 192&#8211;195 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1540" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1540" type="letter">
        <head>1540. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1808-11-22">22 November
                        1808</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/ H. M. S. Dreadnought/ Plymouth
                        Dock/ Single <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30927<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                        Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 192&#8211;195 [in
                        part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1808-11-22">Nov. 22. 1808.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not quite sure which deserves the severest carts-tailing, you or your Admiral,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tom&#8217;s ship HMS <hi rend="ital">Dreadnought</hi> was now under the command of Rear Admiral Thomas Sotheby
                        (1759&#8211;1831), younger brother of the author, William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s acquaintance.</note>
                    you for what you say of <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Freres</ref> translation, he for what he says of mine.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> A reference to Southey&#8217;s edition of the <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808), to
                        which three of Frere&#8217;s translations from the <title>Poema del Cid</title> were appended.</note> A translation is good
                    precisely in proportion as it faithfully represents the matter, manners &amp; spirit of its original. &#8211; this is equally well done
                    in his verse &amp; my prose, &amp; I will venture to say I never has been, &amp; never will be better done elsewhere. You do not
                    like it at all. &#8211; with what notion have you been reading it? not I am sure with the recollection that &lt;it&gt; is part of the
                    oldest poem extant in any modern language, &#8211; being of the time of William the Conqueror, &#8211; the manner &amp; the metre of which
                    have been represented as accurately as possible. In fact his translation had long been the wonder of all who had seen it, &amp; I
                    had heard wonders of it from <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>, <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> &amp; the <ref target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Hollands</ref> before I saw it. Your phrase of eking out is carts-tailable &#8211; without
                    benefit of clergy. If you will please to sum up that pages of that thin book you will find that they only fall 30 short of the
                    thick Madoc,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; &amp; instead of wanting materials, I supprest half a draw full of notes, besides my own
                    King Ramiro &amp; Garci Ferrandez.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey instead published &#8216;King Ramiro&#8217; revised, in the
                            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and with revisions in
                            <title>Poetical Works</title> (1837&#8211;1838). It had first appeared in September 1803 in the <title>Morning Post</title> and
                        on 12 May 1804 in the <title>Iris</title> (edited by <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">Taylor</ref>). He published &#8216;Garci Ferrandez&#8217;, in the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register for 1809</title> (1811), in <title>Minor Poems</title> (1815 and 1823) and <title>Poetical Works</title>
                        (1837&#8211;1838).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now to soft Tommys criticism. He seems to suppose that a book ought always to be rendered into English of the
                    newest fashion, &#8211; &amp; if not, that it should be given in the English of its own age, &#8211; a book of the fifteenth century (16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> he means) in that of the fifteenth. He did not recollect that in the thirteenth century there was no such
                    thing as English, which is I think answer enough. But the fact is, that both in the Chronicle &amp; in Amadis<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s translation of the Spanish romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> I have
                    not formed a style but followed one. The originally when represented as literally as possible ran into that phraseology, &#8211; &amp;
                    all I had to do was to avoid words &amp; forms of words of modern creation, &amp; also such as were unintelligibly obsolete. There
                    is, as you must have heard <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> point out, a language of pure intelligible
                    English which was spoken in Chaucers time &amp; is spoken in ours &#8211; equally understood then &amp; now, &amp; of which the Bible is
                    the written &amp; permanent standard in prose, as it has undoubtedly been the great means of preserving it. To that beautiful
                    manner of narration which characterises the best Chronicles this language is peculiarly adapted, &amp; in fact it is <hi rend="ital">appropriated</hi> to such narration by our books of chivalry, &amp; I might almost say <hi rend="ital">consecrated</hi> to it by the historical parts of scripture. &#8211; It so happens that of all things which I have ever done the
                    only one for which all the Reviews with one accord commended me, was for the manner in which I had rendered Amadis; &#8211; I wish he
                    may steer clear of all mischief as I shall of them upon this occasion. The fault which he finds is that I have translated the
                    Chronicle of the Cid instead of writing his history. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The list of books which I am about to order for you is this: Madoc, Specimens, Metrical Tales, Letters Sp &amp;
                    Portugal, 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Annual,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second editon of <title>Madoc</title>
                        (1807), <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), <title>Metrical Tales and other Poems</title> (1805),
                            <title>Letters written during a Journey in Spain, and a Short Residence in Portugal</title> (1808), and the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1806</title>, 5 (1807).</note> &#8211; all of which except the Letters I forgot that you had not.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Kehama went off yesterday,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was sending
                        his brother drafts of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810) in instalments.</note> &#8211; it just brings you onto new ground.
                    Upon fore-summing what remains to be written it does not appear that the Poem will extend much beyond 4800 lines &amp; I am
                    getting on toward 2700. There <del>xx</del> seem to be only seven sections more, which can hardly be averaged at more than 200
                    each. A little they may perhaps grow under my hands, &#8211; yet I think not much. In correcting &amp; inweaving after ornaments a
                    couple of hundred may probably be added. I had originally guessed the poem would run from 5 to 6000, &amp; on thinking about it
                    last night in bed was agreably startled to find myself as it were within sight of the end &#8211; so much sooner than I had expected. At
                    the end of a journey one quickens one pace &amp; I think I shall get on faster with it than ever for this reason &#8211; Especially as I
                    long to be rattling the chariot wheels over the brazen floors of Hell.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Events at the end
                        of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bonaparte may get to Madrid. I expect many &amp; great reverses for him for a while, but as for his establishing
                    Joseph on the throne<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph-Napol&#233;on Bonaparte (1768&#8211;1844) was the elder brother of
                        Napoleon, who made him King of Naples and Sicily (1806&#8211;1808), and, in August 1808, King of Spain and the Indies as Joseph I of
                        Spain (1808&#8211;1813). Joseph was forced by a revolt to abandon Madrid and did not return until January 1809, after French
                        reinforcements retook the city.</note> &amp; conquering <del>xx xx</del> Spain! &#8211; he may as well try to put out the Sun as to
                    crush the spirit of that nation. The French would not have won half their victories, had it not been for their cowardly spirit
                    which supposes they must be victorious. A man <hi rend="ital">ought</hi> to lose his ears for entertaining such an opinion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our projected county meeting came to nothing. <ref target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> set his
                    face against it, &amp; upon consultation with Curwen,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Whig MP for Carlisle, Workington landowner.</note> we were convinced that it was hopeless to muster
                    support against his merry men, who would have bellowed as loudly against us at the meeting, as they had done against the cursed
                    Convention, before they were under the orders of mum. So <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> went home to
                    ease his heart by writing a pamphlett,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Concerning the Concerning the
                            Relations of Great Britain, Spain, and Portugal, to Each Other, and to the Common Enemy, at this Crisis; and Specifically
                            as Affected by the Convention of Cintra</title> (1809) was triggered by the agreement, made on 30 August 1808, of the
                        British generals to allow a defeated Napoleonic army to withdraw from Portugal to France unmolested and with its weapons &#8211; a
                        decision he and Southey thought pusillanimous.</note> which you may be sure will be a right good one, &amp; contains more true
                    philosophy &amp; true patriotism than has for many a long year appeared in such a form. How he gets on with it I have not
                    heard.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The new Review<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> is to appear in April.
                    Among the persons who are calculated upon to write in it there <ref target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref>, <ref target="people.html#EllisGeorge">G. Ellis</ref>, your Admirals brother,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> William
                        Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Southey&#8217;s acquaintance.</note> who stands in about the same relation to me as a poet,
                    that he does to you as a seaman, &amp; is withal in other things a man of more than common talents, &amp; well to be liked, &#8211; <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>, Copplestone the Oxford Poetry Professor (a great admirer of Madoc) &#8211; Miss
                        Baillie,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joanna Baillie (1762&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), the Scottish dramatist,
                        friend of the <ref target="people.html#AikinArthur">Aikins</ref> and of <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref>.</note> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon Turner</ref> &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#BurneyJames">Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Burney</ref>. A good many of these persons I know have the thorough
                    conviction of the destructive folly which it would be to make peace, that I &amp; <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                        Scott</ref> have. &#8211; for to do <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref> justice, all his best &amp; bravest
                    feelings are alive upon that subject. I think we shall do good, &amp; will do my part with a hearty good will. What I said to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> was that as long as the Government Caravan was travelling my road I
                    was content to travel with it, &#8211; &amp; that tho all my opinions hang together, all the hanging which they imply does not
                    immediately appear.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> For this, see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 9 November 1808
                        (Letter 1530) and 11 November 1808 (Letter 1532).</note> &#8211; One good thing is that I shall be pretty sure of civil treatment
                    here, &amp; the Review will carry great weight with it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you mean to send all my books to <ref target="places.html#LowBrathay">Brathay</ref> as they come out, what with
                    their binding &amp; their travelling expences you will have enough to pay. I should think you had made quite presents enough of
                    this kind. <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> can much better afford to buy these books than you can to give them
                    to him, &amp; if he does not think them worth buying I know not why you should wish them to be upon his shelf.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had a book case put up opposite the great map on the landing place, &#8211; which it greatly ornaments, being
                    filled with respectables, &#8211; some of my <del>xx</del> &lt;geese<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s name for his
                        better quality books; his more dilapidated ones were called &#8216;ducks&#8217;.</note>&gt;, &#8211; such as are not gaudy but clean. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has but one batch more of junipering<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        &#8216;To juniperize&#8217; was Southey&#8217;s term for adding a gold border and lettering to the bindings of his books. The allusion was to
                        Friar Juniper, disciple of St Francis, who cut the silver bells off the gold border of an altar cloth to give to a poor woman
                        begging alms.</note> to get thro the whole.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your niece</ref> sends &amp; receives her regular kisses. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> goes stout, fat, &amp; strong, you would be delighted with him. As for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEmma">Emma</ref> she is as yet only entering into the state of kissability. She is as lively &amp;
                    good humoured as ever, &amp; every body admires her. But my boy is the beauty of the house. Another month &#8211; God willing &#8211; will set
                    her on her legs to stand at least &amp; perhaps walk by the window &amp; chairs, &#8211; &amp; then she will become a play thing in her
                    turn.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hear as seldom from the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">man-slayer at Durham</ref> as you do. He is
                    got into a furnished house, &amp; offers me a bed, &#8211; which I mean to occupy early in the new year, having resolved to pay him a
                    weeks visit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> has not written to me. There will be such a tremendous campaign that the
                    chances are much against any individual &#8211; especially one who will seek the hottest service as he will do. In the field he is but
                    one, &amp; as obnoxious to a ball as the merest machine of a soldier, &#8211; but should he be in a besieged town, such a man is worth a
                    whole regiment there. God protect him wherever he be.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>