<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1333</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2455</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Cornell University Library, Cottle album..  Previously 
                        published: Joseph Cottle (ed.), Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey (London, 1847), pp.
                        229&#8211;230 [in part].Dating note: The letter was written over a longer time than the date indicates, as Southey states that
                        it &#8216;has remained longer in my desk than it should have done&#8217;.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1333" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1333" type="letter">
        <head>1333. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1807-06-18">[started before, and
                        continued on] 18 June 1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/
                        Brunswick Square/ Bristol/ Single <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Cornell University Library, Cottle album.<lb />Previously
                        published: Joseph Cottle (ed.), <title>Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey</title> (London, 1847), pp.
                        229&#8211;230 [in part].<lb />Dating note: The letter was written over a longer time than the date indicates, as Southey states that
                        it &#8216;has remained longer in my desk than it should have done&#8217;.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Cottle</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Long since I ought to have thanked you for a letter which interested &amp; affected me very deeply ; &#8211; &amp; this I
                    should have done, &amp; have sent you according to your desire what I had said of poor <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos</ref>, had I made any use of its contents.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had planned to include Amos
                        Cottle in his <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807), co-edited with <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, but he was omitted from the final
                        publication.</note> But [MS missing] to wait till it arrived I had dispatched a few lines (of [MS missing] respect</p>
        <p>[Half a page of MS missing]</p>
        <p rend="indent1">but when all went to wreck &amp; ruin, one of the last things which was done was to obtain for me a pension of 200 &#163;
                    per year. The net income will be 160 the sum which I have till now received from <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, &amp; which of course I shall now receive no longer, the necessity no longer existing.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The so-called Ministry of All the Talents, in which Wynn had served as Under Secretary of State in the Home
                        Office, had broken up in March 1807. Before he left office, Wynn had succeeded in arranging that the pension he paid Southey
                        from his personal funds was replaced by a government pension.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This letter has remained longer in my desk than it should have done. Mean time I have learnt that fees &amp; taxes
                    are not contented with a fifth, but that of 200 they will take 56.</p>
        <p>every item of it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By this time you will have found out that as to &#8216;Saul&#8217; you have made the often-made mistake between Sotheby<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), the poet and translator, published
                            <title>Saul. A Poem in Two Parts</title> in 1807.</note> &amp; Southey. It seems to me very doubtful whether my career of
                    poetry is not at an end: I have disused it so long that as <del>before</del> &lt;for&gt; every thing else after long disuse, the
                    inclination &lt;for it&gt; is gone. There is a calmer &amp; steadier pleasure in acquiring &amp; communicating the knowledge of
                    what has been &amp; of what is, &#8211; I am passionately fond of history, &#8211; even when I have been most delighted with the act of
                    poetical composition. the recollection that all was but fable in the story with which I had exerted myself, frequently mingled
                    with the delight. I am better pleased with rendering justice to the mighty dead, &#8211; with holding up to the world the action of
                    Kings, Conquerors, Heroes &amp; Saints, not as they have usually been held up, but as they really are, good or evil, according to
                    the opinions formed of them by one who has neither passion, prejudice, nor interest of any kind to mislead his mind. There is a
                    delight in decoding great actions, &amp; (this of a different kind) in execrating bad men beyond any thing which poetry can give,
                    when it departs from historical truth. There is also a source of power even beyond what the poet, creator as he is, can exercise.
                    It is before my earthly tribunal that these mighty ones are brought for judgement. Centuries of applause, trophies &amp; altars,
                    canonizations or excommunication <del>xxxx</del> &lt;avail&gt; nothing with me. No former sentences are cognizable in my court.
                    The merits of the case are all I look to, &#8211; &amp; I believe I have never failed to judge of the <hi rend="ital">actions</hi> by
                    themselves, &amp; of the <hi rend="ital">actor</hi> by his motives, &amp; to allow manners, opinions, circumstances &amp;c their
                    full weight in palliation. What other merits my words will have others must find out for themselves, &#8211; but this I will vouch for,
                    that never was the heart of any historian full of purer opinions, &amp; that never any one went about his work with more thorough
                    industry or more thorough good will.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your account of Churchey<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Churchey (1747&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Welsh poet who published <title>Poems and Imitations of the British Poets</title> in 1789. Southey had asked Cottle for information on
                        Churchey with a view to including him in his <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807); see Southey to Joseph
                        Cottle, 11 August 1806 (Letter 1210) and 2 November 1806 (Letter 1232). Churchey was not included in the
                            <title>Specimens</title>.</note> is very amusing. I shall like much to see the pamphlet of which you speak. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is coming down to see me: he is just publishing two books, &amp; is I hope
                    &amp; believe more likely to maintain himself comfortably &amp; attain some rank &amp; society than he ever has been. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be kindly remembered to you &amp; your mother &amp; sisters. Some
                    summer holy day you &amp; <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Miss Cottle</ref>
          <hi rend="ital">must</hi> visit us. The way is long, but you will think the journey well repaid, &#8211; &amp; I am charged by <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> to say that there is no person whom it would give her greater delight to see
                    than <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">your sister</ref>. Remember that I <hi rend="ital">bespeak you</hi> for next years
                    midsummer, if God willing, we be all alive &amp; well. You &amp; I are now friends of twelve years standing, &amp; now that I am,
                    for the first time in my life, <hi rend="ital">settled</hi>, you will not do the part of a friend if you do not come &amp; visit
                    me.</p>
        <closer rend="indent1"> God bless you<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <salute rend="indent8">
            <date when="1807-06-18">June 18. 1807.</date>
          </salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RSouthey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Remember me to <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Robert</ref> when you see or write to him.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>