<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1564</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2686</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        34046.  Previously  published: Mary Stuart (ed.), Letters from the Lake Poets, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, William
                            Wordsworth, Robert Southey, to Daniel Stuart (London, 1889), pp. 397&#8211;404.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1564" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1564" type="letter">
        <head>1564. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Daniel Stuart</ref>, <date when="1809-01-13">13 January
                        1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Daniel Stuart Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Courier
                        Office/ Strand/ London<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ JAN16/ 1809<lb />Endorsement: Southey/ Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>/ 1809/ Cintra &amp; Spain/ Home politics/ Coleridge&#8217;s &#8216;Friend&#8217;<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        34046<lb />Previously published: Mary Stuart (ed.), <title>Letters from the Lake Poets, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, William
                            Wordsworth, Robert Southey, to Daniel Stuart</title> (London, 1889), pp. 397&#8211;404.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-01-13">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 13. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> had not undertaken to write upon the Cintra
                        Convention,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Convention of Cintra, signed on 30 August 1808, whereby the French
                        army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by Anglo-Portuguese forces under Sir Arthur Wellesley (later the
                        1st Duke of Wellington) (1769&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>) at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its
                        weapons, from Portugal.</note> I believe I should, for no public event ever distressed me so greatly. He has more leisure than
                    I have, &amp; will do the thing better. &#8211; Like you I had strong hopes of Spain before the public dared <del>any</del> entertain
                    any, &amp; shall have strong hopes long after the public will despair. There is not under heaven so patriotic a people as the
                    Spaniards. they are proud of their past greatness, &amp; sensible of their present degradation, &#8211; yet with the feeling that the
                    degeneracy is not in them but in their government. It is the same with the Portugueze, &#8211; I was never ten minutes in conversation
                    with one, that he did not allude to the state of the country, as if he sought by expressing his sense of national shame, to
                        <del>xxxx</del> show that none of it attached to him as an individual. &#8211; From these people every thing is to be expected,
                    except what our ministry was weak enough to expect, &#8211; that they should at once be able to stand against equal or superior numbers
                    of the French in the field. The war of the Low Countries against Philip 2 is the only parallel in modern history,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip II (1527&#8211;1598), King of Spain, Portugal, Naples and Sicily 1554&#8211;1598, whose rule over the
                        seventeen provinces of the Netherlands (1556&#8211;1581) led to open warfare from 1568.</note> &#8211; &amp; then the first brunt of the
                    business was borne by German mercenaries, till the Dutch themselves <del>xxxxxx</del> became good soldiers by experience. &#8211; What
                    should have been done is so plain, &amp; has been so grossly neglected that I can neither speak nor think upon the subject with
                    patience. But I have thought it worth while to trouble you with a letter because a few more blunders will ruin all.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bonaparte will beyond a doubt push for Seville &amp; Cadiz, &amp; for Lisbon. Cadiz is a regular fortification
                    &amp; may hold out. Seville depends wholly upon the passes of the Sierra Morena, &amp; the city itself is larger than Madrid &amp;
                    equally defenceless. It is hardly of less importance than Madrid, perhaps indeed of more, as the Junta has no other Capital of
                    imposing name to retire to. Now in the present state of things ten thousand British could better defend those passes, than any
                    force the Spaniards have, &#8211; &amp; yet upon every breath of bad news we disembark our troops, &amp; countermand sailing orders,
                    instead of running them over in ships of war as fast as they could be got on board. If it be possible to ruin that country &amp;
                    this too, such fancies &amp; such pusillanimity will do it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am inclined to think Sir J. Moore<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Scottish General with a long and varied military career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784&#8211;1790.
                        After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the command of the British troops in the Iberian
                        peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna.</note> has misled himself for the sake of drawing Bonapartes main
                    force towards the North, &#8211; by which means he will be able to land troops at Porto, Lisbon or Cadiz, before the enemy can march
                    there. Lisbon is effectually defended on one side by the Tagus, which is fordable no nearer than Santarem (nearly fifty miles up)
                    &amp; then only in the dry season. This too is a passage which never would be <del>ventured</del> attempted against any
                    respectable force on the heights of the town. At Abrantes there is a bridge of boats. If an invading enemy enter Portugal higher
                    up &amp; keep on the North of the Tagus, as hitherto they have always done, &#8211; then the river Zezere which falls into the Tagus
                    about ten miles below Abrantes, is supposed to be the strong post on which the safety of Lisbon depends. I have crost this river,
                    it is about as wide as the Bath river, &amp; its banks are steep. If the enemy enter from Galicia &amp; keep along the coast, it
                    is but to break down bridges, &amp; the Minho, the Douro, &amp; the Mondego are each impassable. <del>If</del> Higher up these
                    rivers is one uninterrupted track of mountains. Very few countries are so defensible as Portugal. Hitherto we have been keeping
                    10,000 men <del>there</del> at Lisbon to preserve Portugueze traitors from justice, in virtue of the blessed convention of Cintra.
                    The main part of them are now it seems marched into Spain, in what direction we know not. If it be towards Seville <del>all is
                        well. But</del> that would be well. But Portugal requires at this time 30,000 English, &amp; with that force it would be safe,
                    unless Sir Hew, or Sir Harry, <del>were at</del> or any &lt;other&gt; old woman in regimentals be at their head.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Hew Whitefoord Dalrymple, 1st Baronet (1750&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>), one of the army
                        generals who agreed to the Convention of Cintra (30 August 1808), by which the defeated French army in Portugal was
                        repatriated in British ships. The other general responsible for this decision was Sir Harry Burrard, 1st Baronet (bap.
                        1755&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>). This act was condemned by the British press and public.</note> Not an hour should be lost in
                    sending out all the troops we can spare, as fast as they can go, in frigates &amp; ships of the line that may run singly, without
                    fear of enemy or weather. Some for Porto some for Lisbon, some for Cadiz. And if we had a floating army off Catalonia, to land
                    just when &amp; where they would be most serviceable, Bonaparte will feel our navy to be a far more formidable power than he has
                    ever yet done.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That letter in the Courier of the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> alludes I suppose to some kind of defensive armour.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> A letter in <title>The Courier</title> of Tuesday 10 January 1809, p. 2, alludes to a
                        &#8216;Military Plan of the greatest importance&#8217; without disclosing directly what the plan entails, but stating that its object is
                        &#8216;to bring every action immediately to a close engagement, [and] to render portable fire areas useless to the enemy&#8217;.</note>
                    One hears of all new projects with a suspicion just in proportion to the great effects which they promise. Defensive armour was
                    left off, as I happened to discover in some chance passage of an old author, because the &#8216;rags&#8217; as he calls them of the armour
                    made a worse wound than the ball. If any thing be devised proof against a common musket ball, steel balls would immediately be
                    adopted. Yet I am curious to see more about this discovery, for I have long believed that something might be done towards saving
                    soldiers, &#8211; a matter of no light consequence to us &#8211; who have so much difficulty in raising them, &amp; yet stand in need of so
                    many.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is hopeless to think about home-politicks, &amp; almost impertinent to say any thing about them to you. There
                    will be a schism however between the Grenvilles &amp; the Foxites<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Factions within the Whig
                        party who were followers of the policies of <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Charles James Fox</ref> or <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">William Wyndham Grenville</ref>.</note> whenever the question of peace is touchd upon,
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref>, who is ashamed of some of his colleagues, hankers to have the
                    Grenvilles in with him. Neither the King<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III (1738&#8211;1820, King of Great Britain
                        1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> nor the people would like this. And every change that can now be made must tend to
                    weaken the government by convincing the people that no good is to be expected from any, unless indeed Lord Grenville were bold
                    enough &amp; wise enough to make himself popular by insisting upon the necessity of removing the Duke of York.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Prince Frederick, Duke of York and Albany (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Commander in Chief of
                        the army. He held the post from 1798&#8211;1809, but was forced to resign in the wake of allegations that he had profited by
                        allowing his mistress, Mary Anne Clarke (c. 1776&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), to accept money from army officers, in return for
                        which promotion was arranged.</note> Whatever public man of adequate talents &amp; respectability should venture to do this,
                    would stand upon such <del>gro</del> strong ground that the Crown itself could not shake him. I was right glad to see the hint
                    upon this subject in the Courier.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Courier</title> of Monday 9 January 1809, p.
                        2, carried an article on the Duke of York in the light of allegations against him. See note 8.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have many fears about &#8216;the Friend&#8217;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The journal that Coleridge was
                        proposing to produce and publish from the Lake District. It ran from June 1809 to March 1810.</note> which however I do not
                    express to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> for did he once perceive that we doubted his going on,
                    that would be sufficient effectually to put a stop to all efforts on his part. The main, &amp; as it appears to me the insuperable
                    difficulty in the way of his present plan, is the unlikelihood &#8211; or rather the impossibility of his carrying on any periodical
                    work with regularity. If his habits were regular enough his health is not, unless he began with a large stock in hand, which
                    certainly he will not do. My advice to him is that he publish a number of half a crown or five shillings worth whenever he is
                    ready with it, a &#8216;this day is published&#8217; in the newspapers will then be sufficient prospectus, &amp; it will find its way with the
                    other periodicals. Matys Review<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Paul Henry Maty&#8217;s (1744&#8211;1787; <title>DNB</title>)
                            <title>New Review</title>, which summarised foreign publications, was published from 1782 to 1786.</note> did this some
                    years ago, &#8211; &amp; the Edinburgh<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, a periodical
                        published in quarterly issues from 1802 to 1929.</note> does so now. I will not say that this is as good a plan as that of a
                    weekly paper. &#8211; perhaps it is not, &#8211; but I have a strong fear, &#8211; almost a conviction that in any other shape the thing would soon
                    drop. If indeed he begun with ten or twelve weeks in advance, then if <del>any</del> he were at any time incapacitated from
                    keeping that stock up I would to the best of my power, supply his place as long as was necessary, &#8211; but the first number will be
                    sent off wet from the pen to the press, &#8211; &amp; unless a sudden popularity should come upon him like sunshine, a very few weeks
                    struggle against inaction will fret &amp; fever him into inability. I therefore am pressing him not to promise any thing
                    periodical, &#8211; not to trouble himself with prospectuses &amp; subscribers, but to make his way by the weight of his own name, &amp;
                    all-commanding powers of mind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I know not that this letter contains any thing worth sending, &#8211; but some public occasions have gone by on which I
                    have repented not having written to tell you what I knew upon the point &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>