<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1268</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2390</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                    47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1268" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1268" type="letter">
        <head>1268. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1807-01-30">30 January
                        1807</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: E/ FEB 2/ 1807<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                    47890<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Charles </salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have not quite so much forethought about you in packing a box as I should have expected, &#8211; or you would have
                    remembered when you filled it up with waste sermons that I was to pay by weight for it &amp; that waste paper weighs as heavy as
                    books. Had you instead of &lt;thus&gt; filling that heavy Portugueze box (wood is cheap there &amp; they put thrice the quantity
                    in one that we do in England) bought a tea chest I should have had at least two stone less to have paid for, which on a journey of
                    300 miles amounts to a great deal. I wish too when you laid in the book of prints for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> amusement you had added the two volumes belonging to it for mine, in place of part of the abominable
                    sermons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> However thank you for a great deal of trouble which you must needs have taken. __</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just received yours. You had indeed in your letter of the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> not expressed yourself
                    unintelligibly, but made the very ingenious mistake of telling me that you could not find all the books which you had found, &amp;
                    that you had found those which it seems you could not find. All is right except the other two MS.S. about which however I will not
                    again plague you, but there they are among the other books &amp; not in the trunks. I will only say one thing more about the books
                    &amp; that is &#8211; if the great book of prints of Batalha<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Murphy (dates unknown),
                            <title>Plans, Elevations and Views of the Church of Batallia, in Portugal</title> (1792).</note> has not suffered from
                    damp &#8211; &amp; there be any danger that it should &#8211; to beg you would take it into your care; at any rate &#8211; look at it to see, &amp;
                    if the prints be mouldy wipe them, which had not been done by the prints sent for Edith, &#8211; &amp; I am sorry to say that wiping is
                    even more essential for the insides of books than the outside.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whitfields Journal is a sad duck<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey named his more dilapidated books
                        &#8216;ducks&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; is not that part of his Journals which I most wanted &#8211; but the Letters supply the place well.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Whitefield (1714&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), Calvinistic Methodist leader, whose
                            <title>Journals</title> were published in an unauthorised version in 1738. The authorised version, <title>The Two First
                            Parts of Whitefield&#8217;s Life, with his Journals Revised, Corrected and Abridged</title>, appeared in 1756. In the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, no. 3010 is George Whitefield&#8217;s <title>Select Collection of
                            Letters</title> (1772).</note> I am glad you have sent my pocket books.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had a touch of influenza which was soon shaken off. This very unseasonable weather has bred all sorts of
                    infection about us, for which <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> seems like a hot bed, &#8211; there is always a fever
                    lurking there among the dirty poor. I lost three days by the attack &amp; that was all. But three days are a good deal according
                    to my present rate of travelling. &#8211; The conclusion of D Manuels second volume goes by this post to the printer, &#8211; &amp; very
                    little remains to compleat the third. I am hurrying Richard Taylor,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor
                        (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), whose firm was printing <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella.
                            Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &amp; begin to be wishing to see how it looks in boards, &amp; to hear
                    what will be said about it, &#8211; a pleasure which you will have in perfection, for it is not that sort of book &#8211; that will be read
                    &amp; not talked about.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So William Reid is married! You never tell me any thing of <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam</ref>, &amp; I
                    should be glad to hear he was going on well. Is he still at Liverpool?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot guess what is in the trunks, &#8211; but be it what it may they had better be opened lest the contents should
                    spoil. When my book is ready for the Press Taylor-like I shall &#8216;go home with my work&#8217;,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>) was printing <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella.
                            Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; &amp; will then by a bit of what <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my poor Mother</ref> used to call a circumbendibus<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A roundabout way.</note> make Bristol in my way, &amp; overhaul all my unhappy chattels which seem to want me as much as I
                    want them. Settle them &amp; myself too I certainly will with the first three hundred pounds I can get, &amp; it is not for want
                    of working that I have <del>xxx</del> not got it yet, &#8211; but it will come all in good time: most probably the neighbourhood of
                    Bath, or Bath itself, will be my choice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SmithGrace">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Smith</ref> sent me <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edwards</ref> letters in the Box with a note wishing me to do something for him. On that subject my mind has long been made
                    up. Any money bestowed upon him would be thrown away. If he is ever reclaimable, nothing but absolute want &amp; suffering can
                    reclaim him. After the opportunities which he has had &#8211; three times in the navy &amp; once in the army, &#8211; &amp; after the things
                    which he has done &#8211; there is no hope. Sink he will &amp; sink he must. He must be left to seek his fortune. Into whatever abject
                    situation he may fall if he does his duty in it, whenever I am satisfied of that, (which it must require some time to be &#8211;) I will
                    then help him up. But I cannot afford to throw money away where it will be of no use; neither if I could afford it, would I. If
                    should go in some better direction.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> writes in bad spirits. He suffers dreadfully from chilblains,
                    &amp; from the weather, having got a West Indian constitution. Nothing would give me so much pleasure as his promotion, &amp;
                    thank Heaven there certainly seems to be a good chance of it. He will be very glad to hear from you &#8211; direct Pallas.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Launched in 1804, the <hi rend="ital">Pallas</hi> was a 32 gun fifth rate frigate, whose first
                        captain was Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), under whom she was involved in the
                        capture of many French and Spanish warships. In 1807, command passed to Captain George Miller (dates unknown).</note> Plymouth
                    &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has the same strange shaped eyes as all my children, &#8211; they are in colour
                    singularly beautiful, &amp; except in their shape &#8211; he is as fine a child as you have ever seen. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> is like my old books, ugly &#8211; but good, &#8211; She will be very plain
                    certainly &#8211; But she has guts in her brains &#8211; to use a genteel phrase, &#8211; &amp; is as quick as thought in her intellect. She would
                    make a famous playfellow for you, &amp; I heartily wish you were here to play with her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is some hopes that <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> will come here in the end of the
                    summer &#8211; bring <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R</ref> &#8211; leave her here &#8211; &amp; go on upon
                    business to the Highlands &#8211; in which case I will go with him.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey and Rickman did not
                        visit Scotland together until 1819.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#WilsonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wilson</ref> often talks of you. What an excellent good woman is that.
                    &#8211; You will see <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> on his way to Devonshire &amp; see him much
                    altered. His countenance is more changed for the worse than I could have believed possible. the eyes have lost all their life &#8211;
                    partly from fat &#8211; &amp; still more from the quantity of laudanum which he takes, &amp; the quantity of spirits. &#8211; nothing
                    intoxicates him, &amp; he is not sensible &amp; will not be easily convinced that he drinks enough to kill any body, &#8211; frequently
                    when he was at home nearly a bottle of rum in a day. Do&#8217;nt talk about this, for it is better kept to ourselves &#8211; but he is
                    everyway the worse for his long absence except in his understanding.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1807-01-30">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 30. 1807.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>