<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.902</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2024</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 266&#8211;268 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.902" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="902" type="letter">
        <head>902. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1804-02">February 1804</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 266&#8211;268 [in
                        part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1804-02">Feb. 1804</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not sorry that you gave <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref> a dressing,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> For more in this incident;
                        see Southey to John King, [1]&#8211;5 March 1804, Letter 904.</note> and should not be sorry if he were occasionally to remember it with the comfortable reflection &#8216;<hi rend="ital">in vino veritas</hi>;&#8217;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Latin translates as &#8216;in wine [there is] truth&#8217;.</note> for, in plain truth, already it does vex me to see
                    you so lavish of the outward and visible signs of friendship, and to know that a set of fellows whom you do not care for and ought not to care for, boast every where of your
                    intimacy, and with good reason, to the heat of their understanding. You have accustomed yourself to talk affectionately, and write affectionately, to your friends, till the
                    expressions of affection flow by habit in your conversation, and in your letters, and pass for more than they are worth; the worst of all this is, that your letters will one day
                    rise up in judgment against you (for be sure, that hundreds which you have forgotten, are hoarded up for some Curl or Philips<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund Curl
                        (c. 1675&#8211;1747), unscrupulous bookseller and publisher, and Ambrose Philips (1674&#8211;1749), pastoral poet published by Curl, were both mocked as dunces by Alexander Pope
                        (1688&#8211;1744; <title>DNB</title>) in <title>The Dunciad</title> (1728&#8211;1743).</note> of the next generation), and you will be convicted of a double dealing, which, though you do
                    not design, you certainly do practise. And now that I <hi rend="ital">am</hi> writing affectionately <hi rend="ital">more meo</hi>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                        Latin translates as &#8216;going on in my own way&#8217;.</note> I will let out a little more. You say in yours to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Sara</ref>, that you love and honour me; upon my soul I believe you: but if I did not thoroughly believe it before, your saying so is the thing of all things that would make me open my
                    eyes and look about me to see if I were not deceived: perhaps I am too intolerant to these kind of phrases; but, indeed, when they are true, they may be excused, and when they are
                    not, there is no excuse for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> ______<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thus in text. Unidentified.</note> was always looking for such things, but he was a foul feeder, and my moral
                    stomach loathes anything like froth. There is a something outlandish in saying them, more akin to a French embrace than an English shake by the hand, and I would have you leave off
                    saying them to those whom you actually do love, that if this should not break off the habit of applying them to indifferent persons, the disuse may at least make a difference. Your
                    feelings go naked, I cover mine with a bear-skin; I will not say that you harden yours by your mode, but I am sure that mine are the warmer for their clothing. . . . . . . . It is
                    possible, or probable, that I err as much as you in an opposite extreme, and may make enemies where you would make friends; but there is a danger that you may sometimes excite
                    dislike in persons of whose approbation you would yourself be desirous. You know me well enough to know in what temper this has been written, and to know that it has been some
                    exertion; for the same habit which makes me prefer sitting silent to offering contradiction, makes me often withhold censure when, perhaps, in strictness of moral duty, it ought to
                    be applied. The medicine might have been sweetened perhaps; but, dear Coleridge, take the simple bitters, and leave the sweetmeats by themselves.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That ugly-nosed <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref> has led me to this. I dare say he deserved all you gave him; in fact, I have never forgiven him
                    his abuse of <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, and do now regret, with some compunction, that in my reviewal of his Chaucer,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed William Godwin, <title>Life of Geoffrey Chaucer ... Including Memoirs of ... John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster; with Sketches of the
                            Manners, Opinions, Arts and Literature of England in the Fourteenth Century</title> (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 462&#8211;473.</note> I struck
                    out certain passages of well-deserved severity.&#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;
                    &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; Two days of S. T. C.&#8217;s time given to ______.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thus in text. Unidentified.</note> Another
                        Antonio!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The friend of Sebastian in Shakespeare&#8217;s <title>Twelfth Night</title> who proves unable to tell him apart from
                        Cesario.</note> If we are to give account for every idle hour, what will you say to this lamentable waste? Or do you expect to have them allowed to you in your purgatory score?
                    &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;
                    &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;.
                    &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160;. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; If he had not married again, I would
                    have still have had some bowels of compassion for him; but to take another wife with the picture of <ref target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">Mary Wollstonecroft</ref> in his
                    house! Agh! I am never ashamed of letting out my <hi rend="ital">dislikes</hi>, however, and, what is a good thing, never afraid; so let him abuse me, and we&#8217;ll be at war.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish you had called on <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. That man has a kind heart of his own, and I wish you to think so: the letter he sent
                    me was a proof of it. Go to one of his Saturday evenings; you will see a coxcomb or two, and a dull fellow or two: but you will, perhaps, meet <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> and <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>, and <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> is worth knowing;
                    make yourself known to him in my name, and tell him how glad I should be to show him the Lakes. I have some hope, from <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman&#8217;s</ref> letter,
                    that you may see <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> in town; that would give me great pleasure, for I am very desirous that you should meet. For universal
                    knowledge, I believe he stands quite unrivalled; his conversation is a perpetual spring of living water; and then in every relation of life so excellent is he, that I know not any
                    man who, in the circle of his friends, is so entirely and deservedly beloved.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>