<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1573</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2695</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Mitchell Library, Glasgow.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 212&#8211;215.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1573" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1573" type="letter">
        <head>1573. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebeneezer Elliott</ref>, <date when="1809-02-03">3 February
                    1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Mr E Elliott Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Rotherham<lb />Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: Mitchell Library, Glasgow<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 212&#8211;215.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-02-03">Friday night. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 3. 1809</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yesterday I received your note inclosing the specimen of your poem. I have perused that specimen, but my advice
                    cannot be comprized in a few words.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A Literary as well as a medical opinion Mr Elliott must needs be blindly given unless the age, &amp;c of the person
                    who requires it is known. When I advised <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry White</ref> to publish a second volume of
                    poems, it was because he had fixed his heart upon a university education, &amp; this seemed to be a feasible method of raising
                    funds for that end, &#8211; his particular circumstances rendering that prudent which would otherwise have been very much the reverse.
                    For poetry is not a marketable article, unless there be something strange or peculiar to give it a fashion; &amp; in his case what
                    money might properly have been raised would in almost every instance, have been considered rather as given to the author, than
                    paid for his book. Your poem would not find purchasers, except in the circle of your own friends; out of that circle not twenty
                    copies would be sold, &#8211; &lt;I believe&gt; <del>probably</del> not half that number.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are probably a young man Sir, &#8211; &amp; it is plain from this specimen that you possess more than one of those
                        <del>xxx</del> powers which form the poet, &amp; &lt;those&gt; in a far more than ordinary degree. Whether your plans of life
                    are such as to promise leisure for that attention (almost it might be said that devotement) without which no man can ever become a
                    great poet, &#8211; you yourself must know. If they should, you will in a very few years have outgrown the poem, &amp; <del>will</del>
                    &lt;would&gt; then be sorry to see it in print, irrecoverably given to the public, because you would feel it to be an inadequate
                    proof of your own talents. If on the other hand you consider poetry as merely an amusement or ornament of youth, to be laid aside
                    in riper years for the ordinary pursuits of the world, with still less indulgence will you then <del>xxx</del> regard the printed
                    volume, for you will reckon it among the follies of which you are ashamed. In either case it is best not to publish.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is very far from my wish to discourage or depress you. There is great promise in this specimen, &#8211; it has all the
                    faults which I should wish to see in the writings of a young poet, as the surest indications that he has that in him which will
                    enable him to become a good one. But no young man can possibly write a good narrative poem, tho I believe he cannot by any
                        <del>xxxx</del> &lt;other means&gt; so effectually improve himself as by making the attempt. I myself published one at the age
                    of six &amp; twenty,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s dating is ambiguous: &#8216;twenty six&#8217; would suggest a poem
                        of 1800 or 1801, that is, <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), but later in the paragraph &#8216;fourteen years ago&#8217;
                        suggests his first published narrative epic <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796).</note> &#8211; it made a reputation for me, &#8211; not so
                    much by its merits as because it was taken up by one party, &amp; abused by another, almost independently of its merits or
                    demerits, at a time when party spirit was more violent than it is to be hoped it ever will be again. What has been the consequence
                    of this publication? that the poem from beginning &lt;to end&gt; was full of incorrect language, &amp; errors of every kind, that
                    all the weeding of years could never weed it clean, &#8211; &amp; that &lt;many&gt; people at this day rate me not according to the
                    standard of my present intellect but by what it was fourteen years ago. &#8211; Your subject also has the same disadvantage with mine, &#8211;
                    that it is anti-national, &amp; believe me this is a grievous one; for tho <del>bo</del> we have both been right in our feelings,
                    yet to feel against ones own country can only be right upon great &amp; transitory occasions, &#8211; &amp; none but our contemporaries
                    can feel with us; &#8211; none but those who remember the struggle <del>at the time</del> &amp; took their part in it. And you are more
                    unfortunate than I was, &#8211; for America was acting at this time unnaturally towards England, &amp; every reader will [MS torn] this,
                    &amp; his sense of what the Americans are now will make him fancy that you paint falsely in describing them as they were
                        then.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey refers to &#8216;A Soldier&#8217;s Love&#8217;, a poem that remained, on his advice,
                        unpublished. Elliott published, under the pseudonym Britannicus, <title>The Soldier; and Other Poems</title> in 1810.</note> &#8211;
                    There is yet another argument &#8211; criticism is conducted upon a different plan from what it was when I commenced my career. You live
                    near the Dragon of Wantleys<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The seventeenth century parody of medieval romance &#8216;The
                        Dragon of Wantley&#8217;, in which the knight More of More Hall fights and kills the dragon with a well-placed &#8216;kick on the &#8230;.&#8217;, see
                        Thomas Percy (1729&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</title>, 3 vols (London, 1765), III,
                        pp. 277&#8211;286 (esp. 285). Elliott lived near the dragon&#8217;s den, supposedly at Wharncliffe Crags, five miles to the north of
                        Sheffield, South Yorkshire. Elliott would publish &#8216;Night, or, The Legend of Wharncliffe&#8217; in 1818.</note> den; but you will
                    provoke enemies as venomous if you publish &amp; Heaven knows whether or no you are gifted with armour of proof against them. Nor
                    is it the effect that malicious censure &amp; ridicule might produce upon your own feelings which is of &lt;so&gt; much
                    consequence as what <del>they</del> would be produced upon your friends. They who are so only in name will derive a provoking
                    pleasure from seeing you laughed at &amp; abused; they who love you will feel more pain than you yourself, because you will &amp;
                    must have a higher confidence in yourself, &amp; a stronger conviction of injustice than they can be supposed to possess.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The sum of my advice is, &#8211; do not publish this poem, &#8211; but if you can without grievous imprudence afford to write
                    poetry continue so to do, because hereafter you will write it well. As yet you have only green fruit to offer &#8211; wait a season
                    &amp; there will be a fair &amp; full gathering when it is ripe.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I do not know how to send back your manuscript.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>