<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1643</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2765</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 509&#8211;511. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1643" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1643" type="letter">
        <head>1643. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1809-06-15">15 June
                    1809</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Bristol<lb />Endorsements: [various calculations on address sheet]<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 509&#8211;511. </p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1809-06-15">June 15. Thursday. 1809.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for the books I never dreamt of your bringing them, &#8211; folios being far too bulky for that sort of travelling.
                    Send them off by the waggon, either now, or after your return, as may be most convenient. There were some in the list for which I
                    would have been in a hurry, had they been procured, &#8211; these others I am glad of, but not in haste for them. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You had better cross the sands from Lancaster, <hi rend="ital">which is <del>xxx</del> safeliest done by the
                    stage</hi>, &#8211; see <ref target="places.html#FurnessAbbey">Furness Abbey</ref> on the way, go up the side of Coniston, &amp; from the head of that Lake strike to the Ferry
                    on Windermere. You will of course call on <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref>, &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> you will find at Wordsworths, who now lives in a great house on the
                    other side of Grasmere,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Allan Bank.</note> about a quarter of a mile or rather more
                    above the church, but no tarriance there, farther than is necessary to let <ref target="people.html#JardineDavid">David</ref>
                     see the country, &#8211; for I must have all the time you can spare. I will go with you from hence to Paterdale, where we will
                    sleep, <del>&amp; xxx</del> getting half a day to see the things thereabouts; &#8211; from thence if the weather permit we will cross
                    Helvellin to Grasmere, &amp; return to Keswick over the Stake. We must also contrive to see Eskdale.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I returned yesterday from Durham having been about eleven days. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is well settled there; &#8211; he makes at the rate of 200 a year now, which for so young a practitioner is very much.
                    A Bill in Chancery will put him soon in possession of 600&#163; left to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMaryHarriet">his wife</ref>
                     some years ago, &amp; in the hands of the Court for her use, &#8211; the interest is disputed, but without the
                    slightest shadow of right. This sum will enable him to go on till his profession can compleatly support him. And if his wife
                    outlive her father<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Southey&#8217;s</ref>
                        father-in-law, Richard Sealy (dates unknown) a wealthy Lisbon merchant.</note> he will have enough to enable him to retire
                    from practice altogether. &#8216;Some thing handsome&#8217; is a phrase which Sealy makes use of, &#8211; I apprehend not less than 10,000 &amp;
                    probably half as much more. Sealy is at present in Lisbon, &amp; will <del>xxx</del> I suppose make his daughter some present as
                    soon as he hears of the marriage, which is now with his perfect approbation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All this you will say is very well, &#8211; better still you will think when I tell you that my new sister is an
                    accomplished woman, gentle-minded, with a very pleasing countenance, &amp; by the testimony of all who know her best, a good
                    heart, &#8211; to which I am sure she &lt;has&gt; all possible right of inheritance. But there is one evil which counterbalances the
                    whole, &#8211; at least it would so to me. By some accident in her childhood her shape has suffered, so little that I, who have no very
                    curious eye for these things, did not perceive it till I was told so; &#8211; but it is enough to affect her health. she has an habitual
                    nervous cough, &#8211; when at the best, that is in its general state, it shows itself by one or two <hi rend="ital">hems</hi> &#8211; as if
                    to clear the throat, &#8211; but of a deep &amp; distressing sound; &#8211; unattended with any pain however, except to the hearer. &amp;
                    whenever she catches cold this ceases, &#8211; which is a curious circumstance. The last earthquake terrified her so much <del>th</del>
                    (for she was then very ill) that she has even since been subject to something more distressing still to my ear, &#8211; a way of
                    groaning at times when she breathes, &#8211; something like the noise a man makes in paving the streets only in a very low tone. It
                    would break my heart to hear it, if she were my wife. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> says there is
                    nothing alarming in all this, &#8211; &amp; as she has had the cough for eight years it may be so. But this was the objection I made
                    when he first told me of his attachment, &#8211; &amp; I confess it would have prevented me from ever forming one. I always liked her, &#8211;
                    like her better now that I have seen her more.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I came home thro Newcastle for the sake of staying a day with <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">Losh</ref>
                    . He enquired for you, &amp; expressed a great wish that you might one day take that road. It was seven years since I had
                    seen him, he in better health than ever, &amp; has five fine children.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has vexed me by his &#8216;Friend&#8217;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The first edition of Coleridge&#8217;s new periodical <title>The Friend</title> was published on 1 June 1809.</note> &#8211; the
                    affectation of humility even to downright canting, is to me insufferable, &#8211; &amp; the folly of talking as he does about his formed
                    principles is still more. It is worse than folly, for if he was not a Jacobine, in the common acceptation of the name, I wonder
                    who the Devil was. I am sure I was, am still, &amp; ever more shall be. I am sure too that he wrote a flaming panegyric of Tom
                        Paine,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Paine (1737&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; that I delivered
                    it in one of my lectures.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Delivered by Southey at the end of April 1795. For the gist
                        of the panegyric, &#8216;O Paine! hireless Priest of Liberty! unbought teacher of the poor! chearing to me is the reflection that my
                        heart hath ever acknowledged &#8212; that my tongue hath proudly proclaimed &#8212; the Truth &amp; Divinity of thy Doctrines!&#8217;; see
                        Southey to Thomas Southey, 9 May 1795, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 126.</note> As
                    to his announcing a sketch of his own life, &#8211; there is one comfort which is &#8211;&#8211; that he will never write it. The Friend will never
                    go on,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge began the journal in June 1809; the last number appeared in March
                        1810.</note> &#8211; it is impossible that he should carry it on to 20 numbers. I regard every number as a dead loss, &#8211; &amp; worse
                    than all I fear he will totally degrade himself before he has done. There is a baseness in talking about himself as he has done
                    for which even all his powers of intellect cannot atone.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. We shall heartily rejoice to see you &#8211; write from Liverpool. Double bedded down we have none, &#8211; I
                    hope &amp; trust however we shall have two beds, &#8211; but if the one happen to be pre-occupied, &#8211; (for we never know when <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> may come, <del>&amp;</del> nor if he comes when he may go) &#8211; we
                    will engage John Fishers<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> A neighbour of Wordsworth who had lived at Skyeside, at
                        Townend, Grasmere. Where Fisher lived in Keswick is not known but Espriella lodges at the &#8216;neat&#8217; house of a Keswick barber and
                        his wife, which &#8216;bears marks of industrious frugality&#8217; during his Lake tour in <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel
                            Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807), Letter 41.</note> bed for <ref target="people.html#JardineDavid">David</ref>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>