<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1027</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2149</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker
                        From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 144&#8211;147.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 313&#8211;315. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1027" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1027" type="letter">
        <head>1027. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1805-01-26">26 January
                    1805</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Congreve/ Penkridge/ Staffordshire <lb />Postmark:
                        [partial] KESWICK/ 2<lb />MS: MS untraced; text from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker
                        From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 144&#8211;147<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 313&#8211;315. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am to acknowledge the receipt of a ham who arrived well on Wednesday last, &amp; is at present the great ornament
                    of our kitchen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">Sir Edward</ref>  may well excuse me for not recognizing Udal ap Rhys<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Udal ap Rhys, <title>An Account of the Most Remarkable Places and Curiosities in Spain
                            and Portugal</title> (1749). When Littleton, via Barker&#8217;s letters, had previously sought information about &#8216;Price&#8217;s book
                        on Spain&#8217; Southey had forgotten that Price is an anglicised form of ap Rhys, and had mistaken the author, looking for a work
                        on Spain by his contemporary Uvedale Price (1747&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), author of an <title>Essay on the
                            Picturesque</title> (1796), rather than one by Price&#8217;s grandfather Udal ap Rhys/Uvedale Tomkyns Price (1685&#8211;1764). Thus,
                        writing to Barker on 1 May 1804 (see letter 931, of this edition) he declared that he did not know Price had written such a
                        work. On 10 December 1804 (see letter 1010), Southey again declared his ignorance of the book. According to Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, (&#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967), pp. 144&#8211;147),
                        Littleton then wrote on the blank third page of Southey&#8217;s letter, confusingly: &#8216;Uvedale Price Esq. of Foxly wrote an account
                        of Spain said to be a Plagiarism from some Spanish writer; a Pamphlet in ridicule of Whister; Fine Lady&#8217;s Catechism
                        Conversation between 2 Lap Dogs, Scipio &amp; Braganza&#8217;. Because Littleton still failed to distinguish between grandfather and
                        grandson, Southey continued to mistake the author in his letter to Barker of 29 December 1804 (letter 1010).</note> by the
                    name of Price &#8211; the gentleman put his Welsh name in the titlepage &#8211; &amp; I all along concluded that you meant the present man,
                    never recollecting that Uvedale Price is the English of what had appeared to me very uncouth for a title page not above fifty
                    years old. I have seen the book, &amp; cursorily looked it thro, only cursorily because it is my intention to buy it whenever it
                    falls in my way, &#8211; as a part of my collection. You asked if it was the work of a plagiarist &#8211; It is one of those books which does
                    not pretend to much originality &#8211; like many old travels being chiefly an account of what such &amp; such towns had been, what had
                    happened there &amp;c &#8211; things which must be compiled from other authors. It is a part of my plan to give an account of all the
                    books which have been written concerning Portugal &#8211; &amp; of their respective authors, &amp; as this gentleman seems to have been
                    a very odd fellow I pray you remember for me all the odd things you may hear of him, &amp; give me a list of his other works &amp;
                    an account of them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I see the stupid advertisement about which I most expressly cautioned <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> has taken you in. When we talked about the <hi rend="ital">re</hi>publication &amp; settled it I bade them be sure &amp; advertise it as such<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Southey&#8217;s <title>Metrical Tales and Other Poems</title> (1805) contained his contributions to the<title> Annual
                            Anthology</title> (1799&#8211;1800).</note> &#8211; it made me swear bitterly when I saw that they had neglected this, &amp; I wrote
                    immediately to desire it might be altered for the future, that people in the country might not be deceived. It was stupid in you &#8211;
                    as if you would not have known if I had been publishing any thing new. As for Madoc you &amp; I may both whistle for it. It is a
                    very common thing Senhora, for authors to be out in their reckoning. the Scotch presbyterian printers have got as drunk at Xmas as
                    if they were becoming right orthodox churchmen.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> was printed at
                        Edinburgh by the firm of <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James Ballantyne</ref> for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>.</note> there are still six or seven sheets of notes unprinted, of which
                    I have been expecting one or two every day for this week.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you bring with you the Welshmans book about the fairies?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edmund
                        Jones&#8217;s (1702&#8211;1793) <title>A Relation of Ghosts and Apparitions which Commonly Appear in the Principality of Wales</title>
                        (1767). Barker cites this work, saying &#8216;See the Rev. ____ Jones&#8217;s invaluable account of the Welsh Fairies, lately published&#8217;
                        in <title>A Welsh Story</title>, 3 vols (London, 1798), I, p. 53n.</note> &#8211; I am going to make a book for the lucre of gain in
                    which you can help me &#8211; Letters from England by a Spaniard<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England
                            by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807).</note> &#8211; which I mean to pass off as a
                    translation &#8211; so mind you keep the secret &#8211; for my name is not to appear. In this all that I know of England is to appear, &amp;
                    such a collection of stories &amp; odd things it will be, as will very likely be a profitable &#8211; certainly a very amusing &amp;
                    curious book Now you have some odd things which will help me &#8211; some Welsh anecdotes, &#8211; also about <ref target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcote</ref>
          <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> An account of the
                        prophet Joanna Southcott is given in <title>Letters from England</title>, Letter 70.</note> &#8211; the county Rovers<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Letter 44 of Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters from England</title> describes Scotch drovers and their
                        lawless ancestors, the border reivers.</note> &amp;c all which we will talk over when we meet. I want to give a compleat
                    picture of the actual state of England such as it would appear to a foreigner, indefatigable in looking about him, who had keen
                    eyes of his own, &amp; intelligent friends to aid his curiosity. When this stupid reviewing is over, &amp; the last book but one
                    is now in hand I shall begin this &#8211; as the Ways &amp; Means extraordinary for the year.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">Mrs Barebalds</ref>  Essay<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Anna Letitia Barbauld&#8217;s essay &#8216;On Romances&#8217;
                    appeared in <title>Miscellaneous Pieces in Prose</title>, ed. J. and A. L. Aikin (1773).</note> (so <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> always calls her &#8211; saying the name is a pleonasm of nakedness,) is
                    abominable for manifold reasons. so ignorant &amp; so conceited, that one might swear the authoress was not only a school
                    mistress, but a presbyterian school mistress. She ventures to talk about the history of romances of which she knows no more than
                    the living <hi rend="ital">John</hi>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Barker has written &#8216;his Ass&#8217; above the line
                        in pencil and signed her initials &#8216;MS&#8217; (Mary Slade).</note> or the dead <hi rend="ital">Peter</hi>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mary Barker has written &#8216;my pig&#8217; above the line in pencil and signed her initials &#8216;MS&#8217; (Mary
                        Slade).</note> &amp; she speaks of Sir Philip Sidney<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Philip Sidney (1554&#8211;1586;
                            <title>DNB</title>): courtier, soldier, diplomat, poet and author of the romance <title>The Countess of Pembroke&#8217;s
                            Arcadia</title> (1580, pub. 1590).</note> in a manner which shows that she hath neither eye to see, or heart to feel, nor
                    understanding to comprehend what is beautiful in invention or exquisite in language. When you come down you shall read the Arcadia
                    &#8211; it is the one book in our language which has most of Shakespere in its manner. The life &amp; death of that man were equally
                    lovely. I do not think that there ever existed a more perfect human being. The remarks of Mrs Barbauld upon the works of such a
                    man can be compared to nothing but the blasphemies of a Jew dealer in old cloaths, or the criticisms of a French barber upon
                    Shakespere.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is quite recovered. We go on as usual &#8211; one day like another &#8211; &amp; the
                    happiest lives are those which have the least variety. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter</ref> tries to walk &amp; talk. she is too forward, but thank God all seems well as yet, she has rare stout legs of her own &amp;
                    is very strong. Of her beauty the less we say the better &#8211; but she is the best tempered little creature in the world &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-01-26">Saturday 26 Jany. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>