<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1194</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2316</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                    47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1194" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1194" type="letter">
        <head>1194. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1806-06-26">26 June
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ JUN 30/ 1806<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
                    47890<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you should have heard of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southeys</ref> death, &amp; not of his will,
                    you will be in an uneasy state of hope on my account. He has left every thing from me. 2000&#163; in legacies, one estate, which I
                    suspect is a large one, to a very distant relation of his mothers, &#8211; all the rest to his <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">own brother Thomas</ref>, who is whole &amp; sole executor, &amp; residuary legatee.
                    From him I received this intelligence yesterday evening, in a civil letter, concluding with an invitation to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &amp; me to visit him at the Cottage. Brothers are nearer than Nephews, &amp; the
                    old man was right in setting me aside there; &#8211; but he should <del>xxx</del> not have given an estate to one almost a stranger, so
                    very remotely related that I never heard of him before. However I was a stranger in every thing but blood, &amp; certainly do not
                    authorize the Devil to commence a suit against him on my account.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This will vex <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>, because if he had not unaccountably offended the old
                    man, he would have had the property. He is on his way home with the Convoy &amp; may soon be expected.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey had been serving on HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi> in the West Indies, as part of the British
                        campaign to achieve naval dominance in the Caribbean during the Napoleonic wars.</note> The frigate will probably go into dock
                    for a thorough repair, &amp; in that case he hopes to obtain a months leave &amp; come down to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Palmerin &amp; the Cid are no secrets,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey published an English
                        translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title> in 1807, and his <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title>
                        was published in 1808.</note> &#8211; Neither will Espriella be so long.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> was published in 1807.</note>
                    my only motive is a wish that it may &lt;pass&gt; as a translation with those reviewers who criticise my books with no other
                    object than to injure me. I have corrected eight sheets, twelve &amp; a half make a volume. It may easily be out early in the
                    winter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Where is <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Tyler</ref> ? if I could hear that she
                    was gone the same road as the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">old Gentleman</ref> that would be good news. I cannot for the
                    life of me conceive how she can have got into the Spiritual Court. &#8211; As for trying to remove <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> into the regulars he must remain in one situation long enough to get a
                    character, before any attempt at that can be made. The truth is that I have no hope whatever of him. That farce of turning Roman
                    Catholick it seems is true. <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> saw him receive the sacrament at their Chapel on
                    Good Friday. The only way of explaining this is that he gets money from some poor Papist by pretending to be a convert. The most
                    unpleasant thoughts which ever cross my mind are when his name comes into it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not want the Reviews &#8211; but M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Madox&#8217;s<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers
                        lived in Park Street, Bristol, with his old business partner, Charles Madox (or Maddox) and his brother, John (dates unknown);
                        see Southey to Thomas Southey, 1&#8211;5 January 1806, Letter 1140.</note> name reminds me luckily of the cheeses &#8211; If it be not too
                    late provide a couple for Lisbon. &#8211; The Macclesfield letter was from a school-boy &#8211; to tell me that he admires my poems; &#8211; there
                    was better reason for his admiration than for his letter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Monthly Magazine will not be the worse for any change of Editor. <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Phillips</ref> has been the efficient conductor.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Phillips established the<title>
                            Monthly Magazine</title> in 1796. It was edited by <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">John Aikin</ref> until they
                        quarrelled in 1806, when the editorship was taken over by George Gregory (1754&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), until his death in
                        1808.</note> He has provided the foreign journals from whence the best articles are made up, &#8211; he has bespoken specific
                    articles &#8211; collected the notices, &amp; arranged the deaths &amp; marriages. The new Magazine which <del>xxx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>
                    are arranging will be better if they adhere to my advice, <del>xxx</del> exclude gratuitous matter, &amp; pay a good price for
                    good work.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Aikin became the editor of <title>The Athenaeum</title>, published by
                        Longman.</note> Heaven knows which of <ref target="people.html#PhillipsRichard">Phillips&#8217;s</ref> merry men has succeeded to
                    the doctor; but certainly it is not <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">the Count</ref>. I left him living with <ref target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref>, &amp;
                    working at his book, which I prevailed upon <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to purchase.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Burnett&#8217;s <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers, from the Earliest Times to the Close of the
                            Seventeenth Century</title> was published with Longman in 1807. This compilation formed a companion work to George Ellis&#8217;s
                            <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790, 2nd edn. 1801, 3rd edn. 1803) and Southey&#8217;s own anthology,
                        jointly edited with Bedford, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807).</note> If he continues to work as he
                    was then doing, he will be reprieved from starving as long as 100&#163; will last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of late I have been unusually liable to take cold &#8211; &amp; have indeed long expectorated habitually more phlegm than
                    is fitting. I have put the flannel waistcoat next the skin, &amp; given up the air bath. The slightest exposure to cold air makes
                    me sneeze very violently six or eight times &#8211; this violent sneezing is a family-propensity, &#8211; but not the excitability to it by
                    the slightest change of temperament. Perhaps <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> can tell me whether the expectoration
                    can be stopt by any means, &#8211; I am subject to it whether I have a cold or not.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The two Ediths <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>
                        and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>.</note> are both in good health. in October I expect son
                    or daughter.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Southeys&#8217; first son, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, was born on 11 October 1806.</note> by the time the young one is capable of bearing the voyage I suppose
                    that there will be peace, or that the fate of Portugal will be settled, but Peace is to be expected as far as I can see or
                    learn.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref> is very ill,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Susannah Rickman had suffered a miscarriage shortly after Southey left London; see Southey to Mary Barker, 26
                        May 1806, Letter 1187.</note> &#8211; better but not yet out of danger &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-06-26">Thursday. June 26. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>