<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1051</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2173</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New
                        York Public Library, 3 A.L.S. to Richard Duppa.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1051" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1051" type="letter">
        <head>1051. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Richard Duppa</ref>, <date when="1805-03-29">29 March 1805</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Richard Duppa Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 13. Poland Street/ Oxford
                        Street/ London./ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: [partial] 29<lb />Watermark: 1797<lb />MS: Berg Collection, New
                        York Public Library, 3 A.L.S. to Richard Duppa<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Duppa</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am a little surprized at <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hills</ref> pertinacity. &#8211;
                    Three years ago I received a letter signed with that name requesting that <del>my xxx</del> &lt;I&gt; would be graciously pleased
                    to beautify the Monthly Mirror with my portrait, &#8211; to which I returned a civil answer declining that honour, as I had done on
                    former occasions of the same kind. here it ended &#8211; I afterwards became acquainted with <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hill</ref>, who is the very useful dry-salter in <ref target="places.html#QueenHithe">Queen Hithe</ref>,
                    &#8211; &amp; recognised his hand-writing. but the portrait has never since been mentioned to me, &amp; I am still in the same mind,
                    that it is better to keep out of the Magazines. If you are plagued again say I have an objection to it, &amp; have
                        <del>always</del> returned the same answer to other applications.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall now look seriously to Michel Angelo, &amp; will send you the best I can.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> After Duppa&#8217;s visit to the Lakes in the summer of 1804, both <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> and Southey translated poems for Duppa&#8217;s <title>Life and Works of Michel Angelo Buonarroti</title>,
                        which was published in 1806. Wordsworth translated one sonnet; Southey three sonnets and a madrigal. A further poem, &#8216;And
                        sweet it is to see in summer time&#8217;, was a joint effort, the first four stanzas by Wordsworth, the following five by Southey.
                        See Kenneth Curry, &#8216;Uncollected Translations of Michelangelo by Wordsworth and Southey&#8217;, <title>Review of English
                            Studies</title>, 14 (1938), 193&#8211;199.</note> the Italian is not easy, but we shall make it out. &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is at this time setting out, or on his way home,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge was working as the private secretary to Sir Alexander Ball (1757&#8211;1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>), the naval officer governing Malta. He arrived back in England, in August 1806, but did not come back
                        to live in <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</note> so that, if no mishap delay him he may be expected in time
                    to lend a hand.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Spaniard, D. Manuel Alvares Espriella,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The fictional protagonist of
                        Southey&#8217;s fake travel narrative <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella. Translated from the
                            Spanish</title> (1807).</note> is a young man, of good family, travelling solely for instruction. he is come to England
                    with a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> J. a London merchant, with whom he had become acquainted in Spain, &amp; in whose family he is
                    domesticated in London. He arrives early in May &amp; travels immediately to town, where he remains for a few weeks, &amp; then
                    takes certain journeys into the country &#8211; winters in London, &amp; returns late in the spring thro the West of England to
                    Falmouth. He brings some knowledge of the language with him, is indefatigably industrious, <del>&amp;</del> has an eye for every
                    thing around him, &amp; is fortunate in having intelligent friends to assist his enquiries. in short as able a man as I can make
                    him, with high notions of family, &amp; a rooted belief in the Catholic faith, even in its absurdities, &#8211; which weakness is not
                    inconsistent with his general talents, if you conceive that his fathers <hi rend="ital">solar</hi> (family seat) is in a remote
                    province, &amp; not in a town, &#8211; &amp; that he is affectionately attached to his Confessor.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Such a man when he feels the present degradation of his own country, looks with some pleasure to the symptoms of
                    decline in this. you may conceive him familiar with the pictures of Titian, Rubens, &amp; the Spanish Masters Velasquez &amp;
                    Murillo &#8211; &amp; Mengo<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> All Old Masters from Italy or artists influenced by Italian
                        painting: Vecellio Tiziano (Titian) (1490&#8211;1576), Pieter Pauwel Rubens (1577&#8211;1640), Diego Vel&#225;zquez (1599&#8211;1660), Bartolom&#233;
                        Esteban Murillo (1617&#8211;1682), Fray Juan Bautista Maino (Mayno) (1581&#8211;1649).</note> if he be worth thinking of &#8211; for he would
                    have seen the collections at Madrid &amp; the Escurial.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The palace, monastery and museum
                        built for the Spanish king, Phillip II (1527&#8211;1598), near Madrid.</note> In literature he knows that of his own country well,
                    which, as far as he can <del>know</del> learn any thing of English literature, excels it because it being impossible that he can
                    appreciate Shakespere &amp; Milton &amp; our few first rates &#8211; the rest are really very scurvy cattle. What he most abominates
                    here (except our heresy) is the spirit of trading which has poisoned every thing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will be impossible to finish this book without going to London. <del>xxx</del> it must contain something of <hi rend="ital">travels</hi>, which I can make sufficiently dramatic. there are certain papers of mine in town which will furnish
                    some sketches for this part, which my memory will not; &amp; also it is necessary that some little matter-of-fact-ery appear, from
                    topographical histories &#8211; just enough to give an appearance of verisimilitude to the whole. Now &amp; then those dull deadlily
                    dull books, which are the disgrace of English literature contain an historical anecdote, or notice of some antiquarian local
                    custom, which would look well if set in a better place. But all the thinking-part of the business the satire, &amp; the philosophy
                    &amp; the speculation, can be done here. I have begun many letters. &amp; finished but few, &#8211; leaving off when the vein is for the
                    time expended. This method saves time &#8211; the first &#8211; which is mere travelling I will send by way of the Emperor of the Franks<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A nickname for the Speaker of the House of Commons, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>, who had the power to frank mail. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, his
                        secretary, used this facility on Southey&#8217;s behalf.</note> that you may see <del>xx</del> whether or no I have looked thro
                    Spanish spectacles. It is a very likely speculation to attract notice &amp; to succeed &#8211; for there will be a precious mystery of
                    iniquity laid open, &amp; I expect never to be troubled with bile after the thorough discharge, as long <del>x</del> as I live. &#8211;
                    The letters are written home &#8211; to father mother or brother.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By this time you have &#8211; or ought to have &#8211; my book.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> what I began to think was gone to the bottom of the sea by way of getting rid of an
                    edition speedily. I wrote to <ref>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Smith</ref> three weeks ago, thinking it was then ready for delivery.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We go on well. I never go beyond the premises tho our weather has been delightful, <del>xx xxx</del> more so
                    perhaps than ever winter was remembered here. the snow has never covered the valley half an hour during the whole winter. <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref> is not yet returned.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> She was visiting the family of Dr Peter Crompton (dates unknown) of Eton House, Liverpool, a radical reformer who supported
                            <ref target="people.html#ThelwallJohn">John Thelwall</ref> in the 1790s and who contested elections at Nottingham (1796,
                        1807, 1812), Preston (1818) and Liverpool (1820).</note> We live as compleatly without society as <del>if</del> we could do in
                        Kamschatka,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Kamchatka: a peninsula in the East Asian part of Russia, proverbial for
                        cold and isolation.</note> &amp; feel it as little as you may imagine. Summer is coming on &amp; then there will be too much
                    of it. I get on steadily with my Opus Majus the history,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;,
                        which was never completed.</note> &amp; only wish that I were rich enough never to do any task work, <del>&amp;</del>
                    sometimes to have an amanuensis at hand, &amp; to buy all the books which would be useful to me. As for family events the most
                    important is that Johnny Cockbain<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Keswick tailor (dates unknown).</note> has made me a
                    new pair of pantaloons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me at Stockwell<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Stockwell Park, Surrey was the home of <ref target="people.html#SmithThomasWoodruffe">Thomas Woodroffe Smith</ref>.</note> &#8211; &amp; to <ref target="people.html#EdridgePainter">Edridge</ref> when you see him. I expect to hear from <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &amp; from every body else when they have had time to cut open the leaves of
                    Madoc. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> was instructed to send the book to you &#8211; Tomkins<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Tomkins (1743&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>): writing-master and calligrapher, who carried out
                        commissions for decorative book titles of luxury publications, including Southey&#8217;s <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Sharon</ref> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>. You can perhaps learn whether they have been delivered that if not I may
                    renew my instruction. All here desire to be remembered &#8211; We talk of you very often &amp; wish you were here again</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-03-29">March 29. 1805</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>