<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1153</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2275</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 20&#8211;23 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1153" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1153" type="letter">
        <head>1153. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1806-02-08">8 February
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850), III, pp. 20&#8211;23 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> That I have been thinking of you, will appear by the half letter written last June, &#8211; which I send now, because it
                    will save me the trouble of replicating some of its contents.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Nicholas
                        Lightfoot, [June 1805], Letter 1077.</note> The pencil too goes at last to its destination, &#8211; this very evening <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has informed me that he is appointed Under Secretary of State in the Home Office
                    &#8211; &amp; <del>xxx xxx</del> the first use I make of his privileges is to frank this large enclosure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You tell me to write as an egotist, &amp; I am well disposed so to do, for what &lt;else&gt; is it that gives
                    private letters their <del>value?</del> greatest value <del>than</del> &lt;but&gt; the information they bring us of those for whom
                    we are interested? &#8211; I saw your marriage in the papers<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux
                        (b. 1778) in 1801.</note> &#8211; &amp; perhaps the reason why my letter has remained so long unfinished in my desk is a sort of
                    fear least I should mention it &#8211; after death &lt;might&gt; have dissolved it &#8211; a sort of superstitious feeling to which I am
                    subject. I wish you &#8211; being a father myself &#8211; as large a family &#8211; as you can comfortably <del>suppor</del> bring up, &#8211; &amp; if
                    you are not provided with a godfather upon the next occasion I beg you to accept of me &#8211; as an old &amp; very affectionate friend;
                    &#8211; tis a <del>sort</del> voluntary kind of relationship in which it would gratify me to stand to a child of yours, &amp; which I
                    should consider as a religious pledge on my part for any useful <del>xxx</del> kind &lt;&amp; fatherly&gt; offices which it might
                    ever happen to be in my power to perform.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have for some time looked on with pleasure to the hope of seeing you in the course of next autumn, when, in all
                    probability if the situation abroad do not prevent me, I shall once more visit Portugal, not for healths sake, but to collect the
                    last materials for my history, &amp; to visit those parts of the kingdom which I have not yet seen.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey never returned to Portugal after his second residence there in 1800&#8211;1801, and his planned &#8216;History of
                        Portugal&#8217; was never completed.</note> In this case my way will lie thro Devonshire, &amp; I will stop a day or two at Crediton
                    &amp; talk over old times.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You enquire of the wreck of the <ref target="people.html#Sewardfamily">Seward</ref> family &#8211; a name as dear to my
                    inmost heart as it can <del>xxx</del> be to yours. No change has taken place among them for some years, as I understand from <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>, who was my guest here this <del>summer</del> autumn before last, &amp; with
                    whom I have an occasional correspondence. The two sisters still live on within sight of Worcester, where I saw them in 1798. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Severne had been deranged in her intellect &#8211; but had recovered, &#8211; &amp; her good husband was doing well in
                    the world.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#Sewardfamily">Francis Severn</ref> (1751&#8211;1828), Rector
                        of Kyre and Abberley, Worcestershire, was married to a sister of <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund
                        Seward</ref>.</note> If I remember right in the last letter you received from me poor Williams fate was mentioned.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#Sewardfamily">William Seward</ref>, a lawyer, based in Ledbury,
                        Herefordshire, who shot himself.</note> he destroyed himself, &#8211; chiefly it was supposed from domestic uneasiness &#8211; heightened
                    by the irreparable loss of two such brothers. Duppa has an admirable likeness of <ref target="people.html#Sewardfamily">John
                        Seward</ref> &#8211; I would give half I am worth for such a one of our dear <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund</ref> &#8211;
                    All the letters which he ever wrote to me are tied up together &#8211; I have never had the heart to open them, &amp; probably never
                    shall.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My school &amp; college friends still continue to be the persons with whom I chiefly associate when I get into the
                    world, &amp; with whom I keep up the closest association from this distance. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &#8211; <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> &#8211; .
                        <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> was with me a few months ago &#8211; he had been in Poland in the family of
                    Count Zamoyski,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Count Stanis&#322;aw Kostka Zamoyski (1775&#8211;1856), a Polish nobleman,
                        politician, and patron of arts.</note> living among Princes &amp; Princesses, &amp; <del>was</del> returned to England in the
                    hope of recovering from a disease of low spirits little less than madness. He mended here, &amp; is now in London, with some hope
                    &amp; some chance of getting a comfortable situation in some public office. &#8211; Poor <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> dropt down in an apoplectic fit last summer &#8211; I had not for many years seen him, nor indeed did I much wish it,
                    for his life was very irregular, &amp; it is not desirable to meet an old friend retaining all the form &amp; external of the
                    person you loved yet inwardly so changed. But his death gave me a shock, for he was a man whom it is impossible to
                        <del>recall</del> remember without affection. <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref> is the only old
                    acquaintance whom I have purposely dropt, because he grew purse-proud &amp; had no more heart in him than &lt;is in&gt; an empty
                    nutshell. &#8211; I heard accidentally of little Daubenys death, in consequence of his irregular life at Corpus.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Perhaps Frederick Daubeny (c. 1776-?), son of George Daubeny (1742&#8211;1806), a Bristol plantation owner and
                        MP.</note> Cad. Rogers sent me a friendly message lately, he is as you perhaps know a fellow at Balliol, &amp; I am sorry to
                    add, affects to be a very strict disciplinarian.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Cooke Rogers (b. c. 1777), the son
                        of Edward Rogers of St Asaph. A contemporary of Southey&#8217;s at Balliol, nicknamed by him &#8216;Cadwallader&#8217;, he went on to become a
                        Fellow and Bursar of the College.</note> Scobill I hear keeps a school at Henley<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        George Pender Scobell (1775?-1837). A fellow student at Balliol (graduating BA in 1795) and later a clergyman, Scobell was
                        master of the grammar school at Henley-on-Thames.</note> &#8211; I heard all my College news from a Scotchman of a later generation
                    than <del>we were</del> ours, who brought letters from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> here last
                    spring. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Poole<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> was in a sad state of nervous
                    imbecillity &#8211; I past thro Oxford two years ago &amp; walked thro the town at four o clock in the morning &#8211; the place never
                    appeared to me half so beautiful. I looked up at my old windows, &amp; as you may well suppose felt as most people do when they
                    think of what changes time brings about.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you have seen, or should see the Annual Review you may like to know that I have borne a great part in it thus
                    far, &#8211; &amp; I may refer you for the state of my opinions to the Reviewals of the Periodical Account of the Baptist Mission &#8211; Vol.
                    1. &#8211; of Malthus&#8217;s Essay on Population, Miles&#8217;s Hist. of the Methodists, &amp; the Transactions of the Missionary Society &#8211; Vol. 2
                    &amp; 3 &#8211; &amp; the Report of the Society for the Suppression of Vice Vol. 3. In other articles you may trace me from
                    recollections of your own, by family likeness, by a knowledge of Spanish literature &#8211; &amp; by a love of liberty &amp; literature
                    freely &amp; warmly expressed.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had been reviewing for the <title>Annual
                            Review</title> since it began. He reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803): Martin Sauer (dates
                        unknown), <title>An Account of a Geographical and Astronomical Expedition to the Northern Parts of Russia Performed by Joseph
                            Billings in the Years 1785&#8211;1796</title> (1802), 7&#8211;17; Alexander Mackenzie (1763/4&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Voyages from Montreal, on the River St Laurence, through the Continent of North America, to the Frozen and Pacific
                            Oceans in the Years 1789 and 1793</title> (1802), 18&#8211;30; Frederick Augustus Fischer (1771&#8211;1829), <title>Travels in Spain
                            in 1797 and 1798</title> (1802), 35&#8211;43; Giuseppi Acerbi (1773&#8211;1846), <title>Travels through Sweden, Finland and Lapland,
                            to the North Cape, in the Years 1798 and 1799</title> (1802), 45&#8211;56; Maria Guthrie (dates unknown), <title>A Tour
                            Performed in the Years 1795&#8211;6, through the Taurida, or Crimea</title> (1802), 62&#8211;66; Peter Simon Pallas (1741&#8211;1811),
                            <title>Travels through the Southern Provinces of the Russian Empire, in the Years 1793 and 1794</title> (1802), 66&#8211;73;
                        Guillaume Antoine Olivier (1756&#8211;1814), <title>Travels in the Ottoman Empire, Egypt and Persia</title> (1801), 89&#8211;101;
                            <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (1800&#8211;1801), 207&#8211;218; Augustin Louis Josse
                        (1763&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), <title>El Tesoro Espanol o Biblioteca Portatil Espanola</title> (1802), 557&#8211;566; Henry Kett
                        (1761&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Elements of General Knowledge, Introductory to Useful Books in the Principal Branches
                            of Literature and Science</title> (1802), 579&#8211;584; Henri Louis Cain (1728&#8211;1778), <title>Memoires de Henri Louis Le
                            Kain</title> (1801), 595&#8211;599; William Coxe (1748&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of Horatio, Lord
                            Walpole</title> (1802), 599&#8211;601; Francis Wrangham (1769&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems</title> (1802), 655&#8211;657;
                        Walter Savage Landor, <title>Poetry by the Author of Gebir</title> (1802), 663&#8211;666; Pierre Lambinet (1742&#8211;1813),
                            <title>Recherche Historiques, Litteraires et Critiques sur l&#8217;Origine de l&#8217;Imprimerie</title> (1799), 704&#8211;711. Southey
                        reviewed, in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804): James Burney, <title>A Chronological History of the
                            Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean ... Illustrated with Charts</title> (Vol. 1; 1803), 3&#8211;12; James Stanier
                        Clarke (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Progress of Maritime Discovery, from the Earliest Period to the Close of
                            the Eighteenth Century, Forming an Extensive System of Hydrography</title> (1803), 12&#8211;20; James Curtis (dates unknown),
                            <title>A Journal of Travels in Barbary in 1801 ... With Observations on the Gum Trade of Senegal</title> (1803), 20&#8211;23;
                        Louis Maria Joseph, Count O&#8217;Hier de Grandpr&#233; (1761&#8211;1846), <title>A Voyage in the Indian Ocean, and to Bengal ... To Which is
                            Added a Voyage in the Red Sea, Including a Description of Mocha, and of the Trade of the Arabs of Yemen</title> (1803),
                        48&#8211;54; John Davis (1774&#8211;1854), <title>Travels of Four Years and a Half in the United States of America, During 1798, 1799,
                            1800, 1801, and 1802</title> (1803), 54&#8211;59; Lockhart Muirhead (dates unknown), <title>Journals of Travels in Parts of the
                            Late Austrian Low Countries, France, the Pays de Vaud and Tuscany in 1787 and 1789</title> (1803), 59&#8211;63; Charles William
                        Doyle (1770&#8211;1842), <title>A Non-Military Journal; Or, Observations Made in Egypt, by an Officer upon the Staff of the British
                            Army: Describing the Country, its Inhabitants, their Manners and Customs</title> (1803), 63&#8211;66; William Wittman (fl.
                        1799&#8211;1804), <title>Travels in Turkey, Asia Minor, Syria, and Across the Desert into Egypt During the Years 1799, 1800, and
                            1801, in Company with the Turkish Army and the British Military Mission</title> (1803), 66&#8211;71; [Ann Blund (dates
                        unknown)], <title>Journal of a Short Excursion among the Swiss Landscapes</title> (1803), 79&#8211;80; Isaac King (dates unknown),
                            <title>Letters from France</title> (1803), 88&#8211;90; <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the Society for
                            the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London, 1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity
                            of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public Support</title> (1803), 187;<title> Transactions of the Missionary
                            Society</title> (Vol. 1, 1803), 189&#8211;201; William Myles (1756&#8211;1828), <title>A Chronological History of the People called
                            Methodists ... With an Appendix, Containing Two Lists of the Itinerant Preachers ... With the Last Will and Testament of
                            the Rev. J. Wesley</title> (1803), 201&#8211;213; Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the
                            Principle of Population, as it Affects the Future Improvement of Society; with Remarks on the Speculations of W. Godwin,
                            M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803), 292&#8211;301; William Godwin, <title>Life of Geoffrey Chaucer ... Including
                            Memoirs of ... John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster; with Sketches of the Manners, Opinions, Arts and Literature of England in
                            the Fourteenth Century</title> (1803), 462&#8211;473; George Mason (1735&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Richard
                            Earl Howe</title> (1803), 499&#8211;501; Joseph Ritson (1752&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Ancient Engleish Metrical
                            Romancee&#776;s</title> (1802), 515&#8211;533; George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (3rd edn 1803),
                        538&#8211;542; Richard Mant (1776&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Poetical Works of the Late Thomas Warton</title> (1802),
                        543&#8211;546; William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life and Posthumous Writings of William Cowper,
                            Esq.</title> (1803), 457&#8211;462; Peter Bayley (bap. 1778&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems</title> (1803), 546&#8211;552;
                        Henry Kirke White, <title>Clifton Grove, a Sketch in Verse, with other Poems</title> (1803), 552&#8211;554; Josiah Walker (d. 1831),
                            <title>The Defence of Order, a Poem</title> (1803), 557; <title>The Inquiry. Part 1</title>, 557&#8211;558; William Barnes
                        Rhodes (1772&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Epigrams</title> (1803), 558; James Woodhouse (bap. 1735&#8211;1820), <title>Norbury
                            Park, a Poem with Several Others Written on Various Occasions</title> (1803), 558; Henry William Tytler (1752/3&#8211;1808),
                            <title>The Voyage Home from the Cape of Good Hope</title> (1803), 559; Luke Booker (1762&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Calista, or a Picture of Modern Life, a Poem</title> (1803), 564; D. A. G. B. Cassano (dates unknown), <title>Il
                            Fiore della Poesia Italiana</title> (1802), 562&#8211;563; Percy Clinton Sydney, 6th Viscount Strangford (1780&#8211;1855;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poems from the Portuguese of Luis de Camoens</title> (1803), 569&#8211;577; William Lisle Bowles,
                            <title>The Picture, Verses Suggested by a Magnificent Landscape of Rubens</title> (1803), 582; John Peter Roberdeau (bap.
                        1754&#8211;1815), <title>Fugitive Verse and Prose</title> (1803), 582&#8211;583; George Owen Cambridge (d. 1841), <title>Works of Richard
                            Owen Cambridge, Esq. with an Account of his Life and Character</title> (1803), 583&#8211;585; Anne-Louise-Germaine Necker,
                        Baroness de Sta&#235;l-Holstein (1766&#8211;1817), <title>A Treatise of Ancient and Modern Literature</title> (tr. 1803), 643&#8211;650;
                            <title>Asiatic Researches; or Transactions of the Society Instituted in Bengal for Enquiring into the History and
                            Antiquities, the Arts, Science and Literature of Asia</title> (vol. VII, 1803), 898&#8211;908. Southey reviewed, in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805): John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of Travels
                            into the Interior of Southern Africa, in the years 1797 and 1798, including Observations on the Geology &amp; Geography,
                            the Natural History ... and Sketches of the Various Tribes Surrounding the Cape of Good Hope</title>, Vol. II (1804),
                        22&#8211;33; Robert Percival (1765&#8211;1826), <title>An Account of the Cape of Good Hope</title> (1804), 34&#8211;41; Daniel Mackinnen
                        (1767&#8211;1830), <title>A Tour Through the British West Indies, in the years 1802 and 1803 giving a Particular Account of the
                            Bahama Islands</title> (1804), 50&#8211;56; John Barrow, <title>Travels in China: Containing Descriptions, Observations and
                            Comparisons Made and Collected in the Course of a Short Residence at the Imperial Palace of Yuen-min-yuen, and on a
                            Subsequent Journey from Pekin to Canton</title> (1804), 69&#8211;83; <title>Sir John Froissart&#8217;s Chronicles of England, France,
                            and the Adjoining Countries, from the Latter Part of the Reign of Edward II to the Coronation of Henry IV</title>, trans.
                        Thomas Johnes (1748&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>) (1804), 189&#8211;194; George Heriot (1766&#8211;1844), <title>The History of Canada, From
                            its First Discovery: Comprehending an Account of the Original Establishment of the Colony of Louisiana</title>, 194&#8211;197;
                            <title>Part the First of An Address to the Public from the Society for the Suppression of Vice, Instituted, in London,
                            1802, Setting Forth, with a List of the Members, the Utility and Necessity of such an Institution, and its Claim to Public
                            Support</title> (1803), 225&#8211;231; Edward Ledwich (1738&#8211;1823), <title>The Antiquities of Ireland</title> (1804), 398&#8211;413;
                            <title>Original Correspondence of Jean Jacques Rousseau, with Mad. La Tour de Franqueville and M. Du Peyrou</title>
                        (1804), 485&#8211;488; Anna Seward, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Dr. Darwin, ... with Anecdotes of his Friends and Criticisms on
                            his Writings</title> (1804), 488&#8211;93; David Irving (1778&#8211;1850),<title> The Lives of the Scotish Poets; with Preliminary
                            Dissertations on the Literary History of Scotland and the Early Scotish Drama</title> (1804), 493&#8211;499; Walter Scott,
                            <title>Sir Tristram: A Metrical Romance by Thomas of Ercildoune</title> (1804), 555&#8211;563; Charles Abraham Elton
                        (1778&#8211;1853), <title>Poems</title> (1804), 564&#8211;565; William Day (dates unknown), <title>The Shepherd&#8217;s Boy: being Pastoral
                            Tales</title> (1804), 567&#8211;568; E. Warren (dates unknown), <title>The Poet&#8217;s Day, or, Imagination&#8217;s Ramble</title> (1804),
                        568; <title>Cupid turned Volunteer: in a Series of Prints, Designed by her Royal Highness the Princess Elizabeth; and Engraved
                            by W. N. Gardiner, B.A., with Poetical Illustrations by T. P</title> [Thomas Park (1758/9&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>)]
                        (1804), 568&#8211;580; Thomas Green Fessenden (1771&#8211;1837), <title>Original Poems</title> (1804), 571; John Blair Linn (1777&#8211;1805),
                            <title>The Powers of Genius</title> (1801), 571; Thomas Clio Rickman (1761&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Ode in
                            Celebration of the Emancipation of the Blacks of Saint Domingo, November 29, 1803</title> (1804), 572; Robert Bloomfield,
                            <title>Good Tidings</title> (1804), 574; William Robert Spencer (1770&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Year of
                            Sorrow</title> (1804), 574&#8211;575; <title>British Purity: or, the World we Live in. A Poetic Tale, of Two Centuries&#8230;By Lory
                            Lucian and Jerry Juvenal, &#8230; Assisted by S. Scriblerus, etc.</title> [pseud.] (1804), 575; William Falconer (1732&#8211;1769),
                            <title>The Shipwreck</title>, (1804), ed., James Stanier Clarke (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), 577&#8211;580; William Tooke
                        (1777&#8211;1863), ed., <title>The Poetical Works of Charles Churchill: with Explanatory Notes and an Authentic Account of his
                            Life</title> (1804), 580&#8211;585; J. Amphlett (dates unknown), <title>Invasion: a Descriptive and Satirical Poem</title>
                        (1804), 585; Joseph Jefferson (1766&#8211;1824), <title>Horae Poetic&#230;. Poems, Sacred, Moral and Descriptive</title> (1804), 586&#8211;587;
                        Alexander Campbell (1764&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Grampians Desolate, a Poem in Six Books</title> (1804),
                        587&#8211;591; William Crowe (bap. 1745, d. 1829; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lewesdon Hill</title> (1804), 593&#8211;594; John Finlay
                        (1782&#8211;1810), <title>Wallace, or, The Vale of Ellerslie, and other Poems</title> (1804), 594&#8211;596; Jessie Stewart (dates
                        unknown), <title>Ode to Dr. Thomas Percy</title> (1804), 597; John Belfour (1768&#8211;1842), <title>Fables on Subjects Connected
                            with Literature. Imitated from the Spanish of Don Tomas de Yriarte</title> (1804), 597&#8211;598; <title>Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society</title> (1804), 621&#8211;634; Edward Davies (1756&#8211;1831), <title>Celtic Researches, on the Origin,
                            Traditions, &amp; Language, of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory Sketches, on Primitive Society</title> (1804),
                        634&#8211;644; [Anon.] <title>No Slaves &#8211; No Sugar: Containing New and Irresistible Arguments in Favour of the African Trade by a
                            Liverpool Merchant</title> (1804), 644&#8211;648; William Tennant (1758&#8211;1813), <title>Indian Recreations, Consisting Chiefly of
                            Strictures on the Domestic and Rural Economy of the Mahommedans and Hindoos</title> (1803), 658&#8211;670; John Gardiner (fl.
                        1758&#8211;1792), <title>Essays Literary, Political and Economical</title> (1804), 670&#8211;674; Richard Duppa, <title>Heads from the
                            Fresco Pictures of Raffaele in the Vatican</title> (1802), 918&#8211;923. Southey reviewed in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1805</title>, 4 (1806): James Bruce (1730&#8211;1794;<title> DNB), Travels to Discover the Source of the Nile in the Years
                            1768&#8211;73</title> (2nd edn, 1804&#8211;1805), 2&#8211;16; Thomas Lindley (dates unknown), <title>Narrative of a Voyage to Brazil; ...
                            with General Sketches of the Country ..., and a Description of the City and Provinces of St. Salvadore and Porto
                            Seguro</title> (1805), 27&#8211;32; Joseph Skinner (dates unknown), <title>The Present State of Peru, Comprising its Geography,
                            Topography, Natural History, Mineralogy, Commerce, the Customs and Manners of its Inhabitants; Embellished by ...
                            Engravings of Costumes</title> (1805), 49&#8211;60; John Griffiths (dates unknown), <title>Travels in Europe, Asia Minor and
                            Arabia</title> (1805), 67&#8211;77; James Stanier Clarke (1765?&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Naufragia, or, Historical
                            Memoirs of Shipwrecks</title> (Vol. 1; 1805), 99&#8211;100; Charles Franc&#807;ois Dominique de Villers (1765&#8211;1815), <title>An Essay
                            on the Spirit and Influence of the Reformation of Luther</title> (1805), trans. B Lambert (dates unknown), 177&#8211;187;
                        William Roscoe, <title>The Life of Pope Leo X, Son of Lorenzo de Medici</title> (1805), 449&#8211;467; Arthur Cayley (1776&#8211;1848),
                            <title>The Life of Sir Walter Ralegh</title> (1805), 477&#8211;483; Dieudonn&#233; Thi&#233;bault (1733&#8211;1807), <title>Original Anecdotes
                            of Frederic the Second, King of Prussia, and of his Family, his Court, his Ministers, his Academies, and his Literary
                            Friends: Collected During a Familiar Intercourse of Twenty Years with that Prince</title> (1805), 488&#8211;495; William Parr
                        Greswell (bap. 1765&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of Angelus Politianus, Joannes Picus of Mirandula, Actius
                            Sincerus Sannazarius, Petrus Bembus, Hieronymus Fracastorius, Marcus Antonius Flaminius, and the Amalthei: Translations
                            from their Poetical Works: and Notes and Observations Concerning Other Literary Characters of the Fifteenth and Sixteenth
                            Centuries</title> (1805), 509&#8211;515; George Ellis, <title>Specimens of Early English Metrical Romances</title> (1805),
                        536&#8211;544; Henry John Todd (bap. 1763&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of Edmund Spenser</title> (1805), 544&#8211;555;
                        William Lisle Bowles, <title>The Spirit of Discovery</title> (1804), 568&#8211;573; William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Ballads; Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals, with Prints, Designed and Engraved by William Blake</title>
                        (1805), 575&#8211;576; John Hoppner (1758&#8211;1810), <title>Oriental Tales: Translated into English Verse</title> (1805), 576&#8211;578;
                        Francis Burroughs (dates unknown), <title>A Poetical Epistle to James Barry Esq.</title> (1805), 578&#8211;579; Vincenzo Monti
                        (1754&#8211;1828), <title>Penance of Hugo: A Vision</title> (1805), trans. Henry Boyd (1748/9&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>), 581&#8211;588;
                        James Grahame (1765&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Sabbath</title> (1805), 588&#8211;591; Sir Martin Archer Shee (1769&#8211;1850;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rhymes on Art, or, The Remonstrance of a Painter</title> (1805), 592&#8211;596; Samuel Whitchurch,
                        (dates unknown), <title>Hispaniola, a Poem</title> (1804), 596&#8211;597; Matthew Rolleston (dates unknown), <title>The
                            Anti-Corsican, A Poem</title> (1805), 597&#8211;598; Charles Grant, Baron Glenelg (1778&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Poem
                            on the Restoration of Learning in the East</title> (1805), 598; Edward Coxe (dates unknown), <title>Miscellaneous
                            Poetry</title> (1805), 598&#8211;600; Malcolm Laing (1762&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Poems of Ossian, Containing the
                            Poetical Works of James Macpherson in Prose and Verse, with Notes and Illustrations</title> (1805), 615&#8211;620; Archibald
                        Macdonald (1739&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Some of Ossian&#8217;s Lesser Poems Rendered into Verse [from Macpherson]; with a
                            Preliminary Discourse, in Answer to Mr. Laing&#8217;s Critical and Historical Dissertation on the Antiquity of Ossian&#8217;s
                            Poems</title> (1805), 620; Philip Massinger (1583&#8211;1640; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Plays</title> (1805), ed. William
                        Gifford, 625&#8211;634; Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729&#8211;1781), <title>Nathan the Wise; a Dramatic Poem in Five Acts</title> (1805),
                        trans. William Taylor, 634&#8211;639; John Collett (dates unknown), <title>Sacred Dramas: Intended Chiefly for Young Persons</title>
                        (1805), 639; Henry Mackenzie (1745&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Report of the Committee of the Highland Society of
                            Scotland, Appointed to Inquire into the Nature and Authenticity of the Poems of Ossian</title> (1805), 679&#8211;699; Hannah
                        More, <title>Hints Towards Forming the Character of a Young Princess</title> (1805), 708&#8211;713; Joseph Lancaster (1778&#8211;1838),
                            <title>Improvements in Education as it Respects the Industrious Classes of the Community</title> (3rd edn, 1805), 732&#8211;736;
                        Samuel Jackson Pratt [pseud. Courtney Melmoth] (1749&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Harvest-home: Consisting of
                            Supplementary Gleanings, Original Dramas and Poems, Contributions of Literary Friends and Select Re-publications</title>
                        (1805), 736&#8211;738; William Henry Ireland (1775&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Confessions of William Henry Ireland
                            Containing the Particulars of his Fabrication of the Shakespeare Manuscripts</title> (1805), 743&#8211;745.</note> I was
                    ministerial under Addington<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757&#8211;1844;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1801&#8211;1804.</note> &#8211; regarded his successor<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> with the utmost indignation &amp;
                    contempt &#8211; &amp; am exceedingly well pleased at the present changes. Time you say moderates opinions as it mellows wine. my views
                    &amp; hopes are certainly altered, tho the heart &amp; soul of my <del>xxx</del> wishes continues the same. It is the world that
                    has changed &#8211; not I. I look the same way in the afternoon that I did in the morning &#8211; but sunset &amp; sunrise make a different
                    scene. If I regret any thing in my own life it is that I <hi rend="ital">could</hi> not take orders, for of all ways of life, that
                    would have best accorded with my nature &#8211; but I could not get in at the door. Now &#8211; without being in communion with any particular
                    church or sect &#8211; I believe in Christ Jesus as the true teacher, &amp; derive my best hopes from that belief. It will be however
                    necessary for me, for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughters</ref> sake to join some church &#8211; &amp; that will be
                    the established one, &#8211; I like every thing belonging to it except its articles.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the
                        Church of England the 39 Articles of Religion, of 1563, establish the basis of belief.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In other respects time has not much altered me &#8211; I am as thin as ever, &amp; to the full as noisy, &#8211; making a noise
                    in any way whatever is an animal pleasure with me, &amp; the louder it is the better. Do you remember the round hole at the top of
                    the staircase, opposite your door?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is daily expected to return from Malta where he has
                    been now two years for his health.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge was in the process of returning from Malta
                        via the continent and reached England in August 1806.</note> I inhabit the same house with his wife &amp; children, &#8211; perhaps
                    the very finest single spot in England. We overlook Keswick Lake, have the Lake of Bassenthwaite in the distance on the other
                    side, &amp; <ref target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> behind us. But we only sojourn here for a time &#8211; I may perhaps be
                    destined to pass some years in Portugal, which indeed is my wish, &#8211; or if otherwise must ultimately remove to the neighbourhood of
                    London, for the sake of public libraries. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; My dislike was not to schoolmasters &#8211; but to the Rod &#8211; which I dare warrant you do not make much use of. &#8211; Here
                    is a long letter &#8211; &amp; <del>xxx xxx</del> you have in it as many great <hi rend="ital">I&#8217;s</hi> as your heart could wish &#8211; It
                    will give me much pleasure to hear again from you &#8211; &amp; to know that your family is increased. If I cannot be <del>xxx</del>
                    godfather now let me put in a claim in time for the next occasion, but I hope you will write to tell me that three things have
                    been promised &amp; vowed in <hi rend="ital">my</hi> name by proxy &#8211; No man can more safely talk of defying the World the flesh
                    &amp; the Devil &#8211; with the World my pursuits are little akin &#8211; the flesh &amp; I quarrelled long ago &amp; I have been nothing but
                    skin &amp; bones ever since &#8211; &amp; as for the Devil I have made more ballads in his abuse than any body before me.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you Lightfoot!</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1806-02-08">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 8. 1806.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>