<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1703</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2825</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters
                            of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 519&#8211;521.Dating note: Southey dates the letter
                        &#8216;Oct 29. 1809&#8217; but this must be an error as it is postmarked 26 October 1809. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1703" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1703" type="letter">
        <head>1703. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1809-10-26">[c. 26 October 1809]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r.</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmarks: E/ OCT 26/ 1809; [partial]
                        OCT 26/ 1809 EV<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c. 24<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters
                            of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 519&#8211;521.<lb />Dating note: Southey dates the letter
                        &#8216;Oct 29. 1809&#8217; but this must be an error as it is postmarked 26 October 1809. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I called Captain Bligh<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Bligh (1754&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>), naval
                        officer, and later colonial governor, who was captain of HMS <hi rend="ital">Bounty</hi> when the ship&#8217;s crew mutinied off
                        Tahiti in the South Pacific in 1789.</note>
          <hi rend="ital">notorious</hi> as the only way in which I could imply that he was a thorough rascal. It was an act of much
                    self-controul not to accompany the sentence with a bitter sarcasm, saying the Missionaries had a lucky escape, for his unendurable
                    tyranny might have driven more Christians to desperation.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey made reference to Bligh
                        in his review of <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South Sea Islands</title> in the <title>Quarterly
                            Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 24&#8211;61 (25): &#8216;A mission to these islands was proposed; adventurers volunteered for the
                        service; the notorious Capt. Bligh, who was then about to return to Taheite for the bread-fruit-tree, offered to take them out
                        gratuitously, and the Lords of the Admiralty gave their consent: but when it came to the point, they who had offered
                        themselves to the work, and been a year under tuition for the purpose, shrunk back.&#8217;</note> I know a great deal of that affair
                    of the Bounty from <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">James Losh</ref> who with Professor Christian<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Edward Christian (bap. 1758&#8211;1823), jurist and magistrate, who published the minutes of the court martial of
                        the recaptured <hi rend="ital">Bounty</hi> mutineers in 1794, in which he presented their motives sympathetically, so
                        provoking a public debate with Bligh (<title>DNB</title>).</note> (poor Fletcher C.s<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Fletcher Christian (1764&#8211;1793?; <title>DNB</title>), mutineer considered the ringleader of the rebellion on HMS <hi rend="ital">Bounty</hi>.</note> brother) went to the mutineers that were brought home, &amp; collected their testimony
                    concerning all the circumstances which led to it. I know too, or rather have every reason to believe that Fletcher C. was within
                    these few years in England &amp; at his fathers house, &#8211; an interesting circumstance in such a history, &amp; one which I hardly
                    ought to mention, &#8211; so do not you let it get abroad.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> There were several rumours that
                        Fletcher Christian had returned to visit his relatives in Cumberland after the mutiny, but the account of John Adams (alias
                        Alexander Smith; 1768?&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), the only surviving mutineer, that he died on Pitcairn Island where the <hi rend="ital">Bounty</hi> finished its voyage, is the generally accepted one.</note> For <del>xxx xxx</del> &lt;tho&gt; the
                    Admiralty would be very sorry to hang him, some rascal or other would gladly enough apprehend him for the price of blood, &amp;
                    hung of course he would be; <del>tho</del> &lt;but&gt; if every man had his due Bligh would have had the halter instead of the
                    poor fellows whom we brought from Taheite. Is not that a sad story of Stewart &amp; the Taheitian Girl?&#8211; the verses are by a young
                    banker of Birmingham by name James,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#JamesPaulMoon">Paul Moon James</ref>, whose poem &#8216;The Otaheitean Mourner&#8217;, recounting the fate of
                        George Stewart (1766?-1791) and his Tahitian &#8216;wife&#8217; was published in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 26 (December 1808),
                        457&#8211;458. Stewart, a midshipman on the Bounty, had been forced to join the mutiny. At Tahiti he lived with &#8216;Peggy&#8217;, a Tahitian
                        woman until in 1791 he was arrested there and confined on HMS <hi rend="ital">Pandora</hi>, sent to bring the mutineers back
                        to Britain for court martial. Imprisoned in a cell on deck, Stewart was killed on 29 August 1791 when the <hi rend="ital">Pandora</hi> foundered on the Great Barrier reef. The <title>Monthly Magazine</title> article described Stewart&#8217;s parting
                        from Peggy: &#8216;Peggy Stewart was the daughter of an Otaheitean Chief, and married to one of the Mutineers of the Bounty. On
                        Stewart&#8217;s being seized and carried away in the Pandora Frigate, Peggy fell into a rapid decay, and in two months died of a
                        broken heart, leaving an infant daughter, who is still living&#8217;.</note> who sent me some of his first attempts for the intended
                    third vol. of the Anthology.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey edited two volumes of the <title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> in 1799 and 1800; the third never appeared.</note> By that circumstance I discovered them to be his,
                    &amp; as I really admired them very much inserted them in the Quarterly<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey included
                        two stanzas from James&#8217;s poem in his review of the <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society in the South Sea
                            Islands</title> in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 2 (August 1809), 24&#8211;61 (50).</note> partly for the sake of giving
                    him &amp; his friends a very unexpected pleasure, for which they do not know to whom they are obliged.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will really do me some service by lending his Majestys my quarters pension. Mea negotia sunt mala ad hoc
                    tempus, erunt melioria mox. Sum valde pono manum cum Longo Homine. Scribo &#8211; scribo &#8211; scribo quid hunc? populus non emit. Ego
                    abstergam meum tergum-latus cum Thalab&#226;, cum Madoco, cumque Keham&#226; nil dubito &#8211; idem est (quod equidem miror) cum nobilissimo
                    Campedatore. Iste Campedator dormit<del>xx</del> tam profundi in vico Patrum Nostrum quam in sepulchre suo ad S. Petri
                        <del>Cade</del> Cardinesis. Ego haurio &amp; haurio super Longum Hominem. Longus Homo est bonus homo ille sinit me haurire,
                    nil contradicens. Habet satis in manibus suis omne liquidare ad finem. Hoc vero inconveniens est, quod credo alii bibliopol&#230;
                    darent me bonum summum pecuniae pro pro quolibet opere novo, et ego non possum ire ad eos, quia hoc modo obligatus sum ad Hominem
                        Longum.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Kenneth Curry translates this passage as &#8216;My business affairs are bad at this
                        time, but they will soon be better. I am working very hard for <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. I write
                        &#8211; write &#8211; write &#8211; to what end? The public did not buy. I&#8217;ll no doubt wipe my backside with <title>Thalaba</title>
            <title>,
                            Madoc</title>, and Kehama [Southey&#8217;s poems <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), <title>Madoc</title> (1805) and
                            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810)] &#8211; it is the same (as to that I likewise wonder) with the most noble Knight
                        [Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808)]. This Knight sleeps as deeply in the office of Our Fathers [the
                        publisher <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> and Company] as in his tomb in San Pedro at Carde&#241;a [his
                        original burial place was the monastery of San Pedro de Carde&#241;a in Castile]. I borrow and borrow from Longman. The Long Man is
                        a good man, he allows me to borrow, denying nothing. He has enough in his hand to settle everything at last. It is certainly
                        inconvenient, but I believe that other booksellers would give me a good sum of money for any new work, but I am not able to go
                        to them because I am obligated in this way to the Long Man&#8217;, <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and
                        New York, 1965), I, pp. 519&#8211;520.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now as some comfort after this Expos&#232; &#8211; I believe this engagement with <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> for his Annual Register<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1810 to 1812 Southey contributed to
                        the &#8216;History of Europe&#8217; for 1808&#8211;1810 in James Ballantyne&#8217;s <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>.</note> will if it
                    continues for two or three years, set me fairly above water again. I am to have 400 &#163; for it. Now my yearly drafts upon <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> have never reached 300, &#8211; rarely <del>more than</del> &lt;as much as&gt; 250.
                    Immediately therefore on coming into the receipt of this I shall be enabled to let my copyrights, which are <del>held</del> in his
                    hands, as a joint concern, <del>xxx xxx xxx</del> &lt;rest &amp;&gt; pay off the balance against me. As for any thing from the
                    Powers above, that is to say the earthly Powers, &#8211; my creed about them is a little like that of Capaneus;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Capaneus was an immensely strong mythological warrior who was killed by a bolt of lightning when he scoffed at
                        Jupiter, the Roman king of the Gods.</note> if my own right hand does not uphold me, &#8211; I may fall to the ground for them:
                    &lt;yet I believe that&gt; <ref target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> was <del>probably</del> in earnest <del>xxx</del>
                    in his professions, for he could have had no motive in making them, except the intention of carrying them into effect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am doing nothing for the Quarterly which is <ref target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> fault. Had he sent
                    me the Methodistical book which I wrote for, before he left town, that article would have been written by this time, or far
                        advanced,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed [James Sedgwick (1775&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>)],
                            <title>Hints to the Public and the Legislature, on the Nature and Effect of Evangelical Preaching. By a Barrister</title>
                        (1809), in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (November 1810), 480&#8211;514. The request to Murray for this book was made on 4
                        August 1809 (see letter 1664 of this edition).</note> &#8211; for I am yawning over the parliamentary part of this Register work,
                    &amp; should have been glad to have roused myself at intervals with work of a more awakening character. <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> says he shall send me some books &#8211; I wish he would, &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I also looked at the use which the Butler made of the Cohora, &#8211; tho I did not laugh till I came to it, &#8211; for want
                    of a key to the jest. <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The key is now lost. The Butler was the compendium of whimsical
                        stories that Bedford and Southey elaborated at school; Southey wished Bedford to develop them for publication. This Bedford
                        never did. A cohora was a mortar used for firing grenades.</note> By the bye I really envy the man who made the son of God
                    save John Bull<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> A comic version of the national anthem, sung by the Old Price rioters at
                        Covent Garden theatre, as part of their protests at new increased ticket prices imposed when the theatre reopened in 1809
                        after a fire: <lg type="stanza">
              <l rend="indent3">God save great Johnny Bull,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Long live our noble Bull,</l>
              <l rend="indent4">God save John Bull!</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Make him uproarious,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">With lungs like Boreas,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Till he&#8217;s victorious,</l>
              <l rend="indent4">God save John Bull!</l>
              <lb />
              <l rend="indent3">O Johnny Bull, be true,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Oppose the <hi rend="ital">prices new</hi>,</l>
              <l rend="indent4">And make them fall!</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Curse KEMBLE&#8217;S politicks,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Frustrate his knavish tricks,</l>
              <l rend="indent4">Confound them all!</l>
              <lb />
              <l rend="indent3">No <hi rend="ital">private boxes</hi> let</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Intriguing ladies get &#8211; </l>
              <l rend="indent4">Thy right, John Bull!</l>
              <l rend="indent3">From little <hi rend="ital">pigeon-holes</hi>,</l>
              <l rend="indent3">Defend us jolly souls</l>
              <l rend="indent3">And we will sing, <hi rend="ital">by Goles</hi>,</l>
              <l rend="indent4">God save John Bull!</l>
            </lg>
            <p rend="indent5">&#8216;Memoranda Dramatica&#8217;, <title>Monthly Mirror</title> (October 1809), 243.</p>
          </note> for Covent Garden, &#8211;
                    that <hi rend="ital">uproarious</hi> rhyme ought to have been mine</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You forgot to inclose the receipt. When it goes back the cohora shall go also, together with another book of
                    Kehama. That which you received last ought to please you. The story of Veeshnoos incarnation as the Dwarf is told with lucky
                    facility of language.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 15, lines 69&#8211;87.</note> &amp; the passage of Ladurlads descent into the
                        sea,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 16, lines 1&#8211;135.</note> &#8211; &amp; his daughter forgetful of the Curse recalling
                        him,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), Book 5, lines 132&#8211;154.</note> is in my judgement one of the best things in the
                    poem. It is not yet finished, &#8211; for I never write a line of it except before breakfast, &#8211; &amp; if my rest be broken I cannot rise
                    for this employment. But it is very-very-near the end &#8211; I have reached the part which requires most fire &amp; fury, &amp; it is
                    like yeast in the aorta <del>to</del> only to think of it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made an attempt to get <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> promoted, which cost me no little
                    effort, &amp; my hopes of its succeeding are not very strong. It is thro <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G
                        Beaumont</ref>,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Southey to Sir George Beaumont, 12 October 1809, Letter
                        1692.</note> &#8211; &amp; he has promised to ask Ld Mulgrave<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Phipps, 1st Earl of
                        Mulgrave (1755&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>): diplomatist and politician, appointed First Lord of the Admiralty in 1807.</note> to
                    make him Commander. If Ld Mulgrave were at the Admiralty, <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter">Scott</ref> I think would serve me
                    there.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent3">
            <date when="1809-10-29">Oct 29. 1809.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>