<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.991</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2113</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG
                        1996.5.56.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 284&#8211;287.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.991" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="991" type="letter">
        <head>991. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1804-11-21">21
                        November 1804</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ H. H. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ to
                        be left with <ref target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Guthrie</ref>. Bookseller./ Nicholson Street/
                        Edinburgh<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: NOV/ 1804/ 24<lb />MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG
                        1996.5.56<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                        vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 284&#8211;287.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#LowBrathay">Old Brathay</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1804-11-21">Wednesday. 21 Nov. 1804</date>
          </dateline>
          <dateline>We return on Sunday &#8211; or Monday at latest.</dateline>
          <salute>Dear <hi rend="ital">Hutton</hi>
            <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> A joke at the expense of Henry&#8217;s illegible
                            handwriting.</note>
          </salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your prize question seems oddly worded for in the common acceptation of civilization Hindostan is a highly
                    civilized country. Who proposes the question? &amp; to whom is it proposed? if to men of only your standing, it will be your own
                    fault if you do not win it. &#8211; Send me the official language of the question &#8211; the more I think of it the less intelligible does it
                    appear. if it means how are the Hindoos to be brought to the standard of European civilization, that is, how are they to be
                    converted, I can furnish you with some valuable facts on such a subject, &amp; shall probably in the necessary course of my
                    reading meet with more. The Hindoos can never advance till the system of Casts be destroyed, &amp; that system can only be
                    destroyed by introducing a new religion &#8211; in other words by converting them. You should first describe the system &amp; its
                    consequences, then show that the common opinion of the unconvertability of this people is ill founded, because they have
                    heretofore been converted in great numbers, &amp; lastly enquire what is the best method of attempting it. the more of anecdote
                    you can introduce the better, &amp; I can supply some of exceeding importance which it is not likely any of your competition
                    should have met with.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do beseech you mend your <del>xx</del> uglyography! As a proof how rascally a hand you <del>xxxx</del>
                    &lt;write&gt; every proper name in the Ballad which you transcribed for the Iris<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s
                        &#8216;Queen Urraca and the Five Martyrs of Morocco&#8217; had been published, with a misprint in the Queen&#8217;s name, in the newspaper that
                            <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> edited,<title> The Iris</title>, on 3 November. See
                            <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt (London, 2004), V, pp. 406&#8211;413.</note> was
                    misprinted except Coimbra which <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylors</ref> geography enabled him
                    to understand. Urra<hi rend="ital">i</hi>a, A<hi rend="ital">l</hi>fonso &#8211; Alsinger for Alangner. You use but three characters &#8211;
                    one for all those letters that are of the middle size, another for &lt;all&gt; the tall ones, &amp; the third for all that have
                    tails to them. Whenever you print a book you will find this unpardonable carelessness considerably expensive. the printers must
                    compose by guess &amp; you will be obliged to pay for the time spent in correcting their mistakes, perhaps even to doubling the
                        <del>expense</del> &lt;cost&gt;. I believe no man who ever wrote to any good purpose with a bad hand. the trouble of
                    understanding your own MSS. will seriously impede you if ever they should multiply &#8211; &amp; moreover NB. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> H.
                    H. H. H. H. I have weak eyes &amp; it better behoves you to mend them than to make them worse.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Frost spoils potatoes by making them sweet. is there then a formation of sugar? if this have not been investigated
                    it may be worth while to make some experiments, &#8211; to see what quantity of sugar can be obtained from equal quantities of the same
                    root in its sound state, &amp; when frost-bitten. the modus operandi might involve some important discovery, &amp; it is not
                    impossible but some <del>useful</del> practical utility might arise from it. perhaps as in malt the sweetness is produced by
                    destroying the life &#8211; the germinating power of the root. It should be tried also upon the more saccharine roots.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write from <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref> where we have been some days. the parcel arrived &#8211;
                    I was made pay 5/&#8211; 2 carriage &#8211; &amp; know not how to detect the imposition, whether at Penrith or Carlisle. &#8211; Kenyon<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Kenyon (1784&#8211;1856), friend of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> and benefactor of Robert Browning (1812&#8211;1889; <title>DNB</title>) and Elizabeth Barratt Browning
                        (1806&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), who in 1838 went on a tour of France with Southey. In 1826 Southey solicited votes on behalf
                        of Kenyon to enable him to be elected to the Athenaeum Club.</note> is gone. <ref target="people.html#EdridgePainter">Eldridge</ref> has written me a letter of thanks, in which he mentions that <ref target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Colonel</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#PeachyEmma">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachey</ref> had called on him in London. &#8211;
                    I sent off one cargo of books before we left home, &amp; wish myself back again that I might kill off another.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> That is, finish his reviewing for the <title>Annual Review</title>.</note> your Aubrey<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey and his brother Harry were reviewing Robert Charles Dallas (1754&#8211;1824), <title>Aubrey: a
                            Novel</title> (1804) for the <title>Annual Review</title>. However the review of this work (which appeared in the
                            <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 551&#8211;553) was not by Southey, according to letter 1093 of this edition,
                        which states his article was suppressed.</note> will do well. the sooner you let <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref> have the note from the Cambrian Register<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> There is a note in
                            <title>Madoc</title>, Part 1, book 1, line 31, which is derived from the <title>Cambrian Register</title>. See
                            <title>Robert Southey: Poetical Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), II, p. 574.</note>
                    the better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here I have read Lady Wortleys letters<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The letters of Lady Mary Wortley
                    Montagu (1689&#8211;1762; <title>DNB</title>) were published by James Dallaway (1763&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), in <title>The Works of the Right Hon. Lady Mary Wortley Montagu ... Published, by Permission, from
                            her Genuine Papers</title>, 5 vols (1803).</note> with exceeding delight &#8211; a real &amp; valuable acquisition to English literature. for excellent good sense, &amp; exquisite purity of
                    language they are almost unequalled. here too I have looked thro Richardsons <del>correspondence</del> &lt;papers&gt;.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Correspondence of Samuel Richardson</title>, ed. Anna Laetitia Barbauld (1804).</note> the letters of Klopstocks
                    wife are very interesting, nor do I ever remember having been more deeply affected than by the termination of that
                        correspondence.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Margaretha (Meta) Moller (1727&#8211;1758) married the German poet Friedrich
                        Gottlieb Klopstock (1724&#8211;1803) in 1754; her correspondence with Richardson ended with her untimely death aged thirty-one. Her
                        last letter is full of hopes concerning her as-yet unborn first child; it ends with her determination not only to mother but
                        also to nurse it herself.</note> As for the rest of the book<del>s</del> it is quite as worthless as <ref target="people.html#BarbauldAnnaLetitia">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> B<hi rend="ital">are</hi>b<hi rend="ital">a</hi>lds</ref>
                    prefatory prittle-prattle, in other words as bad as bad can be. I pray you look at what that <del>presbytari</del> presbyterian in
                    petticoats has the modesty to say of Sidneys Arcadia,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Philip Sidney (1554&#8211;1586;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Countess of Pembroke&#8217;s Arcadia</title> (1590). Barbauld said of this work, &#8216;it is a book
                        that all have heard of, that some few possess, but that nobody reads&#8217; in <title>The Correspondence of Samuel
                            Richardson</title>, ed. Anna Laetitia Barbauld, 6 vols (London, 1804), I, p. xviii.</note> in a sentence [MS torn] three
                        <hi rend="ital">thats</hi> instead of one <hi rend="ital">which</hi>, &amp; asserting a plump lie into the bargain. She calls
                    my Amadis <hi rend="ital">elegant</hi>,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Barbauld terms Southey&#8217;s <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title> (1803) &#8216;an elegant abridged version&#8217;, in <title>The Correspondence of Samuel Richardson</title>, I, p.
                        xii.</note> &#8211; happy epithet! <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> takes in the British Critic &#8211; a precious
                    Review. its praise is milk &amp; water, &amp; its censure sour small-beer. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My
                        Uncle</ref> thinks the Annual too severe. I begin to think so too &amp; shall mend upon <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylors</ref> model &#8211; always excepting Malthus &amp; the
                        Methodists<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population, as it Affects the Future Improvement of Society; with Remarks on the
                            Speculations of W. Godwin, M. Condorcet and Other Writers</title> (1803) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for
                            1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292&#8211;301; his review of William Myles (1756&#8211;1828), <title>A Chronological History of the People
                            called Methodists ... With an Appendix, Containing Two Lists of the Itinerant Preachers ... With the Last Will and
                            Testament of the Rev. J. Wesley</title> (1803) appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804),
                        201&#8211;213.</note> &#8211; if they come in my way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We left John<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Probably a joky reference to the ass, named John, which
                        Southey had bought and kept at <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>.</note> well &#8211; he would I am sure desire
                    his fraternal remembrances if he knew I were writing to you. &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Worgan<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Worgan (1759&#8211;after 1812): almoner, musician, resident of a cottage at Storr&#8217;s Hall, Windermere, who
                        composed <title>A Set of Sonnets</title> (1810), and hymns, one of which, &#8216;Windermere&#8217;, was included in George Worgan&#8217;s (b.
                        1802) collection <title>Gems of Sacred Melody</title> (1841).</note> &amp; I pun against one another with great glory. Alas
                    what will not the world lose for want of a Boswell!<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> James Boswell (1778&#8211;1822;
                            <title>DNB</title>), friend and biographer of Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I think I should
                    outshine M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Miller if I had but an honest chronicler.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Joseph Miller
                        (1684&#8211;1738), was a popular comic actor on the London stage from 1709 until his death. In 1739 Joe Miller&#8217;s
                            <title>Jestbook</title> was published, a joke-book compiled by the hack writer John Mottley (1692&#8211;1750). Many further
                        editions appeared, and &#8216;a Joe Miller&#8217; became shorthand for a bad joke.</note> &#8211; Why is Sir Cloudesly Shovel like Werter? &#8211;
                    because he was felo-de-sea.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The eponymous hero of the novel by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe
                        (1749&#8211;1832), <title>The Sorrows of Young Werther</title> (<title>Die Leiden des Jungen Werthers</title>) (1774/1787) who
                        killed himself; Admiral of the Fleet, Sir Cloudesley Shovell (1650&#8211;1707; <title>DNB</title>), was full of the sea because he
                        drowned in a notorious naval disaster off the Scilly Isles.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was accurate about the Galatea.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship, HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, was a fifth-rate 32-gun frigate, which on 14 August 1804, had made an unsuccessful attempt to
                        cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near Guadeloupe. Of the 90 men sent on the mission, 65 were killed or wounded, and Southey
                        suspected that Tom was among the dead.</note> no official accounts have yet arrived but <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> saw a long letter at the Admiralty from one who had been in the
                    action. it was very particular, &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> name never occurred in it. we have therefore
                    reason to hope he may have escaped. but the loss has been very serious.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As soon as you tell me more about this prize question I will write to you upon the subject, give you all my
                    materials to think upon, &amp; direct you to the books which may most instruct you. you have no right to calculate that the <hi rend="ital">best</hi> essay will win &#8211; but you may be sure the most <hi rend="ital">amusing</hi> will. It will lead you to old
                    travels, which are very delightful &amp; very instructive. I am thoroughly acquainted with the subject, not only as my history has
                    led me to it, but also from the quantity which I have read for the sake of Kehama.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> For
                        Southey&#8217;s voluminous reading as he wrote <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), see the notes to <title>Robert Southey: Poetical
                            Works 1793&#8211;1810</title>, gen. ed. Lynda Pratt, 5 vols (London, 2004), IV.</note> God bless you.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>