<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1229</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2351</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1229" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1229" type="letter">
        <head>1229. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1806-10-18">18 October
                        1806</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Charles Danvers Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Bristol/
                        Single<lb />Endorsements: [various calculations on address sheet]<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ OCT 22/
                        1803<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would be in vain to tell you how I am perplexed &amp; distressed about the books. To have them sent here &#8211; when
                    according to all human probability I shall not remain here myself six months longer &#8211; would be a grievous expence &amp; yet upon
                    my soul I do not see what else is to &#8211; or can be done. <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has no room for them.
                    To ask favours at the Cottage<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> The house of Uncle <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southey</ref>, now rich after inheriting the estate of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref>.</note> is what I have no inclination for &#8211; yet if I should go abroad
                    with a probability of remaining there I would in that case beg leave to deposit all my books there, &amp; fit up a library for
                    him. But the fact is that the situation of Lisbon is more precarious than ever, &amp; it is in the highest degree improbable that
                    I can remove my family there.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not return to Portugal.</note> In that case &#8211; if
                    it be still possible for me to go there in the spring without them, I shall think of settling them here &amp; look upon this as my
                    home. But what to do with the books now? Can <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref>
          <hi rend="ital">let</hi> me a garret in her house, where those which are damp may be put up &#8211; a few shelves you could have knocked
                    up for me. If it can be managed thus the whole may be removed there from <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Kings</ref> or at
                    least every thing except the books &#8211; the linen &lt;&amp;c&gt; would be more accessible &amp; could be opened &amp; taken care of. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wonder you advise me to go to Taunton. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southey</ref> might
                    well think me a hungry hunter after legacies if <del>I were</del> he were to see me come from this distance to pay him a visit &#8211;
                    at an expence which I can so very ill afford. In the Spring I must go to London &#8211; whether on the way to Portugal or not &#8211; then
                    there will be no unfitness in my proceeding to Somersetshire &amp; returning by way of Bristol &#8211; but to set off from hence on
                    purpose &#8211; without pretext or the shadow of a pretext, would make me contemptible in my own eyes &amp; in his too &#8211; he might well
                    laugh at me as one whose mouth was gaping for what would never drop into it. In the spring something will probably turn up to
                    decide my plans &amp; settle me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a notion that N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 7 was that packing case which came to pieces &#8211; so that you had the
                    books repacked in two. It must have been a large packing case by the number of books which it contained. If you find it take out a
                    folio Dante<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> No. 712 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library was a folio edition of
                        Durante degli Alighieri (1265&#8211;1321),<title> La Divina Commedia con l&#8217;Espositioni di Christ</title> (Venice, 1596).</note>
                    likewise &#8211; of which there is a fine copy of the valuable edition of the Cat. the Nobiliario<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan Bautista Lava&#241;a (1550&#8211;1624), <title>Nobiliario de D. Pedro Conde de Barcelos Hijo del Rey D. Dionis de Portugal</title>
                        (1640), no. 3571 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> is the book most wanted of all which I have sent for &#8211; do
                    not take the trouble of looking for the others which you could not find &#8211; they are of no consequence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> prize money<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> It was customary for naval
                        officers to be allotted a share of the value of &#8216;prizes&#8217;, meaning ships and their cargo, captured in armed conflict.</note> is
                    less than you seem to suppose. He left me in my desk a draft for 50&#163; &#8211; which I am using<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        See Southey to Thomas Southey, 28&#8211;29 September 1806, Letter 1221.</note> &#8211; as I should else have borrowed that sum elsewhere,
                    &amp; shall repay into his agents hands in about six months I trust. He will whisk away his money in post chaises so fast that he
                    will soon find it is ebb tide with him. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has recommended him to <ref target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">his Uncle</ref> for promotion, but says he cannot flatter us with hopes of <hi rend="ital">early</hi> success: he underlines the word as if depending upon success ultimately. Meantime <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has collected certain documents respecting S. America which Ld S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincent<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent (1735&#8211;1823;
                            <title>DNB</title>) had been First Lord of the Admiralty from 1801&#8211;1804 until he fell out of favour with the Tory
                        government. Under the &#8216;Ministry of All the Talents&#8217; he was one of the commissioners to Lisbon between August and October 1806,
                        when, owing to the threat of a French invasion of Portugal, the British proposed securing the Portuguese fleet and
                        transporting the royal family to Brazil.</note> will be glad of, &amp; which he will give to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. I think Tom will return here very shortly &#8211; if he is not employed &#8211; to fag hard at
                    Spanish &amp; Portugueze &#8211; which may both be of essential importance to him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thought it was in Park Street you lived &#8211; but directed them to travel in the stage &#8211; arrive in the morning &#8211;
                    &amp; call at the office.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would be of some use if it were mentioned in the papers here that Madoc is printing in America &#8211; &amp; also that
                    Thalaba was printed there &#8211; piece by piece &#8211; in the newspaper.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s poems
                            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) and <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801). An American edition of <title>Madoc</title>
                        was published by subscription in 1806 by Munroe and Francis of Boston, Massachusetts.</note> I
                    would have asked you to have inserted a paragraph to this purpose in Rudhalls paper<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> John
                        Rudhall (d. 1803), a Bristol printer who was a proprietor of the newspaper, <title>Felix Farley&#8217;s Bristol
                        Journal</title>.</note> &#8211; had he been alive. it would have been copied into the London papers &#8211; &amp; serve <del>xxx</del>
                    more effectually than an advertisement. I suppose it is the same Boston bookseller who published Joan of Arc.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The American edition of <title>Joan of Arc</title> had been published in Boston in 1798 by
                        Manning &amp; Loring, for the bookseller J. Nancrede.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Scotts is a bad ballad<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>The Lay Of The Last Minstrel</title>
                        had been published in 1805.</note> &#8211; I heard <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffray</ref> read it &#8211; there is one
                    masterly line in it &#8211; which I forget &#8211; but the rest is good for nothing. <ref target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>
                    has been visiting William Smith the Member,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Smith (1756&#8211;1835;
                        <title>DNB</title>), politician and dissenter, who was the Member of Parliament for Norwich from 1802 to 1806.</note> &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> visiting him there &#8211; he has been in England between nine &amp;
                    ten weeks<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Coleridge had travelled abroad to Malta for his health in 1804, taking up a
                        temporary post there as Public Secretary to the British Civil Commissioner. He arrived back in England in August 1806 but
                        though returning to Keswick for a short time, did not live there again.</note> &#8211; we expected him last Saturday &#8211; &amp;
                    received instead a letter saying he was going to Bury with <ref target="people.html#ClarksonCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Clarkson</ref> &#8211; as she had prest him &amp; he could not refuse her. He is daily &amp; indeed hourly expected &#8211; but to say
                    when he will come is as impossible as &lt;to&gt; tell which way our weathercock will cock his tail tomorrow. He is to Lecture at
                    the Royal Institution upon the Principles common to the Fine Arts.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> He did not in fact
                        lecture there until 1808, on the subject of the Principles of Poetry, Shakespeare and Milton.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> if he can but keep up his health &amp; spirits is in a fairer way than he
                    ever was. This book which I invented for him, has driven him into such a course of reading that <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">the Count</ref>
                    is become learned in old English literature &amp; likely to flourish as an Editor.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Burnett&#8217;s <title>Specimens of English Prose Writers, from the Earliest Times to the Close of the Seventeenth Century</title>
                        was published in three volumes with <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> in 1807. This compilation formed a
                        companion work to George Ellis, <title>Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790; 2nd edn 1801; 3rd edn 1803) and
                        Southey&#8217;s own anthology, jointly edited with Grosvenor Charles Bedford, <title>Specimens of the Later English Poets</title>
                        (1807).</note> I have now to write him a long letter respecting certain projects of republication which he has written to
                    consult me about, &amp; some of which are very likely to succeed, to get him both money &amp; reputation &amp; be of service to
                    Literature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am hard at work &#8211; never harder. Palmerin<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was preparing for the
                        press an English translation of <title>Palmerin of England, by Francisco Moraes</title>, published in 4 volumes in
                        1807.</note> is a laborious job &#8211; tho I undertook it thinking it would be no labour, &#8211; &amp; Espriella<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from England: by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella; Translated from the Spanish</title> published in 1807.</note> is
                    now so far advanced that I sit at it joyfully. The whole is to consist of 300 of my pages, &amp; now that I have turned 200 every
                    page tells in reducing the remainder. If the printer<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Richard Taylor (1781&#8211;1858;
                            <title>DNB</title>), printer and naturalist, who would go on to establish the publishing firm of Taylor and Francis with
                        his son William Francis (1817&#8211;1904; <title>DNB</title>) in 1852.</note> had hurried me it would have been done. I shall soon
                    be in sight of land, &amp; certainly if my health &amp; eyes fail not (&amp; these eyes are better now) clear compleatly off both
                    this, Palmerin, &amp; the Cid<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> was published
                        in 1808.</note> by the end of the winter, with some reviewing beside &#8211; so to be ready in the spring to go wherever fortune may
                    call me &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">little Edith</ref>, &amp; Less
                            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> all well &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1806-10-18">Sunday Oct. 18. 1806. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>