<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1022</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2144</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 311&#8211;313 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1022" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1022" type="letter">
        <head>1022. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1805-01-20">20 January 1805</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: 20 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>
                        1805<lb />MS: Bodleian Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 311&#8211;313 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> First thanking you for what you have done in this business &amp; also for what you did &amp; did not say in the
                    affair of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> &#8211; I proceed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a civil office for the Inspection of Accounts &#8211; &amp; I am adequate to be Inspector &#8211;, so if you cannot
                    learn <del>of xxx</del> that there be any thing more proper let that be the thing asked. but &#8211; consult <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &#8211; I have only proceeded on newspaper authority &#8211; &amp; if the expedition be not
                    going to Portugal &#8211; would not take the best office any where else. &#8211; Actual work I expect, &amp; have seen enough of the last army
                    at Lisbon to know that Commissaries &amp; <del>xxxx</del> Inspectors have plenty of leisure. &#8211; This much General Moore must
                    know,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761&#8211;1809; DNB), Scottish General with a long and varied military
                        career. He was also MP for Lanark Burghs 1784&#8211;1790. After the controversial Convention of Cintra (1808), Moore was given the
                        command of the British troops in the Iberian peninsula. He was fatally wounded at the Battle of Corunna. In December 1804 he
                        was sent to review the practicability of defending Portugal from a French invasion. His favourable report was widely leaked to
                        the press, e.g. <title>Aberdeen Journal</title>, 9 January 1805.</note>
                    whether we are to send <del>x</del> forces to Portugal &lt;or not,&gt; for it depends upon his report &#8211; if the papers lie not. If
                    we do &#8211; the place where all the civil operations are carried on is Lisbon &#8211; there the Commission &#8211; <del>xxx xxxxx</del> &amp;c
                    remain if the army takes the field. there I want to go &#8211; you know for what purpose. To say that I do not wish to make money would
                    be talking nonsense &#8211; but the mere object of making money would not take me from home. I can inspect accounts, &#8211; I can make
                    contracts &#8211; (for beef &amp; <del>xxx</del> oats are soon understood.) &#8211; &amp; doing these things can yet have leisure for my own
                    pursuits. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> perhaps knows more of these things, what situations there are to
                    which I am competent, &amp; what are the most desirable. show him this &amp; follow his suggestions rather than mine. What efforts
                    I make are more because the thing is prudent, than agreeable. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is well out of a scrape into which he was got by no fault of his own. if he scapes
                    the fever the Court Martial was a lucky days work for him.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 14 August 1804, the boats of
                        Thomas Southey&#8217;s ship the <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi> made an unsuccessful attempt to cut out the French privateer <hi rend="ital">General Ernouf</hi> (formerly the British sloop of war <hi rend="ital">Lilly</hi>) lying at the Saintes near
                        Guadeloupe. 65 of the 90 men sent on the mission were killed or wounded. Due to Thomas having been placed under arrest (and
                        subsequently court-martialled) he was replaced on the raid by Lieutenant Charles Hayman (dates unknown) who died.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Madoc is provokingly delayed. Job once wished that his enemy had written a book. if he himself had printed one it
                    would have tried his patience.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The biblical character, Job, who remained steadfast to God
                        despite the extreme tests sent to try his patience.</note> I am every day expecting the Great Snake<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805), was published with three illustrations: the engraved titlepage with <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn&#8217;s</ref> shield upon a <hi rend="ital">troph&#233;e</hi>; the palm and cross upon the
                        rock (after the Table of Contents); and the snake before the cave, intended as the title-page of the second part, &#8216;Madoc in
                        Aztlan&#8217; but placed incorrectly (after page 320, instead of after page 184).</note> in a frank from <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref>. My emblem of the cross prefixed to the poem &#8211; with the In hoc signo<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Meaning &#8216;in this sign&#8217;, alluding to the early Christian tradition that the Emperor Constantine I
                        (272&#8211;337) had a vision of the sun with a cross above it and the words &#8216;&#949;&#957; &#964;&#959;&#973;&#964;&#8179;
                        &#957;&#943;&#954;&#945;&#8217; (meaning &#8216;by this, may you conquer&#8217;), which is often translated in Latin as &#8216;In hoc signo vinces&#8217;.
                        Constantine adopted the phrase for his battle standards.</note> &#8211; &amp; what I have said in the poem of the Virgin Mary is
                    more liable to misconstruction than could be wished.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was concerned that he might
                        seem to Protestant reviewers to be endorsing &#8216;superstition&#8217; because he portrayed, for reasons of historical accuracy, the
                        Catholic beliefs of his medieval Welsh heroes. He was indeed criticised, but rather for aligning Christian rituals with the
                        &#8216;savage&#8217; ceremonies of the Aztecas, than for Catholicism, in the <title>Eclectic Review</title>, 1 (1805), 899&#8211;908. See
                            <title>Robert Southey: The Critical Heritage</title>, ed. Lionel Madden (London, 1972), pp. 106&#8211;108.</note> In what light
                    I consider these things may be seen in the Reviews of the Missions to Bengal &amp; Otaheite.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey reviewed the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (1800&#8211;1801)
                        in the<title> Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 207&#8211;218, and the <title>Transactions of the Missionary Society</title>
                        (1803) in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 189&#8211;201.</note> I have just finished another article for this
                    year upon the South African missions.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Transactions of the
                            Missionary Society</title> (1804) in Africa, appeared in the <title>Annual Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805),
                        621&#8211;634.</note> the great use of reviewing is that it obliges me to think upon subjects on which I had been before content to
                    have very vague opinions, because there had never been any occasion for examining them &amp; this is a very important use.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will do me a world of good to see the first proof sheet under favour of the Grand Parleur.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> The privilege of using the Royal Mail gratis was available to Southey, because his friend <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> was Secretary to the Speaker of the House of Commons, <ref target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Charles Abbott</ref>.</note> I shall begin to think seriously of the preface. &#8211; you will
                    find it worth while to go to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> for the sake of seeing the new publications,
                    which all lie on his table. a good way of knowing what is going on in the world of typography &#8211; to call it the world of letters
                    would be paying a very undeserved compliment to my contemporaries.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-01-20">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 20. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>