<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1061</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2183</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1061" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1061" type="letter">
        <head>1061. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1805-04-18">18 April
                        1805</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Bristol./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Endorsement: Magazines/ Barrys Book/ Beauties of England/ Aunts Travels/ George Lukins/
                        <lb />Bundle Letters/ Nine Pins/ [illegible word]/ Lukins <lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Charles</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Had you complained that Madoc was too expensive I should readily have agreed with you &#8211; or that it was too dear &#8211; I
                    should have said it seems so &#8211; but the price is likely to be a fair one &#8211; because tho I objected to it, the publishers have
                    persisted in affixing it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805) was published in a luxurious quarto, costing 2 guineas.</note> But when you talk of wide margins
                    &amp; waste paper the only reply must be that you have been finding fault without consideration. As for margin it may be
                    dishonestly broad in a work of prose, &#8211; but unless you would have two <hi rend="ital">verses</hi> in one line &#8211; you must be
                    contented with <hi rend="ital">one</hi>. To have used a larger type, as <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantyne</ref>
                    advised, would indeed have narrowed the margin at the expence of about ten sheets of paper &#8211; i &#8211; e &#8211; 7/6 more in the price of the
                    book. As for blank paper there is but one blank page in the whole volume &#8211; which is between the first &amp; second part of the
                    Notes &#8211; &amp; which I did not order the Printer to alter &#8211; because it would have <del>delayed</del> occasioned a delay of <del>two
                        or</del> three days. That the blank on the page where a section concludes should sometimes be larger than is sightly is a
                    thing of mere accident; to have begun the next section on the same page would sometimes have produced a greater deformity, would
                    certainly have made the volume far less beautiful &amp; less handsome, &#8211; &amp; could not on the most liberal computation have
                    diminished its price more than fourteen pence. I ordered 30 lines in a page &#8211; it did not suit <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">Ballantynes</ref> types &amp; he would only promise 24 &#8211; at the same time recommending 20
                    &amp; the same type as Scotts Lay of the Last Minstrel.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Walter Scott, <title>The Lay of
                            the Last Minstrel: A Poem</title> (1805), which was also printed by <ref target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James
                            Ballantyne</ref>, in Edinburgh.</note> The Notes could not have been printed smaller &#8211; I have not used one fourth of what
                    I had prepared &#8211; &amp; they take up about a sixth less room than if they had been at the bottom of the page. &#8211; I am afraid the
                    vignette of the snake is misplaced in all the copies &#8211; it ought to be at the beginning of the second part &#8211; &amp; the leaf <hi rend="ital">counts</hi> as P&#8211;185&#8211;6.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The engraving of the snake, intended for the
                        title-page of the second part of <title>Madoc</title>, &#8216;Madoc in Aztlan&#8217;, was placed incorrectly (after page 320, instead of
                        after page 184).</note> remember that your binder remedies this foolish blunder.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Never mind the books as you have them not.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked Danvers to
                        send him several books; see Southey to Charles Danvers, 13 March 1805, Letter 1048.</note> I know they are not at <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Kings</ref> &#8211; but thought they might be loose with you. the bundle of letters of which I speak
                    is a large paper parcel &#8211; which if I recollect aright George<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Either <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref> or <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George
                        Fricker</ref>.</note> carried down to you, as a thing which I might perhaps want, &#8211; the letters being spread you may easily
                    have supposed it to contain something different. put in your trunk the Numbers of the Beauties of England<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Beauties of England and Wales</title> (1801&#8211;1818) was a series of lavishly-illustrated accounts of the historical
                        features of Britain, produced by John Britton (1771&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), an antiquary, with his friend Edward Wedlake
                        Brayley (1773&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>).</note> which are loose in your possession.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your route had best be thus &#8211; from Liverpool in the Long Coach to Lancaster &#8211; from thence by stage over the sands
                    to Ulverstone. if you are lucky you may effect this the same day that you leave Liverpool. See <ref target="places.html#FurnessAbbey">Furness Abbey</ref> &amp; come on by way of Conistone Lake to <ref target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> which is at the head of Winandermere. I know not the distances here &#8211; but know
                    that this is the best possible route for seeing things in the best possible way. Ambleside is 16 miles from hence. If I knew when
                    to expect you there, which cannot well be because of the uncertainty of crossing the sands I would meet you at Grasmere. If the
                    inn at Ambleside be full &#8211; get on to Grasmere &#8211; which is 3 miles &#8211; where there is a little inn sufficiently comfortable &#8211; &amp;
                    call at Wordsworths to show you the way, &#8211; very probably I shall be there on the look out for you. from Grasmere to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is a magnificent walk of 13 miles.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I knew not till now that <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref> had been at <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">Estlins</ref>. his scheme seems promising &#8211; I saw Carpenter<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dr Lant Carpenter (1780&#8211;1840), a Unitarian minister who held the post of librarian at the Liverpool Athenaeum
                        from 1802 until 1805, when he left to become pastor of a chapel in Exeter.</note> at Liverpool, &amp; liked him, &amp; heard
                    him very well spoken of. Does <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam</ref> succeed him at the Athen&#230;um<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Founded in 1797, this Liverpool gentleman&#8217;s club offered a forum for intellectual discussion. Reid did not
                        become a librarian there.</note> as sub-Librarian?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> are always blundering.
                    the Cyclop&#230;dias<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ephraim Chambers&#8217; (1680?&#8211;1740), <title>Cyclopedia, or, An Universal
                            Dictionary of Arts and Sciences</title> was first published in 1728 and reprinted many times in the eighteenth century. An
                        expanded edition, updated by Abraham Rees (1743&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), was published from 1778&#8211;1788. Rees began an
                        entirely new edition in 1802.</note> for which they enquire were sent to Barrys<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                        Bartholomew Barry (dates unknown), a Bristol bookseller and stationer.</note> with Pinkertons Geography<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Pinkerton (1758&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Modern Geography, a Description of the
                            Empires, States, and Colonies, with the Oceans, Seas and Islands in all Parts of the World</title> (1802).</note> &#8211; &amp;
                    by you sent back to them &#8211; on their way here &#8211; being now on my shelves.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Will you laugh if I say that your Aunts travels would be useful to me? pray bring them &#8211; they will furnish a
                    curious account of English manners a century ago, which any Spaniard may collect in the real way &#8211; from a MS.S. in the family of
                    one of his friends.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Danvers&#8217;s aunt was the traveller Celia Fiennes (1662&#8211;1741;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Danvers gave Southey a manuscript of her diary, which Southey used for <title>Letters from England
                            by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella: Translated from the Spanish</title> (1807). Extracts from it were also included in his
                        and Coleridge&#8217;s <title>Omniana</title> (1812).</note> And can you get me the newspaper or other account of George Lukins?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Lukins (b. 1734) was, on Friday, 13 June 1778, exorcised by seven clergymen,
                        having, he believed, been possessed by demons who made him speak in voices not his own. His <title>Narrative of the
                            Extraordinary Case of George Lukins, of Yatton, Somersetshire, who was Possessed of Evil Spirits for 18 years: Also, an
                            Account of his Remarkable Deliverance, in the Vestry-Room of Temple Church</title> (1788) was supervised by John Wesley
                        (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>). The Methodist interpretation that Lukins was possessed by evil spirits was contested by John
                        Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), who viewed Lukins as an imposter, attributing his symptoms to epilepsy and St Vitus&#8217;
                        Dance, in the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title>, 58, part 2 (July, 1778), 609&#8211;610.</note> &#8211; I have got on some way in this
                    book &amp; with some success.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Capt. never gave me a letter about the wine &#8211; which was lying at Liverpool.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had ordered a shipment of Portuguese wine from Danvers; see Southey to Charles Danvers, [started
                        before and continued on] 11 October 1804, Letter 981.</note> It is now on its way, &amp; I am in daily expectation of it &#8211;
                    &amp; in want having yesterday opened my last bottle of Bucellas<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> A Portuguese sweet white
                        wine.</note> &amp; borrowed port for a friend of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> from
                    Malta.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edithling</ref> is ailing with her teeth &#8211; but we are not alarmed &#8211;
                    as there are none but ordinary symptoms &#8211; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> little girl<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dora Wordsworth (1804&#8211;1847).</note> is ill with the Croup &#8211; which is ravaging the neighbourhood
                    &amp; gives me some uneasiness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is always in the way of danger &#8211; just got the yellow fever out
                    of the ship &amp; now the French are come!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> In March 1805 the French Mediterranean Fleet,
                        under Vice-Admiral Pierre-Charles Villeneuve (1763&#8211;1806), sailed from Toulon for the West Indies. Later in the year a squadron
                        of French ships commanded by Contre-Admiral Zacharie Allemand (1762&#8211;1828), and based at Rochefort, slipped past the British
                        blockade and harassed British ships in the Atlantic and West Indies.</note> What think of you Lord Melville?<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Henry Dundas, 1st Viscount Melville (1742&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War
                        1794&#8211;1801, and First Lord of the Admiralty from 1804.</note> of the infamous man&#339;uvre practised to prevent the House of
                    Commons from presenting their resolution in due form? &amp; of the Kings<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> George III
                        (1738&#8211;1820, King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).</note> writing a complimentary letter to the scoundrel as if
                    for the express purpose of insulting the publics feelings?<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> From 1802&#8211;1805, Melville&#8217;s use
                        of public funds when Treasurer of the Admiralty (1782&#8211;1800), was investigated by a Royal Commission. On 9 April 1805, after
                        its report, Melville, despite governmental procedural manoeuvres, was censured in the House of Commons on the grounds that he
                        had allowed the naval paymaster, Alexander Trotter (dates unknown) to misuse public funds. Melville resigned and impeachment
                        proceedings were commenced against him.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to your brother Dan &#8211; to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> &#8211; Hort<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Jillard Hort (1764&#8211;1849): Unitarian minister and writer, he was one of many acquaintances who stored
                        books for Southey.</note> &#8211; &amp; who else may enquire for me.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-04-18">Thursday April 18. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>