<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 3: 1804-1809 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.1045</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce2167</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2013-05-27">May 27, 2013</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. D3.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.1045" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-05-27" n="8">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after final proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2013-04-22" n="7">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms after proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2013-02-01" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proofing Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2012-01-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran Transforms for proof copies of Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#DR" when="2011-12-02" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Transforms for Southey Part 4</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="1045" type="letter">
        <head>1045. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1805-03-07">7
                        March 1805</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ H. H. Southey Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ to the
                        care of <ref target="people.html#GuthrieJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Guthrie</ref>, Bookseller./ Nicholson Street./ Edinburgh/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmark: MR/ 1805/ 9<lb />Endorsement: Fair be thy/ To a friend about to depart for
                        <lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. D3<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not Oviedos History, &#8211; but this passage occurs in his Relacion sumaria de la Historia Natural de las Indias.
                    &#8211; Cap. 77.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Gonzalo Fern&#225;ndez de Oviedo y Vald&#233;s (1478&#8211;1557), <title>Sumario de la Natural
                            Historia de las Indias</title> (1526). Oviedo&#8217;s more famous history, which Southey refers to, was <title>Historia General
                            y Natural de las Indias, Islas y Tierra Firme del Mar Oc&#233;ano</title>, of which the first part was published in 1535. The
                        publication of the second part was interrupted by the author&#8217;s death. Henry Southey was soliciting information from his
                        brother for his university dissertation to graduate as MD. This was on the origins and course of syphilis, in which he
                        suggested an American origin for the disease.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The chapter treats of the Guayacon<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Guayacan, or lignum sanctum (<hi rend="ital">Guaiacum officinale</hi>). The Spanish used an extract from the root to treat syphilis.</note> or Holy Wood as
                    the Spaniards calls it, &amp; mentions it as the remedy used in the Islands<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The West
                        Indies, where the tree is native.</note> for the disease. &#8211; &#8216;Your majesty (the treatise is addressed to Carlos 5.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charles V (1500&#8211;1558) was ruler of the Holy Roman Empire from 1519, and as Carlos I of Spain, he
                        ruled the Spanish Empire from 1516, until his abdication in 1556.</note>) may be certain that the disease came from the
                    Indies. it is very common among the Indians but not so dangerous in those parts as in these; indeed the Indians in the islands
                    cure it easily with this wood, &amp; on the main land with other herbs, or things with which they are acquainted; for they are
                    great Herbalists. (he has said that the Guayacon does not grow on the continent to his knowledge) &#8211; The first time that the
                    disease was ever seen in Spain was after the Admiral D Christoval Colon discovered the Indies &amp; returned to these parts. some
                    Xtians who had been with him upon that discovery, &amp; those who were in his second voyage who were more, brought back the
                    plague, &amp; from them others were infected.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Epidemic syphilis had arrived in Europe by
                        1495, two years after the return of Christopher Columbus&#8217;s (1451&#8211;1506) sailors from the New World.</note> And afterwards in
                    the year 1495. when the Great Captain D Gonzalo Fernandez de Cordova passed over to Italy with troops in favour of the King of
                    Naples D Fernando the young, against K Charles of France, he of the large head, by order of the Catholic King D Fernando &amp;
                    Do&#241;a Isabel, of immortal memory, the grandsires of your Majesty, this disease went with some of his soldiers, &amp; this was the
                    first time it had been seen in Italy.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Spanish expedition against the French in Italy,
                        was led by Gonzalo Fern&#225;ndez de C&#243;rdoba (1453&#8211;1515), the aim being to restore to his throne the descendant of Ferdinand I of
                        Naples (1423&#8211;1494), brother-in-law of the Spanish king Ferdinand II of Aragon (1452&#8211;1516) and deposed by the invasion of the
                        forces of Charles VIII of France (1470&#8211;1498).</note> And as it was that time the French were there with the said K Charles,
                    the Italians called this evil the French evil, &amp; the French called it the evil of Naples, because they also had never seen it
                    till that war, &#8211; &amp; from thence it has spread thro all Xtendom, &amp; past into Africa, by means of some men &amp; women
                    infected with it, for in no other manner does it spread so much, as by the connection of man &amp; woman, as has often been seen.
                    &amp; also by eating from the sauce, or drinking from the dish or cup which the disease have used, &amp; still more by sleeping in
                    the sheets &amp; linen wherein the diseased have lain. It is so so sore &amp; dolorous an evil, that no man who has eyes must have
                    seen many persons rotten, &amp; turned away from Saint Lazarus&#8217;s<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Military and
                        Hospitaller Order of St. Lazarus of Jerusalem established leper hospitals all over Europe at the beginning of the twelfth
                        century.</note> on account of it, &amp; <del>many of xxx xxx</del> many have died of it. Few of the Xtians who connect
                    themselves with the female Indians escape &#8211; but as I have said it is not so perilous &#8211; there as here &#8211; as well because this tree
                    being fresh is more profitable &amp; operates better, as because the temperature of the earth is without cold, &amp; helps
                        <del>the diseas</del> such diseased persons better than the air &amp; constellations here.&#8217;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Oviedos larger work was written before this, but not published.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Ovideo&#8217;s
                            <title>Historia General y Natural de las Indias, Islas y Tierra Firme del Mar Oc&#233;ano</title> was not published as a
                        complete work until 1851&#8211;1855.</note> You will most likely find <del>both</del> the passage from it as well as this, in the
                    History of Medicine. You have here the whole of this, literally rendered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I remember a story in a miscellaneous book of Elizabeths time<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Elizabeth I
                        (1533&#8211;1603, Queen of England and Ireland 1558&#8211;1603; <title>DNB</title>).</note> made up from Spanish and Italian writers
                    &#8211; so that from whence it originally came heaven knows &#8211; but it is certainly older than her time, to this effect. That two persons
                    (Spaniards I believe) being grievously diseased determined to go among the Indians to be cured, &amp; accordingly to the Islands
                    they went &amp; cured they were, chiefly by eating lizards. The folly of the remedy does not impugn the main import of the fact &#8211;
                    that they believed the Indians had more knowledge of the disease than the Europeans.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If a man 250 years hence were to argue that the French Revolution existed an indefinite time before we now suppose
                    it to have broken out, because we read of mobs in London, &amp; sedition every where, &#8211; he would argue just like those who deny
                    the American origin of Venereal disease &#8211; the facts that it was notoriously called either French or Neapolitan, &amp; that it was
                    common in the Islands, where Oviedo had lived, are decisive. It is not a thing to be claimed for his countrymen by any vanity. The
                    single cases which seem to have occurred at an earlier period you can better account for than I. how far the description of
                    cancers, scrofulous swellings &amp; ulcers &amp;c may explain them.</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And thus, Sir, have I replied to your Presidentships<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Harry was elected as
                        one of the four annual presidents of the Royal Medical Society of Edinburgh in December 1804.</note> letter immediately upon
                    receiving it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have been alarmed about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the child</ref> &#8211; have blistered behind her
                    ears, &amp; administered calomel.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The common name for mercury chloride, which was taken
                        for various ailments.</note> the symptoms have completely disappeared &#8211; but not so my uneasiness. If the disease should
                    decidedly manifest itself, I shall bleed her in the jugular vein, by which <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> has saved
                    three children. she seems well at present.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had news from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> on the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> when he wrote he had been on board the Amelia a month, in which time they had buried 60.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> HMS <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi> was a 38-gun H&#233;b&#233;-class frigate of the French navy captured in 1796 and
                        commissioned into the British navy. On taking up his appointment on the <hi rend="ital">Amelia</hi>, Thomas found the ship&#8217;s crew
                        struck down by fever.</note> he was well, &amp; in good spirits.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will sooner know when Madoc is published than I shall. My directions concerning copies have been sent to <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> some time, who will I suppose instruct Constable<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Archibald Constable (1774&#8211;1827), the Edinburgh publisher and bookseller who distributed <title>Madoc</title>
                        in Scotland.</note> to supply you according to my desire. &#8211; I have been twice at <ref target="places.html#GrasmereDove">Grasmere</ref> for some days with poor <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> whose heart is almost
                    broken by the loss of his brother in the Abergavenny.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Wordsworth (1772&#8211;1805),
                        captain of the East Indiaman, the <hi rend="ital">Earl of Abergavenny</hi>, went down with his ship on the Shambles rocks off
                        Portland Bill, on 5 February 1805.</note> I fear too he loses much of his own little property, but <del>of</del> this he is
                    not able to think of or feel. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1805-03-07">Thursday. March 7. 1805.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>