<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce885</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.876</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British
                        Library, Add MS 47890.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 244-248 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.876" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="876" type="letter">
        <head>876. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas
                        Southey</ref>, <date when="1803-12-31">31 December 1803</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Lieutenant Southey/
                        H. M. S. Galatea/ Cove of Cork/ or elsewhere./ Single.<lb />MS: British
                        Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 244-248 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear </salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tom &#8211; (you see my hand slipt down too soon after the address to
                    the place for beginning the letter.) I have just received yours &amp; regret
                    that I did not write sooner upon a reasonable calculation that convoys are even
                    more uncertain than packets. A letter per bottle, I see by the newspapers,
                    thrown in on the way to the West Indies. &#8211; if I recollect right in Lat. 47 &#8211; has
                    found its way by the Isle of Sky, having travelled five miles per day <hi rend="ital">against</hi> prevalent winds &#8211; therefore a current is certain.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">It was widely reported in the press (e.g. <title>Hampshire Telegraph</title> and <title>Sussex Chronicle</title>, 26 December 1803) that a bottle thrown overboard on 9 September 1802 had been recovered on the Isle of Skye on 23 February 1803</note> I
                    will send into town for the paper &amp; send you the particulars if not in this
                    in my next. do not spare bottles on your passage, &amp; be sure that I have a
                    letter from the Western Isles.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope you will received my last time enough to save Henry<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Henry (1718-1790;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of Great Britain</title>, 6 vols
                        (Dublin, 1789), no. 1316 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
                    &#8211; for it will be seized at any English Custom House.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> &amp; his
                    Exeter friends &amp; Exeter creditors I have heard nothing more. I also like you
                    am vexed &#8211; perhaps more vexed than you, being more hopeless of the boy, &amp;
                    more convinced that there is some radical &amp; incurable defect in his nature.
                    that total want of all diffidence &#8211; of all shame which has been apparent in him
                    even from his infancy, is to me something frightful &amp; monstrous. it is as
                    much a defect in moral organization as it is in the bodily frame to be born
                    without head or feet, &amp; God knows a thousand-fold worse in its consequences.
                    No doubt he is returned to <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his infamous
                        Aunt</ref>. you need be under no uneasiness for his immediate fate. but that
                    such a boy can ever turn out well &amp; occasion any thing but grief &amp; shame
                    to his relatives, or obtain any thing but sorrow &amp; shame for himself is
                    according to all my foresight utterly impossible.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For Gods sake adapt your mode of living to the climate you are
                    going to, &amp; abstain almost wholly from wine &amp; spirits. General
                        Pech&#233;,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Pech&#233; (d. 1823),
                        Major-General in the East India Company&#8217;s Army.</note> an East Indian
                    Officer here, with whom we dined on Xmas day, told me that in India the officers
                    who were looking out for preferment &#8211; as a majority &amp;c. &amp; who kept lists
                    of all above them, always marked those who drank any spirits in a morning with a
                    X &amp; reckoned them for nothing. One day, said he, when we were about to march
                    at day break, I &amp; Capt Somebody were in my tent &amp; we saw a German of our
                    Regiment &#8211; so I said we&#8217;d try him. We calld to him &#8211; said it was a cold morning
                    &amp; asked him if he would drink a glass to warm him &#8211; I got him a full beaker
                    of brandy &amp; water &amp; egod &#8211; he drank it off. when he was gone, I said &#8211;
                    Well &#8211; what dy&#8217;e think? We may cross him, may&#8217;nt we? oh yes &#8211; said he &#8211; cross
                    him by all means. And the German did not live twelve months. Spice is the
                    stimulus given by nature to hot countries, &amp; eaten in whatever quantities
                    can do no harm. But the natives of all hot countries invariably abstain from
                    spirits as deadly. eat fruits plentifully &#8211; provided they do not produce flux.
                    animal food sparingly in the hot season &#8211; fish will be better than meat. do not
                    venture to walk or ride in the heat of the sun, &amp; do not be ashamed of a
                    parasol &#8211; it has saved many a mans life. I am sure all this is very physical
                    &amp; philosophical sense. But I will desire <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref>, who knows the West Indies to write out to you a letter of
                    medical advice. this is certain that bilious people fare worst &#8211; &amp; nervous
                    people &#8211; for fear predisposes for disease. from those causes thank God you are
                    safe.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> will go on with Madoc for
                    you, &amp; a letter full shall go off for Barbadoes this week. my last set you
                    upon a wide field of inquiry. I know not what can be added, unless you should be
                    at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincents, where the Caribs<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">St Vincent was one of the few West Indian islands on which
                        the native Carib people had been able to survive.</note> would be well
                    worthy attention, making the same queries, of &amp; to them as to the Negroes.
                    of course there are no Spanish books except at the Spanish islands &#8211; Oh that I
                    were at Mexico for a hunt there! &#8211; could you bring home a live alligator? a
                    little one of course, from his hatching to six feet long &#8211; it would make both me
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> quite happy, for
                    he should have him. &amp; pray &#8211; pray some live land crabs <hi rend="ital">that
                        they may breed</hi>, &amp; any other monsters. birds lose their beauty,
                    &amp; I would not be accessory to the death of a humming bird for the sake of
                    keeping his corpse in a cabinet. but with crocodiles, sharks &amp; land crabs it
                    is fair play &#8211; you catch them or they you. Your own eyes will do all that I
                    could direct them. how unfortunate that neither of us can draw! I want drawings
                    of the trees. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thompson the friend of Burns; whose correspondence with him about
                    songs fills the whole fourth volume &#8211; has applied to me to write him verses for
                    Welsh airs.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">George Thomson (1757-1851;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Select Collection of Welsh Airs Adapted
                            for the Voice, United to Characteristic English Poetry</title>
                        (1809-1817). The correspondence with Robert Burns (1759-1796;
                            <title>DNB</title>) can be found in James Currie (1756-1805;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of Robert Burns: With an Account
                            of His Life</title> (1800).</note> of course I have declined it &#8211;
                    telling him that I could as soon sing his songs as write them &amp; referring
                    him to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> whom he knows,
                    for an estimate of that simily of disqualification. Still I am at reviewing &#8211;
                    but ten days, thank God, will lighten me of that burthen &amp; then huzza for
                        history<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished &#8216;History
                        of Portugal&#8217;.</note> &amp; huzza for Madoc<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had completed a version of <title>Madoc</title> in
                        1797-1799 and was revising it for publication. It did not appear until
                        1805.</note> for I shall be a free man again! &#8211; I have bought Pinkertons
                        Geography<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Pinkerton (1758-1826;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Modern Geography</title> (1802), no. 2333 in
                        the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> after all &#8211; for the love of
                    the maps, having none; it is a useful book &amp; will save me trouble.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We shall not think of holding any part of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                        Domingo.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The French army sent to
                        re-conquer its colony of Haiti was being worn down by disease and defeat in
                        1803. The ex-slaves&#8217; success at the Battle of Vertieres on 18 November 1803
                        paved the way for a formal declaration of Haiti&#8217;s independence on 1 January
                        1804. British forces in the West Indies had captured the French islands of
                        St Lucia and Tobago, and intervention in Haiti seemed possible.</note> what
                    has been done can only have been for the sake of what plunder was to be found,
                    &amp; perhaps also to save the French army from the fate which they so justly
                    deserved &#8211; God Almighty forbid that ever English hand be raised against the
                    Negroes in that Island. poor wretches &#8211; I regard them as I do the hurricane
                    &amp; the pestilence, blind instruments of righteous retribution &amp; divine
                    justice; &amp; sure I am that whatever hand be lifted against them will be
                    withered. Of Spanish politics I can say nothing &#8211; nor give even a surmise. here
                    at home we have the old story of invasion &#8211; my notion is that the newspaper
                    editors set up God save the King in their offices, upon which the types
                    naturally range themselves into a very alarming &amp; loyal leading paragraph.
                    Let him come, say I, it will be a fine thing for bell ringers &amp; the tallow
                    chandlers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I trust this will reach you before your departure. write
                    immediately on your arrival &amp; afterwards by every packet &#8211; for any omission
                    will make me uneasy. I will not be remiss on my part, &amp; Madoc will furnish a
                    pretty large cargo. I design to print it this summer &amp; have already told my
                    friend to procure me subscribers &#8211; but this is done rather to give me a
                    satisfactory answer to them who say why do you not publish by subscription &#8211;
                    than with any hopes of success. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. </salute>
          <salute>&#8211; A happy new year &amp; many returns! R S.</salute>
          <date when="1803-12-31"> Dec. 31. 1803.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>