<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce684</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.675</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        47890.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        275-277.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.675" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="675" type="letter">
        <head>675. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1802-05-10">10 May 1802</date>
          </head><p>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        47890<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        275-277.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been procrastinating my letter day after day in the hope
                    of knowing when we may escape from London, a place which fine spring weather is
                    rendering intolerable. There are some particulars which should be ascertained
                    before my departure &#8211; &amp; these are not in my own reach. I wish to know
                    whether I am to continue doing nothing for <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Corry</ref> another year &#8211; probably not. &#8211; in that case &#8211; is it necessary
                    that I should dangle after him to Ireland for a couple of months. these things
                        <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> will find out for me. my
                        <hi rend="ital">hope</hi> is to leave town on Tuesday in the next week. Of
                    what is to be done thereafter it would be foolish to say anything &#8211; as we know
                    nothing. only &#8211; if as I believe my unsecretaryfying takes place I shall wish to
                    fix somewhere.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Days &amp; weeks slip away one like another &#8211; &amp; from the
                    eternal round of visiting in which I am unavoidably involved, so little is done
                    that I wonder so much time can have past so idly. Since my last we have had <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> in town &amp; by this
                    time he is in Paris: he is wonderfully improved. you will rarely see so fine a
                    young man. &amp; we have had a procession &#8211; a beggarly one God knows to proclaim
                        Peace.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The governments of England and
                        France had signed the Peace of Amiens on 25 March 1802. There was a
                        procession through the City of London to celebrate the peace on 29 April
                        1802.</note> We were all marshalled in battle array on the leads before our
                    parlour windows to see it &#8211; &amp; at night we all went with all the rest of the
                    foolish people in London to see the Illumination<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In celebration of the treaty, areas of central London and
                        other towns and cities across Britain were illuminated.</note> &amp;
                    actually did see M. Ottos<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis-Guillaume
                        Otto, Comte de Mosloy (1753-1817), the French diplomat responsible for
                        negotiating the peace treaty. His residence in London was illuminated as
                        part of the celebrations of 1802; see Robert Southey, <title>Letters from
                            England</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), I, pp. 89, 93-95.</note> house &#8211;
                    which every body tried to do but every body did not succeed. I thought <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> wrong in attempting it &#8211; but
                    she chose to go &#8211; &amp; having been in Portugal I knew it was difficult to make
                    a Mule change her mind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now that my journey to Bristol is so near you will not wonder
                    that I think of half a hundred walks, long &amp; short. the bare recollection of
                    a green field &amp; an open horizon makes me gasp for fresh air. the sound of a
                    brook &amp; the smell of some hedge bank flowers will be a half heaven to me. I
                    am weary of this unsettled vagabond life &amp; seriously disposed to fix
                    somewhere in the country &#8211; devote myself to my history<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s projected &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> &amp; look
                    for nothing else. the steady labour of three years would compleat as much as
                    could be finished in England &amp; from my present materials. I expect &#8211; I have
                    a right to expect &amp; to calculate upon 500 &#163; for each quarto volume. 2500 &#163;
                    at the end of that labour would be to me a fortune. meantime there will be
                    Kehama, there will be Madoc,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The
                            Curse of Kehama</title>, published in 1810. Southey had only drafted
                        Book 1 by this date; <title>Madoc</title>, which he had written in 1797-1799
                        and was revising for publication, did not appear until 1805.</note> &amp;
                    the more certain profits of obscure journey work &#8211; the Jack Ketch<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Jack (John) Ketch (d. 1686; <title>DNB</title>),
                        public executioner whose name and reputation for brutality entered into
                        popular mythology.</note> work of the Review &#8211; the putting living authors to
                    death &#8211; &amp; the raising old Amadis<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation of the romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> was
                        published in 1803.</note> from the dead. I know &amp; feel that I escape
                    transportation to Ireland &amp; can remain the summer &amp; autumn at Bristol &#8211;
                    that I shall work willingly &amp; well, &amp; gallop thro cantos of Kehama
                    before breakfast. Bristol is still the place to which I most cling &#8211; very often
                    do I remember <ref target="places.html#Westbury">Westbury</ref> &#8211; &amp; wish
                    that the years which are past could return &amp; that the grave could give up
                    its dead. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="center">_______</p>
        <p>The Welsh Bard is here &#8211; Edward Williams<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The poet and forger Edward Williams (1746-1826; <title>DNB</title>), who
                        published in English and Welsh and used the pseudonym Iolo Morganwg.</note>
                    &#8211; old &amp; infirm &amp; poor. poor fellow &#8211; but brimfull of genius &amp;
                    jacobinism. have I written to you since my visit to my &#8220;cousin Southeys.&#8221;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">As Southey&#8217;s paternal uncles had no
                        children, the cousins were fairly distant ones. Southey&#8217;s
                        great-great-great-great-grandfather, Thomas Southey (c. 1550-1601?) had nine
                        sons and may have been their common ancestor.</note> two young men both with
                    large families. &amp; apparently very opulent. the family blood it may be &#8211; but
                    by the Lord it is not the family brains. I saw but one M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                    Southey &amp; she was M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Thomas S. a proud &amp;
                    ill-looking woman who probably passes for handsome. we did not make out the
                    actual angle of cousinship. there was some old Southey who had nine sons &#8211; &amp;
                    when nine lines flew off at a tangent they puzzled <del rend="strikethrough">my</del> &lt;our&gt; poor heads. I knew nothing more than that, reasoning
                    from analogy, I must had a grandfather. The Welshmen<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Williams and (probably) <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen Pughe</ref>; see
                        Southey to Charles Danvers, 5 April 1802, Letter 668.</note> were there,
                    &amp; their company with my Cousins dinner made a pleasant day. &#8211; Thank you for
                    what you say about money. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>
                    has not said any thing to me about his debt to you. nor shall I need it. my
                    existing quarter has not been paid in advance. I wish it were not spending in
                    advance &#8211; but on the whole I shall manage with little difficulty &amp; arrive at
                    Bristol with about forty pounds in my pocket. in the middle of July I shall
                    receive forty more. at Michaelmas my year will be up. from the sale at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> there will come some little &#8211; from
                    20 to thirty pounds. &amp; the sixty for Amadis will be paid when the book is
                    done &#8211; some time probably in August. the Bristol bills <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> will pay <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxxxx</del>. things will go on smoothly if I can but
                    stay in one place. That old scoundrel <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">Lovell</ref>! &#8211; if I can but shame him into any thing it will be well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is getting well
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref>
                    writes word. we hear nothing of seperation. As he has wisely made it the gossip
                    of all his acquaintance here. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is very happy, with a happy insensibility to the future &#8211;
                    dreaming what great things he will do, but he has not yet made up his mind which
                    thing to do first. poor fellow he was certainly cut out for a gentleman &#8211; one of
                    lifes butterflies, &#8211; I see him very often. he provokes me by sawneying ever so
                    purportless an existence &#8211; but for all that <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George</ref> is a good fellow &#8211; &amp;
                    there is something in him that makes me love him better than nine tenths of my
                    acquaintance. We are going to Richmond on Thursday to pass the day &amp; night
                    with <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has never yet been there. then
                    I trust our visiting ends &#8211; I will come on the Tuesday if possible &#8211; not only
                    because I wish to come &#8211; but because I am afraid to stay &#8211; being in bodily fear
                    of [Southey inserts profile sketch of a man with a very large aquiline
                        nose]<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Kenneth Curry, <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, p. 277, suggests this may be a caricature of William Godwin.</note> I
                    have terrified <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> with the news of
                    his coming. he actually perspires at the thought.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Kings</ref> is an excellent drawing.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A sketch of the muniment room in St Mary
                        Redcliffe, Bristol, where Thomas Chatterton had supposedly discovered
                        manuscripts by the monk Thomas Rowley (c. 1400-1470). John King&#8217;s drawing
                        was used for the engraving opposite the title page of <title>The Works of
                            Thomas Chatterton</title>, 3 vols (London, 1803), II, unpaginated. It
                        was entitled &#8216;Interior of the Room in Redcliff Church where Rowleys
                        Manuscripts were Said to have been Deposited&#8217;.</note> I shall speedily write
                    to thank him. you see <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">my Member</ref> is
                    returned to town.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A statue to Pitt!!!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        subscription to erect a statue to the former Prime Minister William Pitt
                        (1759-1806; <title>DNB</title>) had been started at Lloyd Coffee House,
                        London, on 8 May 1802. Local and national newspapers continued to publish
                        updated lists of subscribers, for example, the <title>Derby Mercury</title>,
                        24 June 1802.</note> will there be no evil disposed persons in this part of
                    the world? <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx of xxx</del> I thought directly how
                        <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> was cut down.
                        Addington<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Addington, Viscount
                        Sidmouth (1757-1844; <title>DNB</title>), The Speaker 1789-1801, Prime
                        Minister 1801-1804, Home Secretary 1812-1822.</note> is a miserable creature
                    &#8211; but any thing is better than the last ministry. I wanted a transparency for
                    the illumination. Peace beckoning to Justice &#8211; with a distant view of the
                    gallows.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. our love to <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Danvers</ref>.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1802-05-10">Monday May 10. 1802.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>