<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce881</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.872</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47890.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.872" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="872" type="letter">
        <head>872. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1803-12-23">23 December 1803</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Bristol <lb />Stamped: [illegible]<lb />Postmark: E/ DEC
                        26/ 1803<lb />Endorsements: [illegible words and figures on address
                        sheet]<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I began to wonder at your silence &#8211; or rather in truth to feel
                    very uneasy, considering your last account of your health.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> First &amp; foremost I have to tell you that what you have been
                    wishing to take place is likely to come to pass by the latter end of
                        spring.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith Southey was pregnant
                        with her second child, Edith May Southey, who was born on 30 April
                        1804.</note> I have so little internally subdued the last loss that this is
                    not as yet any matter of joy to me. I rather look on with a sort of cowardice &#8211;
                    but all will come in <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> good time. my optimism
                    is of a practical character &#8211; if we knew as much of the moral world as we do of
                    the physical I believe we should find it as wisely &amp; unerringly directed.
                    secondly I wish you to give <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">George
                        Fricker</ref> five guineas for me. poor fellow I wish it were in my power to
                    serve him essentially &#8211; if he had but the head of my brothers &#8211; or they had his
                    good disposition, which God knows is worth ten times more &#8211; what a happy mixture
                    it would be!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whether or not I told you the whole history of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> I cannot remember &#8211; that he
                    drew on me two drafts &#8211; one for three pounds &#8211; the other for 5 &#8211; 13 &#8211; &amp;
                    inclosed me a taylors bill for 11 &#8211; 16 &#8211; 3&#189;. before my Gentleman received the
                    news that I should pay neither the one nor the other he writes to inform me, in
                    answer to my letter about his going to sea again &#8211; that <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his Aunt</ref> had sold all his uniforms
                    to a travelling Jew. of course I could then do nothing but tell him that he
                    &amp; she might settle their matters as they pleased, &amp; so I have done with
                    him. In his last letter he let the cat out of the bag, showing that he was still
                    in correspondence with <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his Aunt</ref>.
                    I have copied his letters &amp; sent them to <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> that he may see that
                    infamous womans conduct. I wish she knew that since she took the boy from the
                        Brig,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">HMS <hi rend="ital">Suffisante</hi>, the brig-sloop on which Southey had found his brother
                        a place.</note> it has been so successful that his share of prize money,
                    sharing only as a foremast man would have exceeded three hundred pounds, more
                    money than <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has made in ten years
                    service. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> tells me this. I wish
                    she knew it because in all probability she would have fingered the money. &#8211; Tom
                    is now first Lieutenant &#8211; &amp; I am sorry to add &#8211; going out with convoy to the
                    West Indies.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will be glad to hear that I am in excellent good health,
                    never better. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is
                    set off for Devonshire &#8211; not Madeira, deterred by the dread of expences beyond
                    his means &amp; resolved to work for a supply by next autumn. I miss him &#8211; but
                    still worse do I miss my poor dear books, &amp; the booksellers shops. Can you
                    not look in at Codys<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Cody&#8217;s identity is
                        uncertain. One possibility is that he is the book-auctioneer William Cody
                        (dates unknown) whose business had been based in Dublin c. 1791-1797. If so,
                        Southey may have made his acquaintance during his time in <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> in 1802. Cody could be the same
                        person as, or connected to, the bookseller and auctioneer of the same name
                        who traded in Bristol c. 1820-1821.</note> for me sometimes &amp; see what
                    Voyages &amp; Travels he has &#8211; &amp; so enable me to make purchases by letter.
                    My second batch of reviewing is gone off &amp; a third arrived just as it went,
                    so that my hands are again full. but I shall soon have done.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref>
                    books. those foreign ones which are in English binding are not liable to duty,
                    &amp; any person at all conversant in books can ascertain English from foreign
                    binding as readily as English from Hebrew. In the small case he says there are
                    many which would be useful to me &#8211; I wish he had sent me a list of them &#8211; &amp;
                    am almost tempted to have the case sent off. the loss of those from Falmouth
                    sadly grieves me. what answer did you get from Russell<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to Thomas Russell &amp; Co., the largest
                        carriers in the West Country, who ran a service from Falmouth to Exeter and
                        London. At this time the business was run by Robert Russell (fl.
                        1792-1816).</note> the waggoner concerning them?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had frost &amp; snow in their full beauty &#8211; &amp; in
                    truth nothing could be more beautiful. now after many days rain it is like June.
                    I have sallied out like a bear from his den, &amp; this morning walked round the
                    Lake, which is a work of more than three hours. If I had but my books I should
                    do very well here, &amp; could with little effort forego society &#8211; but it will
                    never do to live at such a distance from all libraries, hun[MS torn]ring &amp;
                    thirsting for them as I do, &amp; daily as I learn more, discovering, how much I
                    have yet to learn. however here we are, &amp; here for awhile we must remain &#8211;
                    probably till we fix definitively or till I go once more to Portugal. The wine
                    not yet arrived &#8211; I shall write to Liverpool to inquire concerning it, for it
                    ought to have been here surely by this time. &#8211; Inquire of James<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac James (b. 1759) was the son of Samuel
                        James (1716-1773), Baptist minister at Hitchin. He came to Bristol in 1773
                        as a student at the Baptist Academy. He kept a shop as a bookseller,
                        teadealer (and sometimes undertaker) first in North Street and then in Wine
                        Street. He was a member of the Baptist meeting at Broadmead and served as
                        classical tutor at the Baptist Academy in Bristol from 1796 to 1825. During
                        the late 1790s and early 1800s, James collaborated with Joseph Cottle in
                        selling numerous works, mostly by dissenters. Among James&#8217;s own works were
                            <title>Providence Displayed: or, The Remarkable Adventures of Alexander
                            Selkirk</title> (1800). He also tried his hand at poetry, including
                            <title>The Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress. The First Part: Rendered into Familiar
                            Verse</title> (1815), as well as a polemical work, <title>An Essay on
                            the Sign of the Prophet Jonah</title> (1802). An associate of the
                        members of the Baptist Missionary Society Committee, James was well placed
                        to supply the <title>Periodical Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary
                            Society</title> (1800-1817). These were published as a periodical
                        beginning in 1793, but then as bound volumes beginning in 1800.</note> if
                    there be any more numbers of the Periodical Accounts of the Baptist Mission<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had reviewed <title>Periodical
                            Accounts Relative to the Baptist Missionary Society</title> (1800-1801),
                        in <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803), 207-218.</note> since No
                    XI &#8211; &amp; if so get them for me &#8211; &amp; let Barry<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the Bristol bookbinder, printer and stationer
                        Bartholomew Barry (fl. 1790s-1830s).</note> get for me the Transactions of
                    the Missionary Society,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed
                        London Missionary Society, <title>Transactions of the Missionary
                            Society</title> (1803) for <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2
                        (1804), 189-201.</note> which are to be published half-yearly &#8211; he is the
                    pleasantest bookseller in Bristol by far &#8211; &amp; I like to keep up an
                    acquaintance with him &amp; James &lt;Cody&gt; at a distance. Jamess new
                    Pilgrims Progress<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac James, <title>The
                            Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress: From This World, to That Which is to Come</title>
                        (1815).</note> is upon a very excellent idea, &amp; far more in old
                        Bunyans<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bunyan (1628-1688;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress</title>
                        (1678-1684).</note> spirit than any thing I ever saw. What news of my books
                    from Leghorn by way of <ref target="people.html#ReidSamuel">Sam Reid</ref>? or
                    has Bonaparte<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                        (1769-1821, First Consul 1799-1804, Emperor of the French 1804-1814).</note>
                    swallowed ship &amp; all?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> &#8211;
                    &amp; to Hort<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William Jillard Hort
                        (1764-1849), Unitarian Minister and writer.</note> &#8211; &amp; I wish you could
                    to Cupid<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Danvers&#8217;s dog.</note> &#8211;
                    poor fellow he would be very jealous to see me play with Dapper, but tho Dapper
                    is a very intelligent &amp; well-informed dog he is not so good a companion as
                    my poor Cupid. &amp; how goes on Joe?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey&#8217;s dog.</note> &#8211; &amp; how do you &amp; Betty<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Danvers&#8217;s servant, her first name and dates are
                        unknown.</note> go on in your great house? but above all <hi rend="ital">how
                        are you</hi>? how I beseech you write &#8211; if only to answer that question.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. God bless you
                        &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R S. </signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1803-12-23">Dec. 23. 1803.</date>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
          </address>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>