<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce237</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.237</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 136&#8211;138.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.237" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="237" type="letter">
        <head>237. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1797-07-19">19 July [1797]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: C W Williams Wynn
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 5. Stone Buildings &#8212; Lincolns Inn/
                        London<lb />Stamped: RINGWOOD<lb />Postmark: AJY/ 20/ 97<lb />Watermark: Crest/
                        G R<lb /> Endorsement: July 19/ 1797<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 136&#8211;138.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1797-07-19">Wednesday 19 July.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter arrived yesterday by the return of the Mail,
                    consequently too late for an answer. this was owing to the direction which I
                    thought you had known. &#8220;<ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> near
                    Ringwood.&#8221; my letters thus directed are taken out of the Ringwood bag &amp;
                    left at the door as the Post Boy passes; if sent to Ch. Ch. he brings them as he
                    returns.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall soon I think be master of Blackstone.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Blackstone (1723&#8211;1780; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Commentaries on the Laws of
                            England</title> (1765&#8211;1769).</note> you will regulate my after studies
                    by the line you think best for me &#8212; I only beg it may be that which will the
                    soonest enable me to leave it. a good lawyer I certainly will be, but have no
                    wish to be a great one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The ninth book of Joan of Arc will be omitted, &amp;
                    published seperately, with some enlargement.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey removed the 1796 version of book nine from the second
                        edition of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, and revised and expanded it
                        into &#8216;The Vision of the Maid of Orleans&#8217;, first published in his <title level="m">Poems</title> (1799).</note> the objection that satire is
                    misplaced will therefore no longer be valid, if it ever were which I perhaps
                    doubt &#8212; &amp; I think the lines good in themselves. there are
                    &lt;some&gt; very bad ones Page 334 which are condemned <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> for they have not a solitary excuse. The
                    outline of my alterations is briefly this &#8212; to make the Maid relate her
                    knowledge of her own death to Conrade Book 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. to alter the
                    discovery of the arms, so as to reduce the story as much as possible to a moral
                    miracle, there is too much clock-work in it now. I would therefore if possible
                    omit the miraculous healing of Dunois but I have no idea yet how to alter the
                    beginning if this be done. the new ninth book will be the detachment of Burgundy
                    from the English interest by the Maid, which of course will be made <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> essential to the success of the whole. I
                    annihilate all Isabels similies, because country girls are not addicted to them.
                    my verbal alterations will be numberless. Will you transcribe for me a few lines
                    from Hall<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The chronicler Edward Hall
                        (1497&#8211;1547; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> for a note? merely the
                    sentence that says the Maid made her first entry into Orleans in a thunder
                    storm. if you meet with any <del rend="strikethrough">anec&#8212;</del> anecdotes of
                    Joan that may have escaped me, I will make good use of them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Tragedy would advance rapidly if I stole time enough, for I
                    have both brain &amp; back-bone full of ideas for it. it comes on very
                    slowly. of the three acts one is about three parts finished. One fortnight given
                    heartily to it would be enough &amp; then three months correction would make
                    it better than a seven years writing. The Maids martyrdom seems almost a
                    necessary supplement to the poem, &amp; the subject suits me. but if I had
                    not other employment than poetry I should scarcely venture upon the drama. I can
                    manage the Epic better, &amp; that has every dramatic advantage if well
                    handled. perhaps Tassos<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Torquato Tasso
                        (1544&#8211;1595), <title level="m">Jerusalem Delivered</title>
                        (1580&#8211;1581).</note> is the most interesting that has yet appeared. with
                    Homer &amp; Milton no future indeed no other poems can be compared the age
                    of the one &amp; the subject of the other preclude it, independant of their
                    unequalld &amp; perhaps <hi rend="ital">unequalable</hi> merit. But I will
                    &lt;not&gt; allow this to Virgil. his story never can interest,
                    &amp; this is a grievous fault. I read all the obscure epic writers I can
                    lay my hands on. there is one advantage which a dull book possesses, no good
                    thing is lost &#8212; like the dunghill diamond you are sure to see it shine &#8212; or more
                    like a farthing candle in a dark night. These writers are sad imitators &#8212; I
                    might say thieves, for I believe privately borrowing would be interpreted theft
                    at the old Bailey. Did I tell you I had got Chapelain?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapelain (1595&#8211;1674), <title level="m">La Pucelle ou la
                            France D&#233;livr&#233;e</title> (1656). Southey included a summary of it in the
                        second edition of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, published in
                        1798.</note> &amp; <hi rend="ital">how</hi> bad he was?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have prohibited in Madoc &amp; Joan all long speeches,
                    catalogues of armies or navies, geographical descriptions, shield paintings,
                    lists of killed &amp; wounded, prophecies, compliments, lions wolves tygers
                    &amp; all other wild beasts, Auroras, &amp; all the getting up &amp;
                    going to bed of Phoebus. Tempests too are forbidden &#8212; you will be pleased to see
                    how I have managed one in Madoc. item all Devils &amp; Angels &#8212; Gods
                    &amp; Goddesses &#8212; in brief the whole stock in trade of Chapelain Bla[MS
                    torn]more &amp; fifty more. all allegorical personages are included. the
                    subject of Joan is miraculous &#8212; but I have no miracle in Madoc. he is landed
                    now. I wish you would pick me out from the Royal Commentaries of Peru<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Garcilaso de la Vega (1501&#8211;1536), <title level="m">The Royal Commentaries of Peru</title> (1688).</note> if you
                    meet with them or indeed where ever you can, a Peruvian mans name fit for
                    poetry. I have enough of Mexican ones, &amp; am somewhat puzzled to lick the
                    ladies into shape. what think of you of Atotoztli &amp; Tziltomiauh? these
                    are perfect beauties compared with Tlacapantzin &amp; Ilancueith &amp;c.
                    I must spell it Ziltomia &amp; its physiognomy is bearable. I know a man who
                    introduced Agraganda as one of Julius Caesars friends, &amp; made Clomanthus
                    a very accomplished English Lady in the days of James 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> Do
                    christen me a Peruvian &#8212; I should like to say all the names are appropriate.
                    &#8220;these little traits&#8221; as Puff says.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        catchphrase of Puff in Richard Brinsley Sheridan (1751&#8211;1816; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Critic</title>
                        (1779).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The old Lady Strathmore<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Eleanor Bowes (1749&#8211;1800; <title level="m">DNB</title>), heiress,
                        botanist and author of a five act play, <title level="m">The Siege of
                            Jerusalem</title> (1769). Her first husband was John Lyon (1737&#8211;1776),
                        9th Earl of Strathmore and Kinghorne, her second the fortune-hunter Andrew
                        Robinson Stoney (1747&#8211;1810). In 1789, her abusive marriage to Stoney ended
                        in an acrimonious and scandalous divorce.</note> has some curious books. I
                    hope to get from her library the Amadigi of Tassos father.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Bernardo Tasso (1493&#8211;1569), author of an epic on
                        Amadis of Gaul.</note> if he had been a very bad poet Tasso would never have
                    published his works &#8212; &amp; I love every thing belonging to Amadis &amp;
                        Galaor.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Two central characters in
                        the romance <title level="m">Amadis of Gaul</title> (1560).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. if you can get me any poetical information about
                    the River of Amazons I shall be glad &#8212; but I must have no Amazons as Madoc was
                    buried long before Orellana learnt to tell lies. <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco de Orellana (c. 1500&#8211;c. 1549), Spanish conquistador
                        who, in 1542, allegedly encountered the Amazons on the South American river
                        he decided to name after them.</note> Did you ever see Madame Godines
                    melancholy account? <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Isabel Godin des
                        Odonais (d. 1792) related her epic journey across South America in <title level="m">Lettre Contenant la Relation des Madame Godin (par le Fleuve
                            des Amazons)</title> (1778).</note> I shall allude to it by &amp;
                    by.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>