<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce217</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.217</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Morgan Library, MA Unassigned [The letter accompanied the manuscript of the second edition of Southey&#8217;s Poems (1797), Morgan Library, MA 414.].  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 127&#8211;129 [where it is misdated [4 May 1797]].Dating note: The dating of this letter is from internal evidence. It was written on Thursday, 18 May, before Southey left for Ringwood, Hampshire, on Wednesday 24 May 1797.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.217" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="217" type="letter">
        <head>217. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1797-05-18">[c. 18 May 1797]</date>
          </head><p>Address: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/ High Street/ Bristol<lb />Endorsements: Southey 1797; (<del rend="strikethrough">98</del>) <hi rend="ital">13</hi>
            <lb />MS: Morgan Library, MA Unassigned [The letter accompanied the manuscript of the second edition of Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797), Morgan Library, MA 414.]<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 127&#8211;129 [where it is misdated [4 May 1797]].<lb />Dating note: The dating of this letter is from internal evidence. It was written on Thursday, 18 May, before Southey left for Ringwood, Hampshire, on Wednesday 24 May 1797.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1797-05-18">Thursday night</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Cottle</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2">		You will I believe find my directions to the Printer marked with sufficient minuteness in the book.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The letter contains instructions for the printing of the second edition of Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797).</note> it may however be right to tell you, that I would have all the lines alike under the headings &amp; above the notes, &amp; those lines like that under The Triumph of Woman P.7. All the prefaces like that to Rudiger. &amp; no ornaments at the end of each poem. I have put my new arrangement by the Contents. let the Contents be printed exactly in the same manner that they are now. &#8220;Lyric Poems&#8221; &amp; &#8220;Musings&#8221; must each have a black letter title page. I do not think the first Birth day Ode deserves to be reprinted. if however you wish it, it may be inserted the first of the Lyric poems; entitled &#8220;To a Friend on his birthday, &amp; the motto, now assigned to the other, affixed to that.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8217;Birth-Day Ode, 1793&#8217; was omitted from the second edition of Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797) and &#8216;Birth-Day Ode, 1796&#8217; was retitled &#8216;To a Friend&#8217;.</note> this is if you wish it. I condemn the poem &amp; we can spare five pages. the note opposite P. 143 is strictly true; &amp; I should think myself criminal in suppressing so authentic a picture of the horrors of war.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A description of an incident reported to have occurred during the British army&#8217;s retreat to Deventer in 1795.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Cannot the Printers Alphabet or catch letter be omitted? or at least stuck in the corner where it may be cut off in binding? why will not the paging be guide enough for the bookbinder?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	If you have any alteration to suggest it is not yet too late. <hi rend="ital">Do not let them split stanzas</hi>. <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Estlin</ref> will perhaps be kind enough to correct the little Greek there is. Let me likewise again request that I may have a dozen copies upon large paper &#8212; such as the presentation copies of <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">Estlins</ref> sermon;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably John Prior Estlin, <title level="m">The Nature and Causes of Atheism, Pointed Out in a Discourse, Delivered at the Chapel in Lewin&#8217;s-Mead, Bristol. To Which are Added, Remarks on a Work, entitled Origine de Tous Les Cultes, ou Religion Universelle. Par Dupuis, Citoyen Fran&#231;ois</title> (1797).</note>  &amp; I would advise you likewise to have a few for your more particular friends.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	All the mottos should be in Italics.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#Peacockunknown">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Peacock</ref> has not yet had from me all the copies. I shall leave them for him with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> P. thus have we settled. of course we have as yet come to no account, excepting that I do not pay him my quarters rent, but shall send the ten pounds to you, as soon as I receive my money from Cadell &amp; Davies,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The London booksellers and publishers Thomas Cadell Jnr (1773&#8211;1836; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and William Davies (d. 1820).</note> which I daily expect, &amp; which, if I do not receive it before I leave town, will be remitted to me thro <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref>. <ref target="people.html#Peacockunknown">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Peacock</ref> has had from me 29 Letters &amp; 32 &lt;Poems&gt; in all. he has no doubt of disposing of more than are now in readiness for him. <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> I ordered 12 Poems &#8212; 18 Letters from <ref target="people.html#Robinsonfamily">Robinsons</ref> when he first wanted 12 of each; as I wanted two Letters for <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George Dyer</ref> &#8212; &amp; <ref target="people.html#JenningsJames">James Jennings</ref>, &amp; 4 to send to Lisbon. those 4 <ref target="people.html#Peacockunknown">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Peacock</ref> had, &amp; I was (as I told you at the time) obliged to replace them from <ref target="people.html#Robinsonfamily">Robinsons</ref>, as <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> was leaving town who was to carry them to Lisbon. so that you must add to my debtor account 12 P. 22 L.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	You should have sent <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas&#8217;s</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> &amp; the Bedfords<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Walpole Bedford</ref>.</note> copies of Achmed,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Fox (1740?&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">'Aks-i partaw. A Series of Poems, Containing the Plaints, Consolations, and Delights of Achmed Ardebeili, a Persian Exile</title> (1797).</note> to me. it would have been better to have sent the parcel up in <ref target="people.html#Robinsonfamily">Robinsons</ref>. it cost 2s &amp; 4d. &#8212; these rascals always impose upon me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I am you see writing a mere letter of business. why am I &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> put down &#8220;Bristol&#8221; in the list of subscribers with which the book is disgraced?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	As I have given such full directions it would be useless to write any thing to <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Biggs</ref> as I at first intended. I am now much hurried. we dine out tomorrow &amp; I mean to drop the parcel on the road. but I will not lose the opportunity of writing to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#GilbertWilliam">Gilbert</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	You will of course advertise my other books at the end of the volume. I can trust <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Biggs</ref>; but if ever I were condemned to go thro <ref target="people.html#RosserRobert">Rossers</ref> press, &amp; his journeymans correction, I would have every sheet sent to me.</p>
        <p>God bless you. we go Wednesday. I will write to you as soon as we are settled. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. yrs affectionately</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent8">						Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I have not time to write to <ref target="people.html#GilbertWilliam">Gilbert</ref> &#8212; as an opportunity has just offered of sending this safely to Bath. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>