<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce232</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.232</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Beinecke Library, Chauncey Brewster Tinker MS Collection, GEN MSS 310, Box 13, folder 552.  Previously  published: Lynda Pratt, &#8216;Interaction, Reorientation, and Discontent in the Coleridge Southey Circle, 1797: Two New Letters by Robert Southey&#8217;, Notes and Queries, 47.3 (2000), 314&#8211;321.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.232" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="232" type="letter">
        <head>232. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1797-07-11">11 July 1797</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/4. Bedford Square/ London/ Single<lb />Stamped: RINGWOOD<lb />Postmark: AJY/ 12/ 97<lb />Endorsement: 1797 No. 3/ Robert Southey/ Burton 11 July/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 12 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 18 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Beinecke Library, Chauncey Brewster Tinker MS Collection, GEN MSS 310, Box 13, folder 552<lb />Previously published: Lynda Pratt, &#8216;Interaction, Reorientation, and Discontent in the Coleridge Southey Circle, 1797: Two New Letters by Robert Southey&#8217;, <title level="j">Notes and Queries</title>, 47.3 (2000), 314&#8211;321.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1797-07-11">July 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1797. Tuesday.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	I thank you for Chapelain.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey included an account of Jean Chapelain&#8217;s (1595&#8211;1674) epic poem <title level="m">La Pucelle ou la France D&#233;livr&#233;e</title> (1656) in the second edition of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, published in 1798.</note> I read his poem with the hope of finding something &lt;good&gt; &amp; would gladly have reversed the sentence of condemnation, which I must in common honesty confirm. it is very bad indeed, &amp; &lt;can&gt; please only by its extreme absurdity. I have analyzed it, &amp; the analysis will amuse you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I thank you also for your good opinion of me. I would fain be thought well of by the &#8220;ten righteous men&#8221;,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of <title level="m">Genesis</title> 18: 32.</note> &amp; communicate frequently with you as one of them. I too pity the mob of mankind, the oppressors as well as the oppressed, but my pity is strongly tinctured with hatred for the one &amp; contempt for the other. mental anguish can punish but a very small part of the wicked, because that acuteness of feeling which is the best preservative of virtue, is blunted in them, &amp; because &#8220;they know not what they do.&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">Luke</title> 23: 34.</note> look at the plunderers of Hindostan, &amp; the Sugar merchants of our West India islands; these men have no consciences; one memorable exception should never be forgot, the death of the infamous Lord Clive.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Clive, 1st Baron Clive of Plassey (1725&#8211;1774; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Governor of Bengal, was found guilty of maladministration by a parliamentary inquiry in 1773. His death, which Southey attributed to a guilty conscience, was almost certainly suicide.</note> but what is one exception from such a herd of murderers? The lower classes have indeed the terrors of religion, &amp; that man is indeed devoutly to be pitied to whom religion has terrors! but the annals of Tyburn rarely record contrition. in general they either astonish us at the obdurate wickedness of the criminal, or the dreadful effects of our laws. do you remember the case of Mary Jones<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Jones&#8217;s case had been cited in parliamentary debates in late 1777 as an example of the injustices of the penal code: &#8216;It was at the time when press-warrants were issued on the alarm about Falkland&#8217;s Islands. The woman&#8217;s husband was pressed, their goods seized for some debts of his, and she, with two small children, turned into the streets a-begging. &#8217;Tis a circumstance not to be forgotten, that she was very young (under nineteen) and most remarkably handsome. She went to a linen-draper&#8217;s shop, took some coarse linen off the counter, and slipped it under her cloak; the shopman saw her, and she laid it down: for this she was hanged &#8230; When brought to receive sentence she behaved in such a frantic manner, as proved her mind to be in a distracted and desponding state; and the child was sucking at her breast when she set out for Tyburn&#8217;, <title level="j">Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title>, 47 (Supplement, 1777), 616.</note> which was mentioned in the H. of Commons in 1777? every circumstance in that most horrible business was enough to have made every honest man sick of &lt;a&gt; society to whose abuses she fell a victim. but had her guilt exceeded that of the most detestable murderer, what must the executioner have been who could tear her infant from her breast, whilst he fitted the rope round her neck? that such a man can exist <del rend="strikethrough">is</del> would be incredible to you &amp; I if experience did <del rend="strikethrough">it</del> not prove such ferocity frequent, but the most dreadful reflection is that this man was doing <del rend="strikethrough">his duty!</del> what the world call &#8212; his duty!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	It is for the sake of society that I would secede from it. it must be many years before this can be practicable, &amp; I look with a very feeble hope to a period so distant. a thousand obstacles may prevent me. the course of nature or the tempest of revolution may sweep me away, or the few individuals who would commit themselves with me to that little Ark. I suffer no gloomy presages to disturb the tranquil happiness with which God has blest me now, &amp; which I know how to value because I have felt what it is to want every thing except the pride of a well satisfied conscience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	the Sister &amp; niece of Chatterton<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Chatterton&#8217;s (1752&#8211;1770; <title level="m">DNB</title>) sister, Mary Newton (1749&#8211;1804; <title level="m">DNB</title>), and her daughter.</note> are now wholly destitute. on this occasion I appear as editor of all his works for their relief. this is a heinous sin against the worlds opinion for a young lawyer! but it would have &lt;been&gt; a real crime to have refused it. We have a black scene of iniquity to lay before the public. these poor women have been left in want while a set of scoundrels have been reaping hundreds from the writings of Chatterton. Herbert Croft<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Croft, 5th Baronet (1751&#8211;1816; <title level="m">DNB</title>), writer and lexicographer. In 1778, Croft had acquired Chatterton&#8217;s letters from the poet&#8217;s family. He included some of the correspondence in his novel <title level="m">Love and Madness</title> (1780), keeping any profits for himself. Southey attacked Croft in a letter to the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, November 1799. For an account of the resulting feud see Brian Goldberg, &#8216;Romantic Professionalism in 1800: Robert Southey, Herbert Croft, and the Letters and Legacy of Thomas Chatterton&#8217;, <title level="m">English Literary History</title>, 63 (1996), 681&#8211;706. Southey and Joseph Cottle&#8217;s edition of Chatterton was published in 1803.</note> is the great criminal. I hope now to make the catastrophe to the history of the poor boy of Bristol. you shall see the proposals as soon as they are printed. <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> has been with me a few days, &amp; we have arranged every thing relative to this business. he is the publisher &amp; means to get the paper at prime cost, &amp; receive not the usual profit from what he sells. the accounts will be published, &amp; we hope &amp; expect to place M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Newton in comfort during the last years of her life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> brought with him the new edition of Coleridges poems,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">Poems, by S. T. Coleridge, Second Edition. To Which are Now Added Poems by Charles Lamb, and Charles Lloyd</title> (1797).</note> they are dedicated to his brothe[MS torn] <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">George</ref>, in one of the most beautiful poems I ever read. [MS torn] know <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">S T Coleridge</ref> better than any existing being, &amp; yet great part of his conduct is utterly inexplicable to me. last night I wrote to him, requesting some thing for insertion in Chattertons works that his name might appear in the proposals. I then told him that his brother had not known where he was till he learnt it from you. You will be delighted with his new edition, it contains all the poems of <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref>, &amp; I know no volume that can be compared to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	You know not how infinitely my happiness is increased by residing in the country. I have not a wish beyond the quietness I enjoy. every thing is tranquil &amp; beautiful &#8212; but sometimes I look forward with regret to the time when I must return to a city which I so heartily dislike. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is much better here than in town. I must not forget again to remember her to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	If your brother will send the drawing by Joy,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A local carrier, his first name and dates are unknown.</note> he passes this door &#8212; or to the White Hart Ringwood, the Mail will bring it. I am much obliged to him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	The Captain<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The French naval captain Boutet (first name and dates unknown).</note> who behaved so kindly to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> is now a prisoner himself. I am very anxious to get &lt;him&gt; exchanged the earliest opportunity or to procure his parole. &#8212; I have a heavy complaint against my brothers own captain &#8212; Barlow<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Barlow (1757&#8211;1843; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> of the Ph&#339;be. he wrote to my mother &amp; said there was no danger of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom&#8217;s</ref> being lost as the ship was new &amp; sound. now he knew that the men were obliged to keep every pump at work &amp; had sprung their mast, when for the sake of his prize money he sent my brother to conduct her into port. they were expecting to founder when the privateer took them. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> tho could not refuse to go on board tho he knew his danger &#8212; &amp; this they call discipline. but there are no Court-Martials in the next world, &amp; perhaps not <del rend="strikethrough">a</del> Captains enough to compose one, in that to which my brother will go, if every good quality can carry a young man there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">		yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">				Robert Southey.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">could not refuse Southey: Written on fol. 1 r.</note>
          </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>