<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce112</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.112</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Houghton Library, MS Hyde 77 (9).  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 84&#8211;85.Dating note: Dating follows Kenneth Curry&#8217;s and assumes this letter is written just over a week after Southey&#8217;s violent expulsion from the home of Elizabeth Tyler.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="112" type="letter">
        <head>112. Robert Southey to Miss Fricker [probably <ref target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sarah Fricker</ref>], <date when="1794-10-25">[25 October 1794]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Miss Fricker/ Redclift Hill/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped: BATH<lb />Postmark: [illegible]<lb />Endorsement: Southey<lb /> MS: Houghton Library, MS Hyde 77 (9)<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 84&#8211;85.<lb />Dating note: Dating follows Kenneth Curry&#8217;s and assumes this letter is written just over a week after Southey&#8217;s violent expulsion from the home of Elizabeth Tyler.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1794-10-25">Saturday Night.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref> has sent for you! my dear sister she is a vile woman &#8212; fool enough to be contemptible &amp; rogue enough to be odious. ten years knowledge of her enables me to speak with the asperity of truth. I think you should go to her but not alone. I should be frenzied at the idea that you &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> were exposed to her insults, &#8212; take <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> with you. he will remain one day in Bristol for that purpose &#8212; tell him it is my wish &amp; tell him likewise why. &#8212; if this seems foolish to you act as you think best. I am a good deal agitated at the circumstance &#8212; that detestable woman insulted <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your sister</ref> once &#8212; my blood boils at the recollection. would it not be better to take <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> with you? she would not admit <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref>. &#8212; <del rend="strikethrough">Bra xxxxxxxx sapey xxxxxxx xxxx &lt;only&gt; while? Miss? Bowles her servants with you xx hxxxxx hxxxxx xxxxxxxxxxx xxxxxx xxxxxxxx xxxxx xxxx xxxx</del> it is my decided opinion that you ought not to go. she is our bitter enemy &#8212; Shad,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Miss Tyler&#8217;s footman&#8217; inserted, probably in another, unidentified hand. It refers to <ref target="people.html#WeeksShadrach">Shadrach Weeks</ref>.</note> tells me so in a letter &#8212; the woman who could so insult <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your sister</ref> is capable of any thing. for Gods sake do not let <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> expose herself to a repetition. do not expose yourself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Your sister</ref> is like the lilly of the valley lovely in humility but like that delicate &amp; lowly flower she would bend before the storm of pride. if error can be amicable the error of too much humility is so. I wish <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> would think more highly of herself. tis the only fault I have discovered in her &amp; that is almost a virtue!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I am lonely &amp; dull. poetry is again the employment of a heavy hour &#8212; I fall into the daydreams of fancy &amp; sorrow to be roused from their delusions. but a few months &amp; we shall part no more &#8212; would I could sleep over the interval.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I have begun another letter to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your sister</ref> &#8212; for in fact I have been unfitted to day for any other employment. but perhaps I am too assiduous &#8212; if she felt pleasure at receiving a letter she would communicate it by writing herself &#8212; but she <hi rend="ital">suffers</hi> me to write rather in compliance to my wishes than her own. I must not trespass on this sufferance by writing as often as my heart would dictate. you smile at my weakness &#8212; at the weakness of the stern serious philosophic Robert Southey. but mine is the philosophy of the heart &#8212; &amp; to indulge its virtuous affections has been always a favourite maxim with me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Concerning <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> I have written by <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>. thank God he is coming &#8212; most ardently do I long to see him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	The people talk strangely of us! so let them. can you not smile at the envy &amp; absurdity of the many?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	my dear sister I cannot write to you upon any subject but my own reflections. a trifling incident to day has called up a long train of recollections. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your sister</ref> is not fond of writing &#8212; &amp; why indeed should I plague others with the emotions of this strange mind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	farewell. this is a dull egotistic letter. my heart is heavy &#8212; but I should spare your patience.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent5">					yrs affectionately</salute>
        </closer>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent6">						Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I heard from <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> by the same post that brought your letter. let me hear from you. do you tell me how <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">your sister</ref> is &#8212; she dislikes writing herself &amp; I ought not to urge her against her inclination.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>