<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce228</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.228</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797—1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 25–27; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 315–318 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="228" type="letter">
<head>228. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1797-06-26">26 June 1797</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ 4. Bedford Square/ London<lb/> Stamped: CHRIST/ CHURCH<lb/>Postmark: AJU/ 27/ 97 <lb/>Watermark: Crown &amp; anchor/ GR<lb/>Endorsement: 1797 N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2/ Robert Southey/ Burton 26 June/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 27 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 3 July<lb/> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin<lb/>Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title level="m">The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797—1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 25–27; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), I, pp. 315–318 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1797-06-26">Monday June 26. 1797.</date>
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>.</placeName>
</address>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1">	If you will send Chapelain<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Chapelain (1595–1674), <title level="m">La Pucelle ou la France Délivrée</title> (1656). Southey included a summary of it in the second edition of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, published in 1798.</note> by the Poole Mail &amp; direct it here, the Mail Cart will bring it from Ringwood. the Poole Mail sets out from the Bell &amp; Crown, Holborn.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	Neither the best friends or the bitterest enemies of Chapelain could have felt more curiosity than I do to see his poem. good it cannot be, for tho the habit of writing satire, as indeed the indulgence of any kind of wit, insensibly injures the moral character &amp; disposes it to sacrifice any thing to a good point; yet Boileau<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Despreaux Boileau (1636–1711), French poet and critic.</note> must have had some reason for the extreme contempt in which he held this unfortunate production. I am inclined to think it better however than it has always been represented; Chapelain stood high in poetical reputation when he published this, the work on which he meant to build his fame; he is said to have written good odes, certainly then his epic labours cannot be wholly void of merit, &amp; for its characteristic fault, extreme harshness, it is very probable that a man of genius writing in so unmanly a language should become harsh by attempting to be strong. the French never can have a good epic poem till they have republicanized their language; it appears to me a thing impossible in their metres; &amp; for the prose of Fenelon Florian &amp; Bitaubè<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">François de Salignac de la Mothe-Fénelon (1651–1715), theologian and educator; Paul Jérémie Bitaubé (1731–1808), poet and theologian; Jean-Pierre Claris de Florian (1755–1794), poet.</note> — I find it peculiarly unpleasant. I have sometimes read the works of Florian aloud; his stories are very interesting &amp; well conducted, but in reading them I have <del rend="strikethrough">been</del> felt obliged to simplify as I read &amp; omit most of the similes &amp; apostrophes. they disgusted me &amp; I felt ashamed to pronounce them. Ossian<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The controversial series of poems purportedly written by the ancient bard Ossian (son of Fingal) published by James Macpherson (1736–96; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> is the only book bearable in this stile, there is a melancholy obscurity in the history of Ossian &amp; of almost &lt;all&gt; his heroes that must please — ninety nine readers in an hundred cannot understand Ossian &amp; therefore they like the book. I read it always with renewed pleasure.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	Have you seen Madame Rolands Appel a l’impartiale Posteritè?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Marie-Jeanne Roland de la Platiere (1754–1793), <title level="m">Appel a l’Impartiale Posteritè</title> (1795).</note> it is one of those books that makes me love individuals &amp; yet dread detest &amp; despise mankind in a mass. there was a time when I believed in the persuadibility of man &amp; had the mania of man-mending; experience has taught me better. after a certain age the organs of voice cannot accommodate themselves to the utterance of a foreign pronunciation; so is it with the mind, it grows stiff &amp; unyielding like our sinews as we grow older. the ablest physician can do little in the great lazar-house of society. it is a pest-house that infects all within its atmosphere; he acts the wisest part who retires from the contagion; nor is that part either a selfish or a cowardly one; it is ascending the Ark like Noah to preserve a remnant which may become the whole.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	As to what is the cause of the incalculable wretchedness of society &amp; what is the panacea, I have long felt certified in my own mind. the rich are strangely ignorant of the miseries to which the lowest &amp; largest part of mankind are abandoned — &amp; even of those who see &amp; pity &amp; relieve their distresses, you will scarcely find one who has ever felt shocked at the reflection that God has given to the poor mental capabilities that might have infinitely benefited mankind — &amp; given them in vain, — only to be stifled by society. there is not upon this earth one spot where man enjoys “the unfettered use of all the powers which God for use has given.”<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lines contributed by Samuel Taylor Coleridge to <title level="m">Joan of Arc, An Epic Poem</title> (Bristol and London, 1796), pp. 39–40.</note> the savage &amp; civilized states are alike unnatural, alike unworthy of the origin &amp; end of man. hence the prevalence of scepticism &amp; atheism, which from being the effect become the cause of vice; &amp; the <del rend="strikethrough">world</del> civilized world sunk into a depravity dreadful as that which characterized the last ages of Rome seems again about to be renovated by a total <del rend="strikethrough">renovation</del> &lt;revolution&gt;. it is covered by pestilential fogs which nothing but tempests can scatter. &amp; those tempests are begun.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I have lived much among the friends of Priestley<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Priestley (1733–1804; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Unitarian minister, scientist and radical.</note> &amp; learnt from them many peculiar opinions of that man who speaks all he thinks. no man has studied Christianity more or believes it more sincerely — he thinks it not improbable that <hi rend="ital">another revelation</hi> may be granted us, for the obstinacy &amp; wickedness of mankind call for no less a remedy. the necessity of another revelation I do not see myself. what we have had with the right exertion of our own reasoning faculties appears to me sufficient. but in a Millenarian this opinion is not ridiculous, &amp; the many yet unfulfilled prophecies give it an appearance of probability. opinions of this kind may amuse &amp; comfort the solitary speculatist, but something more is required to act upon. were it possible I would immediately retire to try another system — as I cannot do that, all that is left is fully &amp; fearlessly to speak what I believe truth, &amp; point out that system which I <del rend="strikethrough">am</del> hold myself in readiness to embrace whenever it be possible. much in the mean time may be done. example will leaven all around us, &amp; he who cries aloud &amp; spares not, will at least reap the reward of feeling that he has done his duty.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	The Slave Trade has much disheartened me. that this Traffic is supported by the consumption of sugar is demonstrable — I have demonstrated it to above fifty persons with temporary success — &amp; not three of those persons have persevered in rejecting it. this is perfectly astonishing to me — &amp; what can be expected from those who will &lt;not&gt; remedy so horrible an iniquity by so easy an exertion!</p>
<p rend="indent1">	The future presents a dreary prospect — but all will end in good &amp; I can contemplate it calmly without suffering it to cloud the present. I may not live to do good to mankind personally — but I will at least leave something behind me to strengthen those feelings &amp; excite those reflections in others, from whence virtue must spring. in writing poetry with this end I hope I am not uselessly employing my leisure hours.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	God bless you. we are well &amp; happy.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent3">			affectionately yrs</salute>
<signed rend="indent5">					Robert Southey. </signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
