<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce167</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.167</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 112&#8211;115.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.167" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="167" type="letter">
        <head>167. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1796-07-26">26 July
                        1796</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ G
                        C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/
                        Single<lb />Postmark: AJY/ 27/ 96<lb />Watermarks: Figure of Britannia; COLES/
                        1795<lb />Endorsement: 26. July 1796<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                        c. 22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 112&#8211;115.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="left">
            <date when="1796-07-26">Tuesday. July 26.</date>
            <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">July 26: Possibly inserted in
                            another hand.</note>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Why is your letter delayed? I am anxious &amp; apprehensive.
                    it is nearly a week since you told me to expect it in four &amp; twenty
                    hours.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> is at the Hot Wells with his
                    wife who is consumptive. she understands French &amp; Italian &#8212; &amp;
                    has the manners of the world &#8212; but her physiognomy is not good &amp; whether
                    or no she may be pleasing in health, I cannot determine in sickness. to me &#8212; she
                    never would. <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> is the same as
                    when I left him, except that he is now a confirmed Atheist, &amp; to my
                    great surprize tells me <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>
                    is so.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry for this, not that I think any error in judgment
                    criminal, nor do I think the Atheist necessarily a fool &amp; necessarily
                    unhappy. I am a very tolerant man, even to indifference. but certainly he loses
                    the highest source of happiness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> tell me <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> the state of your mind upon religion. but tell me the state
                    of your body first.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> agrees with me that Man is a
                    Beast. he verges towards misanthropy &amp; says that a years crusade to
                    benefit mankind will cure any man of his prejudices in their favor. so say I &#8212;
                    for I have been a Crusader. &amp; so say you who have the benefit of my
                    experience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> but of <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>.
                    you have given me a very good opinion of him, for your applause is a ticket of
                    admission to mine. <del rend="strikethrough">NOW</del> I do not like him a whit
                    the less for his Atheism, but I have forsworn all metaphysics, from my soul
                    abhorring so barren a study. now if the majority of your club are necessarians
                    materialists &amp; atheists (as I believe they are) I, who am neither the
                    one or the other, have no inclination to be in a state of continual
                    argumentation. to tell you the truth, I dislike periodical engagements. I love
                    to pass my evenings at home with <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, &amp; methinks no other company can make me happier or
                    better. besides I am become a very reserved man, never unbending except to those
                    whom I love, consequently to any but my friends I am not an agreable
                    companion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I despise the
                    world. I hate the mob &#8212; I do not love the soi-disant Philosophers &#8212; &amp; I
                    have a thorough contempt for the aristocratical part. I shall mingle in the
                    world, but it will be only with the view of enabling myself to get out of it. I
                    must pass a very dirty road to get into the path of quiet life. now with these
                    intentions &#8212; being without ambition, &amp; alike indifferent to applause or
                    abuse &#8212; why should I make acquaintance? I have a few friends but they <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx</del> &lt;are&gt; enough. you &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &#8212; &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">your brother</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Robert Allen</ref>. then I will have <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> for my philosopher. <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del>
          <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> may be my surgeon. <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del>
          <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> is to be my physician
                    &amp; I shall be my own lawyer. now I want only an apothecary &#8212; &amp;
                    then what the Devil do I want to make more acquaintance for?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> as for <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles
                        Collins</ref> my opinion of him is settled. <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del> his opinion of me will be determind by my success in life,
                    &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> his conduct by my appearance. he
                    is one of the many men of whom I have thought too well. but he has no heart.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> no <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> when I come to London I will live to myself &amp; to
                    you. I will enter into no clubs, no literary societies &#8212; I will use no literary
                    arts. when I have done with the world I will give Madoc to posterity. I shall
                    get the applause of the present generation which I care not for &#8212; but I believe
                    that I may benefit the future.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> things will be better in another world. tell me <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> is there not
                    more real pleasure in that belief &#8212; more consolation in that little sentence
                    &lt;than&gt; in all the systems &amp; maxims of Philosophy?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am become melancholy in writing upon this subject. for to own
                    the truth tho I laugh at all systematizers, when I look at the world I am more
                    inclined to cry with Heraclitus.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Greek philosopher Heraclitus (540&#8211;475 BC), who was often called &#8216;the
                        mourner&#8217;, due to his habit of weeping at the follies and frailties of
                        mankind.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> desires to be remembered to you
                    &amp; Miles.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A friend of the Bedford
                        family, he lived at Vanbrugh Fields, Greenwich. His first name is not
                        recorded.</note> there is a worthy lad in a very unworthy situation. he is
                    as much too good for a Sailor as I am for an Officer or a Pimp or a Hangman or
                    any office equally honourable. tis well I am not the Exterminating Angel!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I saw five or six men on Sunday stoning a dog to death &#8212;
                    &amp; I heard the dog&#8217;s cries &#8212; &amp; I wishd I had been the
                    Exterminating Angel. alas &#8212; how are we hurried into vice by the indignation of
                    virtue!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot tell how I got here. for certainly I am made of very
                    different stuff from the mob of <del rend="strikethrough">ma</del> human beings.
                    perhaps I was created in some better planet &amp; kicked out for sedition.
                    this I am very sure of &#8212; that I feel out of my element in this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now I must give &lt;you&gt; a few very beautiful lines,
                    translated from the Spanish. they were uttered by Luis de Leon when after an
                    unjust imprisonment of five years in the inquisition, he was releasd. <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish humanist and poet Luis de Leon
                        (1527&#8211;1591), who was imprisoned by the Inquisition from
                    1572&#8211;1576.</note>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Adieu dark dungeons! many a wearying year</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Envy &amp; Falshood have confind me here.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Ah happy he who truly wise as good</l>
          <l rend="indent2">From a bad world retires to Solitude!</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For sure Content shall bless his humble fare &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The poor his cottage Peace shall sojourn there.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Unenvying &amp; unenvied pass his days</l>
          <l rend="indent2">&#8220;Prayer all his business &#8212; all his pleasures praise.&#8221; <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">This translation of Luis de Leon&#8217;s
                            &#8216;Aqui la embidia y mentira&#8217; appeared in Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and
                                Portugal</title> (Bristol, 1797), p. 184. The final line is a
                            quotation from Thomas Parnell (1679&#8211;1718; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                            &#8216;The Hermit&#8217; (1722), line 6.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I shall never
                    like Richard Roe<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A fictitious character,
                        often used to signify the defendant in a law suit.</note>
          <del rend="strikethrough">ever</del> &lt;half&gt; so well as Luis de
                    Leon!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I like no trade because in all of them you must mingle too much
                    with this cursed race. I like no profession. the church is the best &#8212; but to me
                    Perjury is the porter. physic requires study that I am afraid &#8212; hardens the
                    heart. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I now
                    think so. as for Law &#8212; c&#230;tera desunt.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Latin translates as &#8216;the rest is wanting&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent2">hiatus valde lacrymabilis!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;a truly lamentable gap&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p>What a comfort it is that you &amp; I can keep one another in countenance &#8212;
                    &amp; &#8220;<hi rend="ital">throw meta-physics to the dogs</hi>&#8221; tho no doubt
                        &#931;&#957;&#953;&#966;&#949;&#955;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek translates as &#8216;Snivel&#8217;, the name
                        of Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s dog.</note> likes <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> &lt;your&gt; conclusion better. Poor
                    &#931;&#957;&#953;&#966;&#949;&#955;
                    did not like physic when I was at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref>.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Some James&#8217;s powder mixt in butter</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Poor Snivel took to make her &#8212;&#8212;</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Were we not very <del rend="strikethrough">very</del> happy then <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>? &amp;
                    shall w[MS torn] as happy again?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Would I had time to finish my sheet. but [MS torn] going out to
                    dinner &#8212; &amp; I must not lose this post &#8212; for indeed I am very anxious for
                    your answer.</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> God bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>remember me to all &#8220;<ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your good
                            family</ref>.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>