<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce98</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.98</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 66&#8211;69 [in part; verses not reproduced]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, p. 216 [in part; 1 paragraph, taken from 5 August section but misdated 1 August 1794].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.98" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="98" type="letter">
        <head>98. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-08-01">1&#8211;21 August [1794]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single<lb /> Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: [partial] EA/ 25/ 94<lb /> Watermarks: G R in a circle; figure of Britannia<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 25 Aug<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1794 Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Sep<hi rend="sup">tr</hi>. 7. 1794<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 66&#8211;69 [in part; verses not reproduced]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, p. 216 [in part; 1 paragraph, taken from 5 August section but misdated 1 August 1794].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1794-08-01">August the first.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	I have this day written to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">your brother</ref>. your letter arrived since. to a few points I can immediately reply. my resolution with regard to America is taken. &amp; the principles which guide me there are so powerful that tho <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> was strongly prejudiced against them he has totally changed his opinion &amp; will go with me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	suffer me <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> to decline answering you when you attack republicanism. think of republicans with candor for my sake when I am gone, &amp; when you are tempted by the contagion of aristocracy to declaim against Levellers &amp; Jacobines remember you knew one at least disinterested &amp; sincere. you can now conform to the opinion of those you live with, &amp; of the multitude without dissimulation. I will not attempt to disturb this, tho so fully have I digested all my principles that I firmly believe it in my power to stagger you in yours. if at any time the dissentions in this country should occasion moderate men to abandon it, I shall hope you will join us in Kentucky. upon what plan we go you shall know hereafter. it is different from what you can imagine. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> partakes my nature as well as name &amp; is not happy in the navy. it is his wish to quit it &amp; share my fate &#8212; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> you must send me huge letters over to Kentucky &#8212; &amp; now &amp; then <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> a good book. but we cannot go before next spring certainly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	One line will clear you of all participation in democracy. Joan was written under your roof &amp; your inspection. <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> will engrave me a vignette &amp; frontispiece if I chuse both. &#8212; mention my resolution of emigrating to no one but <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. from <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">CC</ref> I am much alienated. he is cold hearted. his abilities will gain him whatever he wishes &amp; his principles will never stand in his way. do not mention my design to any body but <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. when I am gone let them shrug their shoulders &amp; pity me. for yourself think of every motive most powerful over the human mind &#8212; &amp; do not condemn me upon suspicion. many of my dearest friends go with me. except <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; yourself I shall leave nothing that can grieve me. but I would rather go alone &amp; abandon every dearest tie than remain dependant, without even hope.</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1794-08-05">August 5</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Every thing smiles upon me. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> is fully convinced of the propriety of our resolution. she admires the plan &#8212; she goes with us. never did so delightful a prospect of happiness open upon my view before. to go with all I love &#8212; to go with all my friends except your family &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>! to live with them in the most agreable &amp; most honourable employment. to eat the fruits I have raised, &amp; see every face happy around me. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> sheltered in her declining years from the anxieties which have pursued her. my brothers<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward Southey</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>.</note> educated to be useful &amp; virtuous &#8212;</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1794-08-21">Aug. 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Time has fled rapidly since I laid down the pen. the unexpected arrival of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> agreably surprized me. we have been constantly together. when your ode reachd me it reminded me of neglect &amp; I blushed as I read. so it is &#8212; to repent &amp; still sin on! this day week we walked together to Bath. passed the day there. &amp; after breakfast the next morning departed staff in hand for Huntspill. to visit <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref> in the road to a friend of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>. Rover accompanied us. &#8220;tis nineteen miles to Wells. Huntspill must be about ten or eleven miles farther &amp; we can reach it by night.&#8221; at Wells we dined. how far to Huntspill? why you must go to Bridgewater. how far to Bridgewater? 18 miles! &amp; 8 from thence to Huntspill. we rose to look at the map in the room &amp; found it shorter to go by Chedder &amp; see the cliffs. how far to Chedder? about seven miles. off we set. we met a coachman. how far to Chedder ten long miles. we askd every person we met &#8212; &amp; received successively 5 &#8212; 7 &#8212; 4 &#8212; 2 &#189; &#8212; 6 &#8212; 4 &#8212; 4 &#8212; 5 &amp;c &#8212; the night began to darken. but we talked philosophy like two poets &amp; often paused one while to drink at a clear spring &#8212; another while to encourage poor Rover now quite lame &#8212; &amp; sometimes &#8212; to mark the glow-worms paley ray. we reachd Chedder about ten anticipating the delights of a good supper &amp; comfortable bed. we enquired the best inn &#8212; &amp; arrived at a poor pothouse in a little village. can you give us a bed. no. all engaged. we went to the other house. mine host was asleep in his chair &#8212; can you give us a bed? he snored no &amp; turned round again. we agreed to go back to the other inn &#8212; get some supper &amp; sleep in the stable. down we sat. demolished the bread cheese &amp; cold a la mode beef &#8212; &amp; petitiond for straw in the stable. they said they would make us up a bed. it was in a garret the only piece of furniture except another bedstead &#8212; on which lay a bed &amp; quilt. poor Rover was condemned to the stable much against his inclination &#8212; it being one of his whims always to sleep in the room with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> or me. but the landlady was inexorable I tied up with a halter locked the door upon him &amp; went to bed. my eyes were half sunk in slumber &amp; the dreams of the past day floating round my head &#8212; when open came the door &#8212; in rushd Rover &amp; the landlady declaring he had broken the halter crawld under the door &amp; must sleep in the room with me. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is a vile bedfellow &amp; I slept but ill. in the morning I rose &#8212; &amp; lo &#8212; we were fastend in! they certainly took us for footpads, &amp; had bolted the door on the outside for fear we should rob the house.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Chedder cliffs amply repaid us. never did I see a grander scene &#8212; immense rocks rising perpendicularly from the glen to such a height <del rend="strikethrough">that</del> as pains the neck of the spectator, &amp; terminating in the most bold &amp; fantastic manner. large trees grew from the interstices of the stone &amp; the sheep browzed on the edge of every precipice. a stream of water cold &amp; clear flows from under the rocks where we paused to drink &amp; pour libations to the Naiad.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	on a similar spring at Chilcompton <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has written a very beautiful poem.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Lines to a Beautiful Spring&#8217;, published in Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <title level="m">Poems on Various Subjects</title> (1796).</note> I have it not but it will soon be publishd &amp; you will see it then.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	You ask me why I did not apply thro you to Nicol<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George Nicol (1740&#8211;1828; <title level="m">DNB</title>), printer and bookseller.</note> about Joan? the thought never struck me &#8212; &amp; had it I should have been unwilling to employ you upon a business rather unpleasant. however if he or any bookseller will give me an hundred guineas for the copy right when I have secured subscribers enough to indemnify the publication, I shall be glad to rid myself of the poem. you know it breathes freedom. but a piece ending with a coronation can hardly be stiled republican.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	thank you for going to Doctors Commons. was there any estate left to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref> &amp; entailed like the others?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s enquiries relate to his hopes of benefiting from the Will of his wealthy distant cousin, John Cannon Southey. They came to nothing.</note> I am perfectly in the dark about the whole business &amp; would gladly accept five hundred pounds for all I may ever inherit in this country. but my age prevents me &#8212; &amp; no gambler will venture that sum on so uncertain a speculation. n&#8217;importe. surely I can write enough to clear 200 pounds before March &amp; more would not be wanted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	farewell. I returned but yesterday from my journey or would have written sooner.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent7">				yrs sincerely</salute>
          <signed rend="indent8">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent6">Sonnet<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version was published in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 2 (October 1796), 732.</note>
          </p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Evening &#8212; as musing on my lonely way</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	I wander on, mine eye delights to view</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	Thy mellowed tints of many a sober hue</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Steal slowly oer the radiance of the day.</l>
            <l rend="indent2">The still hour soothes my soul &amp; wears away</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	Sad Memorys painful thought, as many a dream</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	Fond Fancy pictures in her visioned theme</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Of coming joy. but soon with sterner sway</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Frowns the dark heaven; thy sadly-pleasing light</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	 Friendly to meditation shall decay</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Amid the shadows of descending Night.</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Ah lovely dreams! so tho my soul delight</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	On you to dwell &#8212; Truths form severe pursues</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	To blend your airy forms with Sorrows sabler hues.</l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="indent5">	&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
          <p rend="indent5">Sonnet<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version appeared anonymously in the <title level="j">Morning Post</title>, 26 February 1798.</note>
          </p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Smile on sweet infant &#8212; soon the storm of woe</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	Shall shadow that blest look. smile on poor child &#8212;</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	I too like thee the hours of youth beguild</l>
            <l rend="indent2">With many a fairy dream, ere doomd to know</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Reasons sad sway. the chearful smile was mine</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	Mine the glad bosom bounding to delight</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	Ere her dark power like the chill storm of night</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Sternd the drear scene, &amp; bade me inly pine</l>
            <l rend="indent2">With many a mournful thought. poor infant &#8212; born</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	To taste of sorrow, soon obscurd in woe</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Shall fade thy smile, as when the April morn</l>
            <l rend="indent3">	Beams with the radiance of the varied bow,</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Tho mildly beams around its placid ray</l>
            <l rend="indent2">The driving tempest soon englooms the dreary day.</l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="indent11">	Orson.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The pseudonym Southey used in his unrealised 1794 collaboration with Robert Lovell. The latter&#8217;s contributions were to have been signed &#8216;Valentine&#8217;.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>