<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce133</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.133</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 245&#8211;246 [in part, where it is dated 22 August 1795].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="133" type="letter">
        <head>133. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1795-08-22">[c. 22 August 1795]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster./ Single<lb />Stamped: [partial] TOL<lb />Postmark: AU/ 22/ 95<lb />Watermarks: Figure of Britannia; COLES/ 1794<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Aug<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 22 1795<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 245&#8211;246 [in part, where it is dated 22 August 1795].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">My Uncle</ref> is in England. I am in daily expectation of seeing him again &#8212; yet know not when I shall see him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> when next I see you &#8212; it will not be for a visit. I shall fix my residence near you to study the law!!!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref> urges me to enter the church. but the gate is perjury &#8212; &amp; I am little disposed to pay so heavy a price at the turnpike of orthodoxy. a decided Humanist &#8212; I shall be the advocate of that Xtianity which I believe in because I see it in its native &amp; simple beauty. trust me <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> Infidelity is rapid in its progress &#8212; shallow-headed Deists, &amp; arrogant Atheists swarm every where, &amp; will every&lt;whr&gt; succeed in argument except when they meet with those who believe in the benevolence of God &amp; the inspiration of the man Jesus Christ. Optimism is my creed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	on seeing <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref> I shall communicate to him my intentions concerning the Law. if he disapproves of them &#8212; I have to live where I can &amp; how I can for fifteen months. I shall then be enable to enter &amp; marry.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	if he does &#8212; why then <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> my first business will be to write to you &amp; request you to procure me lodgings. somewhere at Stockwell or Newington &#8212; or any where as far from London &lt;&amp;&gt; as near your road there as possible. I cannot take a house till my finances will suffer me to furnish it &#8212; &amp; for this I depend upon my Madoc &#8212; to which after Xmas I shall apply with assiduity &#8212; always remembering John Doe &amp; Richard Roe!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Fictitious characters, often used to signify the plaintiff (Doe) and defendant (Roe) in legal suits.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	&amp; now &#8212; will you permit me in a volume of Poems<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">An unrealised project for a volume of poems to be written and edited by Southey and Coleridge.</note> which go to the press tomorrow to insert your Witch of Endor either with your name or initials? &amp; to be Corrector Plenipotent? this is an office <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; I mutually assume, &amp; we both of <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> &lt;us&gt; have sense enough &amp; taste enough to be glad of mutual correction. his poems &amp; mine will appear together &#8212; two volumes elegant<del rend="strikethrough">x</del> as to type &amp; hot-pressd paper. &amp; for his &#8212; meo periculo<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;at my own risk&#8217;.</note> &#8212; they will be of more various excellence than any one volume that this country has ever yet seen. I will rest all my pretensions to poetical taste on the truth of this assertion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	give my love to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harry</ref> &#8212; &amp; tell him that if he has time he will oblige me &amp; serve me by sending a description of the catapulta balista scorpion &amp;c as a note for my Joan of Arc. I will make my acknowledgement to him either by name or not by name. the poem is advanced one fourth part &#8212; &amp; will now do me very much credit. I destine the original MSS<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to the first version of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>, written in summer&#8211;early autumn 1793. The MS is now in the Houghton Library, MS Eng 265.</note> as written at Brixton for you <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>. it will not contain 1000 lines of the printed copy &#8212; so completely have I alterd &amp; amended it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	one word more. I print the ode on your birthday (by the by many thanks for mine) &amp; a sonnet addressd to you. may I prefix your name? or if not (&amp; I see no reason why not) what name shall I insert. Grosvenor &amp; Bedford are both used in the poem. <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Birth-Day Ode, 1793&#8217; and &#8216;Sonnet III&#8217; appeared in Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title>, (Bristol, 1797), pp. 67&#8211;71 and p. 109. In both poems Grosvenor Charles Bedford was addressed as &#8216;Bedford&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	God bless you &#8212; &amp; yours.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	my <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> sends her love to you. &amp; bids me press you to come down. I have a bed for you at Bath. &amp; if a hearty welcome can make up the deficiencies of indifferent accommodation I shall be most glad to see you there. so will <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>. &amp; so will one who is not sorry that necessity keeps me from London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Would I were with you to assist in the doing over <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">C.C.</ref>!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	my love to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> &#8212; &amp; remembrances to all friends</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">			farewell</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">				Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">	tell me of Madm Endor speedily.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">	the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book of Joan is advanced in printing. <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harrys</ref> note be early in the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I know his ability &amp; doubt not his will.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>