<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce32</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.32</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c.
                        22.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.32" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="32" type="letter">
        <head>32. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1792-11-29">29 November
                        [1792]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Old Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single
                        Sheet<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: [illegible trace]<lb />Watermark: G
                        R in a circle and figure of Britannia<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ 1792./ Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. [Bedford seems to have misdated his
                        endorsement.]<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, Eng. Lett. c.
                        22<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Bedford &#8212;</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have two apologies to make before I begin the main subject of
                    this letter. one for troubling you with two in one week. the other for ever
                    touching upon politicks when I ought to have recollected that we differd in
                    opinion &#8212; this last shall never happen again &#8212; &amp; most heartily do I add
                    Amen to your prayer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wrote some short time back to <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> intending to renew <del rend="strikethrough">our</del> &lt;a&gt; correspondence with one
                    whom I could have wishd to still think my friend &#8212; the expressions I usd at
                    least blamed myself as much as him &#8212; I am sorry I kept no copy to send you &#8212; the
                    answer I have just received &amp; you have it &#8212;</p>
        <lb />
        <p>Dear Southey &#8212; Yours bearing date the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> came to hand in
                    the beginning of last week. from my having taken so long a time to consider of
                    it, you will naturally conjecture that I have been at loss for an answer. indeed
                    your letter is nearly unintelligible, but from the little I have been able to
                    decypher you seem to hint (&amp; that not very obliquely) that our
                    Correspondence owes its interruption to me. if such is your meaning to say the
                    least your insinuation is unjust. had you <hi rend="ital">impartially</hi>
                    considerd the matter, your justice must have condemnd yourself only. but surely
                    Selfishness should not so far have made you forgetfull of all Modesty as to deny
                    even a share of the blame when you are entitled to the whole. with the same
                    Justice with the same Modesty that you cast the burden from yourself you throw
                    it upon me. But you mistake me Southey. I am no Pack-horse. you have been
                    travelling up &amp; down the country from Bristol to Oxford from Oxford to
                    Bristol &amp; I know not whither &#8212; pray how was I to discover your direction
                    even if I thought a letter from me would have proved agreeable? I thank you for
                    your enquiries by <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lamb</ref> &amp;
                        <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> &#8212; if you really
                    thought proper to consider the Correspondence as droppd surely a verbal message
                    could never be calculated to renew it, &amp; your last letter much less so.
                    after the coolness which had taken place at Westminster (of which perhaps the
                    Flagellant was the cause) you might have been certain that the first must have
                        <hi rend="ital">appeard</hi> haughty to any one &#8212; but your Favour of last
                    week was so in an higher degree tho&#8217; half conceald under an affected humility.
                    However gratified I might have been with the continuance of your Correspondence
                    yet I must not forget what is due to myself as to accept even a pleasure when
                    offerd in so Cavalier-like a manner. &#8212; yet tho I must decline the
                    Correspondence* &#8212; thus offerd &#8212; I trust I never shall consider Southey in any
                    other light than that of affection &amp; esteem &#8212; so I may sign myself with
                    all sincerity y<hi rend="sup">r</hi> constant well wisher <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">George Strachey</ref>. </p>
        <p>* these words written after on the other side.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is exactly his letter markd with &#8212;&#8212; as in the original I
                    send you now my answer. when his letter reachd me I had just begun an ode to
                    Phillis my spaniel. I finishd it &amp; immediately wrote as follows</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Dear <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">George</ref> I have
                    only taken a few minutes to consider your letter (tho it would admit of
                    consideration whether I ever ought to notice it or not) my answer to every
                    paragraph is so easy that (tho I really think <del rend="strikethrough">think</del> you neither expected or wishd to hear more of me) I could not
                    refrain giving it. let me first say it required some <hi rend="ital">time</hi>
                    to persuade yourself that your charges in that letter were upon any score
                    justifiable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> you throw the whole blame upon me in recrimination. I kept no
                    copy of my letter to your therefore cannot speak positively but I do not think I
                    did entirely exculpate myself then, I do now. go back to last Xmas &#8212; the only
                    notice you then took of me was to send a note to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. with regard to the
                    Flagellant, your prudence I highly commend. your behaviour with regard to every
                    other tie you cannot approve yourself. availing yourself of that knowledge which
                    my credulous friendship had given you &amp; of that exemption which your
                    inconsistency &amp; insincerity had procured you, you amused yourself at
                    school in sporting with that knowledge till you had made every one guess at the
                    truth &amp; not content with that, without regard to any promise you
                    mentioned my name to <ref target="people.html#RoughWilliam">Rough</ref>. &#8212; the
                    fact is this <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> you were
                    tired of one who ever scrupled to tell you of your faults &#8212; may they never
                    occasion you more regret than you feel at the loss of my friendship &#8212; the excuse
                    of not knowing my direction is so very flimsy, that I wonder at your inserting
                    it even among others so very unjustifiable. supposing that you had forgotten it
                    with as much facility as you had me <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lamb</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combe</ref> or <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> could have given
                    it you. even had they not you must have known that the old direction would find
                    me. <hi rend="ital">I wrote to you without knowing where you were</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You talk of what is due to yourself. I conceive your meaning.
                    state the case however with that impartiality of the want of which in my letter
                    you so much complain. you had acted ungenerously &amp; unkindly to me. I
                    wrote to you, perhaps in an angry stile, such you deservd but I offerd to renew
                    our correspondence, an offer which I now think I ought not to have made in any
                    manner. you reply that I am solely in fault, talk of what is due to yourself
                    &amp; decline the correspondence &#8212; the words &#8220;thus offerd&#8221; wrote afterwards
                    are meant only to appear as palliating. Was you not <hi rend="ital">certain</hi>
                    that the Flagellant occasioned the coolness on my part? can you forget that your
                    idleness first checkd our correspondence? can you say that you knew not my
                    direction? I will save you the trouble of answering these queries &#8212; you wanted
                    to shake the blame on me. you were conscious of a behaviour equally ungenerous
                    &amp; unjust, &amp; in the space of ten days composd an artful letter to
                    which you never imagined I would have returned an answer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have now done with reminding you of your faults &#8212; it is a
                    hateful task &amp; for twelve months my intercourse with you has been little
                    more. that intercourse is now over for ever. not without regret on my part, on
                    yours it will be treated with the same levity you display upon every subject. </p>
        <p rend="indent8"> your well wisher Robert Southey.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will not disapprove of my conduct. I have done with <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> for ever. will you show
                    this to <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> he knows much of
                    his behavior with respect to the Fl. to him I owd respect. I have twice written
                    to apologize for my former neglect as yet he has answered neither letter. if
                    those apologies are not sufficient you may make as many more as you think
                    proper. the firm consistency of his conduct deserves them &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yours which you directed to Oxford reached me after my last was
                    dispatched &#8212; how you could direct there when in my recent letter I mentioned the
                    day of my departure I am little able to guess &#8212; still less so how it could ever
                    find me at so great a distance. you say it is difficult to answer a letter that
                    requires no answer &#8212; out of thine own mouth will I convict thee. I had beggd
                    your Chartreuse verses in October they reach me on the 20th of November
                    &amp; at the same time that you send them you tell me mine required no
                    answer. I am much obliged to you for them &amp; for your Horace some stanzas
                    of which I much like, but some of the verses are rough a fault which the
                    transp[MS torn]tion of a few words would rectify &#8212; take my translation</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">O thou religion of this spot severe</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> By what name may to thee most pleasing sound</l>
          <l rend="indent2">(For sure some powerful deity reigns here</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> These native streams &amp; antique woods around)</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Here mongst these pathless rocks &#8212; these mountains high</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> These cliffs oerhanging &amp; these sounding streams
                        &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">These groves impervious to the suns gay eye</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> This forest night where never sunshine beams &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Here we the present God more clearly find</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Than formd of cedar burnishd oer with gold</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Here we perceive him in the ecstatic mind</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> More than the Phidian statue sculpturd bold.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Hail thou Religion &#8212; to a youth give rest</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> If Fortune here forbids me to remain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In these sad silent scenes with willing breast</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> But drives me on the waves &amp; stormy main &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Father at least afford some spot retird</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Where I may pass my wintry hours in peace</l>
          <l rend="indent2">There of the world &amp; all its follies tird</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> There gently bid my every sorrow cease. <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation is of Thomas Gray
                            (1716&#8211;1771; <title level="m">DNB</title>), &#8216;O tu severi religio loci&#8217;
                            (1741).</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1"> You seem to expect something beside this translation &#8212; as I am
                    ignorant of what you want I send you this epistle as an equivalent &#8212; if however
                    you will mention in your next any production of mine it is much at your
                    service</p>
        <p rend="indent4"> Berenice to Titus</p>
        <p rend="indent4"> __________</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">The Sun shall from the west his course pursue</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Eer Titus<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Emperor
                            Titus Flavius Sabinus Vespasianus (AD 40&#8211;81; reigned AD 79&#8211;81). In AD
                            70, he led the Roman troops that conquered Jerusalem.</note> prove to
                            Berenice<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A Jewish princess (c. AD
                            28&#8211;?), daughter of Herod Agrippa I (10 BC&#8211;AD 44) and sister of Herod
                            Agrippa II (b. AD 27/28), Kings of Judea. Mistress of Titus.</note>
                        untrue</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Eer that ill fated hour Nights shadowy sway</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Shall mantle oer the full meridian day</l>
          <l rend="indent2">All vows all bonds all Love itself be vain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Or Fortune rear Jerusalem again.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Such were thy vows when oer this flatterd face</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Wealth rank combind to spread superior grace &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">When love soft beaming from the glowing eye</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Wingd every glance &amp; loaded every sigh &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Like Heavens avenging angel whose red arm</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Spreads Fear &amp; Horror round &amp; wild Alarm</l>
          <l rend="indent2">At whose command Want &#8212; Death oershadowing fly </l>
          <l rend="indent2">And victor armies bow their heads &amp; die &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">So oer Jerusalems unhappy tower</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thy hand impelld the stream of Roman power &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Then then when gore dyd arms yclaspd thy form</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Yet red from Desolations death fraught storm</l>
          <l rend="indent2">When scant faint evening trembling gleam no more</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The feast of slaughter &amp; of death was oer</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Swift wouldst thou quit the bloody scene of arms</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Allurd by victor Love&#8217;s more soft alarms.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Swift then with eager transport haste to greet</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And lay thy laurels at thy mistress feet &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nor Time nor Space could check thy fiery way</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nor War nor Danger for one hour delay </l>
          <l rend="indent2">All all were vain &#8212; or Danger Death or Fame</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Of these all forgetful Titus came.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Then Titus wont his joy in silence speak</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To glow with mantling pleasure on his cheek</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Sigh forth his soul &amp; seize the kiss imprest</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And press me half unwilling to his breast.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Past are those days &#8212; no more with watchful ear</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Intent I sit thy well known step to hear</l>
          <l rend="indent2">No more at distance rove with eager eye</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Count all the tedious moments as they fly</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Till Fear &amp; trembling Doubt my bosom move</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Till Fear &amp; Doubt are all forgot in Love.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Past are those days &#8212; this eye bedimmd in vain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Casts the lost gaze around the extended plain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Then sick with expectation turn to grieve</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For Hope itself no longer can deceive.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Dear to my soul return &amp; bless my eyes &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Bid the blest days of happiness arise</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Let no rought blast the sea of pleasure move</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Let every day be happiness &amp; love.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Such pleasure will not deck the regal seat</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Power cannot call her from her lovd retreat</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Where far retird from each intruding eye</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In soft Contentment&#8217;s lap she loves to lie</l>
          <l rend="indent2">She loves the noisy courtier throng to shun</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Blest with her friends but still more blest with one.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The glittering croud &#8212; the guards imperial row</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The lictors state &#8212; the frowning fasces show &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The Tyrian robe the purple pomp of state</l>
          <l rend="indent2">But vex her quiet &amp; provoke her hate.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">I knew thee first Vespasians<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Emperor Titus Flavius Vespasianus (AD 9&#8211;79; reigned
                            AD 69&#8211;79).</note> humble son</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Such wert thou when our mutual love begun</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thou then wert as inferior to me</l>
          <l rend="indent2">As Berenice is now compard to thee</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The mean distinctions of all rank above</l>
          <l rend="indent2">I knew nor rank nor fortune but thy love</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Such thoughts such warm regards possessd my mind</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Will Titus prove ungrateful &amp; unkind</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Can he forget so soon each bliss fraught hour</l>
          <l rend="indent2">When triumphd Love in all his fiercest powr</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Can he forget this form this voice this face</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Which Flattry wont to deck with every grace?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Can he forget &#8212; yes all are now forgot</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Lost in the splendor of imperial cot &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Lost &amp; confounded in the blaze of state</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Augustus has forgot a Titus fate</l>
          <l rend="indent2">When all the world culls forth its brightest [MS torn]</l>
          <l rend="indent2">When every willing beauty seeks thy arms</l>
          <l rend="indent2">&amp; ready smile illumines every face</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And rival charmers court their Kings embrace</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Amid the riot &amp; the gust of power</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Shall Memory dare to claim the grateful hour?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">When soft reclining on the harlots breast</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thy soul with pleasures madning rage possest</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Shall then Reflection check the impetuous vice</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Shall love presume to whisper Berenice?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Ah no it must not be &#8212; these thoughts are vain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">No trace no fond remembrances remain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Yet I will haunt thee on thy guarded throne</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Will claim thy heart thy love thy all alone.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Alas my Titus (fain I&#8217;d think thee mine)</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nature will rage &#8212; the woman will repine &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">These cheeks now pale would bloom at Titus sight</l>
          <l rend="indent2">These eyes now dim would sparkle new delight</l>
          <l rend="indent2">These hands again the silent lute would move</l>
          <l rend="indent2">This cold cold heart again revive to love &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Vain thoughts for ever in oblivion sleep</l>
          <l rend="indent2">These cheeks must hide these eyes must only weep</l>
          <l rend="indent2">This heart grow chill &#8212; the languid pulse beat low</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The silent lute but wake its strings to woe</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Where&#8217;er these eyes regardless move around</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The image of my Titus still is found</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Twas here where first the womans love confest</l>
          <l rend="indent2">He claspt me eager to his thrilling breast</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Twas here where prodigal of oaths he swore</l>
          <l rend="indent2">His love should last till Life itself were oer</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Twas here where Berenice&#8217; too thirsty ear</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Believd so fondly what she wishd sincere</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Twas here he sat &#8212; twas here his bursting heart</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Heavd forth the sigh that told me we must part &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Twas here where slow departing from my view</l>
          <l rend="indent2">His hand unwilling wavd a<del rend="strikethrough">l</del>
                        long adieu.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Ill fated scene still picturd in this breast</l>
          <l rend="indent2">By thee alone in every form possest</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Een now dark Fancy paints with cruel care</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Memory recalls &amp; with it calls Despair.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Canst thou amid the flattring pomp of power</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Canst thou forget that sad that trying hour?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Forget those mingled tears adown each face</l>
          <l rend="indent2">That spoke the anguish of a last embrace?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Forget those vows that I too fond believd</l>
          <l rend="indent2">By thee deserted &amp; by thee deceivd?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Ah no it cannot be. the senates voice</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Forbids the master of the world his choice</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Forbids him place a Jewess on that throne</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Which Messalina<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Valeria
                            Messalina (c. AD 17/20&#8211;48), third wife of the Emperor Claudius (10 BC&#8211;AD
                            54; reigned AD 41&#8211;54). She was renowned for her debauchery.</note> once
                        could call her own.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">And need I urge indeed? &amp; need I move?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Must Berenice intreat her Titus love?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And must I seek to fix thy plain decree</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The easy contest when the prize is me?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Titus no wars no dangers wait thee here</l>
          <l rend="indent2">What from the Senate shall Augustus fear?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thy friends in arms their darling chief adore</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Rome loves &#8212; the senate fear &#8212; can man ask more?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">No more intreat with blushes on thy cheek</l>
          <l rend="indent2">No let them quake to hear their master speak &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Their fond complaints their empty pride despise</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And let Jud&#230;as victor claim his prize.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Ah no &#8212; no longer lovely in thine eye</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The hapless Berenice must learn to die &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Gape then o Grave &#8212; expand thy secret womb</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Receive &amp; hide me in the silent tomb &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">There nor shall pain nor grief nor woe molest</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nor mans ingratitude torment my breast</l>
          <l rend="indent2">This heart that wont to beat to Love alone</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Then cold &amp; senseless as surrounding stone</l>
          <l rend="indent2">These eye-balls then for ever cease to move</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Eyes which were weak to fix my Titus love &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The loathly worm then riot on this breast</l>
          <l rend="indent2">So oft to Titus thrilling bosom prest &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Come then kind Death I ask thy pleasing sway</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Come wear each weak each fruitless charm away</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For then no more shall heave the woe fraught sigh</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For every grief for every joy must die.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The sun ... must die: Verse written in
                            double columns.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent4"> ________________</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Upon second thoughts I do not think <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Stracheys</ref> letter deserves any
                    answer at all. I will not yet send it if I ever do &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> you will be puzzled I fear to read this vile writing as well as
                    tired but it will be some time before you hear again from me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> remember to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">your
                        brother</ref> &amp; little <ref target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Joseph</ref>. if your brother will come with you to the Installation
                    &amp; put up with such <hi rend="ital">in</hi>conveniences as the season
                    will permit I shall be very glad to see him &#8212;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs sincerely</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">RS.</signed>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>Bristol.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1792-11-29">Nov. 29.</date>
          </dateline>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>