<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce68</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.68</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        22.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I,
                        pp. 189&#8211;190 [in part; one paragraph].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="68" type="letter">
        <head>68. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1793-11-12">[12&#8211;15] November
                        [1793]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: ONO/ 18/ 93<lb />Watermarks: Figure
                        of Britannia; G R in a circle<lb />Seal: Red wax [design
                        illegible]<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 18. 1793<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        22<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I,
                        pp. 189&#8211;190 [in part; one paragraph].</note>
        </head>
        <p>
          <date when="1793-11-11">Tuesday night. Nov. 11</date>. <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey has mistaken the date. Tuesday was 12 November in
                        1793.</note> my cheese at the fire. you &amp; I <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> are not unlike
                    two men in Bedlam quarrelling about their imaginary titles. my dear brother
                    visionary, let us plan our respective schemes in peace &#8212; my commonwealth when
                    establishd will be certainly as pacific as your Majestys kingdom &amp; why
                    we debate so vehemently before they are establishd I know not. I was glad your
                    paper was out because you had worked up your feelings till you had lost the
                    mastery of them &#8212; I was angry because I was vext. &amp; I am now vext
                    because I was angry. for the poor Queen<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Marie Antoinette (1755&#8211;1793), wife of Louis XVI (1754&#8211;1793; reigned
                        1774&#8211;1792) and Queen of France, was executed on 16 October 1793.</note> I
                    feel indignant &amp; enraged &#8212; angry with you for falling foul upon me
                    &amp; still more angry with the Convention for continually furnishing
                    arguments against a pure zealous philosophical republican. (I have just eat my
                    cheese) I had rather bellow in the bull of Phalaris<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A bronze bull commissioned by Phalaris, the Tyrant of
                        Agrigentum in Sicily (570&#8211;554 BC). His victims were roasted alive in the
                        bull, their shrieks said to imitate its bellowing.</note> than be the
                    present K of Prussia<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Frederick William II
                        (1744&#8211;1797; reigned 1786&#8211;1797).</note> &#8212; in the former case conscious
                    virtue, tho it could not cure the blisters would cure the soul with indignation
                    not unlike pleasure &#8212; in the latter &#8212; conscience might rationally expect the
                    guillotine in this world &amp; the devil in the next &#8212; well coupled say you.
                    the Convention &amp; the Devil &#8212; I foresaw the remark &amp; as you see
                    forestall it. somebody says there is no spectacle more grateful to the Gods than
                    a good man struggling with adversity. now this is quoting from a quotation in
                    some title page &amp; I forget the author &#8212; but if the Gods are pleased with
                    the sight, it is more than the good man should be with the Gods. according to my
                    idea of a superior being he must have been more pleased with the success of
                        Epaminondas<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Theban general (418&#8211;362
                        BC), famed for his defeat of the Spartans at the battle of Leuctra 371
                        BC.</note> &amp; William Tell<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Legendary national hero of Switzerland.</note> than with the death of
                    Socrates or Algernon Sidney<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Algernon
                        Sidney (1622&#8211;1683; <title level="m">DNB</title>), politician and republican,
                        executed for his alleged involvement in the Rye House plot against Charles
                        II (1630&#8211;1685; reigned 1660&#8211;1685; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note>
                    (oddly coupled you say) the question is this &#8212; whether an all good creator
                    delights more in seeing Virtue rewarded by happiness &amp; admired by
                    popularity or in seeing the many criminated by persecuting a virtuous individual
                    &#8212; or in other words whether he prefers that the many should in some degree
                    partake of the virtue of one by recompensing it or that one should be
                    aggrandized by misfortune &amp; the guilt of the many. it were only wasting
                    words to show the unequal &amp; unjust distribution of worldly goods &#8212; an
                    innocent man can never feel the worm of remorse gnaw his heart but he may be
                    tormented with regret whose sting is as sharp as a wasps &amp; less easily
                    cured. how it would be doing such a man a favour to make a calf of him &#8212; for ten
                    to one if the roasting does not destroy the canker worm &#8212; &amp; the agonies
                    of one great blister render him forgetful of even mental pain &#8212; he would call up
                    all the consolations of conscious Virtue &amp; rejoice in death. now put a
                    villain in this said bull &amp; see how differently roasting will operate
                    upon him. the mental torments he will feel will exceed his bodily sufferings &#8212;
                    the bull will appear a specimen of the kitchen of Lucifer &amp; his end will
                    be damnable indeed. Honesty is indeed the best policy. the good man will be
                    happier in prosperity &amp; tho equally subject to adversity &#8212; adversity
                    will lose half its powers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> now Selim<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A nickname for
                        an unidentified Westminster schoolfellow.</note> would laugh at us for two
                    visionary children &#8212; but Selim himself is the visionary &amp; when he wakes
                    in another world he will find it so. our philosophy will be practical there for
                    heaven will be one great republic of philosophers &#8212; instead of psalm-singers &#8212;
                    &amp; if it is not why I know not what it will be. Mohammeds<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Mohammed (570&#8211;632), prophet and founder of
                        Islam.</note> is too sensual &#8212; Odins<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Odin was the chief god in Norse mythology.</note> too heroic &amp;
                    Orthodoxitys too humdrum. mine perhaps too philosophical &#8212; but my celestial
                    wisemen are not your dry metaphysicians with long beards &#8212; in short they are
                    what Men &lt;ought to be &amp; what they&gt; might be &#8212; good
                    &amp; happy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> how the Bishop would stare to hear of an Epicurean Xtian &#8212; or a
                    republican one. these good old orthodox wiggipotentates when they rail at
                    speculation appear to me like so many owls looking at the sun &amp; hooting
                    with rage. Horseley<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The appointment of
                        Samuel Horsley (1733&#8211;1806; <title level="m">DNB</title>) as Dean of
                        Westminster and Bishop of Rochester in November 1793.</note> is promoted you
                    know. I am tempted to exclaim Ecce iterum Crispinus<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Juvenal (fl. AD late C1 and early C2), <title level="m">Satire</title> 4, line 1. The Latin can be translated as &#8216;Here&#8217;s
                        Crispinus again&#8217;.</note> &amp; so belabour belampoon &amp;
                    bepriestly him<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1783&#8211;1785, Samuel
                        Horseley (1733&#8211;1806; <title level="m">DNB</title>) had defended the Trinity
                        in a series of exchanges with the radical Unitarian Joseph Priestley
                        (1733&#8211;1804; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> &#8212; but the Inquisition has
                    no charms for me &amp; our ecclesiastical Court bears too strong a
                    resemblance to the sacred institution of St Dominic.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">St Dominic (c. 1170&#8211;1221), founder of the order of Dominican
                        friars, which later played a key role in the Inquisition.</note>
        </p>
        <p>You see in what a increasing epistolary cue I am going on &#8212; hand &amp; head
                    equally willing but poor eyes unable &#8212; if I should get blind &#8212; Homer Ossian<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Celtic bard Ossian.</note> &amp;
                    Milton would give me little comfort &#8212; some kind friend must then buy me a halter
                    &amp; thirteen pence halfpenny will be saved to my <hi rend="ital">executors</hi> &#8212; there, a pun spoilt in the execution &#8212; that last makes
                    amend. I am going to bed well pleasd with myself &#8212; to dream of you &amp;
                    heaven &amp; happiness unless the d&#230;mon of dismal dreams pops under my
                    pillow &amp; harrows up my heart with some of his chimeras &#8212; oh if life were
                    all one agreable dream &#8212; or rather if death were &#8212; would there be a crime in
                    taking laudanum as an opiate? good night.</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I shall burst
                    &#8212; such a catastrophe &#8212; such an enterprize &#8212; such a fall &#8212; <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref> &#8212; the sober
                    prudent discreet <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref>!
                    of all men in the world the one who could shrug up his shoulders at the
                    Flagellant to think that he should expose himself &amp; become the standing
                    jest of Christ Church the genteel college. write to him pity him condole him
                    laugh at him. I shall run mad with the idea.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> would you
                    believe it &#8212; <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref> was
                    a member of a society entituled Societas scientium literariorum studiosorum
                    Oxoniensium &#8212; instituted for the purposes of debating &amp; (as <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> says) forming a library to
                    rival the Bodleian. this had been laudable in private. but they draw up a quarto
                    volume of statutes &amp; institutes &amp; march up for the Vice
                    Chancellors permission to obtain a room for public debating!!!!!! he replied
                    (most memorable reply!)</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Vice Chancellor cannot prevent you from making yourselves
                    fools in private but he will assuredly take care that you shall not disgrace the
                    University by doing it in public!!!!!!!!!!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> poor <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> one
                    of the two C Church members is so ridiculed! <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combe</ref> tells me &#8212; the Dean &amp;
                    Hall laugh at him &amp; SAWKINS<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Charles Sawkins (d. 1818), educated at Christ Church, Oxford, BA
                        1778, and from 1797 Perpetual Curate of Binsey, Oxfordshire.</note> has
                    ventured to cut a joke upon the occasion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> now is our <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">pretty
                        Plato</ref> to be pitied or laughd at? must he be elegized or odified? or be
                    sung in villainous ballads to a scurvey tune? I would walk to Oxford &amp;
                    back for the sake of five minutes laugh. the FLAGELLANT &#8212; is revenged. the cubic
                    sage is flagellated &#8212; is not this grand &amp; sublime &#8212; oh that we could
                    both meet for one hour to write a letter &#8212; SAWKINS laughing at <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">CHARLES COLLINS</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1793-11-14">Friday night</date>. My dear <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I am sick of this
                    world &amp; discontented with every one in it. the murder of Brissot<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques Pierre Brissot (1754&#8211;1793), a
                        leading Girondist, was executed in October 1793.</note> has compleately
                    harrowed up my faculties &amp; I begin to believe that virtue can only
                    aspire to content in obscurity &#8212; for happiness is out of the question. I look
                    round the world &amp; every where find the same mournful spectacle. the
                    strong tyrannize over the weak &#8212; man &amp; beast. the same depravity
                    pervades the whole creation. oppression is triumphant every where &amp; the
                    only difference is that it acts in Turkey thro the organ of a grand Seignor in
                    France of a Revolutionary Tribunal &amp; in England of a prime minister,
                    there is no place for virtue. Seneca<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Lucius Annaeus Seneca (4 BC&#8211; AD 65), Stoic philosopher and dramatist, who
                        proclaimed the need to accept suffering. He committed suicide after being
                        accused of involvement in the Pisonian conspiracy against Nero.</note> was a
                    visionary philosopher. even in the deserts of Arabia the strongest will be the
                    happiest &#8212; &amp; the same rule holds good in Europe or in Abyssinia. here
                    are you &amp; I theorizing upon principles we can never practise &amp;
                    wasting our time &amp; youth &#8212; you in scribbling parchments &amp; I in
                    spoiling quires with poetry. I am ready to quarrel with my friends for not
                    making me a carpenter &#8212; &amp; with myself for devoting my time to pursuits
                    certainly unimportant &amp; of no real utility either to myself or to
                    others. I have still three years to waste in the same shameful manner before
                    there will be a possibility of my being of any service to mankind &amp; even
                    then Religion must change the human heart before it can mend it. in short I
                    begin to think a halter a mighty pretty thing &#8212; &amp; one day of these days
                    you will certainly hear that I have swung myself into eternity if the public
                    executioner does not save me the trouble &#8212; as for crime I cannot use the word.
                    Charlotte Corde<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte Corday
                        (1768&#8211;1793) who, on 13 July 1793, stabbed Jean Paul Marat (1743&#8211;1793) to
                        death in his bath. She was guillotined four days later.</note> was
                    meritorious let our friend say what he pleases. nor do I see in what manner we
                    can quit Life more honourably than in ridding it at once of a monster &amp;
                    an useless incumbrance. Religion certainly consists in doing good to mankind.
                    now who renders society the most service the person who feeds as a lapdog or the
                    one who destroys the wolf &amp; the lapdog? Religion &#8212; the word is so
                    prostituted that I am sick of it. instead of a benefit as intended by an allgood
                    &amp; all wise creator it is degenerated into a curse. nay the very
                    scriptures at the same time that they contain the most important truths, may be
                    alledged in vindication of every vice. I could bring you passages equally
                    positive in favor of passive obedience &amp; of tyrannicide, equally
                    positive &amp; equally atrocious for whether the murderer of Sisera<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Sisera was the captain of Jabin, King of
                        Canaan, and killed by Jael; see <title level="m">Judges</title> 4:
                        21.</note> or <del rend="strikethrough">Jael</del>
                        &lt;Agag.&gt;<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The King of
                        the Amalekites was killed by the prophet Samuel; see 1<title level="m">
                            Samuel</title> 15: 33.</note> be most infamous I know not &#8212; would every
                    one adopt our criterion of scriptural truth Religion would be certainly amended
                    as it must be simplified.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> poor <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>! how lamentably will you be puzzled with this pretty cross
                    window writing! did you never when you was a child delight in having cross
                    windows cut upon your bread &amp; butter? I remember the day when it was
                    luxury to me, bread &amp; butter with brown sugar &amp; glass windows
                    was an indulgence which delighted me in days when I &lt;was&gt; more
                    ignorant &amp; more happy. these kind of pleasures are neither sensual nor
                    mental: appropriate to an age when we are happily ignorant of both. that age was
                    the happiest I have yet enjoyed &#8212; &amp; in all human probability the
                    happiest I ever shall enjoy. my grandmother<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s maternal grandmother Margaret, <hi rend="ital">n&#233;e</hi> Bradford. Her first husband was John Tyler, her second, Edward
                        Hill. She lived at Bedminster, near Bristol.</note> then living had a house
                    two miles from Bristol with her I past the greater part of my infancy &amp;
                    never did there exist a woman more respectable in every station of life. her
                    house was the residence of most of her children &amp; the rendevous of all.
                    I lost her when I was nine years old &amp; since that period my life has
                    been little more than one series of undeserved calamities. they have taught me
                    philosophy &#8212; &amp; heavy as is the price it is not too dear.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been reading Courtney Melmoths Liberal Opinions<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Jackson Pratt (pseud. Courtney
                        Melmoth) (1749&#8211;1814; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Liberal
                            Opinions, upon Animals, Man, and Providence</title> (1775&#8211;1777).</note>
                    to-day. I know not if you have ever read the book &#8212; but it contains the history
                    of Benignus &#8212; some parts of which pleasd me much. a young man sets out in life
                    with this principle. To be good is to be happy. of course he becomes miserable
                    by practising or rather by attempting to practise theoretical principles of
                    universal benevolence. Men of feeling (I hate to use the word but no other
                    expreses the meaning) men of feeling are exposed to a thousand pangs which the
                    fool escapes because his faculties are too gross to comprehend them. Forester
                    Brice &amp; Selim<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Boys who had
                        bullied Southey at Westminster School. William Forester (d. 1794), educated
                        at Westminster School (adm. 1782), later entered the army and died of
                        yellow fever during the St Domingo expedition of 1794; Robert Brice (d.
                        1812), became a lieutenant-colonel and died in India. Selim is a nickname
                        for an unidentified contemporary at Westminster.</note> will pass thro life
                    with more wordly pleasure probably than we shall &#8212; but there is another world
                    &amp; there things will be topsy-turvy.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">say what he ... topsy-turvy: Cross hatched.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">&#8211; <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">CCs</ref> club ha! ha!
                    two letters in one week upon the subject! pretty Plato.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8212; CC&#8217;s club ... pretty Plato: Written on address section of
                        fol. 2v.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>