<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce195</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.195</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization
                  unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of
                  1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared
                  only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
                  redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
                  notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt; <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
                        Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or
                  that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
                  additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to
                  all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                  use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4811D. Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
               York, 1965), I, pp. 119&#8211;20.Dating note: The letter is dated from the endorsement; the postmark suggests a date before c. 30 January
               1797.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript
               Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
               Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University
               Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
               Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University; the John Rylands Library,
               Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
               Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public
               Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
               Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne;
               the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the English Department of
               Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.195" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey&#8217;s spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                  http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="195" type="letter">
        <head>195. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1797-01-26">[26 January 1797]</date>
          </head><p>Address: [MS torn] W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  5. Stone Buildings/ Lincolns Inn/ London/ Single<lb />Stamped: BATH<lb />Postmark: [partial] BJ/ 30/ 97<lb />Endorsement: Southey/ Jan
                  26/ 1797<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4811D. ALS; 4p.<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New
                     Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 119&#8211;20.<lb />Dating note: The letter is dated from
                  the endorsement; the postmark suggests a date before c. 30 January 1797.</p>
        <lb />
        <p n="indent1"> I differ from you concerning La Fayette.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Marie-Paul-Joseph-Roch-Gilbert Motier,
                  Marquis de La Fayette (1757&#8211;1834), French general and politician. He was an active supporter of the American side in the War of
                  Independence, but took a moderate position during the French Revolution and eventually fled to Austria, where he was
                  imprisoned.</note> on what pretext is he confined but as the prisoner of the allies? he cannot be supposed the prisoner of the
               Emperor individually. therefore instead of seeing any impropriety in the interference of England, I think for its own honor this
               country should wash its hands of so infamous a transaction. La Fayette is not amenable to the Emperor for aught he may have done. I am
               glad to see the French are opening their eyes to his conduct. how did you like M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wyndhams speech<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Windham (1750&#8211;1810; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Secretary of War, 1794&#8211;1801, declared in the
                  House of Commons on 16 December 1796 that La Fayette&#8217;s imprisonment was not a matter for the British government.</note> upon this
               subject?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Mary&#8221; is a bad poem<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s ballad &#8216;Mary&#8217; was published in his <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797).</note> &#8212; but it is generally liked. it has been selected as a favorite by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Dr Beddoes</ref> &#8212; a hypercritic of the Darwin<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Erasmus
                  Darwin (1731&#8211;1802; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> school, who writes bad verses himself, &amp; of course criticises <del rend="strikethrough">every body</del> all others severely.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Si el sabio no aprueba, malo!</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Si el necio aplaude, peor!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A poem by Tom&#225;s de Iriarte (1750&#8211;1791), translated
                     by Southey as &#8216;The Dancing Bear&#8217;. Southey&#8217;s version of these lines appeared in his <title level="m">Letters Written During a
                        Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (London, 1797), p. 551, as &#8216;Bad is the censure of the wise/ The Blockhead&#8217;s
                     praise is worse&#8217;.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>I begin to think that our opinions upon poetry are not consonant. I am no friend to the harmony with which we have been cloyed since
               the days of Pope.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note>
                  Churchill<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Churchill (1732&#8211;1764; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> is too rough:
               but there is a medium, &amp; I am on the side of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref> versus
               Reviewers:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Negative assessments of the versification and language of William Lisle Bowles, <title level="m">Hope, An Allegorical Sketch on Recovering Slowly from Sickness</title> (1796) had appeared in the <title level="j">Critical Review</title>, 19 (January 1797), 235&#8211;236, and the <title level="j">British Critic</title>, 9 (January 1797),
                  190&#8211;191.</note> who by the by are in general a set of stupid fellows. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has the Monk to review for the Critical<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Matthew Gregory Lewis (1775&#8211;1818;
                     <title level="m">DNB</title>), author of the controversial <title level="m">The Monk</title> (1796), which Samuel Taylor
                  Coleridge reviewed in the <title level="j">Critical Review</title>, 19 (February 1797), 194&#8211;200.</note> &#8212; &amp; I am somewhat
               curious to see how he will handle Lewis. I am engaged when in town to write for the Analytical &amp; should very much like to begin by
               dissecting Ambrosio. I do not think the Monk can be praised too highly, or blamed too severely.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish <ref type="m" target="people.html#NaresRobert">Bob</ref> would insert a review of my writing in the British
               Critic. <del rend="strikethrough">there a</del> it is upon a strange poem with still stranger notes, written by a man of brilliant
               genius &amp; polishd manners who is deranged. it is easy to imply this without doing it in such terms as would wound his feelings. the
               book is &#8220;the Hurricane a Theosophical &amp; Western Eclogue by William Gilbert.&#8221; <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                  Gilbert&#8217;s <title level="m">The Hurricane</title> had been published in 1796.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GilbertWilliam">Gilbert</ref> has been called to the bar. he was clerk to the House of Commons at
               Antigua, &amp; came to England as Counsel on a celebrated cause in the annals of Military Law. I know him &amp; pity him &#8212;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent4"> where a sight shall Sorrow find</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Sad as the ruins of the human mind! <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of William Lisle Bowles,
                        <title level="m">Verses on the Benevolent Institution of the Philanthropic Society</title> (Bath, 1790), p. 16. Southey had
                     previously used these lines as an epigraph to the four &#8216;Botany-Bay Eclogues&#8217; published in his <title level="m">Poems</title>
                     (1797).</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>My book is done.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain
                     and Portugal</title> (1797).</note> &amp; I wait only to get your copies hot pressed to dispatch them. I was obliged to cancel
               two complete sheets &#8212; such blunders did they make in my absence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> to night I return to Bristol to visit the only friend I have there. you know that now I do not rashly use the word. we
               are going to see the skeletons of which you may have seen some account in the papers &#8212; you may expect a true &amp; particular
                  account.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">For Southey&#8217;s account of the skeletons found in 1797 at Aveline&#8217;s Hole in the
                  Mendip Hills, near Burrington Combe, see his letter to the Editor of the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title>, 28 January 1797
                  (Letter 196) and to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 29 January [1797] (Letter 197).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am about to send a Joan of Arc to St Pierre.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques-Henri Bernardin de
                  Saint-Pierre (1737&#8211;1814), author of <title level="m">Paul et Virginie</title> (1788) and <title level="m">Etudes de la
                     Nature</title> (1784).</note> you know he earnestly recommends the subject &#8212; for a drama [MS torn] there is a communication by
               means of Remnant<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">James Remnant (fl. 1790s) a bookseller in High Holborn, who specialised in
                  German books.</note> [MS torn]German bookseller to Hambro &#8212; Rotterdam &#8212; &amp; [MS obscured] Paris &#8212; &amp; a present from one
               literary man to another does not come within the penalties of the Traitrous Correspondence bill.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The Traitorous Correspondence Act of 1793 was designed to prevent British citizens from aiding France in any
                  way.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> farewell.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> R Sou[MS torn]</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>