<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce201</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.201</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Hispanic Society of America, New York.  Previously  published: Joseph Cottle, Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey (London, 1847), pp. 199&#8211;200 [in part, and misdated &#8216;November 1796&#8217;]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 303&#8211;304 [in part, where it is dated February 1797]; Catalogue of the Collection of Autograph Letters and Historical Documents formed between 1865 and 1882 by Alfred Morrison, 6 vols (London, 1883&#8211;92), VI, pp. 157&#8211;158 [in full, but misdated &#8216;17 November 1797&#8217;]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.201" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="201" type="letter">
        <head>201. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1797-02-17">[c. 17 February 1797]</date>
          </head><p>Address: For/ Mr Cottle/ High Street/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped: [partial] GE S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>/ Westminster<lb />Postmark: FE/ 17/ 97<lb />Endorsements: Southey/ Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1796; <hi rend="ital">12</hi> (65)<lb /> MS: Hispanic Society of America, New York<lb />Previously published: Joseph Cottle, <title level="m">Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey</title> (London, 1847), pp. 199&#8211;200 [in part, and misdated &#8216;November 1796&#8217;]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 303&#8211;304 [in part, where it is dated February 1797]; <title level="m">Catalogue of the Collection of Autograph Letters and Historical Documents formed between 1865 and 1882 by Alfred Morrison</title>, 6 vols (London, 1883&#8211;92), VI, pp. 157&#8211;158 [in full, but misdated &#8216;17 November 1797&#8217;]. </p>
        <p rend="indent5">				Sheet B.6.</p>
        <table cols="2" rows="10">
          <row>
            <cell rend="left">P.</cell>
            <cell rend="indent1">369. line 2. after &#8220;the lives of men&#8221; <del rend="strikethrough">add</del> &lt;insert&gt; &#8220;from various dangers&#8221;</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">370 &#8212; 10. after. considers &#8212; insert &#8212; that.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">374. in the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> line of the Spanish for Cuijas &#8212; read &#8212; cujas.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">377.	6 &#8212; for She&#8217;s &#8212; She is.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">&#8212;&#8212; 14 &#8212; for Zaydo &#8212; Zayda</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">&#8212; last but one &#8212; for troche &#8212; trochee</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">378 &#8212; 20 &#8212; after letra place a comma for a full stop.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">&#8212;&#8212; 22 &#8212; for signem &#8212; siguen.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">380 &#8212; last but 3. for Azargue &#8212; Azarque.</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell />
            <cell rend="indent1">382 &#8212; 12 &#8212; for careel &#8212; carcel<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The proofing corrections are for Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>, published by Joseph Cottle in 1797.</note>
            </cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>A tolerable list of blunders from a single sheet, of which two leaves have already been cancelled! I have only to beg you will correct it carefully, send one fine copy to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> &amp; the rest to me. have you sent the letters &amp; poems to <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref>?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	My dear friend my correspondence with you will not for the future be filled with corrections &amp; directions. I am now entered on a new way of life, which will lead me to independance. you know that I neither lightly undertake any scheme, or lightly abandon what I have undertaken. I am happy because I have no want, &amp; because the independance which I labor to attain, &amp; of attaining which my expectations can hardly be disappointed, will leave me nothing to wish.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I am indebted to you <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">
            <hi rend="ital">Cottle</hi>
          </ref> for the comforts of my latter time. in my present situation I feel pleasure in saying thus much</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	As to my literary pursuits, after some consideration, I have resolved to postpone every other till I have concluded Madoc. this must be the greatest of all my works; the structure is compleat in my mind, &amp; my mind is stored likewise with appropriate images. should I delay it, these images may become fainter &#8212; &amp; perhaps &#8212; age does not improve the Poet. thank God <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> comes on Monday next &#8212; I say thank God &#8212; for I have never (since my return) been absent from her so long before, &amp; sincerely hope &amp; intend never to be &lt;so&gt; again. on Tuesday we shall be settled &#8212; [MS torn] Wednesday my legal studies begin in the morning, &amp; I shall begin with Madoc in the evening. of this, it is needless to caution you to say nothing &#8212; as I must have the character of a Lawyer &#8212; &amp; tho I can &amp; will unite the two pursuits no one would credit the possibility of the union. in two years the poem shall be finished; &amp; the many years it must lie by will afford ample time for correction.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Mary has been in the Oracle.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s ballad, &#8216;Mary&#8217;, was published in the <title level="j">Oracle</title>, a London newspaper, on 11 February 1797.</note>  some of my sonnets in the Telegraph, with most outrageous commendations.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A number of Southey&#8217;s poems, including some sonnets and a variant version of &#8216;The Race of Banquo&#8217;, appeared in the London daily newspaper the <title level="j">Telegraph</title> (1794&#8211;1797) in early 1797. It is very possible that Southey contributed to the paper on a regular basis, but it is impossible to estimate the true extent of his contributions, as few issues of the <title level="j">Telegraph</title> survive.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	You know I suppose that we are to lodge at <ref target="people.html#Peacockunknown">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Peacocks</ref>. I am very glad he could receive us, because it is pleasant to be with persons who will not impose upon us, &amp; because the situation secures me from intruding visitors. I have declined being member of a literary club, which meets weekly, &amp; of which I had been pre-elected a member. surely a man does not do his duty, who leaves his wife to evenings of solitude; &amp; I feel duty &amp; happiness to be inseperable. I am happier at home than any other society can possibly make me. with <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> I am alike secure from the wearisomeness of solitude, &amp; the disgust which I cannot help feeling at the contemplation of mankind, &amp; which I do not wish to suppress.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Do you know that Muir has made his escape from Botany Bay. <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The political reformer Thomas Muir (1765&#8211;1799; <title level="m">DNB</title>) had escaped from Botany Bay in February 1796. He eventually made his way to France.</note> Hamilton Rowan<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Archibald Hamilton Rowan (1751&#8211;1834; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Irish nationalist and landowner, whose involvement in radical politics led to a two-year prison sentence in January 1794. He escaped from Newgate jail, Dublin, a few months later, eventually settling in America. He was permitted to return to Ireland in 1806.</note> at the expence of 500 pounds procured an American Ship bound to China to call there, a[MS torn] tho driven by stress of weather. the intelligence comes in a[MS torn] letter from Margarott to Hardy,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The political reformer Maurice Margarot (1745&#8211;1815; <title level="m">DNB</title>), who was transported to Australia in 1794, and Thomas Hardy (1752&#8211;1832; <title level="m">DNB</title>), the founder of the London Corresponding Society.</note> &amp; is certain. I [MS torn] not seen it in the newspapers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I have cause of complaint against you for writing me so very short a letter. were you doing as you would be done by? I shall have no correspondents in your part of the world but you &amp; <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>. I have promised to send him Madoc, book by book, as it is compleated. he will lend it you, &amp; there its circulation stops.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Here is a great deal about myself, &amp; nothing about those whom I have seen in London &amp; of whom we have all heard in the country. I will make a report upon them in my next letter. remember me kindly to your sisters &amp; family.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I do not forget Old Bristol &#8212; &amp; look forward with pleasure to the distant period when I may visit you, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fox &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Fox, &amp; the dog &amp; the parrot<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The poet and orientalist Charles Fox (1740?&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and his wife shared their home with a parrot, whose name is not recorded.</note> &amp; the rest of my acquaintance</p>
        <p rend="indent2">		God bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">			yrs sincerely</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">				Robert Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>