<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce96</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.96</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 60&#8211;64 [in part; verses not reproduced]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 213&#8211;215 [in part, where it is dated 20 July 1794].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.96" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="96" type="letter">
        <head>96. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-07-20">20&#8211;21 July 1794</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb /> Stamped: BATH<lb />Postmark: JY/ 24/ 94<lb />Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> July 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1794. Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. July 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1794/ &amp; sent; Govi me querelis examinas tuis [The Latin can be roughly translated as &#8216;Govi (probably a nickname) you weigh me down with your complaints&#8217;.]<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 60&#8211;64 [in part; verses not reproduced]; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 213&#8211;215 [in part, where it is dated 20 July 1794].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1794-07-20">Sunday. July 20. 1794.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>Bath.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I believe nearly three weeks have elapsed since your last letter at Oxford damped my breakfast with disappointment. to see you at all times would be a source of much pleasure, but I should have been particularly glad to have introduced you to <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>. they shared in my disappointment, but that part of human happiness is not alleviated by partition. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is now walking over Wales. you have seen a specimen of <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allens</ref> poetry but never any of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">his friends</ref>. take these, they are the only ones I can show you &amp; were written on the wainscott of the Inn at Ross, which was once the dwelling house of Kyrle.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Kyrle (1637&#8211;1724; <title level="m">DNB</title>), philanthropist and landscape designer, popularly known as the &#8216;Man of Ross&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Richer than Misers oer their countless hoards</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nobler than Kings, or king-polluted Lords.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Here dwelt the Man of Ross! o Traveller hear!</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Departed Merit claims the glistening tear.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Friend to the friendless. to the sick man Health,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">With generous joy he viewd his modest wealth,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">He heard the Widows heaven-breathd prayer of praise,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">He markd the shelterd orphans tearful gaze,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And, oer the dowried Maidens glowing cheek</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Bade bridal Love suffuse its blushes meek.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">If &#8217;neath this roof thy wine-cheerd moments pass,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Fill to the good man&#8217;s name one grateful glass!</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To higher zest shall Memory wake thy soul</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And Virtue mingle in the sparkling bowl.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">But if, like me, thro Life&#8217;s distressful scene</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Lonely &amp; sad thy pilgrimage hath been.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And if, thy breast with heart-sick anguish fraught,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thou journeyest onward tempest-tost in thought,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Here cheat thy cares; in generous visions melt,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And <hi rend="ital">dream</hi> of Goodness thou hast never felt.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version appeared as &#8216;Lines on the Man of Ross&#8217; in Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <title level="m">Poems on Various Subjects</title> (1796).</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">	Admire the verses <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>, &amp; pity that mind that wrote them from its genuine feelings. tis my intention soon to join him in Wales. then proceed to <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref> seriously to settle with him the best mode of settling in America. yesterday I took my proposals for publishing Joan of Arc to the printers.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey intended to issue a subscription edition of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> with the Bath publisher Richard Cruttwell (c. 1747&#8211;1799; <title level="m">DNB</title>). This plan did not materialise, and the epic was eventually published by Joseph Cottle.</note> should the publication be any ways successful it will carry me over &amp; get me some few acres a spade &amp; a plough. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother Thomas</ref> will gladly go with us &amp; perhaps two or three more of my most intimate friends. in this country I must either sacrifice happiness or integrity. but when we meet I will explain my motives most fully.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I shall not reside next Michaelmas at Oxford, because the time will be better employed in correcting Joan &amp; overlooking the press if I get fifty copies subscribed for by that time. during that time I will see you in town if convenient. to say when is as yet impossible. </p>
        <p>Debrett is very dilatory about our poems.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to the collection Southey and Robert Lovell were planning to publish under the pseudonyms &#8216;Orson&#8217; and &#8216;Valentine&#8217;. John Debrett (d. 1822; <title level="m">DNB</title>) was a London publisher and bookseller, founder of <title level="m">Debrett&#8217;s Peerage and Baronetage</title>.</note> in the mean time we have almost compleated another volume which tis our intention to publish here under the names of Bion &amp; Moschus.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Lovell&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1795), published by Richard Cruttwell.</note> I have ten sonnets in this of which take two.</p>
        <p rend="indent5">The faded Flower<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version appeared in Southey and Robert Lovell&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1795).</note>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Ungrateful he who pluckt thee from thy stalk</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Poor withered flowret on his careless way,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Inhald awhile thine odors on his walk</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Then past along &amp; left thee to decay!</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thou melancholy emblem! had I seen</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Thy modest beauties dewed with evenings gem,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	I had not rudely cropt thy parent stem.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">But left thy blossom still to grace the green</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And I had bent me oer thy opening flower</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	And markd thy leaves in many a hue arrayd,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And as mine eye had loved thy blooming hour &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	So had it dropt the tear to see thee fade.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Ah! blind to Natures charms! whose selfish joy</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Tasted thy virgin sweets but tasted to destroy.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent5">To Reflection<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version appeared in Southey and Robert Lovell&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1795).</note>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Hence busy torturer! wherefore should mine eye</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Revert again to many a sorrow past?</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Hence busy torturer! to the happy fly</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Those who have never seen the sun oercast</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	By one dark cloud: thy retrospective <del rend="strikethrough">gleam</del> &lt;beam&gt;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Serene &amp; soft may on their bosom gleam</l>
          <l rend="indent2">As the last radiance of the summer sky.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Bid them look back on pleasure ere they know</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To mourn its absence: bid them contemplate</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The quick vicissitudes of mortal fate</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Ere unexpected bursts the cloud of woe.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">	Stream not one me thy torches baneful glow,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Like the sepulchral lamps funereal gloom</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In darkness glimmering to disclose the tomb!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Hence busy ... tomb: Verse written in double columns.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">	I much regret leaving your letters at Oxford. in the last but one were some passages on which I wish to reason. tis my opinion that Vice is not natural to Man, by Vice I understand the perpetration of such actions as are injurious to society. in fact it is an atrocious blasphemy to assert the Deity has made any one creature vicious as you thereby make him the author of evil, &amp; either Malignism or Dualism must be establishd. mind is the child of observation &amp; experience. we are certain that innate ideas cannot exist, of course the infant is capable of any impression. that some men have more vigorous passions to combat with than others I readily allow, but you will agree with me that the indulgence of the passions is only vicious as the organization of society renders it so. man cannot act without motives, give him the strongest motives for virtue &amp; take away all motives for vice &amp; Man would approach very near perfect. the many judge of man by what he is in his present degraded situation; this is very unfair, you might as well judge of a persons complexion when he is jaundiced. do you <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> ponder well in your mind how far vice is generated by situation. I think we may one day meet in sentiment; even our difference is a proof how far situation operates. for had we been uniformly together the same coincidence which we feel on other subjects must have taken place in politics. when the storm bursts on England you may perhaps follow us to America. I will get thee a house like my own simple &amp; convenient, &amp; when thou hast once seen the aspheterizing system realized, thou wilt gladly fraternize with us. &#8212; do not my dear <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> run away with the idea that I am mad in these schemes. surely you will not think Edmund Seward likely to be led away by fairy visions. I have many &amp; powerful motives for quitting this country, nor will my mind ever be totally free from despondence whilst I remain in it. whether Lovell will accompany us or not is doubtful &#8212; the leaving him will be one more cord of Affection to break, but Resolution is like Samson &amp; no cords could detain him. &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I do not entertain so high an opinion of <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">CC</ref> as I did twelve months ago, he has modelled his mind to the Christ Church fashion, &amp; allows no merit to any thing differing from it. <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">CC</ref> has frequently told me he never knew a rich Republican, that they were all needy men who wishd a change merely to better themselves. in this is much illiberality, particularly when I mentioned three of my own friends &#8212; of whom one has sacrificed 1000 a year, <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> 800 &#8212; &amp; the third has uniformly refused many places under government which his friends offered to procure for him. when <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> says this he must either judge from his own heart or from the Republicans whom he knows. if he entertains such an opinion of <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> &amp; me why does he not shun us like contagion? if he himself is above such mean motives, why should he not believe that we likewise may be superior to them? if he be not above them, let him not reduce other minds to a level with his own. &#8212; <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> has more coldness of heart than any man I ever met with. his wish in company is always to shine, &amp; to attain this he will sacrifice every thing. we carry our hearts in our hands, our merits &amp; faults are soon discovered; but these cold hearted Temporizers wrap up all their sentiments &amp; all their actions &amp; call it wisdom! </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	when <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> work is published you will see a Latin Poem of <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allens</ref> which did not gain the praise. the subject Ludi Scenici.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Stage plays. Robert Allen&#8217;s poem was possibly going to be included in Coleridge&#8217;s unrealised &#8216;Imitations from the Modern Latin Poets&#8217;, advertised in 1794.</note> of the execution you will judge for my own part I will not scruple to pronounce it very excellent. Coleridge means to translate it. he won the Greek Ode at Cambridge &amp; I have promisd to translate it<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Taylor Coleridge won the Browne medal for a sapphic ode on the slave-trade during his first year at Cambridge (1792). A &#8216;Literal Translation&#8217; appeared in the notes to <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> (Bristol and London, 1796), pp. 63&#8211;64.</note> for his work, so you will have some memorial of us all. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I shall inscribe Joan of Arc to you, unless you are afraid to have your name prefixed to a work that breathes some sentiments not perfectly in unison with court principles. correction will take up some time, for the poem will go into the world handsomely. twill be my legacy to this country &amp; may perhaps preserve my memory in it. many of my friends will blame me for so bold a step, but as many encourage me &#8212; &amp; I want to raise money enough to settle myself across the Atlantic. if I have leisure to write there my stock of imagery will be much enlarged. I should like a good frontispiece to Joan &amp; am minded to apply to <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> for one. if you call upon him make my civic remembrances, he has long asked me for some verses &amp; I must soon write with some. &#8212; <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">your brother</ref> neglect has quite tired me. I will write no more to him till I hear from him. tell him so. when next I come to town I must get your bust. it shall ornament my dwelling in Kentucky. I will ask <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> for his likewise. twill be pleasant to recall the features of an absent friend when seperated from him by the ocean perhaps eternally.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	my proposals will be printed this evening &#8212; I remain here till tomorrow morning for the sake of carrying some to Bristol &amp; inclosing one. methinks my name will look well in print. I expect a host of petty critics will buz about my ears but must brush them off. you know what the poem was at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref>; when well corrected I fear not its success.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	remember me to <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">George Strachey</ref> when you see him. is not his brother on board the Queen Charlotte? <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother</ref> will most probably be in that ship &amp; I should wish them to be acquainted. you never saw <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>. he had a fortnights absence lately to get a wound in his heel cured originating from chilblains &amp; encreasd by the scurvy. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> left me last Tuesday, in great hopes of soon quitting a line of life so contrary to his inclination &amp; frame of mind for peace &amp; independance in America. 18 months spent at sea have improved his bodily strength &amp; corrected many little failings without corrupting his mind. twas not without some apprehensions that I saw him after so long an absence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	direct to me at Bristol I shall remain there perhaps a fortnight &amp; your letters will be forwarded should I be absent. my thankful remembrances to <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Mr &amp; Mrs B</ref>. &amp; whoever enquires for me. Debrett<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Debrett (d. 1822; <title level="m">DNB</title>), London publisher and bookseller, founder of <title level="m">Debrett&#8217;s Peerage and Baronetage</title>.</note> is so dilatory that <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> thinks of going to town; if so you will see the Man of mighty mind. he thinks you a living miracle so republican in practise, &amp; so aristocratic in principle</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I have a linen coat making much like yours, tis destined for much service. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> ambulated to Bristol with me from Oxford. he is a worthy fellow whom I greatly esteem. we have a wild Welchman<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> red hot from the mountains at <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref> who would please &amp; amuse you much. he is perfectly ignorant of the world but with all the honest warm feelings of Nature, &amp; good head &amp; a good heart. <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> is AB. old <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Ball. Coll</ref>. has lost its best inhabitants in old Nick &amp; <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref>. <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> too resides only six weeks longer in the University so it would be a melancholy place for me were I to visit it again for residence. my tutor will much wonder at seeing my name. but as <ref target="people.html#HoweThomas">Thomas Howe</ref> is half a democrat he will be pleased. what miracle could illuminate him I know not, but he surprized me much by declaiming against the war, praising America &amp; asserting the right of every country to model its own form of government. this was followed by &#8220;M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey you wont learn any thing by my lectures Sir, so if you have any studies of your own you had better pursue them&#8221;. you may suppose I thankfully accepted the offer. let me hear from you soon. you promisd me some verses.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4">sincerely yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey &#8212; </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1794-07-21">Monday July. 21</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">	how are the wasps this year? my dogs eats flies voraciously &amp; hunts wasps for the same purpose. if he catches one, he will follow poor Hyder!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A dog owned by the Bedford family.</note> I saved him twice to day from swallowing them like oysters.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>