<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce205</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.205</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Duke University Library, Southey papers.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        121–123.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="205" type="letter">
<head>205. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">John James
                        Morgan</ref> [fragment], <date when="1797-03-06">6 March 1797</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: John James Morgan/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> James’s Square/ Bristol/ Single<lb/> Stamped:
                        [illegible]<lb/>Postmark: [illegible]<lb/>Endorsement: R. Southey
                        Esq<lb/>MS: Duke University Library, Southey papers<lb/>Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        121–123.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<address rend="left">
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#ProspectPlaceLondon">No 20. Prospect Place. Newington Butts</ref>.</placeName>
</address>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1797-03-16">Thursday March 16. 1797.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Amidst all the Bodderation of the Welsh Invasion &amp; the Banks
                        stoppage<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Fourteen hundred French
                        troops had landed in Pembrokeshire on the night of 22–23 February 1797. They
                        surrendered a few days later. The Bank of England had stopped exchanging its
                        notes for gold in February 1797 because of excessive demands caused by fears
                        of invasion.</note> I have remained quietly employed, seeing little, hearing
                    little, saying little &amp; not thinking much. I do not impute the stoppage
                    of the Bank to myself, tho I confess that having some apprehensions I did get
                    cash for a five pound note. perhaps you may not know the history of the Dollars.
                    it is a curious one. England used to purchase dollars from Spain to make use of
                    in the India Trade — East I believe as well as West, &amp; a considerable
                    sum went annually from this country for that purpose. Mr Pitt<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Prime Minister, William Pitt, the Younger
                        (1759–1806; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> took it into his head that
                    he could make the King of Spains money somewhat cheaper than he could purchase
                    it, more especially if the silver was not quite so good. the Spaniards wondered
                    that the English did not want Dollars &amp; Gimbernatt<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Either the Spanish geologist Carlos de Gimbernat
                        (1768–1834), or (though less likely) his father, the physician Antonio de
                        Gimbernat (1734–1816).</note> learnt in conversation from one of the persons
                    employed in the Mint that he had been making dollars. he communicated this to
                    Las Casas<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">M. De Las Casas (dates
                        unknown), Spanish Ambassador in London.</note> the Spanish Embassador
                    &amp; Las Casas made it the subject of one of what he used to call his
                    Lectures to Ld Grenville<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wyndham
                        Grenville, Lord Grenville (1759–1834; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Foreign
                        Secretary 1791–1801 and Prime Minister 1806–1807.</note> [MS torn]
                    consequence Gimbernatt received an order under the Alien[MS torn] Bill to quit
                    this country — &amp; Las Casas immediately wrote his<del rend="strikethrough">x</del> &lt;name&gt; down as one of the
                    secretaries to the Embassy. I saw a Dollar yesterday with the head of Carlos
                        3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> &amp; the name of Carlos 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish kings, Carlos III
                        (1716–1788; reigned 1759–88) and Carlos IV (1748–1819; reigned
                        1788–1808).</note> a Blunder which no Spaniard could <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxly</del> &lt;probably&gt; have committed. I
                    had this account from <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> —
                    the intimate friend of Gimbernatt . — he visited much at Las Casas house. a fine
                    liberal Spaniard — a man who seems to have ingrafted the new French character on
                    the old Spanish one. perhaps words cannot convey a higher encomium.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Gimbernatt is now at Paris. I never saw him — tho he heard many
                    of my Lectures<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A series of
                        ‘Historical Lectures’ ‘Unconnected with the Politics of the Day’, given by
                        Southey in Bristol in 1795.</note> &amp; used to call me The Professor.
                    he sent me introductory letters in that character to Madrid, but they did not
                    reach me till I had arrived at Lisbon.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am at last about to send Joan of Arc to Paris. there it ought
                    to be a national Poem. you will have the portraits of the Directory soon in the
                    Monthly Magazine. I know not whether that of Rewbell<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-François Rewbell (1747–1807), a member of the Directory
                        (1795–1796).</note> may be depended upon, as it is from a German
                    publication, posseses little character, &amp; was upon the same paper with
                    other portraits [MS illegible] if true, give the lie to physiognomy. the other
                    four [MS illegible] Paris, by some accident the fifth was omitted. Phillips<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Richard Phillips (1767–1840; <title level="m">DNB</title>), proprietor of the <title level="j">Monthly
                            Magazine</title>.</note> told me that the account of Jordans Bridge,
                    which Evans had “proved upon paper” <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        reference to two articles: ‘Jordan’s Suspended Bridges’, <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 2 (December 1796), 883, and ‘Mr. Jordan’s
                        Suspended Bridges’, <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 3 (January
                        1797), 48–49.</note> was so compleatly confused, that he was obliged to get
                    the Architect to translate it into intelligible English.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Blackstone<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir William
                        Blackstone (1723–1780; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Commentaries on the Laws of England</title> (1765–1769).</note>
                    &amp; I agree better than perhaps you imagine. true it is that I should like
                    to write Commentaries upon his Commentaries — but mine would be an illegal book.
                    the study fixes my attention sufficiently, when my attention begins to flag, I
                    relieve myself by employing half an hour differently, &amp; then set to
                    again with fresh spirits. I entered at Grays Inn instead of Lincolns Inn for two
                    good reasons. the term is kept by dining once only in the Hall, &amp; the
                    expences at being called to the Bar are very considerably less. the [MS torn]t
                    of these may probably induce [MS torn] to enter there likewise — &amp; I can
                    be your surety — if you want one.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> my mornings are devoted to Law; <del rend="strikethrough">x</del>
                    I allow the evening for pleasanter employments &amp; divide it between the
                    German Grammar &amp; Madoc. with both of which I am getting forwards. I am
                    fond of learning languages. nothing exercises a mans ingenuity more, he sees the
                    progress he makes, &amp; this at once gratifies &amp; encourages. it is
                    my intention to learn Welsh. I shall find it — almost — necessary, to render
                    Madoc as compleat[MS torn] as I intend to. they who understand the language say
                    it is [MS torn] fine one. curious it certainly is from its great &amp;
                    undoubt[MS torn] —quity &amp; <ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">Meirion</ref> in the Monthly Magazine has produced as[MS torn] of its
                    analogy to the Greek &amp; Hebrew. philological inquiries [MS torn] to be
                    ridiculed as they generally are — they may probably on[MS torn] solve many
                    historical problems, &amp; throw a strong &amp; steady light over
                    periods now involved in darkness.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#PugheWilliamOwen">William Owen</ref> is[MS illegible]
                    the man who writes [MS missing] first volume [MS missing]</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love to <ref target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Morgan</ref>
                    &amp; Miss Parker.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a friend
                        of the Southeys from the Bath and Bristol area. Her first name is not
                        recorded.</note> she has seen little &lt;of&gt; London as yet —
                    &amp; likes it not at all. we are as far removed from it as we could with
                    convenience be — but it is a damnable place — &amp; if I had the direction
                    of earthquakes &amp; volcanos — I should [MS missing] </p>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
