<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce81</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.81</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 48&#8211;51; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, p. 204 [in part; undated].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.81" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="81" type="letter">
        <head>81. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-02-02">2 [&#8211;5] February
                        1794</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address:
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/
                        Westminster/ Single<lb /> Stamped: OXFORD<lb />Postmark: [partial] FE<lb />
                        Watermarks: G R in a circle; figure of Britannia<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.
                        1794/ Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8212;<lb />MS: Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 48&#8211;51; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, p. 204 [in part; undated].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="left">
            <address>
              <placeName>Balliol.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1794-02-02">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                            1794 &#8212; Sunday</date>. <time>1/2 past 4.</time>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> At last the date is prefixed. I left <ref target="people.html#CollinsJeremiah">J Collins</ref> this morning soon after
                    nine to write to you. returned to my rooms began some verses &amp; from that
                    hour to this have undergone a perpetual routine of interruptions. <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> wrote to me Monday last to
                    say that circumstances oblige him to reside in Bristol &#8212; much to his advantage,
                    &amp; I believe more than to his inclination. tis unlucky on account of our
                    volume. will you be good enough to convey or cause them to be conveyed to
                        Bell?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bell (1745&#8211;1831; <title level="m">DNB</title>), a London printer and bookseller.</note> I would
                    not ask this if I knew an alternative but if you dislike the job (&amp; I
                    think you will) say so freely. of the plan to be pursued I will say no more now.
                    your answer will let me know if you can convey them to Bell &amp; if that
                    can be done, poems plan &amp; preface shall reach you immediately
                    together.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1794-02-03">Monday morning</date> &#8212; A female scout at Christ Church,
                    only fifteen, has lately delivered herself &amp; strangled the child. what
                    adds to the horror of the circumstance is that her own mother is the only
                    witness. the girl they say is remarkably handsome. I heard this story related at
                    dinner yesterday, &amp; you cannot imagine the effect it had upon me. the
                    situation of the father immediately occurred; for surely one whom the fear of
                    shame carried to such dreadful lengths could not easily have been seduced.
                    nothing is more astonishing to me than that a virtue so rigidly demanded from
                    woman should be so despised among men. Gillies<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Gillies (1747&#8211;1836; <title level="m">DNB</title>).
                        Southey had borrowed the first volume of his <title level="m">History of
                            Ancient Greece</title> (London, 1786) from the Bristol Library Society
                        on 29 January 1793, and here cites I, p. 56.</note> &amp; poor
                        Gibbon<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Gibbon: Edward Gibbon
                        (1737&#8211;1794; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The History of
                            the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title>, 12 vols (London,
                        1788), III, p. 239.</note> have displayed their usual liberality upon this
                    subject in a very few words. here (as almost in every thing else) Europe must
                    shrink from comparison with antient Greece &#8212; &amp; hence as from every thing
                    else ten thousand forcible arguments arise against the present state of things.
                    &#8220;all seems yellow to the jaundiced eye.&#8221;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                        &#8216;An Essay on Criticism&#8217; (1711), line 559.</note> you can apply the line.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1794-02-05">Wednes.</date>
          <time>5 o clock. morning</time>. surely at last I have chosen a quiet hour when
                    there is no fear of interruption from college. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I purpose
                    studying physic. innumerable &amp; insuperable objections appeard to
                    divinity &#8212; surely the profession I have chosen affords at least as many
                    opportunities of benefitting mankind. <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> says no &amp;
                    spoke of the efficacy of prayer. suppose you &amp; I <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> resided in the same
                    village as priest &amp; apothecary. a labouring man with a wife &amp;
                    family is dangerously ill. who renders him the most essential service &#8212; you in
                    talking of heaven &amp; closing his eyes in peace, or I in restoring him to
                    the world &amp; giving him time to prepare for death?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> in this country a liberal education precludes the man of no
                    fortune from independance in the humbler lines of life &#8212; he may either turn man
                    butcher, or embrace one of three professions in all of which there is too much
                    quackery &#8212; Law is of all others the most unpleasant &#8212; the lawyer lives by the
                    vices &amp; follies of his neighbours, blows up the coals of discord,
                    &amp; when the fuel is spent is paid for quenching it. a honest well-minded
                    attorney might be of service to mankind, but he must be independent of his
                    profession in order to be honest &amp; well-minded, &amp; must consider
                    it his duty rather to reconcile enemies than to provoke friends. but before Law
                    can become justice &#8212; a mighty change must be effected in order to simplify it &#8212;
                    the voluminous lumber of tautology must either be burnt or shut up in some
                    sepulchre, a monument of human folly, &amp; the few eternal &amp;
                    immutable laws of justice, with the few that originate from society be collected
                    in one volume that every individual may carry the law of his life in his pocket,
                    &amp; judge for himself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> in all this <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I see nothing very visionary, or indeed anyway impossible.
                    the absurd custom of paying attorneys in proportion to the number of words
                    &amp; lines, has introduced that tautology &amp; barbarism so
                    disgustingly perplexing &#8212; Law as it is disgraces justice &#8212; as it should be
                    &amp; as it may be it becomes simple &amp; useful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> it were easy to point out innumerable objections to divinity, &#8212;
                    but there is one sufficiently obstinate at the threshold. the oaths of this you
                    will form a proper estimate, &amp; tell me whether or no with my principles
                    it were just to enter into orders &#8212; to undertake teaching morality &amp;
                    virtue &amp; begin my pastoral charge by perjury.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> in fact there was no alternative when these ideas had weight. the
                    army I never thought of. to physic I see no objection. the study itself enlarges
                    the mind &amp; the practice affords more opportunities of serving society
                    than any other profession. very soon shall I commence my anatomical &amp;
                    chemical studies. when well grounded in these, I hope to study under
                        Cruikshanks<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Cumberland
                        Cruikshank (1745&#8211;1800; <title level="m">DNB</title>), anatomist.</note> to
                    perfect myself in anatomy &#8212; attend the clinical lectures &amp; then commence
                    &#8212; Doctor Southey!!!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> the only circumstance any ways unpleasant is that I shall be
                    constrained to mix <del rend="strikethrough">more</del> with this world more
                    than is agreable to my wishes &amp; perhaps to my natural disposition,
                    &amp; that I must conform more to its manners. but these imaginary
                    inconveniences are amply balanced by the various agreable circumstances.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> this resolution has relieved me from a weight that hung heavy
                    upon my mind &amp; embittered many hours. I am inclined to think morality
                    &amp; active virtue will do &#8212; nor were it difficult to prove this &#8212; but the
                    human mind is as yet incapable of the pure speculations of philosophical
                    justice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> now then for <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref>. I have changed my rooms very much for the better. do you
                    recollect a door in the grove which opened to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Giles? near
                    the temple of A? my rooms are nearer the new buildings &amp; the study
                    window looks to C&#230;sar.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A building in the
                        grounds of Balliol College, Oxford.</note> the fellows seem resolved to
                    benefit my situation as they are planting a shrubbery in the grove &#8212; so when you
                    visit us at the Commemoration you will find me much more agreably situated. you
                    must have heard of <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">C Collins</ref>
                    famous rooms, of which he talked so much. in his best room they have lowerd half
                    the cieling above a foot much to the injury of its appearance. tis astonishing
                    what enemies he makes by that overbearing manner in conversation &amp; front
                    of adamant. common observers will not look deep enough to discover his virtues
                    &amp; he takes care to display all his faults. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> says he wishes rather to
                    astonish than to please. in proportion as <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> good opinion is valuable his
                    censure is to be feared; nor would he wish so earnestly to reclaim <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> did he not regard him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CollinsJeremiah">Jer. Collins</ref> is with us good
                    humoured as usual &amp; tho laid up with a sore heel, his wit by no means
                    halts. punning is certainly infectious &amp; I am inclined to think that the
                    very air of Oxford gives the disorder for when he &amp; I (we travelled
                    together from Bath) got within ten miles of the place puns began to drop, faster
                    &amp; faster till we arrived at my rooms &amp; found <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> bread cheese &amp; a
                    bottle. but <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref> has met with
                    an irreparable injury &#8212; it has lost the fiddle with one string so oft responsive
                    to the gentle touch of harmony. in its place <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> has a piano forte,to which
                    I sing discordant. the Pot has not attained that ripe rank perfection of
                    impurity which Summer gave it, &amp; the weather is yet too cold for <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> to sit &amp; stew
                    over its vapours.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Tom Lamb</ref> is at Christ Church.
                        <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">his Majesty</ref> well &amp; young
                        <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> sports Claret. next
                    Friday however he drinks port with me &amp; much do I wish that you could
                    join our party. <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#PeckwellRobertHenry">Peckwell</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">C Collins</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combe</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lamb</ref>. <ref target="people.html#CampbellHenry">Horse Campbell</ref> sleeps every night
                    with a stinking dog which <ref target="people.html#PeggeChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pegg</ref> gave him &amp; which report says he
                    feeds at the anatomy school. the Doctors room may be smelt at Woodstock whiffing
                    the accumulated stinks of &lt;the&gt; dead bodies the Dog &amp; the
                    Doctor himself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> of myself one piece of news &#8212; my beard was black I borrowed <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoots</ref> razor with which I
                    scraped &amp; scraped without effect &amp; was at last obliged to finish
                    with the scissors! ten pages of Demosthenes<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek orator Demosthenes (384&#8211;322 BC).</note> must I read
                    for lecture to day, so thank me for this letter &amp; expect a better at
                    leisure. remember me to all enquiring friends &amp; particularly to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harry</ref>. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; I conversed about
                    him. he is the most wonderful child I ever saw, said <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> will <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>
                    come to <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref>? at Ch Ch they
                    come to me to know. I wish him here much for both our sakes. tell him I have
                    begun a letter, which I will finish as soon as possible. now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> write as soon
                    as you can &amp; tell me if you can get the papers conveyed to Bell. then I
                    write to <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">Lovell</ref> &#8212; &amp; then &#8212;
                    make my appearance as Orson.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In medieval
                        romance, &#8216;Orson&#8217; was the brother of &#8216;Valentine&#8217;. A version of this legend
                        appeared in Thomas Percy (1729&#8211;1811; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</title>, 2nd edn, 3 vols
                        (London, 1767), III, pp. 279&#8211;295. In 1794, Southey and Robert Lovell were
                        planning to publish a joint volume of poems under these pseudonyms. The
                        collection never appeared.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made a valuable friend at Corpus. his name <ref target="people.html#HorsemanJohn">Horseman</ref>. <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">C Collins</ref> knows him.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>