<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce88</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.88</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="88" type="letter">
        <head>88. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-04-26">26 [&#8211;c. 29] April
                        1794</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single<lb />
                        Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: AP/ 29/ 94<lb />Watermarks: G R in a circle;
                        figure of Britannia<lb />Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Ap<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 28. 1794; Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. May 1<lb />MS:
                        Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">Bristol.<date when="1794-04-26"> Apr. 26.
                        1794.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I have cut my
                    finger in mending this blackguard pen.</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> how this exordium may amuse you I know not but I hope I shall
                    never make another like it. I have to abuse you for sending your last to Oxford
                    when you received mine dated from hence, &amp; likewise to apologize for no
                    answering sooner. variety of engagements I cannot plead but must alledge
                    particular ones.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> you say her husbands name will please me. in sober sadness no.
                    Integer laude &#8212; fuge suspicari.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                        adaptation of Horace (65&#8211;8 BC), <title level="m">Odes</title>, Book 1, no.
                        22, line 1 and Book 2, no. 4, line 22. The Latin translates as &#8216;you&#8217;re free
                        from praise &#8212; don&#8217;t be suspicious&#8217;.</note> to quote your own quotation.
                    perhaps no being has less suspicion of evil than myself. &#8212;. a hand even as soft
                    as you hyperbolize your gypseys to be, would have little effect<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> upon one armed either with Philosophy or with
                    Love. I forget the old sage whom Lais could not tempt, but I believe the
                        story.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Lais of Hyccara (d. c. 340 BC)
                        was a famous courtesan in ancient Greece. The philosopher who resisted her
                        was Xenocrates (396&#8211;314 BC).</note> your enthusiasm <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> is equal to
                    mine &#8212; like me you grasp at the gay visions of Fancy with avidity, &amp;
                    were I to turn prophet of evils &amp; presage that we should both meet
                    disappointment, I fear the presage would be versified. take however my good
                    wishes with you &amp; believe me twill give me much pleasure to hear you
                    have found your gipsey. but how recognize her when she did not unmask? how be
                    recognized yourself when bepowderd &amp; bebeaued? I have seldom been more
                    pleased with any of your letters than this last; &amp; give you credit for
                    all because I feel the nature of all your have said. <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref>, who wants only a tub
                    to Deserve the name of Diogenes<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek
                        philosopher Diogenes (c. 400&#8211;325 BC), founder of Cynicism. He allegedly
                        lived in a tub. Southey used the pseudonym &#8216;Diogenes&#8217; in a letter published
                        in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 2 (December 1796), see
                        Letter 177.</note> rails much against masquerades. twas one of those topics
                    on which we usd to battle when our opinions deviated but slightly from each
                    other. I allowed in some degree this impropriety of them in general but at the
                    same time professd my intention of visiting the motley groupe. visit one I will
                    possibly without feeling &lt;your&gt; animation or meeting like you with
                    so enchanting a Sybil. your standard of happines reminds me of another subject.
                    when shall we essay our essays again? where shall we do it? how shall we do it?
                    I have much conversation with <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> upon the subject &amp; of course you always make part. the
                    periodical mode pleases me more than a volume at once. do my dear S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter the
                        Hermit (d. 1115), religious fanatic, instrumental in preaching the First
                        Crusade. The pseudonyms &#8216;St Peter&#8217;, &#8216;Peter&#8217; and &#8216;P.H.&#8217; were used by
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford in the schoolboy magazine <title level="j">The
                            Flagellant</title>.</note> think of this subject &#8212; call up the memory of
                    times that are gone &amp; believe that the spirit of Gualbertus<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Gualbert (c. 995&#8211;1073), founder of the
                        Vallombrosian order. The pseudonym &#8216;Gualbertus&#8217; was used by Southey in the
                        schoolboy magazine, <title level="j">The Flagellant</title>.</note> will
                    rise &lt;like&gt; the phenix from his ashes. I have subjects upon
                    subjects ready. how like you the Knight Errant for the title. tis certainly new
                    &amp; novelty is something in the scale of popular opinion when it does not
                    too boldly attack the prejudices of age. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have of course seen <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. I was much with him last term &amp; witnessd some actions
                    which would have raised him in my esteem had that been possible. an old Welshman
                    who had formerly kept a school &amp; lived in affluence &amp; whose
                    productions shewed that he possessd ability &amp; knowledge above
                    mediocrity, was travelling homewards with his wife. at Oxford she was taken ill
                    &amp; they were both old friendless &amp; penniless. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> supported them there. paid the
                    apothecary to attend M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Denham<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The wife of the &#8216;old Welshman&#8217; mentioned earlier in the
                        paragraph. The Denhams first names are unknown.</note> &amp; supplied
                    them with money to carry them comfortably home. the manner in which he did it
                    almost equalld the act. &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> would never have mentioned the circumstances even to me had I
                    not accidentally witnessed great part. the inequality of property would seem
                    like a blessing did Fortune always shower her favours on such as our friend. I
                    know not his direction or would write to him. he has promised to examine a Will
                    for me at Doctors Commons. should you see him tell him tis of John Canon
                        Southey<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Distant cousin of Southey&#8217;s,
                        he was the son of John Southey and the heiress Mary Cannon. Southey&#8217;s
                        long-held hopes of inheriting a substantial sum from the estate were in
                        vain.</note> who died in 1768. the contents of that Testament may possibly
                    decide the tenor of my future life. I expect it however without very much
                    anxiety. if it be in my power to sell the reversion for any comfortable
                    &amp; immediate independance, in all probability I shall do it. I do not
                    wish for affluence. Man wants but little here below &amp;c. my wishes are
                    bounded &amp; tho they partake a little of romance &lt;they&gt; are
                    certainly practicable. the study of physic pleases me much &amp; what little
                    knowledge I can gain in that line will certainly be my object to pursue. but the
                    length of time required in the study &amp; the additional expences are such
                    that I fear it will be impossible to pursue <del rend="strikethrough">them</del>
                    it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wish <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> you would visit Oxford very soon &amp; meet <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> there. we have determined
                    upon publishing Valentine &amp; Orson at Oxford &amp; he will be with me
                    a week shortly. can you not come then and at the commemoration? remember you
                    have promised me an annual visit &amp; recollect that I should like a
                    monthly weekly &amp; daily one better. or rather one visit to last all the
                    year round. am I ever to see <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> there? if it be but out of compassion to me send him to <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref>. for <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref> is gone! &amp; <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> soon goes &#8212; then will
                    I hang my harp on the wash hand basons stand &amp; sit down by the waters of
                    the pot of abomination. poor <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref>! he is now with <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref> in Worcestershire but <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> lost his place tho he
                    got up at four o clock &amp; put on his <hi rend="ital">new</hi> leather
                    breeches &amp; boots. &amp; then <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> went to bed again in
                    his <hi rend="ital">new</hi> leather breeches &amp; boots. &amp;
                    surprized <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnet</ref> &amp; me at
                    breakfast by his unexpected appearance. oh had you but seen <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> in the affair of the
                    Imposition when he had 42 pages of Ralph Churton<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Ralph Churton (1754&#8211;1831; <title level="m">DNB</title>), a
                        Church of England clergyman and philosophical writer.</note> to Latinize
                    &amp; all this because the Grace was omitted!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you seen the Children in the Wood<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Morton (c. 1764&#8211;1838; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                            <title level="m">Children in the Wood</title> (1793), a two-act musical
                        entertainment.</note> yet? I never recollect being more delighted at a
                    theatre than at the representation of this simple piece. Nature is all in all.
                    however the Aristotelian Critics {Luthers<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Luther (1483&#8211;1546), religious reformer.</note> opinion
                    of Aristotle in a parenthesis. Certam est, Aristotelem <hi rend="ital">mortuum</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">damnatum</hi> esse doctorum hodie
                    omnium universitatum magis quam Christum!!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;it is certain that of learned men in
                        all today&#8217;s universities, Aristotle is more dead and damned than Christ&#8217;.
                        Southey is paraphrasing Luther&#8217;s answer to Ambrosius Catharinus, a
                        translation of which was included in William Dell (d. 1669; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Tryal of Spirits Both in Teachers
                            &amp; Hearers Wherein is Held Forth the Clear Discovery and Certain
                            Downfal of the Carnal and Antichristian Clergie of These Nations
                            Testified From the Word of God to the University-Congregation in
                            Cambridge</title> (London, 1660), pp. 141&#8211;152.</note> to elucidate this
                    or rather to say how I came by this erudition i must lengthen my parenthesis.
                    Saturday last the day I began this letter I was at Downing at old <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">Robert Lovells</ref>. the most primitive
                    of Quakers but withall an affable intelligent pleasant man. he was pleasd with
                    me &amp; in a manner which interested me very much, offerd to lend me a good
                    book written by William Dell.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Dell, educational reformer and Puritan minister, who regarded himself as the
                        spiritual heir of the early reformers John Huss (1369&#8211;1415), Jerome of
                        Prague (1379&#8211;1416) and Martin Luther. Dell&#8217;s <title level="m">The Doctrine of Baptisms</title> (1652) was especially popular with
                        Quakers.</note> the offer was so made that if I could I would not have
                    refused him. &amp; in fact I am reading a large octavo full of mysticism.
                    tis but a few hours stole from rhyming &#8212; it gives him pleasure &amp; I shall
                    get a little knowledge of John Huss Jerome of Prague &amp; Martin Luther.
                    Nullus est alius antichristus in mundo, neque venturus quam sacerdotes.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;There is no
                        other Antichrist in the world, nor will there be, than priests&#8217;.</note> Jo.
                    Huss. you may see the tenor of the book from these quotations in it) however the
                    followers of Aristotle (who certainly is dead &amp; as Luther says damned if
                    the imprecations of those he has puzzled take effect) may ridicule the idea of
                    tragicomedy I am myself partial to that stile of writing. look at Hamlet. who
                    would feel half the pleasure at seeing it represented if it were all upon the
                    stills of tragedy. excuse one bit of democracy. Kings &amp; Queens not only
                    engross the world but almost the stage too. yet domestic distress goes nearer
                    the heart. empire overthrown &amp; monarchs dethroned excite astonishment &#8212;
                    but the wife weeping over the crimes or the misfortunes of her husband &amp;
                    alive to every transport &amp; feeling of maternal heart, rouses all the
                    finer feelings of the heart.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have ventured upon the drama at last. &amp; chosen for my
                    subject that memorable passage in Tacitus which struck me so powerfully on the
                    first perusal &amp; which I pointed out to you at Brixton. possibly you may
                    have forgotten it. if so turn to the fourteenth annal &amp; read the murder
                    of Pedanius Secundus &amp; the execution of four hundred slaves.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Tacitus (AD 55&#8211;117), <title level="m">Annals</title>, Book 14, chapters 42&#8211;45. Secundus was City Prefect of
                        Rome during the reign of Nero. In AD 61, he was murdered by one of his
                        slaves and, in accordance with Roman law, all 400 of his house slaves were
                        executed. If Southey did write a drama on this subject, it has not
                        survived.</note> tis a bloody tale. with what success I manage it you will
                    judge hereafter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> remember me to <ref target="people.html#Deaconfamily">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Deacon</ref>. I
                    thought I saw M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> D in Bristol but was mistaken. how is <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your fathers</ref> gout? </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> the ligament which suspends my liver is undergoing an unpleasant
                    extension owing to the vacuity of my intestines. the gastric juice is devouring
                    my stomach for want of other food. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I am ravenous.
                    but dinner is not yet ready &amp; I have about time to give you some rhyme
                    in the fag end of the sheet. I shall soon write to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">yrs sincerely</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent5">To a College Cat<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                            revised version was published in the <title level="j">Annual
                                Anthology</title> (1799).</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent3"> &#8212;&#8212; (how <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> would like the subject</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Friend &amp; companion of my lonely room,</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> (For why should Truth the name deservd refuse?)</l>
            <l rend="indent2">To thee the associate of collegiate gloom</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Her tuneful tribute hymns the grateful Muse.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">And thou hast much about thee worthy praise.</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Thy well streakd fur of many a varying hue,</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Thy emerald eyes long light retaining rays</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Thy legs so powerful &amp; so slender too.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Thy tail with intermingled stripes bedight,</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Oft stretchd in threatning playfulness thy claws,</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Thy death-denouncing fangs so sharp so white</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> And this soft murmur that bespeaks applause</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Nor does thy Beauty only serve to please</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> The vagrant glance that leaves no trace behind.</l>
            <l rend="indent2">For much of moral drawn from scenes like these</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Fill &amp; improves the philosophic mind.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">For what thou fairest of the tabby race</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Has saved thee from the ill that race pursues</l>
            <l rend="indent2">What but thy finishd form of strength &amp; grace</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> What but all powerful Beautys pleasing hues?</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">For tho the Sage in musing moral hour</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> May scorn bewitching Beautys chain to wear,</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Tho much he talks how fading Youths gay flower</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> How frail how empty all that Man thinks fair</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Yet when the soft enchantress languid eye</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Beams on his sight &amp; thrills thro all his
                            frame</l>
            <l rend="indent2">How soon he find each serious maxim fly</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> And cynic Reason but an empty name.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Tho lives its Beauty but a little hour</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Tho Time shall steal the fading charm away,</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Yet is the short lived spell of mighty power</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Yet when we see the charm, we must obey.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">For even in thee Grimalkin Beautys spell</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Commands protection &amp; applause from all &#8212;</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Gives thee on this forbidden ground to dwell</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Range round the kitchen &amp; parade the hall.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Even the stern fellow little usd to know</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> How mighty is the power of Beautys spell</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Knows not in wrath to bid Grimalkin go</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> But breaks the statutes &#8212; for he loves thee well.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">And hence it is that thus domestic grown</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Thou comest familiar at the friendly call,</l>
            <l rend="indent2">And hence it is that every fear unknown</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> From none you fly &#8212; but sport &amp; play with
                            all.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Stern tho thy nature savage tho thy kind</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Insidious bloody resolute &amp; wild,</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Thee far remote from cruelty we find</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Familiar gentle playful meek &amp; mild.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">And hence the moralizing mind may learn</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> How pleasing yet how strong affections band &#8212;</l>
            <l rend="indent2">And hence the philosophic eye discern</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Mightier than strength affections gentle hand.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">That gentle hand of power enough to draw</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> The large-limbd elephant by one small hair</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Might well supply Oppressions tyrant law</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Redress Affliction &amp; prevent Despair.</l>
          </lg>
          <lb />
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent2">Hadst thou been kickd &amp; beat wheneer in sight</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> If dogs when worrying thee had found applause</l>
            <l rend="indent2">Would it be strange if thou hadst learnt to bite</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> Would it be strange if thou hadst not thy claws?</l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="indent5"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
          <p rend="indent11"> Orson.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> when <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> told <ref target="people.html#HoweThomas">Thomas
                            Howe</ref>
            <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> that Powell courted Miss Hornsby,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> Thomas replied
                        &#8220;Ah Sir they will say so when Men do visit houses where such things be.&#8221;</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>