<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce211</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.211</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bristol Reference Library,
						B20871.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London
						and New York, 1965), I, pp. 123&#8211;124.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.211" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="211" type="letter">
        <head>211. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">John Prior Estlin</ref>, <date when="1797-04-09">9 April 1797</date>
          </head><p>Address: For/ The Reverend J P Estlin/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Michaels Hill/
						Bristol<lb />Stamped: BRIDGE S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>/ Westminster<lb />Postmark: DAP/ 10/ 97<lb />MS: Bristol Reference Library,
						B20871<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London
						and New York, 1965), I, pp. 123&#8211;124.</p>
        <epigraph>
          <table cols="2" rows="2" width="740" border="0" align="left">
            <row>
              <cell width="330">
                <date when="1797-04-09">Sunday April 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>&#8212; 1797</date>.</cell>
              <cell width="410">
                <address>
                  <placeName>{ 
									<ref target="places.html#ProspectPlaceLondon">Prospect Place. Newington Butts</ref>
                  </placeName>
                </address>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell width="330" />
              <cell width="410">
                <address>
                  <placeName>{ No 20.</placeName>
                </address>
              </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </epigraph>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2"> I take the earliest opportunity of thanking you for your work,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Prior
						Estlin, <title>The Nature and Causes of Atheism, Pointed out in a Discourse, Delivered at the Chapel in Lewin&#8217;s-Mead, Bristol.
							To Which are Added, Remarks on a Work, Entitled Origine de Tous Les Cultes, ou Religion Universelle. Par Dupuis, Citoyen
							Fran&#231;ois</title> (1797).</note> which was delivered to me yesterday at Johnson&#8217;s.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Johnson (1738&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>), publisher and bookseller. His shop was at 72 St Paul&#8217;s Churchyard,
						London.</note> I have read it with much pleasure &amp; much attention. it is a subject often present to my mind, for I see
						<del rend="strikethrough">xxxx of</del> &lt;many&gt; Atheists &amp; Sceptics, &amp; as I never decline
					controversy, seldom see<del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> them without an argument. your discourse does not touch upon what
					appears to me the principal cause of Atheism, the existence of physical &amp; moral evil, &amp; the difficulty of
					reconciling its existence with that of a God powerful &amp; benevolent. The system of Optimism, to which I assent &amp;
					which I therefore profess, is not without difficulties, great &amp; many. but every other system appears to me to have more
					&amp; greater, &amp; therefore I assent to this; to have used the word <hi rend="ital">believe</hi> would have been
					perhaps expressing myself too strongly. Many of my friends &amp; acquaintance believe these difficulties insuperable; I find
					them atheists or sceptics not because they are vain &amp; conceited, not because the texture of their minds is coarse, but
					because there is evil in the world. the contemplation of the misery of others, or the endurance of their own, without giving <hi rend="ital">an unnatural asperity</hi> to their characters induces them to doubt or to disbelieve the existence of that Being,
					who if he exists must be benevolent &amp; powerful, &amp; whose power could execute what his benevolence must prompt. this
					I believe to be the principal cause of Atheism. To answer these arguments so as effectually to overthrow them is beyond my power,
					such is the tyranny of the present over the future; &amp; when I would direct the attention from individuals to the whole, I
					am told that an individual is every thing to himself. my mind is not adapted for methodical reasoning, &amp; like Rousseau the
					answer to a question always recurs to me too late.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The eternal series is the common basis of Atheism. I always attempt to prove the necessity of an intelligent first
					cause, &amp; deduce his attributes from his existence. this fort I find impregnable. the arguments from the evil in the world
					then become weaker when the present is merged in futurity. but the existence of a future state depends upon the benevolence of God
					&amp; those arguments attack that basis.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your work will not in all probability be read by those who are decidedly Atheistical. they are in general
					self-satisfied, &amp; no man likes to have his settled opinions shaken. but it will fall into the hands of many whose
					scepticism inclines that way, &amp; there I think &amp; hope it will be useful. I will not wish you to examine the
					arguments upon the origin of evil in a second edition, because the subject deserves a seperate discussion, &amp; I should
					gladly see another work from <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Estlin</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your observations upon Dupuis<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Frances Dupuis (1742&#8211;1809), French
						mathematician, astronomer, revolutionary and author of <hi rend="ital">Origine de Tous Les Cultes, ou Religion
						Universelle</hi> (1795).</note> may do great good by showing the astonishing credulity of an Atheist. have you not perhaps
					praised Watsons book<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Watson, Bishop of Llandaff (1737&#8211;1816; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">An Apology for Christianity in a Series of Letters Addressed to Edward Gibbon Esq., Author of
							The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776). Watson was also the author of an <title level="m">Apology for the
							Bible, in a Series of Letters, Addressed to Tom Paine</title> (1796).</note> too highly? the ablest man of my acquaintance
					rose from its perusal with the full conviction that Watson was himself a disbeliever.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Christian world will probably ere long be divided into two classes &#8212; the Roman Catholics, &amp; the
					Socinians or Low Arians &#8212; those who allow every thing &#8212; or nothing to authority. I have heard from one who lives much with the
					more able Catholics that they despise the reformed sects heartily &#8212; but are very much afraid of the Socinians. this is a curious
					fact.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will I hope excuse the liberty I have taken. gratified &amp; instructed by both your publications, forgive
					me if I suggest a subject that deserves a third.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> our remembrances to <ref target="people.html#EstlinMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Estlin</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent8"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>