<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce60</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.60</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        22.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="60" type="letter">
<head>60. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1793-10-14">14 [–18] October
                        1793</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/
                        James Deacon Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Long Room/ Custom House/
                        London<lb/>Postmark: AOC/ 19/ 93<lb/>Watermarks: Portal &amp; Co; crown
                        with shield<lb/>Endorsements: Recd Oct. 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1793;
                            Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: Oct. 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. &amp; 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        22<lb/>Unpublished.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="left">
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton Causeway</ref>.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1793-10-14">Oct. 14. Monday morning 1793</date>. day before my
                        departure</dateline>
<salute>My dear Grosvenor.</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> as I do not know when I may again find so excellent an
                    opportunity of beginning — I seize old Time by the forelock &amp; there will
                    I hold him till I want him. so no more at present from your sincere friend.
                    where my letter is destined to be finished I know not but the continuation comes
                    from Reading where I am writing in a small room with a good fire &amp; two
                    London Riders dissertating upon robberies &amp; the most likely places for
                    such adventures. as one of them is at the same table I cannot versify as I
                    intended &amp; had begun so plain prose must tell how I got this far. the
                        <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Doctor</ref> left me at
                    Brentford I proceeded on sad &amp; solitary to Hounslow &amp; there gave
                    one shilling for Sir Launcelot Greaves<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Tobias Smollett (1721–1771; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Adventures of Sir Lancelot Greaves</title> (1762).</note> to amuse
                    me on the road. at Cranford Bridge — thirteen miles from Hyde Park corner I took
                    a dinner. but I found the day growing late &amp; myself unwilling to be
                    fatigued against tomorrow so I first mounted the Maidenhead Stage &amp; then
                    the Reading. as evening approachd got in the last &amp; here I am at a most
                    execrable Inn in not the most agreable of humours.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I know nothing so unpleasant as leaving the friends we love
                    &amp; — yet such is the state of society that life is hardly any thing than
                    continual parting. you are an exception — but observe the general tenour of life
                    — school &amp; college occupy what ought to be &lt;the&gt; happiest
                    ages — then comes business &amp; perhaps the opportunity of happiness when
                    the relish is gone. Universities might certainly be made useful institutions but
                    at present they are pernicious to individuals &amp; to the nation at large.
                    the morality of Oxford you know how to estimate but with respect to the
                    polishing which I know I want but fear I shall never attain — is it to be found
                    there? steel receives its last polish from a womans hand I believe — &amp;
                    my rugged ore requires the same management — this I shall never meet with. three
                    years must be spent in studies which lead to nothing — &amp; the remainder
                    of my life in forming theories of happiness which I never can practise<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>. <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund
                        Seward</ref> says very truly that &lt;a&gt; man who indulges himself
                    in literature merely for self amusement deserves no more respect from the public
                    than the glutton or the voluptuary. this is very true but selfishness is deeply
                    implanted in the human heart so deeply that even the strong hand of Philosophy
                    cannot root it up. you &amp; I may indulge ourselves in theories of
                    reforming the taste &amp; morals of a corrupt age &amp; perhaps our
                    theories are not wholly visionary — but is our disinterestedness such as might
                    prompt us to this against our inclination?</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Removd my dear <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> from each
                        friend away</l>
<l rend="indent3"> In mood most unpleasing I write</l>
<l rend="indent2">Reflection assumes her relentless stern sway</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And my bosom is dark as the night.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">When I see the dull shadows arising around</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And the mists mantling over the plain</l>
<l rend="indent2">When I hear the keen night blasts so dismal resound</l>
<l rend="indent3"> My breast seems to seek to complain.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">As I traversd along busy Fancy’s keen eye</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Cast to <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref> the
                        glance of adieu</l>
<l rend="indent2">And I heavd as I wanderd the sorrowful sigh</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And I wisht myself present with you.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">As the clock pronounced four still at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref> my eye</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Saw you look at the unemployd chair</l>
<l rend="indent2">And I sighd as I fancied that you heavd the sigh</l>
<l rend="indent3"> When you saw that RS was not there.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">As the morning arose &amp; the red orb of day</l>
<l rend="indent3"> In full splendour illumind around</l>
<l rend="indent2">I felt my breast warmd by the all chearing ray</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And my bosom with gratitude bound</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">More chearful &amp; sprightly I travelld along</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And inhald the fresh breeze with delight</l>
<l rend="indent2">And beguild the long way with that excellent song<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The popular song ‘The Farthing
                            Rush-Light’.</note>
</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Of Sir Solomon puffing the light.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">So charming I sung &amp; so clear the notes flow</l>
<l rend="indent3"> That each envious bird fled away</l>
<l rend="indent2">I scared every magpye &amp; frightned each crow</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And the ravens fled out of my way</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Then Death &amp; the Lady<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A popular ballad.</note> a ditty so sad</l>
<l rend="indent3"> I sung loud &amp; charming &amp; shrill</l>
<l rend="indent2">And then warbled wildly young Harrys the lad</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And moreover the maid of the mill<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of the popular song ‘The Maid of the
                            Mill’.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">But at last Orpheus<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In
                            Greek mythology, a hero particularly associated with poetry and
                            music.</note> like in poetical rage</l>
<l rend="indent3"> I was forced to be silent for fear</l>
<l rend="indent2">For the horses enchanted that drew the Bath stage</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Had overthrown it indeed very near</l>
<l rend="indent2">Then pitying the coachman no longer I sung</l>
<l rend="indent2">But trudgd merrily on &amp; held still my sweet
                            tongue.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">In mood ... tongue: Verse
                            written at a right angle to the main part of the letter across the bottom part of fol. 1 r.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent1"> I soon found the two Riders were Democrats when they began upon
                    politics, so up went your letter &amp; I joined in the discourse. eat a
                    boild rabbit with the one who remaind &amp; got to bed. next morning
                    sketched the gate house of the abbey (which you shall have as soon as I reach
                    Bristol) put a biscuit in my pocket &amp; trudged on. after eighteen miles
                    walking without rest or other food than my biscuit I reachd Dunnington Castle —
                    more fatiguing pilgrimages have certainly been performd by greater fools but
                    none with more devotion. I had the idea of Chaucer<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Geoffrey Chaucer (<hi rend="ital">c</hi>. 1340–1400; <title level="m">DNB</title>), poet and administrator. Dunnington Castle, near
                        Newbury, was reputed to have once belonged to the Chaucer family.</note>
                    &amp; you were in great danger of a rhapsody. had the merry old Bard resided
                    there now I should certainly have claimed acquaintance &amp; drank some of
                    his old October — but the castle is desolate &amp; I must proceed to Newbury
                    to dinner. I just reachd it as the last coach past thro. mounted the box — made
                    a good dinner &amp; reachd Bath a little before ten last night,
                    Wednesday.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> on Saturday morning I purpose proceeding to Bristol. Oxford I do
                    not visit. you will direct to me as usual &amp; the sooner you write the
                    better. I have some good odes in embryo to fill up this letter — in the interim
                    you shall have the remarks that occurrd upon reading Sir Launcelot Greaves on
                    the road. broad coarse humour seems to be the chief excellence of Smollet
                    incidents almost too gross to please &amp; too strange to be probable happen
                    at every inn his heroes stop at &amp; we are sure to find the sailors
                    dialect &amp; the clowns broad Scotch or broad Yorkshire in the place of
                    humour. when he gets upon those subjects which perhaps none but Rousseau knew
                    how to treat he rhapsodizes about charms angels &amp; Hymens &amp;
                    thinks passion &amp; nonsense mean the same. some strange discovery of birth
                    comes in at the end &amp; all the dramatis personæ are tacked together at
                    the altar. yet with all these faults you are not soon tired of Smollets novels.
                    they insensibly lead you on &amp; if they do not come near the heart
                    certainly play round the head. Humphrey Clinker<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Tobias Smollett, <title level="m">The Expedition of Humphry
                            Clinker</title> (1771).</note> strikes me as his best — the characters
                    are less outrè &amp; of course more natural. perhaps the epistolary form of
                    it kept him in some bounds.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I copied these four lines from the hospital at Reading</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">{Aye whose hours exempt from sorrow flow</l>
<l rend="indent3">{Behold the seat of Pain of Want &amp; Woe</l>
<l rend="indent3">{Think whilst your hands the intreated alms extend</l>
<l rend="indent3">{That what to us ye give to God ye lend.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<p rend="indent4"> To the ME at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref>
</p>
<p rend="indent5"> ———</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">O thou Myself who now</l>
<l rend="indent4"> At <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref> rear’st
                        aloft my pretty head</l>
<l rend="indent3">Perchance sad emblem what once may be</l>
<l rend="indent4"> When I am dead</l>
<l rend="indent3">O thou the other Me</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Thou with white face &amp; Paris plaister brains</l>
<l rend="indent3">Attend to this ME’s salutary strains.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">Whilome or else Tradition is a liar</l>
<l rend="indent4"> That celebrated friar</l>
<l rend="indent3">So far renownd by name Friar Bacon<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">According to legend, the philosopher Roger Bacon (<hi rend="ital">c</hi>. 1214–1292?; <title level="m">DNB</title>)
                            created a talking brazen head which could answer any question. Southey
                            later incorporated this myth into <title level="m">Thalaba the
                                Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 10, lines 281–284n.</note>
</l>
<l rend="indent4"> All heads to surpass</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Of burnishd brass</l>
<l rend="indent3">With necromancing art resolvd to make one.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">So wisely judging that a brazen face</l>
<l rend="indent3">Is of much use amongst this mortal race</l>
<l rend="indent3">And passes for good sense with many an ass</l>
<l rend="indent3">He actually made this head of brass</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Which could hold conversation</l>
<l rend="indent4"> And give information</l>
<l rend="indent3">Talk Latin &amp; Hebrew &amp; English &amp;
                        Greek</l>
<l rend="indent3">Solve a problem in Euclid<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Euclid of Alexandria (dates uncertain, between 325 and
                            250 BC), mathematician.</note>
</l>
<l rend="indent3">Better (<ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>) than ever you did</l>
<l rend="indent3">And teach dumb people to speak.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">But oh thou bodiless ME I do not ask</l>
<l rend="indent3">The fates to undertake so hard a task</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Thro the dark night</l>
<l rend="indent4"> I would not have thee speak</l>
<l rend="indent4"> To <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> in Persic or <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> in
                        Greek</l>
<l rend="indent3">For that would make them tremble with affright.</l>
<l rend="indent3">So much so that before they could recover</l>
<l rend="indent3">And answer as they ought, the sheets might suffer.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">No gentle ME — I ask for no such thing</l>
<l rend="indent4"> But if it please</l>
<l rend="indent4"> The fates to hear such meek requests as these</l>
<l rend="indent3">(And my soft tongue</l>
<l rend="indent3">To please the sisters stern</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Should many a ditty turn</l>
<l rend="indent3">More sweet than ever Orpheus sung)</l>
<l rend="indent2">I would desire that thou mightst learn to sing</l>
<l rend="indent3">As well as well can be</l>
<l rend="indent3">Just like this Me.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg>
<l rend="indent4"> And head of Me</l>
<l rend="indent4"> If it be agreable to thee</l>
<l rend="indent3">To move the soul to laughter —</l>
<l rend="indent4"> I would have thee able</l>
<l rend="indent4"> To sing little Label<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The song ‘A Duet’, from Prince Hoare (1755–1833; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Prize</title> (1793).</note>
</l>
<l rend="indent3">And the farthing rushlight<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The song ‘The Farthing Rush-Light’.</note> after</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">And if thy — (soul I was just going to say</l>
<l rend="indent3">Tho I don’t know where thy soul could stay)</l>
<l rend="indent3">And if thy brains would move</l>
<l rend="indent3">The softening soul to love</l>
<l rend="indent2">Then I would have thee sing like me that song</l>
<l rend="indent2">Whither my Love ah whither art thou gone.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The song ‘Whither, My Love’.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">And at the dismal hour of night</l>
<l rend="indent4"> If thou wouldst then require</l>
<l rend="indent3">To wake the soul to wild affright —</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Do just as I desire.</l>
<l rend="indent2">Sing how uncivil Death approachd the Lady<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The popular ballad ‘Death and the
                            Lady’.</note>
</l>
<l rend="indent4"> And how that Uncle good</l>
<l rend="indent3">Left the poor children in the wood</l>
<l rend="indent2">And Robin Redbreast buried each poor baby.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The popular ballad ‘The Children in the
                            Wood’, included in Thomas Percy (1729–1811; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Reliques of Ancient English
                                Poetry</title>, 2nd edn, 3 vols (London, 1767), II, pp.
                            211–217.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">But Head of me — with all thy tricks</l>
<l rend="indent2">For thy own sake never talk politics</l>
<l rend="indent3">For in these times of war</l>
<l rend="indent3">(Thought horribell)</l>
<l rend="indent3">Who can tell</l>
<l rend="indent2">But you may be stuck upon Temple Bar?<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">A gateway into the City of London, on which the heads of
                            traitors were mounted on pikes.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">There shalt thou melt whilst dogs each drop lick</l>
<l rend="indent2">For all the world like a bundle of rags upon a mop stick</l>
<l rend="indent3">And if the fates decree</l>
<l rend="indent3">This end for me</l>
<l rend="indent2">As I have now got time</l>
<l rend="indent3">My epitaph Ill pen</l>
<l rend="indent3">To serve me then —</l>
<l rend="indent2">And thus I build the lofty rhyme.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">Here washd by rains</l>
<l rend="indent3">Are those strange brains</l>
<l rend="indent2">Which filld a stranger head —</l>
<l rend="indent3">In death now still</l>
<l rend="indent3">And damp &amp; chill</l>
<l rend="indent2">Each limb unnervd lies dead</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">His legs so long</l>
<l rend="indent3">Shall stalk along</l>
<l rend="indent2">So many a mile no more</l>
<l rend="indent3">His tongue lie still</l>
<l rend="indent3">That went like a mill</l>
<l rend="indent2">And always ran Reason before.</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3">Here must he stay</l>
<l rend="indent3">One lump of clay</l>
<l rend="indent2">The loathly flesh worms meal</l>
<l rend="indent3">And now at rest</l>
<l rend="indent3">His cold cold breast</l>
<l rend="indent2">Nor joy nor woe shall feel. <note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">O thou ... feel: Verse written at a right angle to the
                        main part of the letter in
                            double columns across bottom part of fol. 1 v.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Yes <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> thus one day this body shall rot</l>
<l rend="indent2">Cold lifeless &amp; putrid — forgetting — forgot.</l>
<l rend="indent2">Yet perhaps even then when I moulder away</l>
<l rend="indent2">Corruption poor fast to original clay</l>
<l rend="indent2">When each lifeless feature is crumbled to dust</l>
<l rend="indent2">Fame may see what I was from this odefied bust<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Yes Bedford … bust: Written up right hand
                            side of fol. 1 v.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent5"> ———</p>
<p>
<date when="1793-10-18">Friday morning</date>.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> the transition from your letter to the card table was not the
                    most agreable last night — particularly as I was in the writing mood — I met
                    with a fellow of Corpus now doing penance in all the horrors of disease for his
                    faults &amp; follies — Goldesbrough<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">John Goldesbrough (d. 1846), a student at Balliol College, Oxford, and
                        later a fellow of Magdalen College, Oxford, BA 1797.</note> he tells me has
                    got the demiship at Maudlin. what a miserable state is that man in, who has only
                    his fellowship to depend upon. if he marries he loses it &amp; how he can be
                    happy without marriage appears to me a paradox. this is a piece of the scarlet
                    whores petticoat — a lump of the old leaven a remnant of idolatry. it might have
                    been reasonably imagined that when the enormities of nunneries &amp;
                    monasteries (most <hi rend="ital">monstrous</hi> institutions) were exposed —
                    that our sage reformers would have provided against their renewal. they ought to
                    have known that the same causes will produce the same effects &amp; when
                    they tolerated matrimony in the clergy they should not have insisted upon
                    celibacy in the universities. In the history of these hot beds of vice I am not
                    well read — but it is probable that when the work of reformation was performd by
                    Rapine — some timeservers who secretly favoured the old Religion presided in the
                    universities &amp; retained thus much of the Babylonian patchwork. the
                    consequences are visible. our fellows are either the most dissolute libertines
                    or good well meaning scholars like <ref target="people.html#HoweThomas">Tom
                        Howe</ref> sauntering about their respective quadrangles with long faces
                    &amp; keeping them free from the impurities of impudent dogs. <ref target="people.html#BarnesFrederick">Ginger</ref> forms a genus of his own
                    &amp; a queer genus it is — distinguishd by the generic marks of everlasting
                    thirst &amp; invincible stupidity to which accomplishment he specifically
                    adds — two eyes like a boild rabbits &amp; the harmonious nasal twang that
                    instead of filling the heart with devotion plays upon the risible muscles of his
                    auditors. for many years these unfortunate animals have been the butt of
                    ridicule whilst the satirist forgets that instead of lashing the victims of the
                    institution he ought to expose the institution itself. Vicesimus Knox<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Vicesimus Knox (1752–1821; <title level="m">DNB</title>), headmaster and writer. See <title level="m">Essays Moral and Literary</title>, 11th edn, 2 vols (London, 1787), I,
                        pp. 323–326.</note> has touchd pretty freely upon these subjects — but much
                    remains to be done. there is an immense Augean stable that wants cleansing —
                    &amp; the filth that now breeds corruption if properly distributed could
                    become excellent manure &amp; fertlize the whole country. a consummation
                    devoutly to be wishd for<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title level="m">Hamlet</title>, Act III, scene 1, lines 64–65.</note> — more
                    to be wishd than expected.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> To me the radical defect of the universities appears this — the
                    association of men with only men. the total absence of that sex from whom only
                    we can receive the last polish. the intercourse in this country is much too
                    distant &amp; of course Man becomes more brutal when the tablecloth is
                    removed the women retire with the dishes they have dressed &amp; of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilkes<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably
                        the politician John Wilkes (1725–1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>), whose
                        profligacy and promiscuity were renowned.</note> two subjects of
                    conversation the one (bad as it is) is above the drinking party. the women of
                    the present day are not in general possessd of those qualifications which we
                    might desire — but I am inclined to think with our correspondent Cassandra<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">A pseudonym used by an unidentified
                        correspondent of Southey’s.</note> that most of these faults originate in
                    our sex. when they see that unaffected simplicity has no charms in the eyes of
                    fashionable folly they give into fashions which Reason would have condemned
                    &amp; Nature scornd. I might alledge the distance between the sexes as an
                    argument against your assertion that man <del rend="strikethrough">were</del>
                    &lt;is&gt; in a state of Nature were I so disposed — should we in that
                    best state be pleasd with Hail Politeness Power divine — the curst little
                    rushlight or the horid squalling of a thing imported from Italy? but I am
                    running from my subject into a rage against opera singers — beings to be pitied
                    most certainly — but 999 degrees below the Men Milliners &amp; that is below
                    nothing.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The human mind is formed as capable of excellence now, as it was
                    in those days when Themistocles<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Themistocles (c. 528–462 BC), Athenian statesman and general.</note> fought
                        Aristides<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Aristides (c. 530–468 BC),
                        Athenian statesman, generally known as ‘the Just’.</note> lived &amp;
                        Æschylus<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Æschylus (525–456 BC),
                        Greek tragic dramatist, reputedly killed when an eagle dropped a tortoise on
                        his bald head, mistaking it for a stone.</note> sung. nor are the faculties
                    of Woman impaired or anyways alterd from what they were in Portia<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Portia, the wife of Brutus (85–42 BC), was a
                        Roman woman with a high tolerance for pain. She gave herself a severe wound
                        in the thigh in order to display her bravery, thus proving herself worthy of
                        being included in Brutus’s conspiracy against Julius Caesar. After Brutus’s
                        death in 42 BC, she committed suicide by swallowing burning coals.</note>
                        Arria<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Arria was the wife of Paetus
                        Caecina, one of the participants in a conspiracy against the Emperor
                        Claudius (10 BC–AD 54; reigned 41–AD 54) in AD 42. On the way to her
                        husband’s trial, Arria stabbed herself to show Paetus that it did not hurt;
                        Paetus followed her example and killed himself before going to trial.</note>
                    &amp; the mother of the Gracchi<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Cornelia Scipionis Africanis (190–100 BC), mother of the radical
                        politicians Tiberius (163–132 BC) and Gaius (154–121 BC) Gracchus. She was
                        considered the ideal of a Roman matron.</note> and yet we seldom see one of
                    these glorious characters arise. there must be a defect somewhere &amp; with
                    respect to one cause — that of education we shall agree. I would not wish my
                    Wife to excel in dancing finger the harpsichord &amp; paint flowers
                    incomparably whilst her knowledge of books was confined to novels &amp; of
                    cookery — to knowing where to place the dishes. she should not be a kitchen
                    wench or a pedant — but I am convinced it would be equally agreable to both were
                    she a companion in my studies &amp; knew how to make a good pudding. as I
                    would not wed a Sycorax<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title level="m">The Tempest</title>, a witch and the mother of Caliban.</note>
                    so neither would I ask a Venus.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Roman goddess of beauty and love.</note> good humour &amp; good sense
                    would always be handsome. surely my wishes are not unreasonable — but they will
                    probably never be gratified. thanks to myself I possess the two best requisites
                    for an old batchelor — I can smoke tobacco &amp; play backgammon — in
                    addition to this I will talk politics with the exciseman of my parish &amp;
                    like a true patriot always be shaved at the Barbers. an old Mrs Piozzi<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">The writer Hester Thrale Piozzi
                        (1741–1821; <title level="m">DNB</title>). Southey is possibly alluding to
                        her platonic relationship with Dr Johnson (1709–1784; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> shall dress my turnips after I have raisd them — I
                    will make my own cyder — &amp; have a flitch of bacon on the rack with my
                    walking sticks, &amp; a good stock of toasting cheese. this is not a very
                    enviable prospect but building Castles in the air for Reason to destroy is an
                    employment I am sick of.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have denominated my stick the Sans Culotte to which name it has
                    the most undoubted title. in my next you will probably have an ode to it
                    &amp; another to the Me at Bristol — but I must have Snivel<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">The Bedford family dog. For the poem to Snivel,
                        see Southey’s letter to his brother Tom, [late October/early November–] 14
                        December [1793] (Letter 65).</note> finishd &amp; an ode to Tom
                        Paine.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">If Southey wrote an ode to
                        the radical Thomas Paine (1737–1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>), it does
                        not seem to have survived.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> the <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Doctor</ref>
                    &amp; I made a fine contrast — the drest travelling democrat &amp; the
                    drest Man Millener! he will be very angry at this so tell him that in five
                    minutes I shall &lt;begin&gt; him a very long epistle. I am in momentary
                    expectation of my baggage &amp; you need not be told a little impatient.
                    make my respects to all <ref target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your good
                        family</ref>. <ref target="people.html#Deaconfamily">Mr &amp; Mrs
                        Deacon</ref> — Mrs Colyns<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; presumably a friend of the Bedfords.</note> &amp;c.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> a la mode <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">CC</ref> you
                    see I have once remembered the rules of Politeness Power divine.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have pleased myself during the filling of this sheet with the
                    idea that you &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> are busied in performing the same task. tomorrow I reach
                    Bristol to dinner direct to me as usual.</p>
<closer rend="indent3">
<salute rend="indent2">yours most sincerely</salute>
<signed rend="indent5">RS.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
