<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce130</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.130</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 97–98 [in part; second extract from Joan of Arc not reproduced].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="130" type="letter">
<head>130. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1795-07-01">[1 July 1795]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single<lb/>Stamped: BRISTOL<lb/>Postmark: AJY/ 2/ 95<lb/> Watermarks: Figure of Britannia; COLES/ 1794<lb/>Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. July 2. 1795; 2 July 1795<lb/>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 97–98 [in part; second extract from <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> not reproduced].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<date when="1795-07-01">Wednesday.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1">	I am hard employed that I may soon visit you. in getting forwards with Joan, &amp; as more than three parts of the poem will be entirely rewritten you may suppose this is no light task. as soon as I shall be a fortnight before the press I will absent myself for that time.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	 do you know <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I hate the idea of coming to see you for a fortnight. poor <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref> — I thought to have seen him this summer. you know I detest the idea of writing upon a lost friend — yet the frame of mind so occasiond will tinge what we are employed upon. these lines are in the first book.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	speaking of the old hermit Bizardo.</p>
<lb/>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">In the full of years he sunk. his eye grew dim</l>
<l rend="indent2">And on the bed of leaves his outstretchd limbs</l>
<l rend="indent2">Lay useless. patiently did he endure,</l>
<l rend="indent2">In faith anticipating blessedness,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Already more than man in that dread hour</l>
<l rend="indent2">When man is meanest. his were the best joys</l>
<l rend="indent2">The pious know &amp; his last prayer was praise.</l>
<l rend="indent2">I saw him die. I saw the dews of Death</l>
<l rend="indent2">Starting on his cold brow — I heard him then</l>
<l rend="indent2">Pour out a blessing on me. — Son of Orleans</l>
<l rend="indent2">I would not wish to live to know that hour</l>
<l rend="indent2">When I could think upon a dear friend dead</l>
<l rend="indent2">And weep not. <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version of these lines appeared in Southey’s <title level="m">Joan of Arc, An Epic Poem</title> (Bristol and London, 1796), p. 22.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p>I think of him <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> when alone — methinks a man has no right to gloom a company with his own melancholy feelings.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> my bookseller (a good man &amp; one whose liberality might rescue the fraternity from all obloquy —) is soon coming up to town — chiefly to get a good frontispiece engraved. this is the subject. it requires to be well designed &amp; by a man of genius.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Last evening lone in thought I wanderd forth.</l>
<l rend="indent2">Down in the dingles depth there is a brook</l>
<l rend="indent2">That makes its way between the craggy stones</l>
<l rend="indent2">Murmuring hoarse murmurs. on an aged oak</l>
<l rend="indent2">Whose root, uptorn by tempests, overhangs</l>
<l rend="indent2">The stream, I sat &amp; markd the deep red clouds</l>
<l rend="indent2">Gather before the wind, whilst the rude dash</l>
<l rend="indent2">Of waters rockd my senses, &amp; the mists</l>
<l rend="indent2">Rose round. there as I gazd a form dim-seen</l>
<l rend="indent2">Descended. like the dark &amp; moving clouds</l>
<l rend="indent2">That in the moon beam change their shadowy shapes.</l>
<l rend="indent2">His voice was on the breeze. he bade me hail</l>
<l rend="indent2">The missiond Maid — for lo! the hour was come!</l>
<l rend="indent2">Then was the future present to my view</l>
<l rend="indent2">And strange events yet in the womb of Time</l>
<l rend="indent2">To me made manifest. I sat entranced</l>
<l rend="indent2">In the beatitude of heavenly vision. <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version of these lines appeared in Southey’s <title level="m">Joan of Arc, An Epic Poem</title> (Bristol and London, 1796), pp. 33–34.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p>And this my dear friend is what I am doing at Bristol! as for the future — I can only hope that it will be — the future in rus.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	however I earnestly hope &amp; labour to be with you in a fortnight. &amp; then you shall know what I am doing &amp; how I hope to live.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I am very earnest to see <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>. God bless him!</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> has got the Greek Epigrams. I have heard well of him from Billsborrow (who wrote those lines prefixd to the Zoonomia).<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Dewhurst Bilsborrow’s (dates unknown) poem appeared in Erasmus Darwin (1731–1802; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Zoonomia; or, the Laws of Organic Life</title>, 2 vols (London, 1794–1796), I, pp. [vii]–viii.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">	remember me to <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">C Collins</ref>. it is a twelvemonth since I have either seen or heard of him. </p>
<p rend="indent1">	that twelvemonth has been a very busy one — &amp; has improved my head &amp; heart whatever effect it may have had on my happiness.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	write to me <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>. the sight of your handwriting rouses a long train of associations of the pleasing order.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I have put your name &amp; titles to decorate my list &amp; lengthen it. but as I wish you to have a specimen of our B[MS torn] binding as well as typery — you must let me provide your [MS torn]y. the list of subscribers is at Cadells<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The London booksellers and publishers, Thomas Cadell, the Elder (1742–1802; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and Thomas Cadell, the Younger (1773–1836; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> — &amp; as they no longer belong to me I feel a more earnest wish to lengthen it. the book will be out by the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> of January.</p>
<p rend="indent4">				fare you well.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent5">					yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent6">						Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
