<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce191</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.191</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="191" type="letter">
<head>191. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1796-12-08">[c. 8 December 1796]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/ High Street/ Bristol<lb/> Stamped: BATH<lb/>Seal: [trace; illegible]<lb/>Endorsements: Feby 1797; 17 (<del rend="strikethrough">67</del>)<lb/>MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library<lb/>Unpublished.<lb/>Dating note: Cottle’s endorsement is clearly incorrect. See also Southey to Joseph Cottle [c. early December 1796] (Letter 189), which has a similar incorrect endorsement. The letter was written from Bath, where Southey was living in December 1796 (he did not move to London until February 1797) and it refers to his reading of Carlyle, which he finished on 8 December 1796; see his letter of that date to Grosvenor Charles Bedford (Letter 190).</note>
</head>
<p rend="indent1">	I have two or three things to say &amp; two or three minutes to spare. I forgot to return you your elegy — of which I like all but the false presage in the second stanza. I enter into your feelings, judging of the sister you have lost by those you still possess: should not such <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">sisters</ref> make you in love with life?</p>
<p rend="indent1">	will you be good enough (if you have done with <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref> poems, to lend them to <ref target="people.html#EstlinMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Estlin</ref>; without mentioning it to him, for he is ashamed of them &amp; evaded her request. </p>
<p rend="indent1">	my Letters<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797).</note> will demand the most shameful list of errors that ever disgraced a book. I cannot read a page without discovering some blunder that totally destroys the meaning. you will be astonished at the number &amp; nature of these mistakes.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I could wish you not to print <ref target="people.html#ProbyJohnCarysfort">Ld Carysforts</ref> name in the lists of Foxe’s subscribers;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Fox (1740?–1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">'Aks-i partaw. A Series of Poems, Containing the Plaints, Consolations, and Delights of Achmed Ardebeili, a Persian Exile. With Notes Historical and Explanatory</title> (1797). The book was published by Joseph Cottle. Lord Carysfort’s name did not appear in the list of subscribers.</note> as my acquaintance with him is not enough to justify that liberty. I have never seen him yet. it is a foolish custom — that of printing subscribers name &amp; serves only to swell the size of a volume &amp; to gratify the vanity of those blockheads who conceive the merit of a book reflects upon the purchaser! or that of the purchaser on the book.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I have met with a curious coincidence of thought this morning in reading Carlyles Specimens of Arabic Poetry a book printed <hi rend="ital">this</hi> year. it was said of Abou Teman — “his mind must soon wear out his body as the blade of a Indian scymetar destroys its scabbard.”<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Dacre Carlyle, <title level="m">Specimens of Arabian Poetry, From the Earliest Time to the Extinction of the Khaliphat, with some Account of the Authors</title> (Cambridge, 1796), p. 64.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I will send copy on Monday by the theatrical conveyance. if <ref target="people.html#RosserRobert">Rosser<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>
</ref> is at a stand — let him reprint the cancelld leaves. the first is — page 87–87. in 87 — let the indenting of the line Pedia celos de cosas<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A correction to the printing of Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797). This translates as ‘s/he accused things of being unfaithful’.</note> — be rectified. the error lies in the last stanza but one.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	Viendo me como me veys — is printed instead of these two line</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Viendo me como me vistes</l>
<l rend="indent2">En vir me como me veys?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A correction to the printing of Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797). The passage translates as ‘Seeing me as you saw me/ In seeing me as you see me’.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p>one — is 375–376. To a Stream must be the title. there are two other errors to be avoided. mugur is wrongly printed instead of muger in the last line of the Spanish. <hi rend="ital">shade</hi> for sheds in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the translation is wrong.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	Leaf 385–386 — must be cancelled owing to a mistake of mine. the three lines</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Trembling then as Zelindaxa</l>
<l rend="indent2">To her pale lips held the water</l>
<l rend="indent2">From her hand the goblet fell —</l>
</lg>
<p>must be struck out. &amp; these inserted in their place.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Heedless in delirious transport,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Eagerly did Zelindaxa</l>
<l rend="indent2">Shower her perfumes on his head.</l>
</lg>
<p>in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> lines from the bottom of the same page — <hi rend="ital">could</hi> ought to be CAN. &amp; inverted commas must be placed before “tho Love no laws acknowledge,</p>
<p rend="indent1">	this will fully employ him till Monday noon. hurry the printers — make <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Biggs</ref> mind the stanzas they must be indivisible. I shall be with you about the middle of next week. can you not come over Saturday or Sunday &amp; make the map? why not? let me know.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	tell <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> that M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Molloy<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> is alive &amp; well</p>
<p rend="indent2">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love.</p>
<p rend="indent3">			fare you well</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent4">yrs sincerely</salute>
<signed rend="indent5">R Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1796-12-08">Thursday night</date>
</p>
<p>I had forgotten an engagement to dine at Bradford on Sunday next. will you come the Saturday following? if no copy should come on Monday let <ref target="people.html#RosserRobert">Rosser</ref> do the cancelld leaves. forget not to send a parcel by Old Floor<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a carrier in the Bristol area, who dealt with booksellers, publishers and printers.</note> of mutton chop celebrity. </p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
