<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce218</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.218</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 312&#8211;314 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.218" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="218" type="letter">
        <head>218. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1797-05-25">25 May 1797</date>
          </head><p>Address: G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: SOUTH/ HAMPTON<lb />Postmark: BMA/ 27/ 97<lb /> Watermark: Crown and anchor<lb />Endorsement: 25. May 1797<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 312&#8211;314 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1797-05-25">Thursday. May 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1797.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName> Southampton</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	In every village of the Susquehanah Indians there is a vacant dwelling called <hi rend="ital">the Strangers House</hi>. when a traveller there arrives at one of these villages he stops &amp; holl&#333;s. two of the elders of the tribe immediately go out to meet him, they lead him to this his house, &amp; go round to tell the inhabitants that a stranger is arrived fatigued &amp; hungry.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Benjamin Franklin (1706&#8211;1790), <title level="m">Philosophical and Miscellaneous Papers</title> (London, 1787), p. 173. This information was later used in a footnote to <title level="m">Madoc</title> (1805), Part 1, book 5.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	They do not order these things quite so well in England. We arrived at Southampton at 6 last evening. &#8220;Lodgings&#8221; were hung out at almost every house. but some would not let less than eleven rooms &#8212; some 7 &amp; so on &#8212; &amp; we walked a very long &amp; uncomfortable hour before we could buy hospitality &#8212; &amp; that at a very dear rate. I mean to walk tomorrow thro Lyndhurst &amp; Lymington to Christ Church. that is if <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> be better &#8212; for she is now very unwell. she is feverish. I hope &amp; believe it is only the temporary effect of fatigue. &#8212; but <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> a single man does not know what anxiety is.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is not well enough to walk out &#8212; I therefore have seen only enough of this place to dislike it. its inhabitants are people connected with shipping &#8212; &amp; sharking shopkeepers &#8212; its visitors the very top scum of aristocracy. the carrion that these vultures feed upon. I want a quiet lonely place. in sight of something green. surely in a walk of thirty miles this may be found &#8212; but if I find the whole coast infected by visitors I will go to Bristol &#8212; where I shall have the Printer on one side, <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref> on the other, <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> in front &#8212; the woods &amp; rocks of Avon behind &#8212; &amp; be in the centre of all good things.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Our journey was hot &amp; dusty. but thro a lovely country. at one time the coach was full &#8212; &amp; all &#8212; but me asleep. <del rend="strikethrough">I</del> something fell off the roof &#8212; &amp; I had the unutterable pleasure of waking all of them by bellowing out to bid the Coachman stop.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	the idea of my lonely expedition is not very agreable. it is thirty miles to Christ Church. I could go 18 by coach. but the coach sets out at 3 in the evening &#8212; so that as it would not be well to walk the other 12 after 7 o clock &#8212; it would occasion an absence of 3 days. I hope <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is better (it is now near 6) &#8212; two days of solitude will be unpleasant to her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Would we were settled &#8212; aye &amp; for life in some little sequestered valley &#8212; I would be content never to climb over the hills that sheltered me, &amp; never to hear music or taste beverage but from the stream that ran beside my door. Let me have the sea too &#8212; &amp; now &amp; then some piece of a wreck, to supply me with firewood &amp; remind me of commerce. This New Forest is very lovely. I should like to have a house in it &#8212; &amp; dispeople the rest like William the Conqueror.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William I, the Conqueror (1027/8&#8211;1087; reigned 1066&#8211;1087; <title level="m">DNB</title>) turned the New Forest into a royal hunting ground.</note> of all land objects a forest is the finest. Gisborne has written a feeble poem upon the subject.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> John Gisborne (1770&#8211;1851; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Vales of Wever, a Loco-Descriptive Poem</title> (1797). Southey reviewed it for the <title level="j">Critical Review</title>, 22 (January 1798), 100&#8211;101.</note> the <del rend="strikethrough">emotion</del> feelings that fill me when I lie under one tree &amp; contemplate another in all the majesty of years &#8212; are neither to be defined or expressed. &amp; these undefinable unexpressable feelings are those of the highest delight. they pass over the mind like the clouds of the summer evening &#8212; too fine &amp; too fleeting for Memory to detain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	And now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> would I wager sixpence that you are regretting my absence, because you feel disposed to come to tea with us. I could upbraid you &#8212; but this is one of the follies of man &#8212; &amp; I have my share of it &#8212; tho thank God &#8212; but a small share. what we can do at any time is most likely not to be done at all. We are more willing to make an effort. is this because we feel uneasy at the prospect of labour &#8212; of something to be done? &amp; so are stimulated to industry by a love of indolence. I am a self observer, &amp; indeed this appears to me the secret spring.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I shall however act in opposition to it now &#8212; &amp; stay here probably till Monday &#8212; tho the idea of going is very uncomfortable &amp; clings like birdlime to every thought. this is because I do not like to leave <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> to the double evil of solitude &amp; indisposition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	farewell <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>. I shall sally forth &#8212; &amp; look for the Post Office. whereunto Write. When I tell you that Southampton has <hi rend="ital">a Quay</hi> instead of a beach &#8212; I need not abuse the blackguard place.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I wish THE Tribunal was established. it would make provisions cheaper. there are so many ugly mouths!</p>
        <p rend="indent2">		God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">			yrs at a distance</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">				R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">	Remember Cupid &amp; Psyche for Carlisle.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Remember ... <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>: Written upside down at the top of fol. 1 r. Possibly a reference to Thomas Taylor&#8217;s (1758&#8211;1835; <title level="m">DNB</title>) translation, <title level="m">The Fable of Cupid and Psyche</title> (1795).</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>