<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce87</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.87</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 845.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.87" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="87" type="letter">
        <head>87. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#HorsemanJohn">John Horseman</ref>, <date when="1794-04-16">16[&#8211;20] April 1794</date>
          </head><p>Address: John Horseman/ at the Reverend John Horseman&#8217;s/ Souldern near/
						Bicester/ Oxfordshire./ Single Sheet<lb />MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 845<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#CollegeGreenBristol">College Green. Bristol.</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1794-04-16">Wed. Apr. 16. 1794</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The pointed sentence &amp; the well rounded period my dear friend are proper &amp; pretty in declamation,
					but the stile of letter writing should flow from the heart, not from the deliberate musing of the head. I remained at old <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Ball. Coll.</ref> till the Friday morning after your departure, &amp; great part of my
					time passed in all the luxury of democratic converse. my friend <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> is an excellent
					republican. his manners urbane &amp; liberal &#8212; in short never did countenance more truly pourtray disposition than his does &#8212;
					if you know the mans appearance you will feel the force of this. we democratized gloriously nor did I quit Oxford without feeling
					something like regret notwithstanding the prospect of revisiting some of my dearest friends. even at school I have perceived this
					sentiment intrude itself on breaking up. tis the local patriotism the heart contracts from habit &#8212; the residence of any length of
					time recalls so many &amp; such various scenes &#8212; every spot calls to mind some particular incident which once pleased
					&amp; still is recollected with pleasure, that I soon domesticate anywhere. Cats have the same attachment to place. do not you
					regard every rats hole round the fish pond at Souldrey?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On the Friday <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> roused me before three &amp; we breakfasted
					together. talkd for an hour &amp; half &amp; then I quitted the high places of orthodoxy in the mail coach. my company a
					master of Trinity. Pickwick<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pickwick (dates unknown), a student at St John&#8217;s
						College, Oxford (matric. 1793). An acquaintance &#8212; not a friend &#8212; of Southey&#8217;s.</note> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Johns
					&amp; Slade<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Slade (dates unknown), a student at Queen&#8217;s College, Oxford
						(matric. 1792, BA 1796). An acquaintance &#8212; not a friend &#8212; of Southey&#8217;s.</note> of Queens. two men whom I never saw before
					&amp; hope I never shall see again. the five &amp; thirty miles to breakfast passed in total silence, &amp; my mouth
					was closed all the rest of the journey. I had however ample food for thought. what philosopher was it that said &#8216;I am never less
					alone than when alone&#8217;?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Cicero (106&#8211;43 BC), <title level="m">De Officiis,</title> Book 3,
						chapter 1. The Latin translates as &#8216;Never less idle than when wholly idle, nor less alone than when wholly alone&#8217;.</note> you
					who are a Solitudinarian must admire the saying as much &lt;as&gt; I do. the reveries of silence are delightful &#8212; a mind
					stored with the ideas &amp; sentiments of Romance &amp; Rousseau may paint so exquisite a scene of visionary perfection
					that when Reason wakes it to human fallibility, disgust attends the contrast. Hawkesworth argues very strongly against indulging
					in these fantastical pleasures &#8212; they enervate the mind &amp; by accustoming it to the dreams of fancy render it totally unfit
					for serious contemplation &amp; abstract reasoning &#8212; they have likewise a worse effect even than this &#8212; they tend to render
					society odious &amp; the world contemptible, till the dreamer possesses all the austerity of a Cynic without the sublimity of
					his virtues.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of John Hawkesworth (c. 1720&#8211;1773; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
							<title level="m">The Adventurer</title>, 4 vols (London, 1777), II, pp. 273&#8211;275.</note> think of this <ref target="people.html#HorsemanJohn">Horseman</ref>. even in my language it may have some effect because it possesses the
					strength of truth. when we meet at Oxford I will show you the paper of Hawkesworth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How like you the gallant city of London? is it not an overgrown monster devouring its own children? a large sink of
					folly dissipation &amp; iniquity?</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Sir I do thank God for it, I do hate</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Most righteously the town<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of John Donne (1572&#8211;1631; <title level="m">DNB</title>), &#8216;Satyre II&#8217; (c. 1594), lines 1&#8211;2.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>so said old Donne. &amp; thank God I join with him heartily. four years residence there gave me experience. &amp; I had
					rather dwell in the poorest hovel to which Monarchy &amp; Aristocracy have condemnd honest labour, than in the proud palaces
					of London. superficial observers &amp; those who rioting in superfluity themselves cry out &#8216;all is well, will hold up the
					magnitude &amp; multitudes of London as proofs of the prosperity &amp; happiness of the state. nimium ne crede
						colori.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;put not your trust in colours&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Large cities are inevitably destructive to morality. &amp; [MS torn] be to those legislators who would found
					the happiness of [MS torn] their people upon any other basis. tis computed that London receives annually six thousand inhabitants
					from the country. ought that to be considered as the proof of national prosperity which annually destroys six thousand men? if you
					have ever passed thro the wretched lanes &amp; alleys of St Giles&#8217;s &amp; various other parts of London, the pestilential
					haunts of Depravity Misery &amp; Disease, tis utterly impossible but you must yourself have cursed the state of society
					&amp; wishd it alterd. partial reformation will not do. who but would blame the surgeon who should from mistaken kindness
					amputate the foot when the knee was gangrened?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> you will write to me as soon as you receive this &amp; give me your adventure in London &amp; whether your
					sentiments agree with mine. lest you should have lost my direction I repeat it. at <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss
						Tylers</ref> Bristol. in a fortnight I expect to revisit Oxford &#8212; the change of scene is pleasant. I found much relief in
					exchanging collegiate uniformity for a more varied life. neither do I meet with half the liberality at Oxford I find in my Bristol
					friends. now I have lost <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> is the only man who searches after truth with all the boldness the search
					requires &#8212; my other &lt;friends&gt; are too timid to throw off prejudices tho they own them to be such &#8212; they think of
					interest &amp;c &amp; worship the Golden Calf of abomination.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <table cols="2" rows="1" width="740" border="0" align="left">
              <row>
                <cell width="375">health &amp; fraternity.</cell>
                <cell width="365">
                  <date when="1794-04-20">Easter Sunday.</date>
                </cell>
              </row>
            </table>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>