<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce27</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.27</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Duke University Library, Southey papers.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter, Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 5&#8211;8 [where it is dated &#8216;College Green, Bristol, 1792.&#8217;].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.27" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="27" type="letter">
        <head>27. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#LambThomasPhillipps">Thomas Phillipps Lamb</ref>, <date when="1792-10-06">[c. 6 October 1792]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: T P Lamb Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Mountsfield Lodge/ Rye/ Sussex<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: OC/ 6/ 92<lb />Seal: Red wax [design illegible]<lb />Endorsements: Southey/ Dog &lt;Puppy&gt; Dash/ Bitch &#8212; Flush<lb />MS: Duke University Library, Southey papers<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter, <title level="m">Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 5&#8211;8 [where it is dated &#8216;College Green, Bristol, 1792.&#8217;].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">		I am at length enabled to answer you with respect to my future situation at Oxford. excuse me if I say <ref target="people.html#VincentWilliam">Dr Vincent</ref> has behaved to me with his accustomed generosity &amp; liberality &#8212; virtues which he praises so much &amp; practises so little. I am rejected at Christ Church &#8212; when I say so without feeling <hi rend="ital">very</hi> warm allow me to possess more patience that either you or I imagined. let me not however attribute the calm state of my mind to so good a motive I cannot help hoping one day to tell him that he has behaved to me in a manner equally ungenerous &amp; unjust. before I wrote that letter (for which I must reproach myself as expressing contrition I did not feel &amp; apologizing for an action which I thought needed no apology) before I was persuaded to write he had engaged his honor never to mention the circumstance. as Queen Bess<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth I (1533&#8211;1603; reigned 1558&#8211;1603; <title level="m">DNB</title>), cited in David Hume (1711&#8211;1776; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">History of England</title>, 4 vols (London, 1764), IV, p. 311.</note> once said God forgive him but I never can.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	enough of a subject upon which I may perhaps have expressed myself with too unbecoming a warmth. I have always acknowledged myself imprudent a harsher term I cannot submit to with truth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I heard yesterday from <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Tom</ref> &#8212; he left Edinburgh last Monday &amp; mentions that the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of October he expects to be in Bristol on his road to King Weston. now he says he fears that he shall neither be able to see his <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Majesty</ref> or me. &amp; as he gives not the least hint where a letter may meet him I have no means but by you of informing him that on that day &amp; after that day till Xmas I shall certainly be in the College Green at Bristol. since as I can only enter at <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Baliol</ref>. Oxford this term it will only detain me three days so that I shall positively be here &amp; as positively expect to see him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	at all events I will by this days post write to York &amp; for fear of accidents only tell him I shall expect to see him. if it misses it is but the postage lost to government &amp; the paper to me &#8212; the latter loss to one who daubs so much is nothing &#8212; the former may be supplied by the superfluous taxes next encampment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I am sorry to add that he will not obtain an audience of the <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">King of Men</ref>. his Majesty being obliged to visit Oxford before that period &#8212; as that University was remarkable for its loyalty to his royal ancestors tis to be hoped he will be equally dutiful to the University.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	French affairs still very bad. is the report of Brunswicks<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles William Ferdinand, Duke of Brunswick-L&#252;neburg (1735&#8211;1806), commander of the Prussian forces that invaded revolutionary France in 1792. Brunswick had captured Longwy on 23 August and Verdun on 2 September 1792.</note> success true? the mobocracy may thank themselves for it &amp; richly do they deserve an event which I dare to say would not have happened had fayette been their lead[MS torn] leaving their present hostilities out of the question do [MS torn] Prussians have been plagues to human nature for this last century [MS torn] were sent to plague mankind &amp; their leaders to plague them. the French are tygers &amp; apes but what are those animals disciplined till they forget obedience to every divine law &amp; every dictate of humanity in a blind submission to their military despot?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I heard it lately observed that the past character of the French differs widely from their present. the Philosopher of Ferney<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Voltaire, Fran&#231;ois-Marie Arouet (1694&#8211;1778), French writer and <hi rend="ital">philosophe</hi>. He owned an estate at Ferney.</note> afford one proof to the contrary &amp; I think history many more. the national ferocity has more than once broke out. the horrid massacre of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bartholomew<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The massacre of the Huguenot leaders in Paris on 23&#8211;24 August 1572.</note> the death of Calas<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Calas (1698&#8211;1762), Protestant merchant of Toulouse who was executed for murdering his son. Voltaire campaigned to prove his innocence and the verdict was overturned in 1765.</note> the punishment of the maniac Damien<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert-Francois Damiens (1715&#8211;1757) attempted to stab Louis XV (1710&#8211;1774; reigned 1715&#8211;1774) and was tortured to death.</note> &amp; the enormities they committed in America before they appeared as protectors of revolution (you see I use an ambiguous term) are so many views of their real disposition prominent amidst all the tinsel of affectation. &#8220;they order these things better in England&#8221;.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is adapting Laurence Sterne (1713&#8211;1768; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">A Sentimental Journey Through France and Italy</title> (London, 1768), p. [1].</note> Peg Nicholson<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Nicholson (1750?&#8211;1828; <title level="m">DNB</title>) attempted to stab George III (1738&#8211;1820; reigned 1760&#8211;1820; <title level="m">DNB</title>) with an ivory-handled dessert knife on 2 August 1786. She was declared insane and confined in the Bethlem Hospital (Bedlam) for the rest of her life.</note> is only in Bedlam Tom Paine is treated with lenity<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Paine (1737&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>) was charged with seditious libel for publishing <title level="m">The Rights of Man</title> (1791&#8211;1792). He was convicted <title level="m">in absentia</title> in December 1792.</note> &#8212; but woe be to him who dares attack the divine right of Schoolmasters to flog or who presumes to think that boys should neither be punished absurdly or indecently.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	vires acquirit eundo<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;we gather strength as we go&#8217;, Virgil (70&#8211;19 BC), <title level="m">Aeneid</title>, Book 4, line 175.</note> says somebody of something I forget who or what. I have undergone enough to break a dozen hearts but mine is made of tough stuff &amp; the last misfortune serves to blunt the edge of the next. one day it will I hope be impenetrable tis well I can speak with levity. but however seriously my dear Sir I wish you to kill your mutton &amp; eat in in peace (I wont <del rend="strikethrough">add</del> quietness for you dont wish it. my best respects to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L. &amp; all friends</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">believe me your much obliged humble sevt</salute>
        </closer>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent11">R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>your black seal much alarmed me.</p>
          <p>
            <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Toms</ref> letter made me easy.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>