<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce148</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.148</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Tipped into a copy of Letters and Journals of Lord Byron: with Notices of His Life, by Thomas Moore. Illustrated with Views, Portraits, etc., 4 vols (London, 1830), IV, between pp. 372&#8211;373; Huntington Library, RB 90327.  Previously  published: Joseph Cottle, Early Recollections of the Late Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 2 vols (London, 1837), II, pp. 6&#8211;14 [in part, and dated 1 February 1796]; and Joseph Cottle, Reminscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey (London, 1847), pp. 193&#8211;199 [in part].Dating note: The letter was probably written over a long period of time and was sent in March 1796.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="148" type="letter">
        <head>148. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>, <date when="1796-02">[February&#8211;March 1796?]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle/ High Street/ Bristol<lb /> Postmark: [partial] DM/ 16/ 96<lb />Endorsements: Southey/ Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1796; <del rend="strikethrough">34</del>
            <hi rend="underline">6</hi>&#8217; &#8216;Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1796; (<del rend="strikethrough">62</del>)<lb />MS: Tipped into a copy of <title level="m">Letters and Journals of Lord Byron: with Notices of His Life, by Thomas Moore. Illustrated with Views, Portraits, etc.</title>, 4 vols (London, 1830), IV, between pp. 372&#8211;373; Huntington Library, RB 90327<lb />Previously published: Joseph Cottle, <title level="m">Early Recollections of the Late Samuel Taylor Coleridge</title>, 2 vols (London, 1837), II, pp. 6&#8211;14 [in part, and dated 1 February 1796]; and Joseph Cottle, <title level="m">Reminscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey</title> (London, 1847), pp. 193&#8211;199 [in part].<lb />Dating note: The letter was probably written over a long period of time and was sent in March 1796.</note>
        </head>
        <lb />
        <p>Certainly I shall hear from <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottle</ref> by the first packet &#8212; said I &#8212; now I say probably I may hear by the next. so does Experience abate the sanguine expectations of Man. &#8220;what &#8212; could not you write one letter?&#8221; &amp; here am I writing not only to all my friends in Bristol but to all in England. indeed I should have been vexed but that the packet brought a letter from <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, &amp; the pleasure that gave me, allowed no feeling of vexation. what of JOAN? M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coates<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the actor Robert Coates (1772&#8211;1848; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> tells me it gains upon the public &#8212; but authors seldom hear the plain truth. I am anxious that it should reach a second edition that I may expunge every line of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> &#8212; remember all he <hi rend="ital">wrote</hi> not all he <hi rend="ital">claims</hi>. he claims the character of Conrade (so <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> told me) of which he never gave a hint nor wrote a line. &amp; I wish to<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">expunge ... wish to: Section deleted, almost certainly by another hand, probably Cottle&#8217;s.</note> write a new preface, &amp; enlarge the last book.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Followed by a comment inserted in Cottle&#8217;s hand: &#8216;I shall omit all in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> book which Coleridge wrote.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Bristol deserves panegyric instead of Satire.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s brother-in-law, Robert Lovell, disagreed, having published his <title level="m">Bristol, a Satire</title> in 1794.</note> I know no mercantile place so literary.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bristol ... literary: Underlined in another hand, probably Cottle&#8217;s.</note> here I am among the Philistines, spending my mornings as pleasantly as books <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del>
          <hi rend="ital">only</hi> books can make them, &amp; sitting at evening the silent spectator of card playing &amp; dancing. the English here unite the spirit of commerce with the frivolous amusements of high life. one of them who plays every night (Sundays are not excepted here) will tell you how closely he attends to profit &#8220;I never pay a porter for bringing a burthen till the next day. (says he) for while the fellow feels his back ache with the weight he charges high &#8212; but when he comes the next day the feeling is gone &#8212; &amp; he asks only half the money.&#8221; and the author of this philosophical scheme is worth 200,000 pounds!! this is a comfortless place, &amp; the only pleasure I find in it, is in looking on to my departure. three years ago I might have found a friend. Count Leopold Berchtold.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Leopold, Graf von Berchtold (d. 1809).</note> this man (foster-brother of the Emperor Joseph<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph II (1741&#8211;1790; reigned 1765&#8211;1790), Holy Roman Emperor.</note>) is one of those rare <del rend="strikethrough">travellers</del> characters who spend their lives in doing good. it is his custom in every country he visits to publish books in its language on some <del rend="strikethrough">use</del> subject of practical utility &#8212; these he gave away. I have now lying before me the two which he printed in Lisbon. the one is an Essay on the means of preserving life in the various dangers to which men are daily exposed.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Leopold, Graf von Berchtold, <title level="m">An Essay to Direct and Extend the Inquiries of Patriotic Travellers</title> (1789).</note> the other &#8212; an Essay on extending the limits of benevolence not only towards men but animals.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Leopold, Graf von Berchtold, <title level="m">Ensaio Sobre a Extens&#227;o dos Limites da Beneficiencia a Respeito, Assim dos Homens Como dos Mesmos Animaes</title> (1793).</note> his age was about 25 &#8212; his person fine, &amp; his manners the most polished. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref> saw more of him than anyone, for he used his library; &amp; this was the only house he called at; he was only seen at dinner &#8212; the rest of the day was constantly given to study. <del rend="strikethrough">one</del> &lt;they&gt; who lived in the same house with him, believed him to be the Wandering Jew. he spoke all the European languages, <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> had written in all, &amp; was master of the Arabic. from Lisbon he went to Cadiz &amp; thence to Barbary no more is known of him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	We felt a smart earthquake the morning after our arrival here. these shocks alarm the Portuguese dreadfully, &amp; indeed it is the most terrifying sensation you can conceive. one man jumped out of bed &amp; ran down to the stable to ride off &lt;almost<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Inserted in another hand.</note>&gt; naked as he was. another more considerately put out his candle because I know (said he) the fire does more harm than the earthquake. the ruins of the great E. <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Lisbon earthquake of 1755.</note> are not yet removed entirely. the city is a curious place a straggling place built upon the most unequal ground &#8212; with heaps of ruins in the middle, &amp; large open places. the streets filthy beyond all English ideas of filth &#8212; for they throw every thing into the street, &amp; nothing is removed. dead animals annoy you at every corner &#8212; &amp; such is the indolence &amp; nastiness of the Portuguese that I really believe they would let one another rot in the same manner, if the Priests did not get something by burying them. some of the friars are vowed <del rend="strikethrough">never</del> to wear the same clothes without changing for a year &#8212; &amp; this is a comfort to them. you will not wonder therefore that I always keep the windward of one of these reverend perfumers. the streets are very agreable in wet weather &#8212; if you walk under the houses you are drenched by the water spouts. if you attempt the middle &#8212; there is a <del rend="strikethrough">little</del> river. would you go between both &#8212; there is the dunghill. the rains here are very violent, &amp; the streams in the streets on a declivity so rapid as to throw down men. &amp; sometimes overset carriages. a woman was absolutely drowned a few years ago, in one of the most frequented streets of Lisbon. but to walk home at <hi rend="ital">night</hi> is the most dangerous adventure. for then the chamber maids, shower out the filth into the streets with such profusion &#8212; that a Scotchman may fancy himself at Edinburgh. you cannot conceive what a cold perspiration it puts me in to hear one dashd down just before me as Thomson says with a little alteration &#8212; to</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">	Hear nightly dashd amid the perilous street</l>
          <l rend="indent2">	The frequent stink-pot.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of James Thomson (1700&#8211;1748; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Seasons</title> (1726&#8211;1730), &#8216;Summer&#8217;, lines 1047&#8211;1048.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>this furnishes food to innumerable dogs that belong to nobody, &amp; annoy every body &#8212; but if did they not devour it the quantities would breed pestilence. <del rend="strikethrough">by</del> &lt;in&gt; a <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del>&lt;moon&gt;light we see dogs &amp; rats feeding at the same dunghill. Lisbon is plagued with a very small species of red ant that swarms over every thing in the houses. their remedy for this is to send for a Priest &amp; exorcise them. the drain from the new Convent opens into the middle of the street. an English pig-stye is cleaner than the metropolis of Portugal. To <del rend="strikethrough">to</del>night I shall see <del rend="strikethrough">a</del> &lt;the&gt; procession of Our Lord of the Passion. this image is a very celebrated one &amp; with great reason, for one night he knockd at the door of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Roques church, &amp; there they would not admit him; upon this he walked to the other end of the town to the Church of Grace, &amp; there they took him in. but a dispute now arose between the two churches, to which the image belongd, whether to the church <del rend="strikethrough">to</del> which he first chose, or the Church that first chose him. the matter was compromised &#8212; one church has him, but the other fetches him for their procession, &amp; he sleeps with them the night preceding it. the better mode of deciding it had been to place the Gentleman between both, &amp; let him walk to which he liked best. what think you of this story being believed [MS repaired] 1796?!!!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	The power of the Inquisition still exists tho they never exercise it &#8212; &amp; thus the Jews save their bacon. fifty years ago it was the greatest delight of the Portuguese to see a Jew burnt. Geddes<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Michael Geddes (c. 1647&#8211;1713; <title level="m">DNB</title>), chaplain of the English factory in Lisbon, 1678&#8211;1688.</note> the then chaplain was present at one of these detestable Auto-da-Fe&#8217;s &#8212; he says that the transports expressed by all ages &amp; all sexes whilst the miserable sufferers were shrieking &amp; begging mercy for Gods sake, formed a scene [MS torn] horrible than any out of hell. he adds that this <del rend="strikethrough">is not</del> barbarity is not the [MS torn] national character, for no people sympathize so much at the execution of a criminal &#8212; but it is the damnable nature of their religion &amp; the most diabolical spirit of their priests. their celibacy deprives them of the affections of men, &amp; their creed gives them the ferocity of devils. Geddes saw one man gagged &#8212; because immediately <del rend="strikethrough">as</del> he came out of the &lt;Inquisition&gt; gates &#8212; he looked up at the Sun whose light for many years had never visited him &#8212; &amp; exclaimed &#8220;how is it possible for men who behold that glorious Orb, to worship any being but him who created it!&#8221;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Michael Geddes, <title level="m">Miscellaneous Tracts</title>, 3rd edn, 3 vols (London, 1730), I, pp. 406&#8211;407.</note> my bloods runs cold when I pass that accursed building, &amp; tho they do not exercise their power &#8212; I feel it a reproach to human nature that the building should exist.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	it is as warm here as in May with you. of course we broil in that month at Lisbon &#8212; but I shall escape the hot weather here as I did the cold weather of England, &amp; quit this place about the latter end of April. you will of course see me the third day after my landing at Falmouth &#8212; or if I can get companions in a post chaise sooner. this my resolution is like the law of the Medes &amp; the Persians that altereth not.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">Daniel</title> 6: 8.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	be good enough to lay by a set of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> Watchman for me &#8212; his lectures &amp; poems. <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Taylor Coleridge&#8217;s <title level="m">The Watchman</title> (1796), <title level="m">Conciones ad Populum</title> (1795), <title level="m">A Moral and Political Lecture</title> (1795), and <title level="m">Poems on Various Subjects</title> (1796).</note> I am very desirous that Joan should reach a second edition &#8212; for the reasons I have given above I want to write a <hi rend="ital">tragedy</hi> here; &amp; can find no leisure to begin it &#8212; I have so much to read &amp; lose so much time in this detestable visiting. I have seen the Monthly Rev. they speak well of Fawcetts poem<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">A review of Joseph Fawcett (<hi rend="ital">c</hi>. 1758&#8211;1804; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Art of War</title> (1795) in the <title level="j">Monthly Review</title>, n.s. 18 (November 1795), 258&#8211;262.</note> &#8212; but abuse Joel Barlow<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The American poet, radical and diplomat, Joel Barlow (1754&#8211;1812; <title level="m">DNB</title>), whose <title level="m">Advice to the Privileged Orders</title> (1792&#8211;1795) was reviewed in the <title level="j">Monthly Review</title>, n.s. 18 (November 1795), 300&#8211;308, and <title level="m">A letter Addressed to the People of Piedmont</title> (1795) in the <title level="j">Monthly Review</title>, n.s. 18 (December 1795), 446&#8211;451.</note> &#8212; as for Joan no body sees its faults more than I do &#8212; &amp; if it reaches a second edition I will neither spare time or trouble to remedy them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	this place is much plagued with robbers &amp; they generally strip a man <del rend="strikethrough">stark naked</del>, &amp; leave him to walk him home in his birthday suit. an English<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Insertion of &#8216;man&#8217; after &#8216;English&#8217; in another hand (probably Cottle&#8217;s).</note> was served so at Almeyda &amp; the Lisbon magistrates on his complaint<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> took up the whole village &amp; impris[MS repaired] them all. contemplate this people in what light you will, you can never see them in a good one. they suffered their best epic poet<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis Vaz de Camo&#235;ns (c. 1524&#8211;1580), author of <title level="m">The Lusiad</title> (1572).</note> to perish for want &#8212; &amp; they burnt their best dramatic writer alive because he was a Jew.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio Jose da Silva (1705&#8211;1739), Portuguese poet and dramatist, who came from a family of Jewish converts to Catholicism. He was executed after being accused of secretly practising Judaism.</note> Pombal<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebastiao Jos&#233; de Carvalho E Melo, Marquis of Pombal (1699&#8211;1782), chief minister (and effective ruler) of Portugal under King Jos&#233; I (1714&#8211;1777; reigned 1750&#8211;1777).</note> &#8212; (a man whose heart was bad enough to make a good minister) reduced the church during his administration. he suffered no persons to enter the convents, &amp; as the old monks &amp; nuns died, threw two convents into one &amp; sold the other estates. by this means he would have speedily annihilated the whole generation of vermin &#8212; but the King died &amp; this Queen<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Jos&#233; I was succeeded by his daughter Maria I (1734&#8211;1816), who was declared insane in 1792.</note> whose religion has driven her mad, und[MS missing] all that Pombal had done. he escaped with life but lived to see his bust destroyed &amp; all his plans for the improvement of Portugal reversed. he had the interests of his country at heart &#8212; &amp; this punishment added to the regret of having committed so many crimes vainly to secure his power, must almost have been enough for this execrable Marquis.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	the climate is delightful &#8212; &amp; the air so clear that when the moon is young I can often <del rend="strikethrough">tho dim</del> &lt;<del rend="strikethrough">distant</del>&gt; distinguish the whole circle. O<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">O: Southey has drawn a moon with one quarter (left side) shaded in.</note> you &amp; <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Robert</ref> may look for this some fine night but I do not remember ever to have observed it in England, nor do I believe the atmosphere is every clear enough there. the stars appear more brilliant here &#8212; but I often look up at the Pleiades as I return home &#8212; &amp; remember how much happier I was when I saw them at Bristol. fare you well &#8212; remember me to all your family kindly &amp; let me know that my friends remember me as well as my enemies.</p>
        <p>[MS missing]</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent8">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I have seen the B. Critic. stupid hounds not to prefer the Monody!<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of Joseph Cottle&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1795) in the <title level="j">British Critic</title>, 6 (November 1795), 539&#8211;540.</note> however our friends there behave very well.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">I have seen ... well: Postscript written upside down at top of fol. 1 r.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>