<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce80</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.80</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 44&#8211;47; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 203&#8211;204 [in part; misdated 24 January 1794].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="80" type="letter">
        <head>80. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Walpole Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-01-04">24 January&#8211;18 February 1794</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand]: H W Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ William Collins Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ <del rend="strikethrough">New Palace Yard</del>/ Maize Hill/ <del rend="strikethrough">Westminster</del>/ Greenwich/ Single<lb /> Stamped: OXFORD<lb />Postmark: [partial] CF/ 19/ 9<lb />Watermarks: G R in a circle; figure of Britannia<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Feb. 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1794<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 44&#8211;47; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 203&#8211;204 [in part; misdated 24 January 1794].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="left">
            <date when="1794-01-24">Friday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 24. 1794.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	Once more am I settled in <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref> &#8212; once more among my friends &#8212; alternately studying &amp; philosophizing &#8212; railing at collegiate folly &amp; enjoying rational society. my prospects in life totally altered &#8212; waiting eagerly to cut up human flesh &amp; resolved to come out &#198;scul&#230;pius<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to Southey&#8217;s medical studies. &#198;scul&#230;pius was the Greek god of medicine and healing.</note> secundus. so much for myself. for you I have more to say &amp; perhaps more to apprehend. as usual your letter partly pleases &amp; altogether distresses me. take care <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> &#8212; the crimes of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Preux were of a less dreadful nature than that of Werter.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Characters in Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712&#8211;1778), <title level="m">Julie, ou la Nouvelle H&#233;lo&#239;se</title> (1761) and Johann von Goethe (1749&#8211;1832), <title level="m">Die Leiden des Jungen Werther</title> (1774). Saint-Preux was in love with a married woman; Werter committed suicide.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I need not tell you with what pleasure my frequent perusals of Werter have been attended. for six months I was never without it in my pocket &#8212; the character is natural. at least it appeared so when tried by the touch-stone of my own heart. yet there are some minds upon which this would operate differently. to use a vulgar proverb &#8220;whats one mans meet is another mans poison. I consider suicide as a crime &#8212; as heinous as irrevocable. if you can suppose a man without connections friends or relations, still suicide would not be justifiable. while there is a possibility that life can be of service to society it is criminal to die.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	the harpsichord at <ref target="places.html#MaizeHill">Maize Hill</ref> vibrated on your heart. I pitied &amp; condemned you. excuse me if I <del rend="strikethrough">expe</del> suspected this from the first. your expressions were too warm for an acquaintance &amp; too empassioned for a friend &#8212;</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1794-02-18">Tuesday. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 18.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	you see how long an interval has elapsed since I began your letter. the various occupations &amp; amusements of a University must plead my excuse. &amp; the decaying state of my eyes now so weak as totally to prevent reading or writing by candle-light must explain what hours I necessarily lose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Continually am I asked at Christ Church, what does <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Bedford</ref> mean to do with himself, &amp; why is he wasting his time. to these questions I can give no answer &#8212; but it is time you should. it is necessary you should absolutely fix. if you chuse one of the three professions &#8212; come to Oxford if the Exchequer do not delay. I have often said this personally to you. you will excuse the repetition as you know the will with which it is made. the University is the place most proper for you, since you want society &amp; know how to select it. do let me soon know what you mean to do. to continue vegetating thus is impossible.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	&amp; now to literary subjects. Glover has written the two Tragedies of Boadicea &amp; Medea.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Glover (1712&#8211;1785; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Boadicia</title> (1753) and <title level="m">Medea</title> (1761).</note> in the first I see but one fault it is that the Romans are treated too respectfully &#8212; the remark has been made by abler critics &amp; will be confirmd by every one who reads the drama. in Medea he has introduced blank lyric but confined them to Iambics &amp; Trochaics. I speak from memory but think it is right. this is all that I have seen of Glovers. <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> however tells me he has written a very beautiful ode upon Astronomy prefixd to Newtons works.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Glover&#8217;s &#8216;Poem on Sir Isaac Newton&#8217;, prefixed to Henry Pemberton's (1694&#8211;1771; <title level="m">DNB</title>) <title level="m">View of Sir Isaac Newton's Philosophy</title> (1728).</note> this I wish much to see, as <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovells</ref> taste is good &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> confirms his judgment of the ode. the Leonidas<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Glover, <title level="m">Leonidas</title> (1737).</note> is a very fine poem in my opinion. J. Warton says it is written with the simplicity of an antient;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Warton (c. 1722&#8211;1800; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">An Essay on the Genius and Writings of Pope</title>, 4th edn, 2 vols (London, 1782), II, p. 401n.</note> when Glover wrote that simplicity of diction was the fashion &#8212; a more vitiated taste prevails at present, since Johnson sonorized our prose &amp; the imitators of Collins &amp; Gray<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title level="m">DNB</title>), William Collins (1721&#8211;1759; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and Thomas Gray (1716&#8211;1771; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> loaded our poetry with awkard imagery &amp; cumbrous metaphor. into this meretricious stile I know myself frequently to have fallen &amp; am pleased to see myself daily reclaiming. simplicity is all in all. you will read the epics of Glover with renewed pleasure upon every perusal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	of blank lyrics my predilection strengthens. Milton Collins Glover &amp; Sayers<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Frank Sayers (1763&#8211;1817; <title level="m">DNB</title>), author of <title level="m">Dramatic Sketches of the Ancient Northern Mythology</title> (1790), which was much admired by Southey.</note> are good names to establish a precedent. I am proud of inventing the new metre in the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> of June &amp; December.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey&#8217;s poems in letters to Bedford of c. 3 June 1793 (Letter 50) and 22 November&#8211;2 December 1793 (Letter 70). Southey published a revised version of his &#8216;Ode written on the first of December 1793&#8217; in <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797).</note> March approaches &amp; another ode with it. if <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">your brother</ref> has read Sayers, Della Crusca,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Merry (1755&#8211;1798; <title level="m">DNB</title>), who adopted the pseudonym &#8216;Della Crusca&#8217;.</note> &amp; Beatties Minstrel<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">James Beattie (1735&#8211;1803; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Minstrel</title> (1771&#8211;1774).</note> I could wish him to send them here with my great coat &amp; boots. tell him so, &amp; let me have my long estranged &amp; long lamented bear as soon as you conveniently can. now do not forget this when you have read the letter &#8212; I remember it <hi rend="ital">feelingly</hi> every morning at chapel.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref> was with us here two hours last night over a bowl of buttered beer. in that way I often see him. to his parties I never am invited, &amp; of course never intrude. we are not so intimate as we were &#8212; perhaps for the reason in Lucan<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcus Annaeus Lucan (AD 39&#8211;65), <title level="m">Pharsalia</title>, Book 1, lines 124&#8211;125.</note> &#8212; he can bear no equal &#8212; I dislike the appearance of assumed superiority &#8212; the presence of one who really is much superior, yet who behaves with modest affability &amp; gives instruction when he seems to seeks it is to me the highest entertainment. for this reason I court <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsleys</ref> company &amp; such society as I meet with at <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref>, whom I see most days.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Our society at <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref> continues the same in number. the freshmen of the term are not estimable (as <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Duppa</ref> says) &amp; we are enough, with the three Corpus men who generally join us. the fiddle with one string is gone, &amp; its place supplied by a harpsichord in <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref> room. <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> still melodizes on the flute &amp; if I had but a Jews Harp the concert would be complete.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	You do not know with what pleasure I opened <ref target="people.html#Deaconfamily">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Deacons</ref> letter, or how its contents damped my spirits for the day. I had been remarkably fond of <ref target="people.html#DeaconKate">Kate</ref>, &amp; expected to hear of her so differently that the news electrified me. do let me know how she is now. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I think delayed <ref target="people.html#Deaconfamily">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Ds</ref> letters if I may judge by the date. you will ease me of much anxiety by writing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I have abjured shooting entirely from the extreme barbarity of the amusement. it gives me pleasure to find my sentiments on the subject similar to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">your brother</ref>. <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> all dislike it equally. you may perhaps receive my Adieu to field sports ere long &#8212; the subject itself is pleasing &#8212; how I may handle it time will best discover. for writing in verse I really have not time, two letters are begun so &#8212; when to be finished I know not. my Botany Bay Eclogues<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey published four &#8216;Botany-Bay Eclogues&#8217; in his <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797). One, &#8216;Elinor&#8217;, had previously appeared anonymously in the <title level="j">Morning Chronicle</title> (18 September 1794). A fifth, &#8216;Edward and Susan&#8217;, was published in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 5 (January 1798).</note> engross my attention at present. one is finished &amp; the second begun. the plan of them you may guess as well as you can from the title till you see them complete. subjects I have plenty &#8212; time &amp; eyesight I want.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	On Friday next my anatomical studies begin. they must be pursued with attention. Apollo<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek god of poetry and medicine.</note> has hitherto only received my devotion as the Deity of Poets. I must now address him as a physician. I could alledge many reasons for my preference of physic. some disagreable circumstances must attend the study but these are more than counterbalanced by the expansion it gives the mind &amp; the opportunities it affords of doing good &#8212; chemistry I must likewise attend. of this study I have always been very fond, &amp; it is now necessary to pursue it with care.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CampbellHenry">Horse Campbell</ref> of course is delighted that I partake his favourite study. he tells he means to acquire a general &#8220;anatomy &amp; divinity I know. this year I shall make myself master of chemistry &amp; botany. study the law next year; &amp; when I know the rudiments of every science after I have taken orders apply myself to excel in any one of them.!!!!!!!!!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	The Dean has obliged <ref target="people.html#CampbellHenry">Horse Campbell</ref> to part with his horse. he wasted two hours for me yesterday in relating the history of his horse &amp; dog. &#8220;<ref target="people.html#PeggeChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pegge</ref> gave him me <del rend="strikethrough">kxx</del> you know, but he prefers my horses company to mine, for they are very loving. the horse put his head &amp; licks the dog all over with his tongue, &amp; so they converse in this manner&#8221; &#8212; &amp; in this manner he converses, whilst I moralize upon the necessity of patience, &amp; say yes &amp; no with all the forbearance of Epictetus.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Stoic philosopher Epictetus (c. AD 60&#8211; after 100), author of the <title level="m">Encheiridion</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <hi rend="ital">Do not forget my great coat &amp;c.</hi>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4">yrs sincerely</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>