<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce146</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.146</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of
                        Wales, MS 4811D.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 20&#8211;24 [in part, where it is dated 26 January
                        1796].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="146" type="letter">
        <head>146. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1796-01-29">29 January [1796]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: CWW Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 5 Stone Buildings/ Lincolns
                        Inn/ London<lb /> Postmark: [partial] M/ 16<lb />Watermark: J
                        LARKING<lb />Endorsement: Southey/ Jan 29/ 1796<lb />MS: National Library of
                        Wales, MS 4811D<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title level="m">Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 20&#8211;24 [in part, where it is dated 26 January
                        1796].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="left">
            <address>
              <placeName>Lisbon.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1796-01-29">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 29.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am safe &amp; in health &#8212; &amp; after a temper[MS torn]
                    sea a journey of eight hundred miles in Spain, &amp; an earthquake at
                    Lisbon, this is more than I had reason to expect. our passage was very bad &#8212; the
                    dead lights were up sixty hours &#8212; the danger was magnified by my apprehensions
                    &amp; the unskillfulness of Spanish sailours &#8212; &amp; I can now form a
                    tolerable idea of what a man feels at the point of death. we remained five days
                    at Coru&#241;a &#8212; the only place where I met with the society I wished. <ref target="people.html#JardineAlexander">Jardine</ref> is Consul there &#8212; you
                    have probably waded thro his travels<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Jardine (d. 1799; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Letters from Barbary, France, Spain, Portugal &amp;c.</title>
                        (1788).</note> &#8212; a book that conveys much thought in a most uninteresting
                    manner. such at least was the opinion I formed of it three years ago. he behaved
                    to me with that degree of attention that soon produces intimacy &#8212; my time at
                    Coruna was chiefly spent at his house &amp; he gave &lt;me&gt; much
                    information respecting the country. I met a singular character<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> there. the filthiest of
                    Spaniards with the finest of physiognomies. he was a monk &#8212; but has walked to
                    Rome to procure a dispensation from his vows, &amp; now employs his time in
                    writing poetry. he lives with his brother a man of some fortune &#8212; &amp;
                    enjoys all the luxury of dirt &amp; indolence the two characteristics of a
                    Spaniard. we conversed in Latin with some difficulty on account of our different
                    pronunciations. he told me that they were very far behind the rest of Europe in
                    literature, but said he crossing his hands &#8212; our hands are tied ist&#226; terribile
                    Inquisitione! I learnt afterwards that his opinions were atheistical &#8212; &amp;
                    indeed I believe there is no medium in the country between the most gross
                    ignorance &#8212; &amp; atheism.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> our journey to Madrid (400 miles) took up eighteen days &amp;
                    a half &#8212; we were up before day break &amp; travelled till after sunset. of
                    the posadas &#8212; you never can have seen an exaggerated account. miserable hovels
                    of filth &amp; wretchedness &#8212; yet we met with the greatest civility. in both
                    countries the peasantry are very hospitable &amp; eager to accommodate &#8212; it
                    is true they are apt to impose upon travellers but this is the case every where,
                    &amp; it is easy to excuse extortion when it arises from want. the higher
                    classes are despicable &#8212; &amp; the whole body of people depraved beyond all
                    my ideas of licentiousness. the Queen of Spain<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Louisa (1751&#8211;1819), wife of Carlos IV (1748&#8211;1819; reigned
                        1788&#8211;1808).</note> travels publicly with her Cortegos<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Queen of Spain was reputed to have a series
                        of lovers.</note> &#8212; &amp; certain families go with the King<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Carlos IV.</note> &#8212; because (say the people
                    here) he cannot do without a wife. You may know a Portuguese nobleman by the
                    feeble &amp; blighted body he inherits from the vice of his ancestors. <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx</del> vice is now more general &#8212; &amp; its
                    consequent disease almost universal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Over the &lt;departed&gt; spirit of [MS torn]ish
                    gallantry &#8212; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Burke might pronounce with propriety a
                    funeral oration. <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Burke&#8217;s
                        (1729/30&#8211;1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>) <title level="m">Reflections on
                            the Revolution in France</title> (London, 1790), lamented that &#8216;the age
                        of chivalry is gone&#8217; (p. 113).</note> [MS torn] American charge
                        d&#8217;affairs<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Either William Carmichael
                        (c. 1739&#8211;1795), American charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires in Madrid, 1783&#8211;1794, or his
                        successor William Short (1759&#8211;1849), American charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires in Madrid,
                        1794&#8211;1795.</note> &lt;at Madrid&gt; lived with a friends wife at the
                    hotel for a week while the husband was in the country. but adultery is
                    universal. a Swiss Officer in the English service &#8212; gave the Marq. Santiago<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The incident is related in full in
                        Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain
                            and Portugal</title> (London, 1797), pp. 114&#8211;115.</note> the lie in his
                    own house &amp; beat him; while we were at Madrid. he remained three days in
                    expectation of a challenge &#8212; &amp; then took himself out of the reach of
                    assassination. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have heard by the papers how the two Kings of Brentford<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to the meeting in 1796 of the
                        monarchs of Spain and Portugal. The comparison is with two mythical
                        characters (&#8216;Kings&#8217; of the Essex town of Brentford &#8212; a place renowned for
                        its dirtiness), whose existence seems to derive from George Villiers, 2nd
                        Duke of Buckingham (1628&#8211;1687; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Rehearsal</title> (1672), a satire on heroic tragedy. A
                        &#8216;mock&#8217; play within Villiers&#8217;s play includes a scene in which the two Kings
                        of Brentford enter hand in hand. In the next century, the phrase entered
                        into wider cultural use; see for example, William Cowper (1731&#8211;1800; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Task, a Poem, in Six
                            Books</title> (London, 1785), p. 5.</note> are to meet. we followed the
                    Spanish court. their train amounted to seven thousand people. &amp; they
                    have marked their way by dirting all the linen &#8212; eating up all the provisions
                    cutting up the roads &#8212; burning &amp; mutilating the trees &#8212; &amp;
                    leaving dead mules horses &amp; asses. at every place we heard complaints &#8212;
                    for not a real had been paid. once they enquired if they were come to pay the
                    Kings debts. They apprehend at Madrid that the King will fix his court elsewhere
                    &#8212; they dislike that place &#8212; &amp; the Queen (a woman very ugly very
                    abandoned &amp; very unpopular) has <del rend="strikethrough">hardly</del>
                    seldom entered it since some seditious washerwomen insulted her two years ago.
                    &#8220;you amuse yourself with your cortegos &amp; dress yourself in your jewels
                    while we are in want of bread&#8221; &#8212; cried the old girls &#8212; &amp; they are now in
                    perpetual confinement. his Majesty is a mighty Hunter, &amp; in the
                    neighbourhood of Merida killed birds innumerable &#8212; five wolves &amp; a pole
                    cat. we saw a cart load of stags horns which he sent to the palace at
                    Madrid.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> the name of an Englishman is a passport thro Spain &#8212; &amp;
                    the only place where we met with incivility was where they thought us French. I
                    am informed that the contrary is the case in those provinces where the French
                    penetrated. &#8212; we broke down three times upon the road, &amp; once slept in
                    the room with a barber surgeon &amp; his wife.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> this Doctor asked <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref> on finding he was an
                    Englishman if he believed in a God. &#8212; &amp; in Jesus Christ too? ask<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> him (said his son-in-law in a whisper loud
                    enough to be heard) ask him &#8212; if he believes in the Virgin Mary.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> as for vermin &#8212; Apollo was fool for fleaing Marsyas<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The legend that Apollo, Greek god of poetry and
                        music, was challenged by the satyr, Marsyas, to a musical contest. Marsyas
                        lost, and Apollo tied him to a tree and flayed him alive.</note> &#8212; he should
                    have put him to bed in Spain &amp; he would have skinned himself by the
                    morning. rich tracks of land are uncultivated for want of hands &amp; so we
                    have often travelled five or six hours without seeing any trace of man except
                    the agreable memento of a few monumental crosses. there are always a great
                    number of children in the neighbourhood of a convent. &amp; this
                    &lt;remark&gt; scandalous as it may seem forces itself upon a
                    traveller.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> no situation can be worse than that of Madrid &#8212; exposed to the
                    extremes of heat &amp; cold, &amp; at &lt;such&gt; a distance
                    from the sea. the necessaries of life are very dear, &amp; the comforts are
                    not to be purchased. we were fifteen days on the road to Lisbon where I arrived
                    after crossing the Tagus at night in a high wind &#8212; to the disappointment of
                    finding no packet had arrived from England since we left it &#8212; &amp; to be
                    awakened at five the next morning by an earthquake, the severest that has been
                    felt since the great one. the people are very much alarmed. it is the seventh
                    shock [MS torn] the beginning of November &#8212; some walls &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> a cross from one of the churches were thrown
                    down by it &#8212; &amp; they say most houses must be weakened so much that
                    another shock if equally strong would destroy them: so much are they alarmed
                    that two persons in the circle of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my
                        Uncles</ref> acquaintance have already removed to a lower situation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter reached me before I left Falmouth. ther[MS torn]
                    wa[MS torn] sinking of the heart when night &amp; distance hid the shore
                    from [MS torn]yond any feeling I could have conceived &#8212; to look round upon such
                    a waste of waters! I was very sick till Fear conquered sickness. the fatigue of
                    travelling did not affect me, tho Ld B<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> [MS torn] who accompanied us to Madrid was almost
                    knocked up by[MS torn] was voracious &amp; perhaps this supplied the want of
                    re[MS torn] allowed very little. I lay awake one whole night t[MS torn] as they
                    settled upon my face.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &amp; of what advantage has this journey been to me? why I
                    have learnt to thank God that I am an Englishman &#8212; for tho things are not quite
                    so well there as in El Dorado<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Legendary
                        gold mines in Spanish America.</note> &#8212; they are better than any where
                        else.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of the sentiments
                        of Dr Pangloss in Voltaire&#8217;s (1694&#8211;1778), <title level="m">Candide, ou
                            l&#8217;Optimisme</title> (1759).</note> I know no news later than the fifth
                    of December &#8212; &amp; indeed I now think so much of private life that public
                    affairs affect me little. I have every reason to expect happiness &#8212; &amp;
                    yet dare not expect it &#8212; my prospects in life have varied so often that I almost
                    doubt the stability of any one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So is my fixed intention to quit this country in May. I came here
                    in compliance with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mothers</ref>
                    earnest wishes &#8212; I have reaped instruction, <del rend="strikethrough">xx
                        xxxx</del> &lt;for&gt; I did &lt;not&gt; expect pleasure.
                    the acquisition of two languages is valuable. I go this evening to an Abb&#232; for
                    the first time, to converse in French. this <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my Uncle</ref> is earnest with me to
                    acquire. &#8212; I had begun to speak a little Spanish when we entered Portugal,
                    &amp; find little difficulty in corrupting it into Portuguese.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> the society of this place is very irksome. the men have no ideas
                    but of business, &amp; tho the women are accomplished &#8212; yet their company
                    only makes the absence of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">one woman</ref>
                    more painful. I cannot play with a <del rend="strikethrough">fan</del> ladies
                    fan &amp; talk nonsense to her &#8212; &amp; this is all the men here are
                    capable of doing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have the maladie du pays &#8212; &amp; a very wearying disorder
                    it is. gladly would I exchange the golden Tagus with the olive &amp; orange
                    groves of Portugal &#8212; for the mud encumbered tide of Avon &amp; a glimpse of
                    Bristol smoke.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Were there leisure in this place I should write a tragedy &#8212; for I
                    struck out a strange subject on the road &#8212; one that if it be not too bold
                    &amp; eccentric is capable of great effect. I have sometimes thought of Inez
                    de Castro &amp; of the revenge of Pedro<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Inez de Castro (1325&#8211;1355) was the daughter of a Castilian
                        nobleman. She secretly married the Portuguese crown prince, Pedro
                        (1320&#8211;1367; reigned 1357&#8211;1367). When Pedro&#8217;s father, Alphonso IV (1291&#8211;1357;
                        reigned 1325&#8211;1357), discovered the marriage, he ordered her murder. On
                        Pedro&#8217;s succession to the Portuguese throne in 1357, he took revenge on his
                        wife&#8217;s killers.</note> &#8212; as the spring advances I shall make a pilgrimage to
                    the tomb of Inez<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Inez de Castro&#8217;s tomb
                        is at the Alcoba&#231;a Monastery in central Portugal.</note> &#8212; tis about two
                    days journey from Lisbon.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>direct to me with <ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">Rev. Herbert
                            Hill</ref>. Lisbon.</p>
          <p>tis almost two years since we have seen each other &#8212; &amp; the Bay of
                        Biscay is between us!</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>