<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce182</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.182</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Houghton Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (16).  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="182" type="letter">
        <head>182. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Walpole Bedford</ref>, 13 October 1796<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: H. W. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single<lb />Postmark: AOC/ 17/ 96<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            <lb />MS: Houghton Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (16)<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1796-10-13">Thursday Oct. 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1796.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>Bristol.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	To India &#8212; Horace! if you have not found happiness among your friends in England do you expect to find it without them in that detestable country? the worthless return from those polluted shores with wealth &amp; honors &#8212; I have heard of one great man &amp; only one who adventurd there &#8212; &amp; Camoens<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis Vaz de Camo&#235;ns (c. 1524&#8211;1580), author of <title level="m">The Lusiad</title> (1572).</note> returned to perish with poverty. surely there is room enough in England: you are younger than I am &#8212; &amp; I have not yet set out on my &#8220;way of life.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	tell me my dear <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> would not the frequent company of a friend whose mind met yours &#8212; remove half the gloom that darkens the morning of your days? <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> is not that friend &#8212; because you live with him. the food of Love is the poison of friendship. I wish I were in London. perhaps I could remove the &lt;religious&gt; doubts that disquiet you. for <hi rend="ital">I have disbelieved</hi>. perhaps I could cure your heresy as to Women for I am married.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	in other points we should probably agree. I think as badly of the mob of mankind as you can do &#8212; but perhaps admit more exceptions to the general rule. you likewise must know how many of our vices &amp; miseries spring from existing institutions. I believe <hi rend="ital">all</hi> of them <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	in all the anxiety that has fallen to my lot &#8212; &amp; I have had my share &#8212; literary occupations have afforded me a resource. poetry has been with me a passion &amp; I am indebted to it as well for happiness, as for bread. whilst employed about Joan of Arc I was tempest-tost on the ocean of life &#8212; but at the moments of composition &#8212; I soard eagle like into the regions of tranquillity above the storm. I was no longer R.S. pennyless &#8212; &amp; doubtful of tomorrows dinner with all my &lt;own&gt; feelings I was transplanted into the wise wildness of Conrade &#8212; or the dignified resignation of the Maid of Orleans. <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> these pleasures are in your power: I have long laid aside the hypocritical language of compliment. the poetry which you have ever sent me evinces powers capable of greatness. cultivate them <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>. <del rend="strikethrough">after xx</del> &lt;let us&gt; have ploughed our fields &amp; manure our pasture grounds &#8212; but let not the flower garden be neglected. you would be happier if your mind were occupied. why not employ it, till you are more settled, in writing a book if the book be bad burn it when it is done &#8212; you will have at least exercised your mind &amp; by exercise only can the mind as well as the body be kept healthful. the water that stagnates will corrupt.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	no <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> Ignorance &amp; Vice shall not eternally coexist with Folly. for Folly &amp; Vice are the children of Ignorance, &amp; their existence by a wise mystery linkd to that of their mother. when you are in your heart an Optimist you will be happy. I feel that I can convince you no medium can exist between Optimism &amp; Atheism &#8212; &amp; Atheism is a self-evident absurdity.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	if you want a book &#8212; read S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pierres Etudes de la Nature.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques-Henri Bernardin de Saint-Pierre (1737&#8211;1814), <title level="m">Etudes de la Nature</title> (1784).</note> it is enough to say that he deserved to be the friend of Jean Jacques Rousseau. I think of publishing a volume of Selections from the Early English Poets &#8212; with copious essays critical &amp;c. the volume publishd by Edwards<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George Ellis (1753&#8211;1815; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Specimens of the Early English Poets</title> (1790) was published by the London bookseller James Edwards (1756&#8211;1816; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> is totally destitute of taste as far as regards the compiler. I have a good many valuable books &#8212; &amp; perhaps M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Reid &amp; Lodge<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly friends of the Bedfords and possessors of their own private collection of books.</note> would allow me the range of their libraries &#8212; as I know <ref target="people.html#ProbyJohnCarysfort">Ld Carysfort</ref> would. I could thro <ref target="people.html#NaresRobert">Nares</ref> have access to the Museum. &amp; I believe I [MS torn] possess those powers for the work which alone can re[MS torn] any other circumstances valuable. to have a book in [MS torn] press is my hobby. I now <hi rend="ital">drive a pair</hi>. a volume of poems is advancing as well as my letters. I expect more praise than profit &#8212; Joan of Arc sells slowly. a matter of consequence to me only as it retards a second edition. the book has had no friends to push it. my private list of subscribers did not amount to thirty &#8212; &amp; of these nine were from the relations of my dear <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref> &#8212; a man whom I must always love &amp; lament.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I shall live a secluded life in London. probably without ever making another friend. the repellent coldness of my <del rend="strikethrough">silence</del> manners will protect me from any acquaintance. for I cover the milk of human kindness with as <del rend="strikethrough">coarse</del> &lt;rough&gt; an outside as the Cocoa nut.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Your brother</ref> has talkd to me of a club. I wish to decline it &#8212; tho perhaps in vain. notoriety is not comfortable <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>. if ever I reach the cot of Independance &#8212; I will prefer changing my name to being persecuted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	if Jupiter<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In Roman mythology, Jupiter, the king of the gods, descended in a golden shower to the mortal woman Danae.</note> would descend in a golden shower to me &#8212; I would allow him to rain hard enough to break my head. whenever he does come &#8212; whenever I can realise a small independance I will pitch my tent near the sea &#8212; &amp; take down the harp from the wall. alas <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> the strings may be untund &#8212; &amp; the hand that strikes them now &#8212; witherd &amp; feeble by age! God bless you &amp; make you as happy </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2">	as Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent3">			the married man.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>