<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce2</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 44796 .  Previously  published: Roland Baughman, &#8216;Southey the
						Schoolboy&#8217;, Huntington Library Quarterly, 7 (1944), 254&#8211;256.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2" type="letter">
        <head>2. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Charles Collins</ref>, <date when="1791-12-10">10 [&#8211;11] December
						1791</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Mr C Collins/ Maize Hill/ Greenwich/ near/ London<lb /> Stamped:
						BATH<lb /> Endorsement: Answerd<lb /> MS: Huntington Library, HM 44796<lb /> Previously published: Roland Baughman, &#8216;Southey the
						Schoolboy&#8217;, <title level="j">Huntington Library Quarterly</title>, 7 (1944), 254&#8211;256.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="indent4">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#DukeStBath">Bath.</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1791-12-10">Saturday. December 10 &#8211; 1791.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Collins</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first hours of my arrival are devoted to you &amp; you will excuse the inaccuries which fall from the pen
					of one tormented with a horrible head ache. <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> will be in town Monday next see him
					as my substitute at <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> &amp; settle whatever you think proper in
					my name but insist upon avowing the paper from Westminster as otherwise it must descend to oblivion &amp; the chandlers shop.
					by dating it thence it will burst into notice very probably acquire correspondents &amp; insure a good local sale. old
					Westminsters at Oxford &amp; Cambridge will be glad to see some sparks of genius from their old habitation. should it fail it
					cannot well be worse than the Trifler <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">The Trifler: A New Periodical
							Miscellany by Timothy Touchstone of St Peter&#8217;s College, Westminster</title> (1788) was a short-lived magazine published by
						pupils at Westminster School.</note> should it succeed it will retrieve the reputation of the school &amp; establish our
					own. Allow me to say I do not much doubt of success. naturally sanguine in my expectations I think I may be so now with justice.
						<ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> are either of
					them equal to any of the authors of the Trifler &amp; if I thought my verses only equal to those in that paper I would burn
					every line. remember what <ref target="people.html#RoughWilliam">Rough</ref> said the other day &amp; allow my vanity not half
					so bad as if I affected modesty.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In my journey down a train of ideas crowded into my mind about the holyday task &amp; I fancy I shall succeed &#8211;
					first invoke Winter describe his seat amongst the Andes &#8211; Iceland &#8211; the Glaciers. Lapland. Siberia, the exiles there. then paint
					the climate of India &amp; the insufferable heat. happy climate of England. the pleasures of a wintry season. Christmas. the
					games of chess &amp; backgammon by the fire. theatres. assemblies &#8211; dancing. &amp; conclude with considering Winter in a
					moral light. I forgot to arrange Ovid <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Ovidius Naso (43 BC&#8211;AD 17) was exiled from
						Rome to Tomis on the Black Sea.</note> in exile properly. take the few lines of the beginning.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3"> Sovereign of the shivering hall</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Thee o Winter thee I call</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Come then from thy frozen seat</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Come from thy secret sad retreat</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Come with all thy train along</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Come inspire the festive throng.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">High where the sullen Andes rear their heads</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> There holds the hoary sire his silent reign</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Where aye the snow a silver mantle spreads</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> When the hot dog star scorches all the plain. <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A complete version of the
							poem is in the Houghton Library, MS Eng 265.2.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>some images from Job may be introduced here &amp; I think I can extend it to an hundred or 150 lines without flagging.</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1791-12-11">Sunday Morning</date>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall to day send a paragraph to the Argus <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A radical London daily
						newspaper that ran between 1789&#8211;1792. It is not possible to confirm that Southey did place a paragraph in the <title level="m">Argus</title>, as the issues from December 1791 have not survived.</note> stating that a new periodical publication is to
					be expected shortly from Westminster &#8211; it will naturally excite the curiosity of the people &amp; they will wait with some
					impatience for it. as you will see young <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> tell him my direction that he may
					write &amp; give me his. a letter directed to me at <ref target="places.html#DukeStBath">No 9 Duke Street Bath</ref> will come
					safe. and now as I have nothing else to say take a story I read yesterday as a true one which strikes me as an instance of more
					refined barbarity than any in the annals of cruelty &#8211; a prisoner in the dreary cells of the Bastile had familiarized a spider the
					only tenant except himself of the miserable spot. to a man secluded thus from the light of day &amp; every living creature
					this reptile was a kind of mournful companion. the Keeper at length took notice of it &amp; told the Governor &#8211; the Governor
					commanded him to tread upon it. <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Wollstonecraft (1759&#8211;1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Original Stories from Real Life</title> (London, 1791), pp. 27&#8211;28.</note> I have read
					instances of barbarity which have made my blood run cold but never did I meet with so wanton so refind a one before. I know not
					whether this may strike you as forcibly as it does me. an animal which time has rendered dear to one becomes as an old friend
					&amp; we feel the same reluctance to part from it. I rememb[MS torn] owl died I could have cried now what must this poor
					wretch have felt [MS torn] companion he was ever like to have crushd to atoms by the wanton tre[MS torn] inhumanity? I certainly
					will introduce the story in some ode one of[MS torn]</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In all probability you are tired with wading thro this epistle &amp; as I[MS torn]</p>
        <p>except that I shall be very glad to hear from you very often[MS torn]</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yours sincerely</salute>
        </closer>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>