<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce30</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.30</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                        Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 165&#8211;168 [in part].Dating note: Misdated 20
                        November, the date it was received by Grosvenor Charles Bedford, in Southey
                        (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="30" type="letter">
        <head>30. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1792-11-16">[16&#8211;17 November
                        1792]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address:
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Old Palace Yard/
                        Westminster<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: ANO/ 19/ 92<lb />Watermark: G
                        R in a circle and figure of Britannia<lb />Seal: Red wax [design
                        illegible]<lb />Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1792./ Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>; Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                            Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 20. 1792<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                        Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 165&#8211;168 [in part].<lb />Dating note: Misdated 20
                        November, the date it was received by Grosvenor Charles Bedford, in Southey
                        (ed.),
                            <title level="m">Life and Correspondence</title>.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1792-11-16">Friday night.</date>
            <date when="1792-11-17">Saturday morn night.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Bedford</salute>
        </opener>
        <p>[central part of fol. 1 r contains Southey&#8217;s sketch of a church]</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I question not but you will surprized at my sending a church
                    neither remarkable for beauty of design or neatness of execution &#8212; waving
                    however all apologies for either if at some future period you are disposed to
                    visit the &#8220;narrow house&#8221; of your friend when he shall be at supper not where he
                    eats but where he is eaten<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">Hamlet</title>, Act 4, scene 3, line 19.</note> you will find
                    it on the other side of this identical church &#8212; the very covering of the vault
                    affords as striking an emblem of mortality as would even the mouldering tenants
                    of the tomb. yesterday I know not from what strange humour I visited it for the
                    second time in my life. the former occasion was mournful &amp; no earthly
                    consideration shall ever draw me there upon a like. my pilgrimage yesterday was
                    merely the result of a meditating moment when philosophy had flatterd itself
                    into apathy. I am really astonished when I reflect upon the indifference with
                    which I so minutely surveyd the heaving turf which inclosed within its cold
                    bosom ancestors upon whom fortune bestowed rather more of her smiles than she
                    has done upon their descendants &#8212; men who content with an independant patrimony
                    lay hid from the world too obscure to be noticed by it &#8212; too elevated to fear
                    its insults &#8212; those days are past &#8212; . three Edward Hill&#8217;s<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The ancestors of Southey&#8217;s mother,
                        Margaret.</note> there sleep for ever the fourth alienated &amp;
                    estranged from all his kin yet lives at a distance. I send the epitaph which at
                    present is inscribed upon one of the cankerd sides. perhaps the production of
                    some one of my forefathers who possessd more piety than poetry.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Farewell this World</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> With all Its Vanity</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Wee hope through Christ</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> To live Eternally</l>
        </lg>
        <p>You have the exact orthography &amp; this inscription will probably cover the
                    remains of one who has written so much for others &amp; must be content with
                    so humble an epitaph himself, unless you will furnish him with one more
                    characteristical.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Were the million to know of this visit to the family vault they
                    would stile it want of feeling &#8212; the Ds<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to <ref target="people.html#DolignonLouisa">Louisa
                            Dolignon</ref> and her sisters.</note> would call it want of principle &#8212;
                    I only say if I am not the better for it till my last visit this heart is worse
                    than I really believe it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Were you to walk over the village (Ashton)<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A village two miles south-west of
                        Bristol.</note> with me, you would like me be tempted to repine that I have
                    no earthly mansion there. it is the most enchanting spot which nature can
                    produce &#8212; my rambles would be much more frequent were it not for certain
                    reflections not altogether of a pleasant nature which must always recur &#8212; I
                    cannot wander like a stranger over lands which once were my forefathers nor pass
                    those doors which are now no more open without feeling emotions altogether
                    inconsistent with pleasure &amp; irreconcileabl with the indifference of
                    philosophy &#8212; what is there <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> contained in that word of such mighty virtue &#8212; it has been
                    sounded in the ear of Common Sense till she is deafend &amp; overpowerd with
                    the clamour. artifice &amp; Vanity have reard up the pageant &#8212; science has
                    adorned it &amp; the multitude have beheld at distance &amp; adord &#8212; it
                    is applied indiscriminately to vice &amp; virtue &#8212; to the exalted ideas of
                    Socrates the metaphysical charms of Plato &#8212; the frigid maxims of Aristotle, the
                    unfeeling dictates of the Stoics &amp; the beasty disciples of the defamed
                        Epicurus.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Epicurus (341&#8211;270 BC),
                        Greek philosopher, founder of Epicureanism.</note> Rousseau was called a
                    philosopher whilst he possessd sensibility the most poignant &#8212; Voltaire was
                    dignified with the name when he deserved the blackest stigmas from every man of
                    principle. whence is all this seeming absurdity? or why should Reason be dazzled
                    with the name when she cannot but perceive its imbecility.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> so far I wrote last night &#8212; upon running it over I find you will
                    conceive you have a rhapsody for the Flagellant<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A schoolboy magazine devised by Southey and his friends, it
                        was forced to cease publication after nine issues.</note> instead of a
                    letter, &amp; really had I continued it in the same mood it would have been
                    little different. if I had any knowledge of drawing I would send you some of the
                    most pleasing views you can conceive whether rural melancholy pleasing or grand
                    &#8212; at some future period I hope to show you the place &amp; you will then
                    judge whether or not I have praised it too lavishly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think it is one month since the date of your last letter
                    &amp; about ten weeks since that of <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref>. he can plead some excuse &amp; quote me for an example &#8212;
                    you cannot. surely in a month you might find one hour when you were extricated
                    from mouldy parchments &amp; moth eaten records &#8212; you promised me a long
                    letter six weeks back &amp; I think your promises more sincere than <ref target="people.html#VincentWilliam">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Vincents</ref>!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> in the course of next summer the Duke of Portland<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland
                        (1738&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783 and
                        1807&#8211;1809, was installed as Chancellor of the University of Oxford on 1 July
                        1793.</note> will be installed at Oxford &#8212; the spectacle is only inferior to
                    a coronation. I have rooms there &amp; am glad of the opportunity to offer
                    them to you. we are permitted to have men in college upon the occasion &#8212; the
                    whole University make up the procession &lt;I would ask <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> too but he will then have
                    rooms of his own&gt; &#8212; it will be worth seeing as perhaps coronations like
                    the secular games will soon be as a tale that is told.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> within this half hour I have received a letter from &lt;<ref target="people.html#HillHerbert">my uncle</ref> at&gt; Lisbon, chiefly
                    upon a subject which I have been much employed with since March 1st I will shew
                    it you when we meet &#8212; it is such as I expected from one who has been to me more
                    than a parent &#8212; without asperity without reproaches &#8212; had it had either I should
                    have despised it &#8212; tomorrow I answer it &amp; as he has desired, send him
                    the Flagellants &#8212; I then hope to drop the subject for ever in this world &#8212; in
                    the next all heart are open &amp; no mans intentions are hid!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I can now tell you one of the uses of Philosophy &#8212; it teaches us
                    to search for applause from within &amp; to despise the flattery or the
                    abuse of the world alike &#8212; to attend only to an inward monitor to be superior to
                    fortune &#8212; such are its real virtues &#8212; why then is the name so prostituted? do
                    give me a lecture upon Philosophy &amp; teach me how to become a Philosopher
                    &#8212; the title is pretty &#8212; &amp; surely the Philosophic S. would sound as well
                    as the Philosophic Hume<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">David Hume
                        (1711&#8211;1776; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> or the Ph of Ferney.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Voltaire, Fran&#231;ois-Marie Arouet
                        (1694&#8211;1778), French writer and <hi rend="ital">philosophe</hi> who owned an
                        estate at Ferney.</note> would it &lt;not&gt; be as truely
                    applied?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am loth to part with my poor Flagellants. they have cost me
                    very dear &amp; perhaps I shall never see them more &#8212; one copy ought to be
                    preserved in order to contradict the inventions of future malice &#8212;. are you not
                    ashamed of your idleness?</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent8">R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> if I can one day have the honor of writing after my name,
                        fellow of <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Baliol College</ref> that
                        will be the extent of my preferment &#8212; sometimes I am tempted to think that I
                        was sent into this world for a different employment &#8212; but as the play says
                        beware of the beast that has three legs &#8212; now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> as you might
                        long puzzle to discover the genus of this beast know that his grasp is
                        always mortal &#8212; that &#8212; in short &#915;&#928;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey has drawn 3 down strokes joined at
                            the head by a horizontal stroke.</note> but as that drawing wants
                        explanation as much if not more than the description know it is the gallows
                        &#8212;. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> about the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of January I begin my
                        residence at Oxford where the prime of my life is to pass in acquiring
                        knowledge &#8212; which when I begin to have some idea of it will be cut short by
                        the Doctor who levels all ranks &amp; degrees &#8212; is it not rather
                        disgraceful at the moment when Europe is on fire with freedom &#8212; when Men
                        &amp; Monarchs are contending to sit &amp; study Euclid<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Euclid of Alexandria (dates uncertain,
                            between 325 and 250 BC), mathematician. His work includes the <title level="m">Elements</title>.</note> &amp; Hugo Grotius?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Hugo Grotius (1583&#8211;1645), Dutch
                            statesman and writer on international law.</note> &#8212; Pindar says a good
                        button-maker is spoilt in making a King<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wolcot, &#8216;Peter Pindar&#8217; (1738&#8211;1819; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Lousiad: An Heroi-comic Poem.
                                Canto I</title> (London, 1785), p. 18.</note> &#8212; what will be spoilt
                        when I made a fellow of <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Baliol</ref>? that question I cannot resolve. I can only say that I have
                        spoilt a sheet of paper &amp; you 15 minutes in reading it &#8212; NB. if you
                        do not soon answer it you will spoil my temper.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>