<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce34</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.34</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                    22.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="34" type="letter">
        <head>34. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1792-12-06">6 December
                        1792</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles
                        Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Old Palace Yard/ Westminster./ Single
                        Sheet<lb /> Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: CDE/ 8/ 92<lb />Watermark: G R in a
                        circle and figure of Britannia<lb />Endorsement: 6 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        1792<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                    22<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <time>Thursday evening.</time>
            <address>
              <placeName>College Green.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1792-12-06">Dec. 6. 1792.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The heat of temper occasioned by political madness must plead in
                    excuse of my last letter &#8212; never will I venture in writing upon the subject
                    again. vox audita perit litera scripta manet<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A commonplace saying, which translates as, &#8216;The spoken word
                        perishes, but the written word remains&#8217;.</note> &#8212; &amp; so if you will
                    burn my paper upon suicide you will destroy the only monument of your friends
                    sophistical impiety. tomorrow sees the rough copy demolished &#8212; I should be glad
                    the one you have were to meet the same fate but perhaps you may like to keep it
                    as a memento of my boyish faults &amp; a check upon future vanity &#8212; when
                    some over officious friends put a Doctor of Divinity<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> to argue me into quitting the Flagellant
                    &#8212; after I had answered all he could say his last resource was to mention the
                    uneasiness my relations would feel at the continuance. I instantly yielded
                    though not without observing that no self-motive should ever have prevailed &#8212;
                    the Reverend Doctor sneered at the romantic affectation of a boy. till that
                    moment I had only felt the character with pleasure &#8212; I then owned it with
                    pride.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> the same boyish sentiments made me forget <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> &amp; myself when I
                    last wrote &#8212;. there was a time when I loved <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> as if he had been my
                    brother but it was when the natural purity &amp; sensibility of
                    &lt;his&gt; character were neither obscured by vanity nor hardened by
                    his wish for the applause of those whom he despised. at that period he
                    entertained the same sentiments for me. but when <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">G S</ref> was willing to do every idle
                    blockheads exercise &amp; contented himself with doing good exercises
                    &amp; neglecting every other study, the applause of the <ref target="people.html#VincentWilliam">Doctor</ref> &amp; the Dunces made
                    him above that friend who was always friendly enough to tell him of his faults.
                    Grif Lloyd<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Griffith Lloyd (d. 1843),
                        educated at Westminster School and Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1797).</note>
                    thought him the cleverest fellow in school &#8212; Jack Shepherd<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard John Stracey Shepherd (dates unknown),
                        educated at Westminster School (admitted 1785) and Trinity College,
                        Cambridge (adm. 1792).</note> lookd up to him as an oracle &amp; the
                    Kings Scholars with the virtuous <ref target="people.html#HookJames">Hook</ref>
                    made him their confident &#8212; (by the by I have a story of Hook presently.) the
                    only notice he had for some time taken of me was his contemptuous jests till the
                    commencement of the Flagellant.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        schoolboy magazine devised by Southey and his friends, it was forced to
                        cease publication after nine issues.</note> his behaviour then is well know
                    to you <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">your brother</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#CombeEdward">Combe</ref>
          <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lamb</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#RoughWilliam">Rough</ref>. what a character <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Stracheys</ref> would make for a number
                    said I to <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lamb</ref> one night &#8212;
                    talking to him the next day upon &lt;the subject&gt; <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">L</ref> repeated what I had said. <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">S</ref> immediately comes to me glowing
                    with anger. (it was in school) I understand said he you intend drawing my
                    character for the Flagellant &#8212; if you do I only say that I will immediately send
                    your name to the &lt;news&gt;paper &amp; act up the work. I was hurt
                    &amp; could not help telling him that if he had been as much my friend as
                    formerly he never could have believed my intentions were such. &#8220;but <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> do not think I am
                    intimidated by your threats. whatever you can do in injury of the Fl. I can
                    despise.&#8221; I felt afterwards angry with myself &amp; was more than once upon
                    the point of apologizing &#8212; but it would have looked like fear. after my retreat
                    from Westminster his significant smiles &amp; shrugs might have intimated
                    the real cause to anyone &#8212; that however was of no object to me the expulsion was
                    a thing I could only glory in. after this I did wrong ever to write to <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> &#8212; still however if you
                    think my letter wrong I will apologize for it &#8212; I will own myself to blame but
                    never never desire his correspondence. I have not answerd his letter &#8212; the
                    destined answer lies in my portfolio to prove perhaps one day that it was not
                    conscious faultiness that held me silent. if the same fortune hitherto attendant
                    upon me &amp; mine, should every bring this head to the block, some hireling
                    scribbler in ripping up my faults &amp; follies will not pass over this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been reading Eheu fugaces<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace (65&#8211;8 BC), <title level="m">Odes</title>, Book 2, no.
                        14, line 1. The Latin translates as &#8216;Alas [the years slide by] so
                        fleetingly&#8217;.</note> &amp; your translation this moment together. the
                    three last stanzas are certainly best but altogether it is in my opinion very
                    good &#8212; tho &#8216;th&#8217;unpardoning God&#8217; I do not like the epithet is rather prosaic &#8212;
                    (you see I will point out what appears to me as faulty) a better may easily be
                    found. &amp; now as I have picked your bone take mine to pick cum notis
                    Sancti Basilii.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as
                        &#8216;with notes by St Basil&#8217;. St Basil (c. 330&#8211;379), founder of eastern
                        monasticism. Basil was a pseudonym used by Southey, particularly in his
                        writing for <title level="m">The Flagellant</title> (1792).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent3">Ille &amp; nefasti te posuit die &amp;c<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace, <title level="m">Odes</title>, Book 2,
                        no. 13, line 1. The Latin translates as &#8216;He planted you on an evil
                        day&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent5"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Unlucky was I ween that dolt</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Old Gray<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds
                            note in right hand column: &#8216;<hi rend="sup">1</hi> a Gray horse of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lambs.&#8217;</note> who reard thee from a colt &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Oft by thy dam unlucky jade</l>
          <l rend="indent2">He in the mire &amp; dirt was laid</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nor he alone &#8212; for one &amp; all</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Who rode have met with many a fall &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Unlucky too the grooms who deck</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The horse to break the riders neck</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For Memory pictures in my mind</l>
          <l rend="indent2">That hour when I got up behind.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds note in right hand column: &#8216;<hi rend="sup">2</hi> once upon a time the author in mounting was by a sudden jerk
                            thrown upon this grays rump. this said gray had been taught to rear
                            whenever the rump was touchd so Gray pranced &#8212; Poet leaped forward
                            &amp; Fortune jumpd him into the saddle. every Bard cannot ride the
                            great horse at Hughes&#8217;s as well as Pegasus.&#8217;</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent2">Some evil D&#230;mons envious power</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Presided at thy natal hour</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Some evil D&#230;mon sure thee sped</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To pitch thy master on his head<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds note in right hand column: &#8216;<hi rend="sup">3</hi> alluding to a very dangerous fall of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                            Lambs.&#8217;</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent2">And turnd thy wandring eyes about</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To fall &amp; fling poor <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Tom Lamb</ref> out.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds note in right hand column: &#8216;<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Tom was driving this horse in a gig when owing to
                            his stumbling he was thrown out &amp; much bruised.&#8217;</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg>
          <l rend="indent2">Your Bessey<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                            adds note in right hand column: &#8216;<hi rend="sup">5</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ls eldest daughter. very ill in a sea party.&#8217;</note> still
                        will dread that day</l>
          <l rend="indent2">That saw her midst old Oceans sway</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Resolvd to tempt his rage no more</l>
          <l rend="indent2">She fears but for her friends on shore.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">The German hireling <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Hesse Cassel, a German state notorious for hiring out its troops as
                            mercenaries, and an ally of Prussia and Austria during their invasion of
                            France in 1792.</note> fears to fight</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Exposd to France &amp; Freedoms might</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Proud Prussias disciplind hussar</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Trembles again to meet the war</l>
          <l rend="indent2">France only dreads the despots chain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And chuses Deaths or Freedoms reign.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Death unprovokd &amp; unforeseen</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Stalks sternly oer the smiling scene</l>
          <l rend="indent2">He grasps his unsuspecting prey</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And sweeps whole nations in his sway.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2"> Well<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds
                            note in right hand column: &#8216;<hi rend="sup">6</hi> after his fall from
                            the gig T D Lamb was put in damp sheets at an inn.&#8217;</note> nigh my
                        friend in Plutos reign<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Pluto, Roman
                            god of the underworld.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent2"> Hadst thou beheld the dark domain</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Well nigh hadst seen in sable row</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The well wiggd Counsellors below</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And stalking thro the realms of night</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Hadst seen poor Gualbertus<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John Gualbert (c. 995&#8211;1073), founder of the Vallombrosian
                            order. The pseudonym &#8216;Gualbertus&#8217; was used by Southey for his
                            controversial attack on flogging as an invention of the devil in the
                            fifth issue of <title level="j">The Flagellant</title> (29 March
                            1792).</note> sprite</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Where fearless he complains to Jove<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Jupiter, the king of the Roman gods.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent2">How stupid boys are floggd above</l>
          <l rend="indent2">There Milton might he hear thy lyre</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Pour forth the flow of godlike fire</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And rear thy Cromwells<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Sonnet
                            XVI, &#8216;To the Lord General Cromwell&#8217; (1652).</note> praise &amp;
                        sing</l>
          <l rend="indent2">How falln how mean a tyrant King</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Whilst listning crowds in silence hear</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And Truths unheard before appear.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">But chief to hear thy patriot song</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Hampden &amp; Sidney<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hampden (1594&#8211;1643; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                            parliamentarian and opponent of Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; reigned 1625&#8211;1649;
                                <title level="m">DNB</title>). He died in a skirmish at Chalgrove
                            Field. Algernon Sidney (1622&#8211;1683; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                            politician and republican, executed for his alleged involvement in the
                            Rye House plot.</note> move along</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And Brutus<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Either
                            Lucius Junius Brutus, the man credited with expelling the last king of
                            Rome, Tarquinius Superbus, in 510 BC; or Marcus Junius Brutus (85&#8211;42
                            BC), the assassin of Julius Caesar (100/102&#8211;44 BC).</note> bends thy
                        soul to know</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And Nature listens in ROUSSEAU.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">What wonder? when the Cherub quire</l>
          <l rend="indent2">From their celestial song respire</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And bend their frenzied heads to hear</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And more exalted strains revere</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The very Ghosts forget their woe</l>
          <l rend="indent2">So grand thy godlike numbers flow.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Een I oer whose ill fated head</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Her deepest viel has Sorrow spread</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Amid dark Fortunes sharpest shower</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Forget that Fortune for an hour</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And lost amid the blaze of day</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Forget my very woes away.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Unlucky &#8230; away: Written in double columns, with the verse
                            in the left hand column and Southey&#8217;s notes in the right.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent3"> ________________</p>
        <p>I have neither &lt;heard&gt; of or from <ref target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lamb</ref> since &amp; am much
                    alarmed at a silence so very uncommon.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">I
                        have ... uncommon: Inserted in the right hand column.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent4"> _____________</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> the classics will soon by published Lucan<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcus Annaeus Lucanus (AD 39&#8211;65), author of the
                            <title level="m">Pharsalia</title>, forced to commit suicide when his
                        involvement in the Pisonian conspiracy against the Emperor Nero was
                        discovered.</note> particularly I suppose in usum republic&#230;.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;advantage of the
                        republic&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HookJames">Hook</ref> has been standing candidate for
                    the gallows at Oxford &#8212; he attempted a rape upon a servant girl at a time when
                    he owns himself clapped. her master heard her cries &amp; rescued her but
                    for two days she remained dangerously ill. Hook gave her a new gown by way of
                    recompense when had they acted justly it would have given him a chance for a
                    halter. I always disliked him for his impudence this brazen faced endowment
                    however carries him thro every thing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8212; I have read 12 Satires of Juvenal<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Decimus Junius Juvenalis (fl. AD late C1 and early C2),
                        satirist.</note> with a vast deal of pleasure &#8212; the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    is the only one which my head (desirous of levelling all to my system) has
                    imitated &#8212; but as I have no wish to fall under the inquisitorial jurisdiction of
                    our new Star chamber &#8212; to lose my hand nose &amp; ears like Lilburne<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">John Lilburne (1615?&#8211;1657; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Leveller and Republican. In 1638 he was brought
                        before the Court of the Star Chamber for distributing unlicensed literature,
                        whipped and put in the pillory.</note> or the Englishman whom Elizabeth
                    punishd for writing against her intended marriage with Anjou<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1579, negotiations were under way for
                        Elizabeth I (1533&#8211;1603; reigned 1558&#8211;1603; <title level="m">DNB</title>) to
                        marry Francois, Duke of Anjou (1555&#8211;1584), heir-presumptive to the French
                        throne. The proposed marriage was deeply unpopular and John Stubbe (<hi rend="ital">c.</hi>1541&#8211;1590; <title level="m">DNB</title>) denounced it
                        in <title level="m">The Discoverie of a Gaping Gulf whereinto England is
                            Like to be Swallowed by Another French Marriage</title> (1579). As a
                        punishment, his right hand was cut off.</note> &#8212; or to run away like
                        Ridgeway<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">James Ridgeway (1755&#8211;1838),
                        well-known publisher of pamphlets, with a shop in York Street, St James&#8217;s
                        Square. In 1793, he was fined &#163;200 and imprisoned for publishing the works
                        of Thomas Paine (1737&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>). In 1794, he
                        agreed to publish Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Wat Tyler</title>. In fact, the
                        play was not published until 1817, when it appeared without Southey&#8217;s
                        consent.</note> &#8212; my poor imitation must lie in my desk. however this hand
                    may dabble in politics for my own private satisfaction it shall fill no more
                    letters with it &amp; if you see any production of mine upon the subject it
                    will only be an ode to the shade of Milton which I have in embryo. Juvenal is a
                    grand nervous Satirist &#8212; your refined criticks prefer the sneering strokes of
                        Horace<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Quintus Horatius Flaccus
                        (65&#8211;8 BC).</note> &#8212; for me I think otherwise &#8212; Johnsons London &amp;
                    Vanity of Human Wishes<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Johnson&#8217;s
                        (1709&#8211;1784; <title level="m">DNB</title>) &#8216;London&#8217; (1738) was a version of
                        Juvenal (fl. AD late C1 and early C2), <title level="m">Satire</title> 3,
                        and &#8216;The Vanity of Human Wishes&#8217; of Juvenal, <title level="m">Satire</title>
                        10.</note> are two of the noblest compositions in our language &#8212; the satire
                    of the first is already become obsolete &amp; some centuries hence posterity
                    will believe the supple French Fop only a creation of some drunken Englishmans
                    brain. the last will retain its original beauty even if 1600 years hence some
                    future Bard should imitate Johnson in some future language.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You say there is some grief &amp; some anger in <ref target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Stracheys</ref> letter &#8212; the grief has
                    escaped my search though I read it more than once &#8212; to use your own expression I
                    must look upon him as a faded flower &amp; regret most the loss of its
                    worth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I much fear my intended journey to <ref target="places.html#MountsfieldRye">Rye</ref> will be very unpleasantly set
                    aside &#8212; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my fathers</ref> health is
                    very precarious &amp; in spite of the hopes with which I have long imposed
                    upon myself I cannot help seeing that he declines rapidly. whether it be apathy
                    or philosophy I know not, but some such passion it must be that enables me to
                    turn from domestic distress &amp; look on to happiness as well private as
                    public. Reflection however will intrude sometimes</p>
        <p rend="center"> ________________</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> there <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &#8212; my defence of suicide is flaming</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent5">yours</salute>
        </closer>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent6">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>