<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce38</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.38</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.38" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="38" type="letter">
        <head>38. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1793-01-08">8 January
                        1793</date>
          </head><p>Address:
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford/ Old Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb />Stamped:
                        BATH<lb />Postmark: AJA/ 10/ 93<lb /> Watermark: Crown and anchor with G R
                        underneath<lb />Endorsement: 8 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1793<lb />MS: Bodleian
                        Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>Bath.</placeName>
            </address>
            <time>Tuesday evening.</time>
            <date when="1793-01-08">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.
                            1793.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p>your last containing the Xmas ode reached me before I left Bristol &#8212; which spot
                    dull as it is I much regret when compared with Bath &amp; shall revisit
                    tomorrow. on Saturday sevennight hence I hope to take possession of my rooms at
                        <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Baliol</ref> &#8212; once more to enter
                    upon a course of doctorial learning &amp; fetter inclination in the chains
                    of pedantry &amp; precedent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In an age when the liberty of the press has been so openly
                    attacked (may this fellow who now grinds god save the King on a hand organ to my
                    inexpressible annoyance, in the next world keep company with Alexander the great
                    Louis the great<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander the Great
                        (356&#8211;323 BC; reigned 336&#8211;323 BC), and Louis XVI (1754&#8211;1793; reigned
                        1774&#8211;1792).</note> &amp; all the rest of the sovereigns of mankind &#8212; in
                    an age when invectives are substituted for argument &amp; a standing army is
                    produced as a convincing reason &#8212; it is a circumstance equally uncommon
                    &amp; flattering to argue dispassionately with a friend upon political
                    subjects &amp; still to keep him a friend &#8212; you ask my arguments &#8212; they
                    indeed ought to be unresistible since they withstand every friend I have
                    &amp; only remain from every attack the firmer &#8212; may they find an abler
                    supporter! your letter is at <ref target="places.html#CollegeGreenBristol">Bristol</ref> so I have only to trust to a head too much occupied with
                    domestic distress to argue methodically. it is unjust (you say) that the
                    minority should give law to the majority &#8212; not withstanding the many
                    associations that cover our pissing posts to the great annoyance of Leakes
                    patent pills &amp; Velno&#8217;s vegetable syrup<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Presumably a patent medicine recommended by John Leake
                        (1729&#8211;1792; <title level="m">DNB</title>), man-midwife who published a
                            <title level="m">Dissertation on the Properties and Efficacy of the
                            Lisboa Diet Drink in the Venereal, Scurvy, Gout &amp;c.</title>
                        (1767), an alleged cure for syphilis, &#8216;The French Disease&#8217;. Velno&#8217;s
                        vegetable syrup was a patent medicine supposed to cure venereal
                        disease.</note> I must still very much doubt that the monarchical advocates
                    are the majority. admitting however the fact (which is yielding a great point) I
                    will mention two or three parallel instances. when England emancipated from
                    papal tyranny what was the majority? an argument adduced from religion will not
                    be despised by you. did not a few fishermen spread their doctrines over the
                    world? &amp; had persecution always clouded Xtianity what would have been
                    its success? &#8212; the genius of Paganism was tolerant. truth obtained a hearing
                    &amp; it asked no more. god forbid that one wish should enter in my heart to
                    plunge England in blood. I only ask the free exercise of reason. Truth never
                    shuns investigation. Falshood only fears the spear of Ithuriel.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> (1667), Book 4,
                        lines 810&#8211;813. The spear of Ithuriel could penetrate any disguise, and
                        revealed Satan in the guise of a toad.</note> the objections to monarchy
                    (&#8220;the monstrous faith of many made for one&#8221;) <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A misquotation of Alexander Pope (1688&#8211;1744; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">An Essay on Man: Epistle III</title>
                        (1732&#8211;1734), line 242.</note> are such, that even its adherents are obliged
                    to own a republic best in theory. experience tells us it is possible in
                    practice. Thebes Sparta &#8212; Athens &amp; Carthage have been. America is.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> since the days of Nimrod<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Old Testament king and reputed builder of the Tower of Babel; see <title level="m">Genesis</title> 10: 8-14.</note> the first usurper mankind
                    have been engaged in the work of destruction. war is the gain of Kings or
                    Aristocrats &#8212; but what matters it to the shepherd the manufacter still less to
                    the philosopher to whom a tract of country belongs or which way the fanciful
                    balance inclines? is it not as easy for ambassadors to prevent as to terminate a
                    war? or what acquisition has been obtained in recompense for the oceans of blood
                    lavished in Germany? had England been a republic would it have been fed with the
                    blood of her children for the long term of contest between York &amp;
                        Lancaster?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The English civil war
                        (1455&#8211;1487), known as the &#8216;War of the Roses&#8217;, between supporters of the
                        rival royal houses of York and Lancaster.</note> would it have plunged in
                    civil war against a Stuart would Hampden &amp; Falkland<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Lucius Cary, 2nd Viscount Falkland
                        (1609/10&#8211;1643; <title level="m">DNB</title>), died at the first battle of
                        Newbury, and John Hampden (1600&#8211;1643; <title level="m">DNB</title>), died of
                        wounds received at the battle of Chalgrove.</note> have bled? or would the
                    disturbances of 1715 &amp; 1745<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        failed Jacobite risings of 1715 and 1745, which aimed to put James III
                        (1688&#8211;1766; <title level="m">DNB</title>), the Old Pretender, on the
                        throne.</note> have ever happened? these wars have been occasioned by the
                    abuse of power or by disputed successions. the other<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> wars which have leaked away our treasures &amp; lavished our
                    blood are owing to monarchy at least the majority of them. our long wars with
                    France originated in the chimerical pretensions of Edward the third<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward III&#8217;s (1312&#8211;1377; reigned 1327&#8211;1377;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>) claims to the throne of France had led to
                        the Hundred Years War.</note> &#8212; &amp; to what can all the continental
                    slaughter of Englishmen be attributed but to Hanoverian interest?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">After 1714, British sovereigns were also rulers
                        of the kingdom of Hanover in Germany, leading to accusations that Britain
                        became involved in continental wars only to defend the interests of
                        Hanover.</note> these instances are from our own annals &#8212; with the book of
                    history you are well acquainted &amp; if you examine the origin of almost
                    every war you will deduce then from the same source of iniquity. the ambition of
                    Rome you will object as an instance of Republican ferocity but Rome was an
                    aristocracy. a government scarcely less hideous in its distorted features.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> to such as we are who wish not to attain the enjoyments of power
                    with the loss of virtue &amp; content it little matters how the world wags.
                    interest is too contemptible to affect us &amp; our motive can only be a
                    wish for the general welfare. to self all is tolerable &#8212; what is it to man or to
                    humanity! look at the hundreds of aged &amp; infirm mendicants who throng
                    your streets &#8212; &amp; then ask your own heart if all is right &#8212; that <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will answer with
                    justice. the labourer toils during the years of vigor &amp; earns his scanty
                    morsel with the sweat of his brow &#8212; yet this man even in the vilest beer he
                    drinks pays to support a set of pensioned courtiers who drink their wines
                    heedless of his wants &amp; cry out &#8212; all is right &#8212; like D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pangloss<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A character in
                        Voltaire&#8217;s (1694&#8211;1778), <title level="m">Candide, ou l&#8217;Optimisme</title>
                        (1759) who, despite evidence to the contrary, consistently asserts all is
                        well in this &#8216;best of all possible worlds&#8217;.</note> when every thing belies
                    them. if this labourer has a wife &amp; family (&amp; surely in a well
                    regulated state from these circumstances advantages only could ensue) he is
                    still more distrest &#8212; sickness comes on &#8212; his hard earned wages go if he be in
                    his parish how pitiful is the allotted relief! if he be not what resource
                    remains! is not the press gang a grievance? are not the multitude of sinecure
                    places a grievance? is not imprisonment for debts unavoidably contracted a
                    grievance?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> our house of Lords have the power of rejecting any tax. they
                    consequently as much as possible shift them upon the people. is this as it
                    should be. the name of Lord carries nothing in it &amp; an equal education
                    would make any Lord &amp; my shoemaker equally philosophic. now I affirm
                    that the first duty of [MS torn] where Liberty &amp; Equality flourish is to
                    regard the education of the people.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> perhaps I may one day draw up my theory in a more regular plan &#8212;
                    at present I will conclude with a few remarks upon the present mode of
                    proceeding. Edmund Burke<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Burke
                        (1729/30&#8211;1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Reflections
                            on the Revolution in France</title> (1790).</note> begins the attack &#8212;
                    he is answerd by the glorious genius of Mackintosh<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">James Mackintosh (1765&#8211;1832; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                            <title level="m">Vindici&#230; Gallic&#230;: A Defence of the French Revolution
                            and its English Admirers</title> (1791).</note> &amp; the bold
                    freedom of citizen Paine<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Paine
                        (1737&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Rights of
                            Man</title> (1791&#8211;1792).</note> &#8212; the advocate of oppression are dumb
                    the militia is summoned. &amp; argument is endeavoured to be suppressed by
                    force. you must have seen the witty letter of Thomas Bull<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">[William Jones, &#8216;of Nayland&#8217; (1726&#8211;1800; <title level="m">DNB</title>)], <title level="m">One Penny-worth of Truth, from
                            Thomas Bull to his brother John</title> (1792).</note> &#8212; are those
                    reasons (my friend) sufficient to convince the philosopher or the man? good god
                    are we to hear again of the divine right of Kings &amp; the impiety of the
                    unanointed republic? if scripture must be drawn in be it our test &#8212; we have the
                    retreat of Sennacherib &amp; the asses of Saul<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Sennacherib, King of Assyria 704&#8211;681 BC; see 2 <title level="m">Kings</title> 19: 35. Saul, first king of Israel 1047&#8211;1007 BC;
                        see 1 <title level="m">Samuel</title> 10, the subject of Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Saul and
                        His Asses&#8217;, published in the <title level="j">Morning Post</title>, 17 July
                        1798.</note> &#8212; are you &amp; I less wise or less virtuous than George
                    the third<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; reigned
                        1760&#8211;1820; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> because we have not been
                    greased by an archbishop! monarchy was established by force &#8212; superior strength
                    or wisdom are necessary &#8212; but shall we find either in any crowned heads? two
                    Antonines &amp; Titus &amp; an apostate<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey could be referring to a number of Roman emperors of
                        the Antonine dynasty, including Trajan (53&#8211;117; reigned 98&#8211;117), Hadrian
                        (76&#8211;138; reigned 117&#8211;138), Antoninus Pius (86&#8211;161; reigned 138&#8211;161) and
                        Marcus Aurelius (121&#8211;180; reigned 161&#8211;180); together with Titus (39&#8211;81;
                        reigned 79&#8211;81) and Julianus the Apostate (331/2&#8211;363; reigned 361&#8211;3).</note>
                    alone illumine the black catalogue of Roman emperors. in modern Europe look at
                    all nations &amp; all ages &#8212; you will find but one Alfred &amp; one
                    Henry the fourth<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The English kings
                        Alfred the Great (848/9&#8211;899; reigned 871&#8211;899; <title level="m">DNB</title>)
                        and Henry IV (1366&#8211;1413; reigned 1399&#8211;1413; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> &#8212; our present soveriengs are no ways remarkable. who
                    will praise the consistency of the last Louis<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis XVI (1754&#8211;1793; reigned 1774&#8211;1792).</note> &#8212; the
                    humanity of Catherine<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Catherine II
                        (1729&#8211;1796; reigned 1762&#8211;1796), Empress of Russia.</note> or the wisdom of
                    &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Solons<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Solon (c. 640&#8211;558
                        BC), Greek statesman and poet, whose reforms earned him the title &#8216;Father of
                        Athenian democracy&#8217;.</note> law that no man in any public commotion should
                    be neuter was a wise one &amp; would have well suited me. improvements never
                    can be made if we are compelled to tread the paths of precedent. but these
                    political discussions lead one on too far I have said nothing of your Xmas ode
                    it is not with me but I can remember nothing [MS torn] it that is not good. let
                    me hint you a good subject for an imitation of your <hi rend="ital">vates</hi>
                        Flaccus.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to Horace
                        (Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65&#8211;8 BC)) as a prophet or soothsayer (the word
                        &#8216;vates&#8217; denoting one of the three classes of Celtic priesthood, with the
                        other two being druids and bards). Southey is suggesting that Grosvenor
                        Charles Bedford admired the Roman poet so much that he treated him as a
                        prophet.</note> you do not disapprove the conduct of La Fayette<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Marie-Paul-Joseph-Roch-Gilbert Motier, Marquis
                        de LaFayette (1757&#8211;1834), French general and politician. Active on the
                        American side in the War of Independence, but a moderate during the French
                        Revolution, he fled to Austria in August 1792, where he was
                        imprisoned.</note> &#8212; apply Justum &amp; tenacem propositi virum<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Horace (65&#8211;8 BC), <title level="m">Odes</title>, Book 3, no. 3, lines 1&#8211;4. The Latin translates
                        as &#8216;a man just and steadfast of purpose&#8217;.</note> to him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have some satires which I much wish to show you but I dare not
                    trust them &#8212; you shall see them when we meet. I shall write again from Bristol
                    before I depart. your last I conceive to have been written before the receit of
                    two of mine. remember <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> though I condemn a defence of Suicide I look not upon it as a
                    deadly sin. every thing of that kind depends upon circumstances. Cato &amp;
                        Brutus<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">The Roman republicans, Marcus
                        Porcius Cato Uticensis (95&#8211;46 BC) and Marcus Junius Brutus (85&#8211;42 BC), who
                        both committed suicide.</note> were incapable of guilt. remember me to
                    little <ref target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Joseph</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">&amp; believe me yours affectionately</salute>
        </closer>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert S.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I heard from the learned Pig<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">A nickname for a friend at Westminster School whose
                            identity is unknown. It might be a reference to Peter Elmsley, who was
                            both clever and plump. The &#8216;learned pig&#8217; was also a well-known
                            fairground show; see Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters From England: By Don
                                Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, pp.
                            48&#8211;9.</note> on Thursday.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>