<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce115</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.115</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.115" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="115" type="letter">
        <head>115. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-11-22">[22 November
                        1794]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Watermark: Crown and anchor with G R
                        underneath<lb />Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 1794 &#8212;/ with a book for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Reed; Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> same day<lb />MS:
                        Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note:
                        Dating from the mention of &#8216;Saturday&#8217; at the end of the letter; the
                        endorsement suggests this probably refers to Saturday, 22 November
                        1794.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2"> thank you for remembering me of the respect I owe to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Reed.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Reed
                        (1742&#8211;1807; <title level="m">DNB</title>), literary scholar and editor of
                        Shakespeare. In 1792, he tried (and failed) to prevent Egerton, the printer
                        of the schoolboy magazine <title>The Flagellant</title>, from revealing
                        Southey as the author of a controversial essay on flogging to the
                        Westminster School authorities.</note> ignorance of his direction makes me
                    send the volume to you. I am ill at writing notes &amp; believe it is not
                    customary on these occasions. <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> gave you his full direction. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 14 Old
                    Market Bristol. I have read your letter. heigh ho! there must be one standard of
                    truth &amp; sorry am I that so difficult is it to be discoverd that we have
                    ranged under different banners.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> with respect to Joan of Arc. in dedicating it to you my only
                    motive was to give a public testimony of private friendship. from what <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has said I conclude it is not
                    agreable &amp; may be prejudicial. I will relinquish my intention. the copy
                    right of the poem will I believe soon be sold for fifty guineas &amp; fifty
                        copies.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had by this time
                        abandoned his earlier plan of publishing his epic in a subscription edition
                        with the Bath publisher Richard Cruttwell (c. 1747&#8211;1799; <title level="m">DNB</title>), and was in negotiations to sell the copyright of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> to Joseph Cottle.</note> in so doing I
                    think I shall do well as the printing will come to &#163;200 pounds &#8212; these cursed
                    politics you say absorb every thing. my soul <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> sickens at the
                    prospect they hold out &#8212; how is it that you are caught in their vortex? had we
                    been more together we must have agreed &#8212; we are now in our detestation of the
                    calamities they are inflicting on mankind. I shall be soon beyond the sphere of
                    their destruction &#8212; would that I did not feel a selfish terror at the coming
                    storm for my friends. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> when the storm breaks &#8212; I earnestly adjure you to avoid its
                    fury. this is not the vain prophesy of a distemperd brain &#8212; it will break. there
                    are bad men &amp; mistaken men in England who do not know that revolutions
                    should take place in mind. let the violence of either party prevail &amp;
                    the moderate will be equally proscribd. death is no mans duty while his life can
                    be of service. be not offended my dear <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> tho this should
                    seem premature &#8212; but if disturbances arise<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> come
                    with your family to us. if you do not like our mode of living &#8212; you can remain
                    there till you find one more agreable &#8212; for it will be the only land at
                    peace.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> be good enough to send me your Witch of Endor. I have a volume of
                        poems<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to
                        Southey&#8217;s collaboration with Robert Lovell on a collection of poems to be
                        published under the pseudonyms of &#8216;Orson&#8217; and &#8216;Valentine&#8217;.</note> &#8212;
                    &amp; my Botany Bay Eclogues in the Booksellers hands at London<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">There is evidence that Samuel Taylor Coleridge
                        took a manuscript of Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Botany-Bay Eclogues&#8217; to London in September
                        1794, offering the poems to Joseph Johnson (1738&#8211;1809; <title level="m">DNB</title>). One of the eclogues, &#8216;Elinor&#8217;, appeared anonymously in
                        the <title level="j">Morning Chronicle</title>, 18 September 1794, probably
                        on Coleridge&#8217;s initiative. Three more were published (alongside a revised
                        version of &#8216;Elinor&#8217;) in Southey&#8217;s <title>Poems</title> (1797), and a fifth
                        in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 5 (January 1798).</note> &#8212;
                    but doubt their success. &#8220;these cursed politics absorb every thing!&#8221;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is quoting Bedford&#8217;s own words back at
                        him.</note> my time is short &amp; to print them on my own account too
                    hazardous. America is a better market for literature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> earnestly as I
                    wish for March my heart seems to palpitate at its approach &#8212; parting with &#8220;the
                    friends we hold most dear&#8221;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A quotation
                        from Southey&#8217;s sonnet, &#8216;Bedford &#8212; My Kalendar Shall Mark This Day&#8217;, sent to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 10 September 1794 (Letter 104).</note> perhaps
                    for ever is a hard lesson to learn. is it paradoxical to say that I hope you
                    will see me embark? </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have experienced the evils of the establishd system most
                    forcibly &#8212; &amp; expect tranquillity in the calm of a different one &#8212;
                    &amp; happiness in the performance of what appears my duty.</p>
        <p rend="indent4"> fare thee well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> remember me to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> B respectfully. &amp; to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harry</ref> remember me likewise. Bedford I envy you that brother.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4"> sincerely yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Saturday.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I have elegized the gallant Kosciusko.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thaddeus Kosciusko (1746&#8211;1817), Polish
                            patriot, whose actions in the causes of American and Polish independence
                            made him a radical hero. Samuel Taylor Coleridge published a sonnet on
                            Kosciusko in the <title level="j">Morning Chronicle</title>, 16 December
                            1794.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>