<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce214</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.214</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Columbia
                        University Library.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 125&#8211;127; Joseph Cottle, Reminiscences
                            of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey (London, 1847),
                        pp. 210&#8211;211 and 212 [in part; as if from two separate letters]; Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, p. 306 n* [in part;
                        section of 1 paragraph].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="214" type="letter">
        <head>214. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph
                        Cottle</ref>, <date when="1797-05-02">2 May [1797]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ Mr Cottle/ High
                        Street/ Bristol<lb />Stamped: Penny Post/ P<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">d</hi>/ NewingnCausey<lb />Postmark: MA/ 2/
                        97<lb />Endorsements: Southey/ April 1797; (<del rend="strikethrough">79</del>) <hi rend="ital">26</hi>; May 1797<lb /> MS: Columbia
                        University Library<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New
                        York, 1965), I, pp. 125&#8211;127; Joseph Cottle, <title level="m">Reminiscences
                            of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey</title> (London, 1847),
                        pp. 210&#8211;211 and 212 [in part; as if from two separate letters]; Charles
                        Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, p. 306 n* [in part;
                        section of 1 paragraph].</note>
        </head>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> To my great astonishment I received your letter dated April 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> &#8212; this morning only (Tuesday May 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>). a strange &amp; unaccountable delay. I have written to you since
                    I received the box. of the parcel I have heard nothing yet &#8212; why this long
                    delay? &#8212; as for <ref target="people.html#RosserRobert">Rosser</ref> &#8212; I am sorry
                    he has lost the little good opinion I had of him. I care not much about the sale
                    of the wine. <hi rend="ital">he shall not have it at any rate. tell him so from
                        me.</hi> when we are settled by the sea we will have a dozen of it there.
                    &amp; the rest on our return. Send me your letter to Herbert Croft.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Croft, 5th Baronet (1751&#8211;1816;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>), writer and lexicographer. Southey and
                        Joseph Cottle both disapproved of his exploitation of manuscripts obtained
                        from members of Thomas Chatterton&#8217;s (1752&#8211;1770; <title level="m">DNB</title>) family. Southey publicly attacked him in a letter to the
                            <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, November 1799.</note> when it
                    will be a proper time to publish for her benefit &#8212; there is no task that I will
                    not gladly perform.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your news is very acceptable. I shall be ready at any time you
                    think proper; &amp; will send you the corrected copy at a weeks notice.
                    There are some pieces in the volume that might be omitted without much loss to
                    make room for the Retrospect.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph
                        Cottle had suggested a second edition of Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797). It appeared later that year, but did not include
                        &#8216;The Retrospect&#8217;, which was not reprinted until 1806.</note> but &#8212; I do not
                    like giving any thing different in the two editions &#8212; to improve what is <del rend="strikethrough">th</del> in the first edition is due to my own
                    character. however if you think it may be done with<del rend="strikethrough">out</del> propriety we will make room for the Retrospect &#8212; &amp; I will
                    correct it. Rosamund does not deserve a place there.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Inscription I. For a Tablet at Godstow Nunnery&#8217;
                        was included in the second edition of his <title level="m">Poems</title>
                        (1797).</note> perhaps they had better be where they are awhile. I have not
                    much to alter &#8212; the arrangement will be somewhat varied. The Paupers Funeral. M
                    Picture &amp; other pieces of that kind, I shall class together under the
                    name of Musings. <ref target="people.html#Peacockunknown">Mr Peacock</ref>
                    strenuously recommends two or three vignettes &#8212; &amp; to make the price six
                    shillings. if you should think seriously of any ornaments of this kind &#8212; I would
                    wish the frontispiece to be Gaspar Poussins exquisite landscape.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The French-Italian painter Gaspard Dughet
                        (1615&#8211;1675), who assumed the surname Poussin when he was adopted as the heir
                        of Nicholas Poussin (1594&#8211;1665). Southey is possibly referring to Gaspard
                        Poussin&#8217;s <title level="m">The Cascade</title>. The second edition of
                        Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797) did not contain a
                        frontispiece, but it did republish his &#8216;Musings on a Landscape of Gaspar
                        Poussin&#8217;.</note> I am inclined to think that prints help a book. that
                    frontispiece, &amp; two vignettes &#8212; one from the Slave Trade Poems &#8212; one
                    Elinor would be enough it is needless to add that I am indifferent concerning
                    all this &amp; merely suggest it as matter of consideration in the profit
                    &amp; loss way. I should like a dozen copies struck off on large paper of
                    the very best quality &#8212; like Estlins sermon.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">John Prior
                            Estlin</ref>, <title level="m">The Nature and Causes of Atheism, Pointed
                            Out in a Discourse, Delivered at the Chapel in Lewin&#8217;s-Mead, Bristol. To
                            Which are Added, Remarks on a Work, Entitled Origine de Tous Les Cultes,
                            ou Religion Universelle. Par Dupuis, Citoyen Fran&#231;ois</title>
                        (1797).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For Joan of Arc.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph
                        Cottle had requested a second edition of <title level="m">Joan of
                            Arc</title>, which was published in two volumes in 1798.</note> your
                    news was unexpected. there I have much labour to look on to. but every thing
                    shall be ready I have only strenuously to recommend that the second edition be
                    in two volumes like the Poems, a mode more elegant &#8212; &amp; more
                    advantageous.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So much then for business. you will wonder at not hearing sooner.
                    but the delay of your letter is very strange. one weeks notice is all I require
                    for the poems.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I saw <del rend="strikethrough">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Hunter</del>
          <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Hunter (1741&#8211;1802;
                            <title level="m">DNB</title>), Church of Scotland minister and
                        translator. Hunter&#8217;s name is probably struck through in another hand, here
                        and elsewhere in this letter.</note> yesterday. &amp; like neither him
                    nor his wife nor his son nor his daughter nor any thing that is his. however he
                    can introduce me to Holloway<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The engraver
                        Thomas Holloway (1748&#8211;1827; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> the
                    engraver. tonight I am to meet Opie<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        portrait and history painter John Opie (1761&#8211;1807; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> &#8212; &amp; I can likewise get an introduction to
                        Westall.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Either the painter and
                        illustrator Richard Westall (1765&#8211;1836; <title level="m">DNB</title>), or
                        (less likely) his half-brother the painter and engraver William Westall
                        (1781&#8211;1850; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> &#8212; so you see I shall have
                    some little interest among painters &amp; engravers as well as
                    Reviewers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a treasure in store for you. a little treatise in old
                    English, very short, upon miracles &#8212; written by John Henderson<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Henderson (1757&#8211;1788; <title level="m">DNB</title>), student and eccentric. Joseph Cottle had attended his
                        father&#8217;s school at Hanham, near Bristol, and John Henderson had encouraged
                        his love of literature and urged him to become a bookseller. Cottle
                        celebrated his life and works in <title level="m">Poems, Containing John the
                            Baptist. Sir Malcolm and Alla, a Tale, Shewing to All the World What a
                            Woman&#8217;s Love Can Do. War a Fragment. With a Monody to John Henderson;
                            and a Sketch of his Character</title> (1795) and later in an &#8216;Appendix&#8217;
                        to <title level="m">Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert
                            Southey</title> (1847).</note> for <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">Coleridges brother</ref> &#8212; &amp;
                    given me by a pupil of his &#8212; <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &#8212;
                    a Lisbon acquaintance &#8212; &amp; a very valuable one. As we shall be somewhere
                    in Hampshire or Dorsetshire &#8212; within a days journey of you &#8212; I do not altogether
                    despair of seeing you by the sea; where we may drink the Claret &amp; talk
                    of the second edition of Joan. one week you may spare &#8212; &amp; trust to us
                    the care of making it a happy one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My translation is finished.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey translated the second volume of <title level="m">On
                            the French Revolution by M. Necker</title> (1797).</note> &amp; the
                    two first book[MS torn] of Madoc now lie on the table packed up to go to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> [MS torn] I have desired
                    him to lend them to you. <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> desires to be remembered to you from Lisbon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> is anxious for a full life of
                    John Henderson. you should get Agutters<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">William Agutter (1758&#8211;1835; <title level="m">DNB</title>), a Church of
                        England clergyman, political conservative and campaigner for the abolition
                        of the slave-trade. A friend of John Henderson&#8217;s, he accompanied his corpse
                        from Oxford (where Henderson had died) to its final resting place, Kingswood
                        near Bristol. He preached Henderson&#8217;s funeral sermon.</note> papers. you
                    ought likewise to commit to paper all you know concerning him &#8212; &amp; all
                    you can collect &#8212; that the documents may at least remain even if you decline the
                    task. these documents cannot be too minute.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What news of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> second edition?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">Poems by S.T. Coleridge, Second Edition. To Which are
                            Now Added Poems by Charles Lamb and Charles Lloyd</title> (1797).</note>
                    I want an answer to this question which is often put to me. you trace me in the
                    last M Magazine on Villegas &#8212; &amp; in Aristodemus.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 3 (April 1797),
                        270&#8211;272, 296 (Letter 208).</note> the Sonnet signed B.W.H. is by <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Bedford</ref>.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 3
                        (April 1797), 296.</note> I am sorry to see a sad plagiarism
                    there in the Anecdotes of the Revolution.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 3 (April 1797),
                        289&#8211;293.</note> Phillips<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Phillips (1767&#8211;1840; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                        proprietor of the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>.</note> has set
                    up a stocking shop.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We dine with <ref target="people.html#WollstonecraftMary">Mary
                        Wollstonecraft</ref> (now Godwin) tomorrow. Oh <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">he</ref> has a foul nose! &amp; I
                    never see it without longing to cut it off. by the by <del rend="strikethrough">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hunter</del> told me that I had exactly
                        Lavaters<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1792, Henry Hunter
                        (1741&#8211;1802; <title level="m">DNB</title>) had published an English
                        translation of <title level="m">Essays on Physiognomy</title> by Johann
                        Kasparr Lavater (1741&#8211;1801).</note> nose. to my no small satisfaction for I
                    did not know what to make of that protuberance &#8212; or promontory of mine. I could
                    not compliment his. he has a very red <hi rend="ital">drinking</hi> face. little
                    good humoured eyes, with the skin drawn up under them &#8212; like cunning &amp;
                    short-sightedness united.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    love.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Look at Herbert Crofts portrait in the European Magazine, for the honour of
                            physiognomy.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Look ...
                            physiognomy: Postscript added on fol. 2r. A portrait of Croft had
                            appeared in <title level="m">The European Magazine, and London
                                Review</title>, 25 (1794), [251].</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>