<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce33</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.33</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="33" type="letter">
        <head>33. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1792-12-04">4 December 1792</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Old Palace Yard/ Westminster/ Single Sheet<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: ODE/ 5/ 92<lb />Watermark: Crown and anchor with G R beneath<lb />Endorsement: 4. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1792<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="left">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#CollegeGreenBristol">Bristol College Green.</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date>Tuesday. December 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1791*</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent11">									is that date explicit?</p>
        <p rend="indent5">					*meant for. December 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 179<hi rend="ital">2</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">* meant ... 1792: Added in another hand.</note>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">	When a Raven shall build In a stone Lion&#8217;s mouth, on the top of Vale Royal house, there shall an heir be born there, who shall live to see great troubles in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	so said the Cheshire fool or prophet, which you will 400 years ago.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Prophecies attributed to the legendary &#8216;Cheshire prophet&#8217; Robert Nixon (supp. fl. late 15th&#8211;early 17th centuries; <title level="m">DNB</title>). <title level="m">Nixon&#8217;s Cheshire Prophecies, At Large</title> went through several editions in the eighteenth century. Traditionally, Nixon was closely connected to Vale Royal, the Cistercian abbey in Cheshire which, after the dissolution, was converted into a country house.</note> &amp; the &lt;present&gt; heir of Vale royal house was born when the stone Lions mouth served for the Ravens nest at this Bedford would not every old woman tremble? I can despise the waking dreams of madmen when old <ref target="people.html#Doyly">Doyley</ref> &amp; Dickinson<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Dickinson (1771&#8211;1837), a pupil at Westminster School, who later went on to Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1793, MA 1795). Civil Lord of the Admiralty, 1804&#8211;1806.</note> thought to terrify me by this very prophecy &amp; that of the 3 thumbed miller (now living on Salisbury Plain whom the fates have destined to hold three Kings horses up to his knees in blood)<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is conflating a prophecy by Robert Nixon, with one by Mother Shipton (supp. fl. 1530; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> I laughed in my sleeve &amp; absolutely frightened them. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	last night I went to see that compilation of turgidity &amp; bombast the Grecian Daughter<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Arthur Murphy&#8217;s (1727&#8211;1805; <title level="m">DNB</title>) tragedy <title level="m">The Grecian Daughter</title> was first performed in 1772.</note> if you recollect there are many passages about loyalty royalty &amp; freedom party ran high God save the King was sung &#8212; Philosophy like Justice was swept silently down the stream &#8212; one man (that word is better than with the gentle prefixd) stood firm to his principles &#8212; when the hat was taken off his went last &amp; unwillingly &amp; the cowardly insults of a surrounding loyal mob he treated with contempt &#8212; when the riotous paroxysm produced by this last proclamatory dose (it will be a working one I believe) was past Citizen Bailey<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Although his identity is not certain, he may be connected to &#8216;Citizen Bailey&#8217;, author of <title level="m">The White Devils Un-Cased. Being the First Discourse upon Ecclesiastical Tyranny, and Superstition: Delivered at Section 2 and 7 of the Friends of Liberty</title> (c. 1795).</note> as they called him in contempt was without a companion. I quitted my seat &#8212; we entered into conversation out of which no Judge can extract treason &#8212; &amp; the vile mob at the conclusion that seperated us prevented me from drinking a bottle with him this day which I won by a wager. he has only been in Bristol three months &amp; where to find him I know not. now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> the agitation of last night brought these old Ravens Lions Millers &amp;c into my head this morning &#8212; your apology is indeed too much. the gentle reprimand you gave I deserved for beginning the subject suffer me to say a few words &amp; drop that subject by letter for ever. these are perilous times give me three lines of any mans writing said Richelieu &amp; I will extract treason from them.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of a quotation attributed to the French statesman Armand-Jean du Plessis, Cardinal-Duc de Richelieu (1585&#8211;1642). It is usually rendered as &#8216;If you give me six lines written by the hand of the most honest of men I will find something in them which will hang them&#8217;.</note> every boy is a patriot &#8212; you say so &amp; I will grant with pleasure that every boy unbiassed by interest is so for this evident reason the mind yet unblackened by guilt hypocrisy &amp; a court is good by nature &#8212; they love their country &amp; its liberty better than themselves &#8212; Fortune links them in the long chain of dependance which surrounds every public office (I need not say Bedford I hope, that as for these motives they have nothing to do with you) &amp; it becomes their interest to continue the deception. &#8212; opposition is but a farce &#8212; a fight like Bagshot battles<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The military manoeuvres and mock-battles staged on Bagshot Heath, near London. These were the subject of the anonymous <title level="m">Bagshot Battle; A Humorous Poetical Burlesque; Designed for the Amusement and Entertainment of Ladies, Who Were Not Present at the Late Military Evolutions</title> (1792).</note> where all seek to obey one leader reform is talked of. but a tree rotten at the core must be &#8212;&#8212;. a standing army is a very dreadful thing, said some old senator of England. oh I could prophecy but that the hand &#8212; not of Death Bedford. if I come to London it will be before Xmas day &amp; we will talk of these thing if you wish it &#8212; for my part as I will never more seek the subject so will I never avoid it &#8212; Justum &amp; tenacem &amp;c.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is quoting from Horace (65&#8211;8 BC), <title level="m">Odes</title>, Book 3, no. 3, line 1. The Latin translates as &#8216;Just and steadfast&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	you talk of reading Juvenal &#8212; read the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> satire<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Decimus Junius Juvenalis (fl. AD late C1 and early C2). Satire 8 is about the pointlessness of tracing ancestors.</note> &amp; you shall one day see my imitation which I finished in two days some parts you will not like &#8212; <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> has often wishd me to attempt this nervous Satirist &#8212; I have at length &amp; I was hardly so well satisfied with myself even when I wrote that devilish good N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 5.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is referring to the controversial fifth issue of <title level="j">The Flagellant</title> (29 March 1792).</note> that we shall be of the same opinion I hope most sincerely &#8212; should the flames of civil war burst forth seas of blood must quench them. est hic est animus lucis contemptor &amp; qui vita bene credat emi &#8212; honorem.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A misquotation from Virgil (70&#8211;19 BC), <title level="m">Aeneid</title>, Book 9, lines 205&#8211;206. The Latin original translates as: &#8216;Mine is a heart that scorns the light, and believes that the glory that you strive for is cheaply bought with life&#8217;.</note> never may the fates of Falkland &amp; of Hampden<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The author and politician Lucius Cary, 2nd Viscount Falkland (1609/10&#8211;1643; <title level="m">DNB</title>), was killed fighting for royalist forces at the first battle of Newbury. The politician John Hampden (1595&#8211;1643; <title level="m">DNB</title>), died of wounds received fighting on the parliamentary side at the battle of Chalgrove.</note> be exemplified in you &amp; me Nature never intended me for a soldier &#8212; when I am agitated every nerve trembles but at those moments when a bystander would think me palsied with some fear I could leap to pluck bright honor from the pale faced moon.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">A misquotation of <title level="m">Henry IV, Part 1</title>, Act 1, scene 3, line 208.</note> I could write an ode &amp; stand to be shot at.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I have already said too much. I have an old poem of the heroic class before me. Pharonnida &#8212; one of the Cantos was finishd on the morning of the second battle of Newberry.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The second battle of Newbury occurred on 27 October 1644. The author of <title level="m">Pharonnida, a Heroick Poem</title> (1659) was William Chamberlayne (c. 1619&#8211;1689; <title level="m">DNB</title>). Southey owned a copy of the first edition of the poem, <title level="m">Sale Catalogues of Libraries of Eminent Persons</title>, gen. ed. A. L. Munby, vol. 9, <title level="m">Poets and Men of Letters</title>, ed. Roy Park (London, 1974), p. 113.</note> take his concluding lines</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">But ere calm&#8217;d thoughts to prosecute our story,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Salute thy ears with the deserved glory</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Our <hi rend="ital">marshal</hi>
            <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds note in left hand margin: &#8216;I do not understand this word&#8217;.</note> lovers puchast here; I must</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Let my pen rest awhile, &amp; see the rust</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Scour&#8217;d from my own sword, for a fatal day</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Draws on those gloomy hours, whose short steps may</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In Britains blushing Chronicle write more</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Of sanguine guilt, than a whole age before.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To tell our too neglected troops that we</l>
          <l rend="indent2">In a just cause are slow, we ready see</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Our rallied foes &#8212; nor wilt out sloathful crime</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Expunge, to say, Guilt wakend them by time.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">From every quarter the affrighted scout</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Brings swift alarums in, hovering about</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The clouded tops of the adjacent hills</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Like ominous vapours lie their troops, noise fills</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Our yet unrallied army &amp; we now</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Grown legible, in the contracted brow</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Discern whose heart looks pale with fear. &#8212; if in</l>
          <l rend="indent2">This rising storm of blood which doth begin</l>
          <l rend="indent2">To drop already, I&#8217;m not washt into</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The grave, my next safe quarter shall renew</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Acquaintance with Pharonnida &#8212; till then</l>
          <l rend="indent2">I leave the Muses to converse with men.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">William Chamberlayne, <title level="m">Pharonnida</title> (London, 1659), pp. 171&#8211;172.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>This man would have written blank verse wonderfully well. he mistook his bent &amp; in spite of an interesting story &amp; a bold imagination Pharonnida is forgotten. you see he was a royalist &#8212; why is C&#230;sar writing his commentaries in Alexandria<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Julius Caesar (100/102&#8211;44 BC) wrote <title level="m">Commentaries</title> on his campaigns, including those in Egypt.</note> or Brutus reading Plato in his tent<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of <title level="m">Julius Caesar</title>, Act 4, scene 3.</note> more renowned than Chamberlain finishing the canto in a manner which certainly is grand at the moment when Death was hovering around? you know Shakespear better than I do &#8212; look at Bellarius&#8217; speech &amp; take that as an answer to the question.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to <title level="m">Cymbeline</title>, but it is unclear precisely which speech by Belarius is meant.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> your friend though no citizen, who has no vote nor is likely to have any upon any occasion, who whether he consents or not must pay for Gods daylight since so commanded by representatives when he had rather represent himself is writing to you a long letter though at this time under the impulse of two contrary power intolerable Indolence &amp; impatient Curiosity &#8212; what I am curious for no human being can divine &#8212; I have Merlins prophecies<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Geoffrey of Monmouth (1100&#8211;1155; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Prophetiae Merlini</title> (pre&#8211;1135).</note> in my desk &amp; let them lie unconsulted to write to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	an ugly time to conclude but this cannot go to day unless this minute</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4">yours</salute>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">	I have not received the letter <ref target="people.html#CollinsCharles">Collins</ref> mentioned. remember me to him.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">	if any one passage here strike you as offensive you have my request to scratch it out &#8212; it is a horrid subject &#8212; like a current you no sooner touch it than it carries you away.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>