<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce180</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.180</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS has not survived.  Previously  published: Monthly Magazine, 2 (October 1796), 697&#8211;700 [from
                        where the text is taken] under pseudonym &#8216;T.Y.&#8217;. For attribution to Southey,
                        see Kenneth Curry, &#8216;Southey&#8217;s contributions to The Monthly
                            Magazine and The Athenaeum&#8217;, The Wordsworth Circle, 11 (1980), 215.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.180" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="180" type="letter">
        <head>180. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the
                            <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>,</ref> [c. <date when="1796-10">October 1796]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has not survived<lb />Previously published: <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>, 2 (October 1796), 697&#8211;700 [from
                        where the text is taken] under pseudonym &#8216;T.Y.&#8217;. For attribution to Southey,
                        see Kenneth Curry, &#8216;Southey&#8217;s contributions to <title level="j">The Monthly
                            Magazine</title> and <title level="j">The Athenaeum</title>&#8217;, <title level="j">The Wordsworth Circle</title>, 11 (1980), 215.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>SIR,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I NOW proceed to perform the promise I made, of presenting the
                    public with farther particulars relative to the poetry of Spain and
                    Portugal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Towards the close of the fifteenth century, was born Mosen Juan
                    Boscan Almogavar,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Almog&#225;ver de Bosc&#225;n (c.
                        1487&#8211;1542), Spanish poet who did much to introduce Italian verse forms into
                        his country.</note> the reformer of Spanish poetry; and, in the year 1503,
                    his more celebrated assistant and friend Garcilaso de la Vega.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Garcilaso de la Vega (c. 1501&#8211;1536), author of
                        sonnets, eclogues and odes.</note> Boscan was tutor to the great duke of
                        Alva:<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Fernando Alvarez De Toledo,
                        Duke of Alva (1508&#8211;1583), Spanish military commander in the
                        Netherlands.</note> &#8220;the heroic virtues that adorned the mind of the pupil
                    prove with what diligence and success the tutor performed his duty;&#8221; so says one
                    of his biographers.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Jos&#233; Lopez de
                        Sedano (1729&#8211;1801), <title level="m">El Parnaso Espa&#241;ol</title>, 9 vols
                        (1768&#8211;1778), VIII, p. xxxi. The translation is probably Southey&#8217;s
                        own.</note> Let not the reader detest the poet Boscan because he had the
                    misfortune to educate the detestable duke of Alva! Alexander had listened to the
                    lessons of Aristotle,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander the Great
                        (356&#8211;323 BC; reigned 336&#8211;323 BC) and his tutor Aristotle (384&#8211;322
                        BC).</note> and the son of Antoninus must have heard the precepts of his
                        father;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to
                        Lucius Verus (130&#8211;169; co-Emperor 160&#8211;169), adopted son and co-successor of
                        the Emperor Antoninus Pius (AD 86&#8211;161; reigned 138&#8211;161). Verus was a noted
                        military commander but led a dissipated life.</note> but no culture can
                    render the night-shade innocent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Before this period, the poetry of Spain was harsh and barbarous;
                    some of their old ballads, indeed, possess that simplicity which is superior to
                    all art, and which no art can bestow; there is, however, in the art of
                    versification something which, though it may fail to charm us, will at least
                    prevent us from being disgusted; how would the insipidity of Addison&#8217;s<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Addison (1672&#8211;1719; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> poems been received, had they been
                    dressed in the rhymes of Dr. Donne?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John
                        Donne (1572&#8211;1631; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Boscan himself tells us, in his dedication to the duchess de
                    Soma, that it was by the advice of Andres Nabagero, the Venetian ambassador,
                    that he introduced Italian metres and Italian taste into the Castilian poetry.
                    &#8220;We were conversing together at Grenada (says he) upon literary subjects, and
                    particularly upon the difference of languages, when he observed to me, that in
                    the Castilian tongue we had never attempted sonnets, and other kinds of
                    composition used by the best authors of Italy; and he not only said this to me,
                    but urged me to set the example. A few days afterwards, I departed for my home,
                    and musing upon many things during the long and solitary journey, frequently
                    thought upon what Nabagero had advised: and thus I began to attempt this kind of
                    verse. At first I found some difficulty, because it is very complex (<hi rend="ital">muy artificioso</hi>) and has many peculiarities different from
                    our own: afterwards, from the partiality we naturally feel towards our own
                    productions, I thought that I had succeeded well, and gradually grew warm and
                    eager in the pursuit. This, however, would not have been sufficient to stimulate
                    me to proceed, had not Garcilaso encouraged me, whose judgment, not only in my
                    opinion, but in that of the whole world, is esteemed as a certain rule.&#8221;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Almog&#225;ver de Bosc&#225;n, &#8216;Libro Secunda Delas
                        Obras de Boscan ala Duquest de Soma&#8217;, in <title level="m">Las Obras de
                            Boscan y Algunas de Garcilaso de la Vega Repartidas en Quarto
                            Libros</title> (Madrid, 1543), fols xx&#8211;xxi. The English translation is
                        probably Southey&#8217;s own.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This innovation, like all other improvements, was not introduced
                    without opposition. Inigo Lopez de Mendoza,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish poet Inigo Lopez de Mendoza Marques de Santillana
                        (1398&#8211;1456).</note> the celebrated marquis of Santillana, had made use of
                    the Italian metres many years before. Don Diego de Mendoza,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish poet Diego Hurtado de Mendoza
                        (1504&#8211;1575).</note> of the same noble house, had the honour of co-operating
                    with Boscan and Garcilaso in a more successful attempt; though such is the
                    caprice of Fame, that he is better known in England as the author of Lazarillo
                    de Tormes,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">La Vida de
                            Lazarillo de Tormes y de Sus Fortunas y Adversidades</title> (1554), an
                        anonymously published novella, often credited as being the origin of the
                        picaresque genre.</note> than as the historian, the poet, and one of the
                    reformers of his country&#8217;s literature: to the disgrace of mankind, whatever work
                    is lively and loose, will certainly be popular. The name of Garcilaso has
                    eclipsed that of his assistants, and he is to this day esteemed the best of the
                    Spanish poets, yet the little volume of Garcilaso&#8217;s productions is more
                    distinguished by melody of versification than sublimity of thought. The volume
                    consists of 184 pages, of which 110 are taken up by three eclogues!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Several of Garcilaso de la Vega&#8217;s eclogues were
                        printed in a collaborative publication with his fellow poet Almog&#225;ver de
                        Bosc&#225;n, <title level="m">Las Obras de Boscan y Algunas de Garcilaso de la
                            Vega Repartidas en Quarto Libros</title> (Madrid, 1543).</note> In the
                    present &#230;ra of taste, no poet possessed of common sense would ever <hi rend="ital">commit</hi> a pastoral; and none but a Spanish or Portuguese
                    poet would ever have extended one to upwards of seventeen hundred lines!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All persons of unvitiated tastes love the country: descriptions
                    of rural scenery, and images drawn from rural life, never worry us; but a
                    shepherd and a crook, and a pipe, is quite as unnatural as one of the cannibal
                    giants of romance, and infinitely less agreeable as a companion by the
                    fire-side. The Spanish Parnassus is very much infested by these gentry, and they
                    are equally troublesome on the Portuguese side of the mountain. Yet, if the
                    following defence of shepherds be not convincing, it is at least curious and
                    amusing. It is prefixed to the Eclogues of Francisco Rodriguez Lobo.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese poet Francisco Rodriguez Lobo (c.
                        1550&#8211;1617).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Nature has hidden in rough shells, at the bottom of the sea,
                    those pearls to which man has affixed such value; she has hidden that gold with
                    which our souls are fettered, in the bowels of the earth, amid barbarous
                    nations, and in distant countries: she has guarded the sea with rocks, and sown
                    it with dangers, to place boundaries to our desires, and lengthen the period of
                    our lives: but Evil, to deprive us of our tranquillity, laid open these secrets,
                    and hid from us the true knowledge where real tranquillity is to be found. Then
                    did this malignant spirit disfigure the shepherds with coarse vile garments, and
                    represent their life of contentment as a life of mean and despicable labour; and
                    by these magical delusions were we taught to despise the only treasure which the
                    earth affords to render the mind happy: but when this fascination is removed,
                    and we see things clearly, how much more beautiful appear the various colours
                    with which the fields are apparelled, and the trees, and the sun, and the
                    horizon beautiful when he sets, than all the deceitful trappings of Vanity! How
                    much more delightful to our ears is the song of innocent birds, than the sound
                    of flattering tongues, that endeavour to entrap our reason! Is not the rock that
                    hangs over the stream, in whose caverns the birds dwell, and under whose shade
                    the fishes sport, more to be admired than the sumptuous and superb edifice, that
                    cannot so well resist the force of the tempest, or the secret sap of time? Where
                    can life pass more delightfully or more tranquilly than among the flocks and
                    herds? How much more secure is the enjoyment of these than the hopes of the
                    court, and the deceits of the city! And if we have so often sighed for that
                    happy age of gold, it is for this advantage, exceeding all others, that men
                    lived then like shepherds, and followed their flocks, and cultivated the earth:
                    and this truth is clearly proved; for the first man whom God created held this
                    office, and the title which God gave him, was that of lord of the animal world;
                    and Abel, the first martyr, in whom the church began, and the other children of
                    Adam, tended their flocks: so likewise did Abraham and Isaac, and Jacob with his
                    beloved Rachel, and Esau; Joseph and his brethren were shepherds, as they
                    confessed to Pharaoh. Moses and Zipporah, Saul and David, kings of Israel, and
                    Mesa, king of Moab, had executed this honourable office; and king Cyrus had
                    exercised it among the ancient Persians. Romulus and Remus, the founders of
                    Rome, with Faustulus, who educated them, kept sheep; and among those valiant
                    Romans, the fame of whose exploits has echoed over the world, we read of many
                    whose names discover their origin, such as the Vituli, the Vitellii, the Porcii,
                    the Capri, the Tauri and the Bubulci. Many persons have risen to the highest
                    dignities, from the pastoral state: Giges, king of Lydia; Sophy, king of the
                    Turks; Primislaus, king of Bohemia; Tamerlane, emperor of the Scythians; Justin,
                    emperor of the Romans; Viriatus, captain of the Portuguese; and Sixtus the
                    first, the Roman pontiff: and, in truth, what is the life of a shepherd, but the
                    similitude of empire? but a system of government, with moderation and mildness?
                    For what can be more similar to the government of a kingdom than the management
                    of a flock? To defend them from wild beasts, to secure them from robbers, to
                    guide them to good pastures, cool shades, and clear waters; to threaten them
                    with his voice, to chastise with the crook those who stray; to amuse them with
                    the pipe and with the song, to cure them with herbs when they are sick; to be
                    clothed with their wool, to feed upon their milk, and thus to pass peaceably
                    through life? Among the vain deities whom the blinded Gentiles worshipped,
                    Apollo, Mercury, Daphne, and Pan, and Proteus, and Paris, and Polyphemus, were
                    shepherds; and the true God whom we serve, is frequently styled a shepherd, in
                    the holy Scriptures; so ancient and so honourable is the pastoral life, which
                    the avarice of men has now made despicable!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Much knowledge is certainly necessary for a shepherd; an
                    acquaintance with the nature of soils and pastures, the virtues of herbs, the
                    changes of weather, the movements of the heavenly bodies, the effects of the
                    sun, and the qualities of animals; and this life, though the most quiet,
                    produces in its employments all things necessary for our subsistence: wool,
                    milk, skins, the flesh of animals, herbs, grain, fruit. What life, then, can be
                    more delightful than the pastoral life? or what prejudice can be greater than
                    that which denies this truth?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;What style can be more conformable to reason, or less vitiated,
                    than the simple style of the shepherd? and therefore is it that the ancient
                    writers have delivered their precepts in the pastoral language, as being most
                    pure and natural. Under this allegory, Solomon veiled the mysteries of our
                    faith, in his Songs to his beloved; instructing us, by his lofty theme, and by a
                    strain of poetry as sublime in itself, as it is humble in its similitude; which
                    example alone would be sufficient, with the men of this age, to dignify pastoral
                    productions. In this style the Greeks and Romans, and the Italians, the
                    Spaniards, and our Portuguese, have written works, many in number, and rare in
                    quality; marvellous works, to enumerate which would be another new undertaking!
                    Therefore, curious reader, I present to you the manners and language of
                    shepherds, as the true doctrine of wisdom. I do not give you gilded pills of
                    poison, nor offer to you flowers that conceal a viper; instead of these you have
                    pearls in the shell, and plain honesty instead of polished falsehood.&#8221;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Discuros Sobre a Vida, e Estilo dos
                        Pastores&#8217;, from <title level="m">Obras Politicas, e Pastoriz de Franscisco
                            Rodrigues Lobo</title>, 4 vols (Lisbon, 1774), IV, pp. 239&#8211;243. The
                        English translation is probably Southey&#8217;s own.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So curiously has this ingenious Portuguese defended pastoral
                    poetry! But though we may agree with him that the life he describes is the most
                    natural and most honourable state of man, we shall be very far from
                    acknowledging, that either his eclogues, or those of any other poet, fairly
                    represent it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Garcilaso de la Vega, in the most enormous of his eclogues, has
                    introduced almost action enough for a drama.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Garcilaso de la Vega&#8217;s &#8216;Ecloga Secunda&#8217; was 1900 lines
                        long.</note> Albanio opens it, with a soliloquy of lamentations, and then he
                    falls asleep. Salicio then enters, singing a translation of Horace&#8217;s favourite
                    ode, &#8220;<hi rend="ital">Beatus ille qui procul negotiis</hi>,&#8221;<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace (65&#8211;8 BC), <title level="m">Epodes</title>, 2, line 1. The Latin translates as &#8216;Happy the man who,
                        far from the troubles of commerce&#8217;.</note> of which there are above twenty
                    versions in the Spanish language. In the middle of it, he stops short, on seeing
                    a man sleeping, dilates upon the excellence of sleep; and then, recognizing
                    Albanio, informs the reader, that he knows him, that he was once very happy, and
                    is now very miserable, but that he had not yet learned the cause. Albanio now
                    talks in his sleep and Salicio interrupts and wakes him. He now requests him to
                    relate his history, and Albanio tells a very long story of his being the
                    intimate friend of a young female relation, with whom he used to hunt; how he
                    one day told his love; she left him, and he is dying with despair. After they
                    are gone out, Camille enters, and lies down by a fountain to take her <hi rend="ital">siesta</hi> &#8212; her evening&#8217;s nap. Albanio finds her, and seizes
                    her, but releases her on her solemn promise to remain and hear him, which she,
                    as soon as released, breaks, and runs away, and Albanio runs mad. Salicio now
                    enters, with Nemoroso: Nemoroso tells a long story about a magician, which is a
                    panegyric upon the family of Alva; and the eclogue concludes with their
                    resolution to get Albanio cured by this magician.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In this very ill-planned poem, Garcilaso has perpetuated his
                    friendship for Boscan, and perhaps no lines in the poem can be perused with more
                    pleasure than these, in which he bears testimony to the virtues of his
                    friend:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent6"> &#8220;Then, hand in hand,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">A youth approach&#8217;d, with Phoebus; in his face</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The skilful eye might read benevolence</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And wisdom; he was perfected in all</l>
          <l rend="indent2">The lore and various arts of courtesy</l>
          <l rend="indent2">That humanize mankind: the graceful port,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And the fair front of open manliness, </l>
          <l rend="indent2">Discover&#8217;d Boscan; and that fire illumin&#8217;d</l>
          <l rend="indent2">His generous face that animates his song,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">With never-fading splendour there to shine.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Garcilaso de la Vega, &#8216;Ecloga Secunda&#8217;,
                            lines 1326-1335; the translation is probably Southey&#8217;s own.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> Garcilaso has, in his second eclogue, introduced a Moorish metre,
                    which has been seldom imitated, and, indeed, which did not deserve to be
                    imitated at all: it is making the middle of the second line rhyme to the end of
                    the first: the middle of the third to the end of the second, &amp;c. Sir
                    Philip Sidney, who was always trying experiments in versification, and making
                    innovations instead of improvements, has left us some specimens of this:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Thy safety sure is wrapped in <hi rend="ital">destruction</hi>,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">For that <hi rend="ital">construction</hi> thine own words do
                            <hi rend="ital">bear</hi>;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">A man to <hi rend="ital">fear</hi> a woman&#8217;s moodie <hi rend="ital">eye</hi>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent2">Makes reason <hi rend="ital">lie</hi> a slave to servile <hi rend="ital">sense</hi>,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">A weak <hi rend="ital">defence</hi>, where weakness is thy <hi rend="ital">force</hi>;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">So is <hi rend="ital">remorce</hi> in folly dearly bought.
                            <note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip Sidney&#8217;s (1554&#8211;1586;
                                <title level="m">DNB</title>) eclogue &#8216;Dicus and Dorus&#8217; in <title level="m">The Countess of Pembroke&#8217;s Arcadia</title> (1590&#8211;1593),
                            Book 2.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> This novelty, however, is to the eye and not to the ear; it is
                    only rhyming regularly in short and irregular lines. A peculiarity similar to
                    this, though infinitely superior, is much used by the Welsh poets; and the Welsh
                    bard, Edward Williams, has given a very happy specimen in English:<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Williams (1747&#8211;1826; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Poems, Lyric and Pastoral</title>, 2
                        vols (London, 1794), II, p. 158.</note>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Retir&#8217;d amongst our native <hi rend="ital">hills</hi>,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And far from <hi rend="ital">ills</hi> of greatness,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">We live, delighted with our <hi rend="ital">lot</hi>,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And trim our <hi rend="ital">cot</hi> with neatness.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">We wisdom seek and calm <hi rend="ital">content</hi>,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> They both <hi rend="ital">frequent</hi> our dwelling;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">From these a deathless comfort <hi rend="ital">springs</hi>,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The joys of <hi rend="ital">kings</hi> excelling.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p>In this the objection to the Moorish metre is removed, by the alternation of a
                    regular rhyme.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Both Boscan and Garcilaso possessed more learning than taste, and
                    more taste than genius. Their poems, particularly those of the latter, are full
                    of imitations from the ancients; they seldom disgust the reader by bombast, but
                    they never elevate his mind by the sublime. There is more prettiness in Boscan,
                    more tenderness in Garcilaso. The following little piece of Boscan is not
                    unhappy, and by the many imitations of it, it appears to have been a favourite
                    conceit:</p>
        <p rend="indent4"> TO A MIRROR.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Since still my passion-pleading strains</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Have fail&#8217;d her heart to move,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Show, Mirror! to that lovely maid,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The charms that make me love.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Reflect on her the thrilling beam</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Of magic from her eye,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">So, like Narcissus, she shall gaze,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And self-enamour&#8217;d die.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Almog&#225;ver de Bosc&#225;n, &#8216;&#193; un Espejo&#8217;. The English
                            translation is probably Southey&#8217;s own.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> The sonnets of Garcilaso are the most interesting of his works:
                    there are some as beautiful, but none superior, to the following:</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">As when the mother, weak in tenderness,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Hears her sick child with prayer and tears implore</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Some seeming good, that makes his pain the less,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Yet, with short ease! the future evil more;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Even as her fondness yields to his vain will</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> She hastes to gratify her sickly son &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Anticipating then the coming ill,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Sadly she sits, and weeps what she has done.</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thus have I pamper&#8217;d my distemper&#8217;d mind;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And yielded thus to fancy&#8217;s wayward mood,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Poor dupe of Fancy! self-condemn&#8217;d to find</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The future anguish in the present good. &#8212;</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Thus do I waste a wretched life away,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">And nightly weep the errors of the day!<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Garcilaso de la Vega, &#8216;Como la tierne madre,
                            quel doliente&#8217;. The English translation is probably Southey&#8217;s
                            own.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> Boscan paraphrased the Hero and Leander of Mus&#230;us, of course he
                    injured it; for to paraphrase is to dilate, and to dilate, to weaken.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Almog&#225;ver de Bosc&#225;n&#8217;s version of <title level="m">Hero and Leander</title> is in <title level="m">Las Obras de
                            Boscan y Algunas de Garcilaso de la Vega repartidas en quarto
                            libros</title> (Madrid, 1543), fols lxxiii&#8211;cxvii. Southey&#8217;s friend,
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, published his own translation of Musaeus&#8217;s (fl.
                        c. early 6th century) poem in 1797.</note> He survived his friend, Garcilaso
                    (who was killed in battle) but a few years: they both died young; but their
                    celebrity will always last; for though Spain may hereafter produce better poets,
                    the glory of reforming the national poetry must still remain.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent11"> T. Y.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>