<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce193</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.193</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 299&#8211;301 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.193" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="193" type="letter">
        <head>193. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1797-01-01">1&#8211;7 January 1797</date>
          </head><p>Address: G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: BJA/ 9/ 97<lb />Watermark: [Obscured by MS binding]<lb />Endorsement: 1 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1797<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 299&#8211;301 [in part].</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">
          <date when="1797-01-01">January the first. 1797.</date> So Bedford begins the year that will terminate our correspondence. I mean to spend one summer in North Wales studying the country for Madoc, &amp; do not intend writing to you then &#8212; because you shall be with me: &amp; for all the rest of the days I look on to clearly, the view is bounded by the accursed smoke of London. methinks like Camoens I could dub it Babylon &amp; write lamentations for the &#8220;Sion&#8221; of my birth place,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In Luis Vaz de Camo&#235;ns&#8217; (c. 1524&#8211;1580) &#8216;Babylon and Sion&#8217; (c. 1552), &#8216;Babylon&#8217; represented Goa and &#8216;Zion&#8217; represented Lisbon.</note> having like him no reason to regret the past <del rend="strikethrough">but txxxxxx it</del> except that it is not the present. it is the country I want. a field thistle is to me worth all the flowers of Covent Garden.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	However <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> happiness is a flower that will blossom anywhere &#8212; &amp; I expect to be happy &#8212; even in London. you know who is to watch at my gate, &amp; if he will let in any of your club &#8212; well &amp; good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Time &amp; Experience seem to have assimilated us. we think equally ill of mankind, &amp; from the complexion of your late letter, I believe you think as badly as I do of their rulers. I fancy you are mounted above the freezing point of aristocracy to the temperate <del rend="strikethrough">regions</del> degree where I have fallen. am <hi rend="ital">I</hi> not obliged to <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> for leading you round? but your mind is yet in a revolutionary state &#8212; mine is calm &amp; settled. I have a belief in politics &amp; religion, both of which I apprehend you want. methinks <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> the last two years have made me the <hi rend="ital">elder</hi>, but you know I never allow the aristocracy of years.</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1797-01-02">Monday</date>. I have this day finished my letters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>, published in 1797.</note> &#8212; &amp; now my times is my own. my &#8220;race is run&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of John Dryden (1631&#8211;1700; <title level="m">DNB</title>), &#8216;Sigismonda and Guiscardo&#8217;, line 337, published in <title level="m">Fables Ancient and Modern</title> (1700).</note> &#8212; &amp; perhaps the next book of mine that makes it appearance may be my &#8220;posthumous works&#8221;! I go to Bristol tomorrow to be present at its completion. you may perhaps receive the volume by this day week. on Saturday next I return to Bath. you shall know when I come as soon as I know myself &#8212; the sooner the better.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I must be on the Surrey side of the water. this will <del rend="strikethrough">please</del> suit me &amp; please you. I am familiar with the <hi rend="ital">names</hi> of your club &#8212; shall I ever be so with them sober? naturally of a reserved disposition, there was a considerable period of my life in which high spirits &#8212; quick feelings &#8212; &amp; principles enthusiastically imbibed, made me talkative; experience has taught me wisdom, &amp; I am again as silent &#8212; as <hi rend="ital">self centering</hi> as in early youth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	After the nine hours law study &#8212; I shall &lt;have&gt; a precious fragment of the day <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> &lt;at&gt; my own disposal. now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I must be a miser of time &#8212; for I am just as sleepy a fellow as you remember me at <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref>. I tell the story of John &amp; the robbers, &amp; never see a wasp without thinking of the myriads we destroyed. you see I am not collected enough to write &#8212; this plaguey cough interrupts me &amp; shakes all the ideas in my brain out of their places.</p>
        <p rend="right">
          <date when="1797-01-07">Saturday. Jan. 7.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	A long interval <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> &amp; it has not been employed agreably. I have been taken ill at Bristol. my trullibubs were in a state of insurrection &amp; sent every thing up that I sent down, I was afraid of a fever &#8212; but the timely aid of some pills opened the back door &#8212; &amp; I hope all the mutinous particles have been ejected. a giddiness of the head which accompanied this seizure rendered me utterly unfit for anything. I was well nurst &amp; am well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	this happened at the house of <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref> &#8212; excepting <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> &#8212; the only man whom I shall leave with regret in this part of the world. when I get to London I have some comfortable plans made but much depends on the likeability of your new friends. you say you have engaged some of them to meet me. now if you taught them to expect any thing in me they must owe their disappointment to you. remember that I am as reserved to others as I am open to you. you have seen a hedge hog roll himself up when noticed? even so do I shelter myself in my own thoughts &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I will not ask you to explain some few little mysteries [MS torn] your last. we shall meet so soon &#8212; but you may send me your Mus&#230;us<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s translation of Mus&#230;us (fl. c. early 6th century), <title level="m">The Loves of Hero and Leander</title>, was published in 1797.</note> first: you should do as you are done by in this respect &#8212; I never send to ask you when you wish to receive my books but pack them off by the first coach. Bob Banyard<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a nickname for <ref target="people.html#NaresRobert">Robert Nares</ref>.</note> has announced you often enough &amp; pompously enough.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I have sketched out a tragedy on the Martyrdom of Joan of Arc which is capable of making a good closet drama my ideas of tragedy differ from those generally followed. there is seldom <hi rend="ital">nature</hi> enough in the dialogue. even Shakespere gets upon the stilts sometimes. the dramatist ought rather to display a knowledge of the workings of the human heart, than his own imagination. high straind metaphors can rarely be introduced with propriety &#8212; similies never &#8212;. do you think I shall strip tragedy of all its ornaments? this time must discover &#8212; yet look at the dramatic parts of Joan of Arc they are best &#8212; the dialogue is impassioned but it is natural. John Doe &amp; Richard Roe<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Fictitious characters, often used to signify the plaintiff (Doe) and defendant (Roe) in legal suits.</note> must however form the chief personages in the last act of my life. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> will it be a tragedy or a comedy? however I will not now think of the catastrophe but rather look on to the pleasant scenes when we shall meet. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	fare you well. I shall write with my book which the frost has delayed. it all be done this day week.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4">				yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">						RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>