<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce142</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.142</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 258&#8211;261 [in part, and giving the appearance of being two separate letters: 30 November 1795 and undated].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="142" type="letter">
        <head>142. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1795-11-29">29 [&#8211;30] November 1795</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: FALMOUTH<lb />Postmark: CDE/ 3/ 95<lb />Watermark: Crown and anchor with G R underneath<lb />Endorsement: 29 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1795<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 258&#8211;261 [in part, and giving the appearance of being two separate letters: 30 November 1795 and undated].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1795-11-29">Sunday. 12. o clock. 29. Nov. 1795.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	Bedford our Summons arrived this morning. the vessel goes Tuesday &amp; when you receive this, I shall be casting up my accounts with the fishes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> you have my Will. if the ship founders or any other chance <del rend="strikethrough">gives me</del> sends me to supper &#8212; all my papers are yours. they are with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> part, &amp; part with <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>. <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> relic-worship is founded upon human feelings &amp; you will value them. there is little danger of accidents, but there can be no harm in these few lines. All my letters are at your disposal &#8212; but it would be right to return your brothers. &amp; if I be drowned &#8212; do not you be surprized if I should pay you a visit. for if permitted, &amp; if it can be done without terrifying or any ways injuring you I certainly will do it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	But I shall visit you in propria person&#226; in the summer. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Would you had been with me the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">14 November 1795, the day of Southey&#8217;s marriage to Edith Fricker.</note> twas a melancholy day yet mingled with such feelings!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	you will get a letter from Madrid. write you to Lisbon. I expect to find letters there, &amp; the expectation will form the pleasantest thoughts I shall experience on my journey.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I should like to find your Mus&#230;us<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Grosvenor Charles Bedford&#8217;s translation of Mus&#230;us (fl. c. early 6th century), <title level="m">The Loves of Hero and Leander</title>, was not published until 1797.</note> at Bristol on my return. if you will direct it to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Miss E Fricker</ref> (heigh ho! <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>.) at <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottles</ref> High Street Bristol &#8212; he will convey it to her. &amp; I believe next to receiving any thing from me, something for me &amp; from my friend will be the most agreable occurrence during my absence. I give you this direction as it will be sure to reach her. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> will be as a parlour boarder with the <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Miss Cottles</ref> (his sisters) two women of elegant &amp; accomplishd manners. the eldest lived as governess in Ld Derbys<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Smith Stanley, 12th Earl of Derby (1752&#8211;1834; <title level="m">DNB</title>), sportsman and Whig politician.</note> family <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> a little while &#8212; &amp; you will have some opinion of them when I say, that they make even bigotry amiable. they are very religious, &amp; the eldest (who is but <del rend="strikethrough">t</del> twenty three) wished me to read good books &#8212; the advice came from the heart &#8212; she thinks very highly of me, but fancies me irreligious because I frequent no place of worship &amp; indulge speculations beyond reason.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del rend="strikethrough">God bless &amp; prosper</del> God bless &amp; prosper you &#8212; &amp; grant I may find you as happy on my arrival, as I hope &amp; expect to be.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">yrs sincerely</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1795-11-30">Falmouth. Monday evening.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">	Well <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref>. here I am waiting only for a wind. your letter arrived a few hours before me. that to Bath came &lt;to&gt; Nanswhyden.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">	I have seen Lord Butes Chaplain, <ref target="people.html#MaberGeorgeMartin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Maber</ref> who goes to Madrid with us. a useful rather than an agreable companion. my heart is sick at the thought of being so long without a friend. who is it says &#8220;thou knowest not </p>
          <p>How sharper than a serpents tooth it is</p>
          <p>To have a faithless friend &#8212;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of <title level="m">King Lear</title>, Act 1, scene 4, lines 287&#8211;289.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">	I recollect as I write that I am altering Lear. this reflection however springs from your [MS torn] my own feelings. I did take a viper to my bosom [MS torn] to injure me was like liking the file.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">	thank you for your verses. a few alterations would make it an excellent ode. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> you will see &amp; know &amp; love. but her virtues are of the domestic order &amp; you will love her in proportion as you know her. I hate your daffidowndilly women &#8212; aye &amp; men too. the violet is ungaudy in its appearance, tho a sweeter flower perfumes not the evening gale &#8212;. tis equally her wish to see you. oh <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> &#8212; when I think of our winter evenings that will arrive &#8212; &amp; then look at myself arrayed for a voyage in an inn parlour! <del rend="strikethrough">whilst to xxx xx xxxxxxxxxx xxxxxxx dry my eye</del> I scarcely know whether the tear that starts into my eye proceeds from anticipated pleasure or present melancholy.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">	I am never comfortable at an inn. boughten hospitality are two ill-connected ideas. &#8212; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> I half shudder to think that a plank only will divide the husband of <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> from the unfathomed ocean! &amp; did I believe its efficacy could burn a hecatomb to Neptune<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In Roman mythology, the god of the sea.</note> with as much devotion as ever burned or [MS torn] Ph&#230;acia.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">An island in the Ionian sea whose inhabitants were renowned for their dissolute behaviour.</note> farewell &#8212;</p>
          <p rend="indent3">			Robert Southey.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>