<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.about</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-03-15">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>Lynda Pratt</author>
            <title>General Introduction</title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.about" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
              <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
              <pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#g5 #g21" scheme="#genre" />
        <catRef target="#EEd.26.1.names" scheme="#people" />
        <catRef target="#EEd.26.1.places" scheme="#places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change n="2" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="1" who="#AB">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="paratext">
        <head>About this Edition</head>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Editorial Methodology</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> is divided into eight Parts: I: 1791-1797, II:1798-1803,
					III:1804-09, IV:1810-15, V:1816-21, VI:1822-27, VII:1828-33, VIII:1833-39. </p>
        <p>The General Introduction outlines the project&#8217;s research context. In addition, each individual Part has a brief introductory essay
					and a chronology covering key events in Southey&#8217;s life. </p>
        <p>Throughout the edition, letters are presented in chronological order, each letter being assigned its own number. Unpublished
					letters have all been newly transcribed from manuscript. Where letters have been previously published, we have returned to and
					transcribed the original manuscript when it survives. In cases where we have been unable to locate the manuscript of a published
					letter, copy-text is taken from the published version and this is recorded in the editorial headnote. </p>
        <p>All letters are transcribed in full and editorial intervention in the text has been kept to a minimum. Southey&#8217;s original spelling,
					and mis-spelling, grammar and punctuation has been retained. Deletions are indicated by striking through the deleted word or
					phrase, but without any attempt to indicate the heaviness of the deletion: e.g. &#8216;<hi rend="strikethrough">he said</hi>&#8217;. Throughout the text, &#8216;x&#8217; is used to
					indicate an illegible character: e.g. &#8216;he xxid&#8217;. Underlining is indicated by italics: e.g. &#8216;<hi rend="ital">he</hi> said&#8217;.
					Editorial [...] within the text of an individual letter are used to indicate issues relating to the manuscript: a tear, cut,
					missing section or area obscured by a seal mark or blot, or a substantial section of a letter in the hand of a co-correspondent.
					See, for example, Letter 56, co-written with Grosvenor Charles Bedford. Editorial &lt;...&gt; are used to indicate an
					authorial insertion of text above or below the line. </p>
        <p>Each letter has an editorial headnote which records the manuscript location and any previous instances of publication. It also
					deals with other relevant issues, such as endorsements, watermarks, postmarks, franks, stamps and dating. This edition provides
					important new information about when many of Southey&#8217;s letters were actually written, and re-dates letters that have been misdated
					or misleadingly dated by previous editors. For example, Southey&#8217;s earliest correspondence is here demonstrated to date to late
					1791, rather than 1790 as claimed by John Wood Warter. The following conventions have been observed in dating individual letters:
					[...] is used in headnotes to indicate an editorial dating; &#8216;c.&#8217; to indicate a dating taken from the postmark or from internal
					evidence within an individual letter; &#8216;before&#8217; is used either when a letter contains an authorial date, but there is evidence
					within the letter that it was begun before that time, or when an endorsement on the letter indicates its date of receipt; &#8216;after&#8217;
					is used when a letter contains an authorial date, but there is evidence within the letter that it was continued after that time;
					&#8216;?&#8217; is used to indicate a dating about which there remains some uncertainty.</p>
        <p>Detailed information about Southey&#8217;s correspondents, along with other important figures in his letters, can be found in the
					&#8216;Biographies&#8217; section. Information about where Southey lived and the homes of friends which he visited is provided in the &#8216;Places&#8217;
					section of this edition. </p>
        <p>Editorial notes to the text are used to clarify references to persons, books, places, and events within the main body of each
					individual letter. They also identify quotations and provide translations of foreign language material.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">People</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Lynda Pratt is Reader in Romanticism and Director of the Centre for Regional Literature and Culture at the University of
					Nottingham. She has published widely on Southey and his circle. She was general editor of <title level="m">Robert Southey:
						Poetical Works, 1793-1810</title>, 5 vols (2004) and is co-general editor, with Tim Fulford, of the forthcoming <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>, 4 vols (Pickering and Chatto, 2011). Her edited collection
						<title level="m">Robert Southey and the Contexts of English Romanticism</title> was published in 2006.</p>
        <p>Tim Fulford is a Professor of English at Nottingham Trent University. He has published several monographs in which Southey
					features, most recently <title level="m">Romantic Indians</title> (2006). He edited <title level="m">Thalaba the
					Destroyer</title>, vol. 3 of <title level="m">Robert Southey: Poetical Works, 1793-1810</title> (2004) and is co-general editor,
					with Lynda Pratt, of the forthcoming <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. Fulford and Pratt's
					edition the <title level="m">Collected Letters of Robert Bloomfield and his Circle</title> is also online at <title level="m">Romantic Circles</title>
        </p>
        <p>Ian Packer is Reader in History at the University of Lincoln. His publications include <title level="m">The Letters of Arnold
						Stephenson Rowntree to Mary Katherine Rowntree</title> (Cambridge 2002). He has published widely on political and religious
					history and is an editor on <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. </p>
        <p>Carol Bolton is Lecturer in English at Loughborough University. Her monograph <title level="m">Writing the Empire: Robert Southey
						and Romantic Colonialism</title> was published in 2007. She has published widely on Romantic period writing and is an editor
					on <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. </p>
        <p>W. A. Speck is Emeritus Professor of History at the University of Leeds and Special Professor in the School of English Studies at
					the University of Nottingham. His <title level="m">Robert Southey: Entire Man of Letters</title> was published by Yale University
					Press in 2006.</p>
        <p>Averill Buchanan is an AHRC-funded research fellow on <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> and is based
					at the University of Nottingham. She completed an AHRC-funded PhD at Queen&#8217;s University Belfast in 2004 on the Anglo-Irish writer
					Mary Tighe. Her monograph <title level="m">Mary Tighe, 1772-1810: The Irish Psyche</title> is contracted to Ashgate and will be
					published in 2011.</p>
        <p>Sam Ward is an AHRC-funded research fellow on <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> and is based at the
					University of Nottingham. He completed an AHRC-funded PhD at Nottingham Trent University in 2006. He has published peer-reviewed
					essays on John Clare John and Robert Bloomfield. His research interests also include James Montgomery.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Contact</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The editors welcome comments and corrections. Please contact:</p>
        <p>Lynda Pratt: <ref target="mailto:lynda.pratt@nottingham.ac.uk">Lynda.Pratt@nottingham.ac.uk</ref>
        </p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Permissions</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The editor thanks the following for permission to reproduce manuscripts in their collections: </p>
        <p>North America</p>
        <p>Beinecke Library, Yale University; Berg Collection, New York Public Library; Boston Public Library, Boston; Brown University
					Library; Columbia University Library; Cornell University Library; Duke University Library; Harry Ransom Center, University of
					Texas, Austin; Hispanic Society of America, New York; Houghton Library, Harvard University; Huntington Library, San Marino;
					McLennan Library, McGill University, Montreal; Morgan Library, New York; New York Public Library (General Manuscript collection);
					Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library; Princeton University Library; Spencer Library, University of Kansas; Tulane
					University Library.</p>
        <p>United Kingdom </p>
        <p>Bodleian Library, Oxford; Bristol City Library, Bristol; British Library, London; Brotherton Library, Leeds University; Keswick
					Museum and Art Gallery, Keswick; Liverpool City Library, Liverpool; National Library of Scotland, Edinburgh; National Library of
					Wales, Aberystwyth; Sterling Library, Senate House, University of London.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part One</title> has been made possible by the generosity, help and
					support of a number of individuals and institutions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The general editors thank the Arts and Humanities Research Council for a Resource Enhancement award. Lynda Pratt
					would like to thank the Arts and Humanities Research Council for a Research Leave grant; the Leverhulme Trust for a Research
					Fellowship; the British Academy for a Small Research grant; the Beinecke Library, Yale University, for an Osborn fellowship; the
					Huntington Library, San Marino, for a Michael Connell fellowship; the Friends of Princeton University library for a research
					grant; and the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Centre, University of Texas, Austin, for a research fellowship. Tim Fulford would
					like to thank the Leverhulme Trust for a Research Fellowship. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title> has also benefited from grants from the Humanities
					Research Centre, University of Nottingham, the Humanities and Social Sciences Strategic Research Fund, University of Nottingham
					and the English Department, Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The editorial team are indebted to the following individuals for their advice, support and assistance in completing
						<title level="m">Part One</title> of this edition: Frances Banks, Anthony Bowen, Averill Buchanan, David Eastwood, Parvin
					Fatemi, Caroline Franklin, Michael J. Franklin, Lynne Hapgood, Laura Mandell, Tilar J. Mazzeo, Souvik Mukherjee, Mike Quilligan,
					Dave Rettenmaier, Nicholas Roe, Diego Saglia, Bill Speck, Sam Ward, Susan J. Wolfson, David Worrall, Duncan Wu and Nahem
					Yousaf.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">About the Design</hi>
        </p>
        <p>This electronic edition was TEI-encoded by Averill Buchanan under the supervision of Laura Mandell and her team at Miami University
					of Ohio, and with the assistance of David Rettenmaier and Mike Quilligan at the University of Maryland. Mandell transformed the
					TEI files into HTML by using modified versions of the transforms provided by the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org">TEI</ref>. The
					HTML pages do not use frames but rather make extensive use of tables and stylesheets for layout and presentation. The site works
					best when viewed with Mozilla Firefox v. 3, Netscape 4.0, Internet Explorer 4.0, or higher, or a comparable browser; earlier
					browsers may not display everything properly.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>