<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce222</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.222</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.222" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="222" type="letter">
        <head>222. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Walpole Bedford</ref>, <date when="1797-06-11">11 June 1797</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Horace Walpole Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb />Stamped: &#8216;CHRIST/ CHURCH&#8217;<lb />Watermark: [Obscured by MS binding]<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1797-06-11">Sunday. June 11th. 1797.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	You who love to be at the <del rend="strikethrough">end</del> &lt;opposite&gt; end of a stick &amp; a string <del rend="strikethrough">with</del> &lt;to the&gt; maggot <del rend="strikethrough">at the others</del> would like Christ Church, in summer. in winter you would like it still more for as the waters swell up to the first floor you might sit by the fire side up to your knees in water &amp; fish. I delight in a clear stream &#8212; there is such a world of business going on in it! &#8212; I shall muse upon in verse one day. a flat country is not the most beautiful, &amp; yet every kind of country has beauties of its own. I have got some acquaintance here too &#8220;for my names-sake&#8221;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title level="m">John</title> 15: 21.</note> &#8212; &amp; am in a far way of finding out all the sedition in this place, which tho the borough belongs to George Rose,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Pittite supporter George Rose (1744&#8211;1818; <title level="m">DNB</title>), MP for Christchurch, Hampshire, 1790&#8211;1818, and Senior Secretary to the Treasury, 1783&#8211;1801.</note> is more than meets the eye. Were we more comfortably settled as to lodgings I should be well satisfied with this place. but we are in bad hands. our landlady &#8212; or rather house-lady, is a woman of whom her husband is tenant for life, remainder in fee to the Devil. if we can remedy this I shall for several reasons wish to remain here. if not &#8212; off we go for Dorset or Devonshire.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I am in want of books: tho it is some consolation to know that I should feel the same want anywhere &#8212; for they are &lt;not&gt; easily got. I am coming to the River of Amazons or Maragnon &amp; have no charts to guide me. Manuel Rodriguez has written a folio upon the very subject I want in Spanish &#8212; but I cannot procure it. there is an 8-vo translation from Acugna. London 1698<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to two books Southey required for <title level="m">Madoc</title>: Manuel Rodriguez (1633&#8211;1701), <title level="m">El Maran&#771;on y Amazonas. Historia de los Descubrimientos, Entradas, y Reduccion de Naciones, Trabajos ... Assi Temporales, como Espirituales en las Dilatadas Montan&#771;as y Mayores Rios de la America</title> (1684) and <title level="m">Voyages and Discoveries in South-America. The First up the River of Amazons to Quito in Peru, and Back Again to Brazil, Perform'd at the Command of the King of Spain. By Christopher D'Acugna. The Second up the River of Plata, and Thence by Land to the Mines of Potosi. By Mons. Acarete. The Third from Cayenne into Guiana, in Search of the Lake of Parima ... By M. Grillet and Bechamel. Done into English from the Originals, Being the Only Accounts of Those Parts Hitherto Extant. The Whole Illustrated with Notes and Maps</title> (1698).</note> &#8212; that too I cannot get. &amp; to go blundering up such a stream is but bad work. bear me in mind when you see a catalogue &#8722; will you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	There is a man here who loves a good dinner; Darteneuf<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The celebrated epicure Charles Darteneuf (d. 1730).</note>
          <del rend="strikethrough">we</del> might learn improvements in epicurism from him. <del rend="strikethrough">one day</del> he had procured two fine jacks for dinner on the following day. &amp; to have them fresh put them in a trough of water, over night. the next morning &#8212; one had eaten the other.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">other: Inserted here, in another hand: &#8216;Var. lect.&#8211;? they had eaten each other&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I shall arrive in town (God willing) on the evening of Tuesday the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp; remain the two following days. will you get me your sonnets ready? I shall have a cargo for Phillips<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Richard Phillips (1767&#8211;1840; <title level="m">DNB</title>), author, publisher and proprietor of the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>.</note> to bring up.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	it is Sunday morning &#8722; &amp; I am fearful that I shall not have time to finish this for the post &#8212; for &#8212; I am actually going to church! &#8722; why? &#8722; because I want to see the inside imprimis &#8212; secondly because I want to see all the persons I know.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	The church is a very fine one, &amp; contains much to interest the antiquarian much to please the architect, &amp; much to delight one who without being either likes architecture &amp; antiquities. the clergyman<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably William Jackson (dates unknown), Vicar of Christchurch Priory 1778&#8211;1802.</note> went round with me after the service &#8722; &amp; we are to visit him this evening. I believe the best effect of a church establishment is that it places in every village of the kingdom one who has certainly had the education of a scholar, &amp; generally &lt;has&gt; the manners of a gentleman. I hate the word gentleman. it has been so prostituted to puppies &#8212; but what can one substitute? Under the new order of things this advantage ought to be preserved, &amp; public instructors scattered over the country. I hoped at one time to have seen something like the Grecian schools of philosophy revived in France &#8212; but France has disappointed me in her internal conduct, &amp; if it be true that Baboeuf<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The French revolutionary and early socialist thinker Fran&#231;ois Noel Babouef (1764&#8211;1797) was executed on 27 May 1797.</note> be put to death &#8212; she has now no man left whom we may compare with the Grecians. for me, I attack not establishments because their titles disgust me. I would destroy Greatness &amp; Wealth because I wish to annihilate Poverty &amp; all the vices that arise from want. how this is to be done is a difficult question &#8212; I think I know the solution &#8212; but if no solution be impossible I should &lt;not&gt; hesitate to adopt the belief of Rousseau &amp; tell mankind if they wish for happiness to seek for it in the savage state.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I am in a state of very unpleasant certainty respecting my brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. he was sent with a prize to Falmouth May 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8722; &amp; has not yet been heard of. the Captain concludes he is taken prisoner, &amp; has no other apprehension. this is particularly unpleasant &#8212; as God knows when we may hear any thing of him! he may be in Spain perhaps &#8212; but be he where he may, there can be no regular communication by letter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	farewell. I want somebody to bathe with me sadly. here is fresh water &amp; salt water &amp; noble bathing in both, but I cannot endure a solitary dip. write. God bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">			yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">				Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Direct to the Post Office Christ-Church. Hants.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>