<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce156</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.156</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>National Library of Wales, MS 4811D.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 29–30.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="156" type="letter">
<head>156. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1796-05-24">24 May 1796</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ Charles Watkin Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 5 Stone Buildings/ Lincolns Inn/ London<lb/> Stamped: BRISTOL<lb/>Postmark: BMA/ 27/ 96<lb/>Endorsement: Southey/ May 24/ 1796<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4811D<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title level="m">Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 29–30.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>direct to <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottles</ref>.</salute>
<dateline>
<date when="1796-05-24">May 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1796.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1">	Can you not spare a few <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx</del> &lt;days&gt; &amp; accompany <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to Bristol? I will get you a bed as near us as possible. it is nearly two years since we seperated at Oxford. two years! certainly the most important of my life.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I am now at lodgings with my <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>. the reliance that I can place on my own application renders me little anxious for the future — &amp; for the present I can live like a silkworm by spinning my own brains. have I published too hastily? — remember that Virgil<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Virgil (70–19 BC), <title level="m">Aeneid</title>, Book 6, line 276. The Latin translates as ‘crime-provoking Hunger’.</note> in the spirit of poetical prophecy gives to Fames the epithet of malesuada.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I was very much shocked by hearing of <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovells</ref> death. tho he had sunk much in my esteem. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> sat up with him three nights tho the Physicians repeatedly warned her of her danger. it was a putrid fever killd him. this was while I was detained for a wind at Lisbon! short sighted that we are — I regretted the delay at the time!</p>
<p rend="indent1">	Come <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> — &amp; see how we are settled. can you enjoy porter as we have done at Westminster? M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pitt has amerced the middle class of their wine<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to the imposition of a 6d tax per bottle of wine by the Prime Minister William Pitt, the Younger (1759–1806; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> — &amp; luckily I have acquired a taste for malt liquors by being so long without them.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	I begin tomorrow to breakfast in my college tea cups. do you remember them? I have a regard for such “mute chroniclers”<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Quotation unidentified; Southey could possibly be citing a letter sent to him by Grosvenor Charles Bedford which has not survived.</note>  of distant days. have you forgot our early walk among the rocks here? &amp; the ships going out? ah <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> what very different animals were you &amp; I then! the heaviest evil I ever knew then was returning to school after the holydays — &amp; all I had to dread — that beast Forester.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Forester (d. 1794), who was educated at Westminster School (adm. 1782) and later entered the army, dying of yellow fever during the St Domingo expedition of 1794. Southey did not like Forester, accusing him of bullying and of forcing him to write Latin verses on his behalf (always making sure that the verses were hopeless enough to pass as Forester’s work).</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">	farewell. I am at my old employments — &amp; shall live six months upon</p>
<p rend="center">Letters</p>
<p rend="center">written during a short residence in</p>
<p rend="center">Spain &amp; Portugal</p>
<p rend="center">by</p>
<p rend="center">R.S.</p>
<p rend="indent1">	they will contain much anecdote &amp; some new information. of politics the less the better. aristocracy has behaved with liberality to Joan of Arc — &amp; if they will favour me by forgetting that I have ever meddled too much with public concerns — I will take care not to awaken their memories.</p>
<p rend="indent2">		God bless you.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent3">			yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent5">				Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
