<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce188</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.188</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>MS has not
                        survived.  Previously  published: Monthly
                        Magazine, 2 (December 1796), 859–862 [from where the text is taken]
                        under pseudonym ‘T.Y.’. For attribution to Southey, see Kenneth Curry,
                        ‘Southey’s contributions to The Monthly Magazine
                        and The Athenaeum’, The Wordsworth
                            Circle, 11 (1980), 215.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="188" type="letter">
<head>188. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the
                            <title level="j">Monthly Magazine</title>,</ref>
<date when="1796-12">[c. December 1796]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has not
                        survived<lb/>Previously published: <title level="j">Monthly
                        Magazine</title>, 2 (December 1796), 859–862 [from where the text is taken]
                        under pseudonym ‘T.Y.’. For attribution to Southey, see Kenneth Curry,
                        ‘Southey’s contributions to <title level="j">The Monthly Magazine</title>
                        and <title level="j">The Athenaeum</title>’, <title level="j">The Wordsworth
                            Circle</title>, 11 (1980), 215.</note>
</head>
<p rend="indent1"> IF LAVATER<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Kasparr
                        Lavater (1741–1801), Swiss poet and physiognomist.</note> had contemplated
                    the portrait of Lope de Vega,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        prolific Spanish writer Lope Felix de Vega Carpio (1562–1635).</note>
                    without knowing whom it represented, he would certainly have pronounced him an
                    extraordinary man; but he would not have suspected him to have been a poet. The
                    Spaniards have well characterised his genius by its <hi rend="ital">monstruosidad</hi>, a word which must literally be rendered monstruosity:
                    no other term could so well have delineated it. Lope de Vega is never sublime,
                    seldom pathetic, and seldom natural; rarely above mediocrity in any of his
                    writings, he has attained to celebrity by their number.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Purity of language and harmonious versification distinguish all
                    the poems of this indefatigable Spaniard. Born and educated at Madrid, if he had
                    beheld no stream but the Manzanares, and no country but the melancholy plains of
                    Castille, we might have expected dullness; but the secretary and favourite of
                    the duke of Alva<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Fernando Alvarez De
                        Toledo, Duke of Alva (1508–1583), Spanish military commander in the
                        Netherlands.</note> must have accompanied his master to Villa Franca and to
                    Oropesa; and the tranquil and majestic beauty of the one, and the wild sublimity
                    of the other, would have awakened all the enthusiasm of poetry, if Lope de Vega
                    had been indeed a poet.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> When a school-boy, he bartered his verses with his
                    school-fellows, for hymns and prints: when a young man, he wrote eclogues, and a
                    comedy, in praise of the Grand Inquisitor; and a pastoral, in honour of the duke
                    of Alva. From these symptoms, one who knew the human heart might have
                    prophesied, that the young poet never would attain to excellence. The Dutch idea
                    of bartering his verses could not have entered the mind of the enthusiast: the
                    young enthusiast carefully conceals his feelings from observation, and he who is
                    not an enthusiast must never expect to be a poet.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">Is there who ne’er those mystic transports felt</l>
<l rend="indent2">Of solitude and melancholy born?</l>
<l rend="indent2">He who needs not woo the Muse? <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">James Beattie (1735–1803; <title>DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Minstrel; or, The Progress of Genius. A Poem. Book the
                                First</title> (1771), Book 1, stanza 58, lines 3-5.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent1"> Were it not for the reverence which fashion has attached to their
                    names, we should yawn over Virgil and Horace, when they prostitute poetry to
                    panegyric. No great or good man ever encouraged a rhymer to bespatter him with
                    praise; panegyric has, therefore, usually been employed on the weak and the
                    wicked, on those whom we despise and detest; but, among the villains whose deeds
                    pollute the page of history, the duke of Alva ranks in the first class. This man
                    united in himself the bigotry of the priest, the duplicity of the politician,
                    and the brutality of the soldier; and to this man did Lope de Vega write a
                    pastoral! Arcadia and the duke of Alva! Madness never produced a more monstrous
                    association!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Arcadia of Lope de Vega is one of the innumerable imitations
                    that swarmed in Spain, after George of Montemayor published his Diana.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega Carpio’s <title level="m">Arcadia</title> (1598) was influenced by <title level="m">Diana</title> (1559), a pastoral romance by Jorge of Montemayor
                        (c.1521–1561).</note> The age had been accustomed to extravagance by their
                    books of chivalry; compared with which, the pastoral romance appeared natural.
                    That this species of composition may possess very great beauty, had been
                    sufficiently proved by Florian, in his alteration of the Galatea of
                        Cervantes,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The French poet
                        Jean-Pierre Claris de Florian (1755–1794), whose <title level="m">Galatie</title>, an imitation of Cervantes, was published in
                        1783.</note> and more particularly in his Estelle. I know of no work in the
                    English language that can properly be classed under this head, though a very
                    interesting one might be produced on the model of Florian, if the French
                    frippery of sentiment, which infects even his writings, were avoided.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I never toiled through the Arcadia of Lope de Vega. After
                    penetrating some thirty or forty pages into the little volume, I found that a
                    few scattered conceits could not atone for its intolerable dullness. Great
                    strength of imagination only can reconcile the reader to a total want to taste,
                    but the imagination of this indefatigable Spaniard was not strong, and his taste
                    may be judged of by a sentence relating to the heroine of his Arcadia: “the rays
                    of Belisarda’s eyes shone upon the water like the reflection of the sun upon a
                        looking-glass.”<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega
                        Carpio, <title level="m">Arcadia</title> (Madrid, 1598), fol. vi. The
                        English translation is probably Southey’s own.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Of his longer poems, I have never seen the Jerusalen
                        Conquistada:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega
                        Carpio, <title level="m">Jerusalem Conquistada</title> (1609).</note> I am,
                    however, well enough acquainted with the style and powers of Lope de Vega, fully
                    to credit Mr. Hayley, when he says, that it is, in every respect, infinitely
                    inferior to the work of Tasso,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Hayley (1745–1820; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">An Essay
                            on Epic Poetry</title> (London, 1782), p. 206, compared Lope de Vega’s
                        poem unfavourably to Torquato Tasso (1544–1595), <title level="m">Jerusalem
                            Delivered</title> (1580–1581).</note> which it attempted to rival. Of
                    his “Beauty of Angelica,” a complete analysis, with specimens sufficiently
                    copious, may soon be expected in a promised work upon Spain and Portugal.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">An account of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio’s
                            <title level="m">La Hermosura de Angelica</title> (1602) appeared in
                        Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain
                            and Portugal</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. 131–165.</note> His Dragontea
                    is very bad.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega Carpio,
                            <title level="m">La Dragontea</title> (1598), dealt with the last voyage
                        and death of Sir Francis Drake (1540–1596; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> It is reported, that Mr. Polwhele<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Polwhele (1760–1838; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> has likewise chosen Sir Francis Drake, as the
                    subject of an epic poem. Sir Francis Drake was a good sailor; he makes a very
                    respectable figure in the naval history of England; but he is but a sorry hero
                    for the poet! A privateer is only a legalized pirate, which old Fuller calls the
                    devil’s water rat, and the worst kind of sea vermin. <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Thomas Fuller (1607/8–1661; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">The Holy State</title> (Cambridge,
                        1642), p. 130.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Diogo de Sousa, in his celebrated satire called the Journey of
                    Diogo Camacho to Parnassus, <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish
                        satirist Diogo de Sousa’s (also known as Diogo Camacho) (fl. c. 1650) <title level="m">Jornada às Cortes do Parnaso De Diogo Camacho, Em Que Ficou
                            Laureado Por Apollo</title> (1794).</note> has made a happy allusion to
                    the rivalry of Lope de Vega with Tasso, and his lamentable inferiority. Camacho
                    calls on the Spanish poet to beg a letter of introduction to Apollo. Lope
                    replies:</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">My father for Arcadia is departing,</l>
<l rend="indent2">(Where I have been myself) and he shall write</l>
<l rend="indent2">Your introduction first. He journeys there</l>
<l rend="indent2">To seek some tidings of a certain lord,</l>
<l rend="indent2">By name*<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds
                            footnote: ‘One of the characters in Lope de Vega’s Arcadia.’ [Editorial
                            note: Lope Felix de Vega Carpio<title level="m">, Arcadia</title>
                            (1598).]</note> Anfriso: it is now some time</l>
<l rend="indent2">Since we have heard ought of him, and we doubt</l>
<l rend="indent2">Whether he lives or not. I answer’d him,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Senhor, I would not have you venture there,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Nor trust yourself in Palestine unmask’d</l>
<l rend="indent2">And heedless; for the very children say,</l>
<l rend="indent2">That, as Torquato did enrich those parts,</l>
<l rend="indent2">So you have ruin’d them!<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Diogo de Sousa, <title level="m">Jornada às Cortes do
                                Parnaso De Diogo Camacho, Em Que Ficou Laureado Por Apollo</title>
                            (Lisbon, 1794), p. 17. The English translation is probably Southey’s
                            own.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent1"> His comedies are said to delineate characters well, and
                    faithfully to represent the manners of the age he lived in. This commendation
                    they could not have obtained without, in some degree, meriting it; and there is
                    a liveliness in the lighter pieces of Lope de Vega, which shows him best
                    qualified for such subjects. He himself excuses his total neglect of all
                    dramatic rules, by alledging the taste of the age. “I have written better (says
                    he); “but seeing what monstrous productions please the women and the mob, I have
                    locked up all my precepts, and turned Plautus and Terence out of my library.
                    Surely it is just that, as the public pay, the public should be pleased.”<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">In his <title level="m">Arte Nuevo de
                            Hacer Comedias</title> (1609), Lope Felix de Vega Carpio discussed his
                        repudiation of the classical dramatic models as represented by Titus Maccius
                        Plautus (c. 254–184 BC) and Publius Terentius Afer (c. 190/180–159 BC). The
                        English translation is probably Southey’s own.</note> A childish and
                    ridiculous defence, which deserves not a refutation!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The burlesque pieces of this universal author were published by
                    him, under the name of the Licentiate Thome de Burguillos, perhaps, because he
                    thought them little consonant to his ecclesiastical character; perhaps, because
                    he was ashamed of a species of poetry so despicable.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega Carpio published the majority of his
                        burlesques, including the mock-heroic ‘Gatomachia’ (1534), under the
                        pseudonym Tomé de Burguillos.</note> An Ode to a Flea was printed in one of
                    those works to which he affixed his name, but never avowed himself to be the
                    author of it. The editor of the Parnasso Espanol calls it a witty and ingenious
                    composition; it displays, however, little ingenuity, and less wit. The poet
                    tells the Flea where he goes, and what he feeds upon, and calls him a greater
                    Turk than Amurath, because he spares nobody. <note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega Carpio’s ‘Ode to a Flea’ was included in
                        Juan José Lopez de Sedano (1729–1801), <title level="m">El Parnaso
                            Español</title>, 9 vols (1768–1778), III, pp. 81–85.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Spanish poets appear to have been little envious of each
                    other’s reputation. In his Laurel de Apolo, Lope de Vega has liberally praised
                    his contemporaries; and poems of the same nature have been composed by Gil Polo,
                    Vicente Espinel, and the great Cervantes. <note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaspar Gil Polo (c. 1530–1591); Vicente Gómez
                        Martínez-Espinel (1550–1624); Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616),
                        author of the satirical romance <title level="m">Don Quixote de la
                            Mancha</title> (1605–1615).</note> They satirized each other’s faults,
                    but they honestly allowed each other’s merits; the abilities of Lope de Vega and
                    of Gongora<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis de Góngora
                        (1561–1627).</note> were acknowledged by those who most strongly exposed the
                    carelessness of the one, and the affectation of the other.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have read nearly two hundred of his sonnets. As might be
                    expected, many of them contain parts that are beautiful; none of them are
                    perfect as <hi rend="ital">wholes</hi>. The following is a fair specimen:</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">To go, and yet to linger on the way:</l>
<l rend="indent3"> To linger, and look back; and yet to go,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> To hear a syren’s pleasant voice, and know</l>
<l rend="indent2">The winds of Fortune waft you far away;</l>
<l rend="indent2">To build gay fabrics in the baseless air;</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Like Lucifer, to fall precipitate</l>
<l rend="indent3"> From Heaven’s high bliss, even to a demon’s state,</l>
<l rend="indent2">To sink despairing; nor regret despair;</l>
<l rend="indent2">From Friendship’s voice affectionate to fly;</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Wildly to rove, and talk in solitude;</l>
<l rend="indent2">To think each passing hour eternity;</l>
<l rend="indent3"> All ill-expecting, not to hope for good;</l>
<l rend="indent2">And all the hell of jealousy to prove,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Is to be absent from the maid we love.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, ‘Ir y quedarse y
                            con quedar partirse’. The translation is probably Southey’s own and
                            appeared under the signature ‘T.Y.’ in <title level="m">The Poetical
                            Register, and Repository for Fugitive Poetry of 1802</title> (London,
                        1803), 303.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent1"> On the 25th of August 1635, died Lope de Vega, in the 73d year of
                    his age; full of honours as of days. If not the best of poets, he was the most
                    fortunate; the wealth he acquired rendered him happy in life, and the use he
                    made of it cheered him in death. He died honoured by the great, celebrated by
                    the learned, and regretted by the poor. His reputation still flourishes in his
                    own country; and though the impartial judgment of foreigners cannot rank his
                    productions above mediocrity, let it be remembered, that he never was excelled
                    in industry as an author, or in liberality as a man.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The following sonnet may serve to show in what estimation he was
                    held by his co-temporaries: it is by Antonio Barbosa Bacellar,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese poet Antonio Barbosa Bacellar
                        (1610–1663).</note> written in Spanish — but a complete specimen of
                    Portuguese taste:</p>
<p rend="indent3">ON THE DEATH OF LOPE DE VEGA.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent2">LOPE! like some fair Syren in a sea</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Of tears, thy Muse was heard! her wond’rous song</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Could still the memory of the dead prolong,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Baffling oblivion by her harmony.</l>
<l rend="indent2">Even Death, astonish’d at that powerful strain,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Heard its enchanting music with alarm;</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And trembled, lest his desolating arm</l>
<l rend="indent2">Should give no victims to oblivion’s reign.</l>
<l rend="indent2">He came, he conquer’d: — surely at some hour,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> When o’er the eye-lids of thy mighty Muse</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Sleep shed the poison of her poppy dews:</l>
<l rend="indent2">He had not conquer’d else that waking power,</l>
<l rend="indent2">Nor rest that bard of life, whose tuneful breath</l>
<l rend="indent2">Would surely then have given thee life — O Death!<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">‘A Morte de Lope de Vega Carpio’, in Mathias
                            Pereira da Silva (fl. 1746). <title level="m">A Fenix Renascida, Ou
                                Obras Poeticas Dos Melhores Engenhos Portuguezes</title>, 5 vols
                            (Lisbon, 1746), IV, p. 313. The translation is probably Southey’s
                            own.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<closer>
<signed rend="indent11"> T. Y.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
