<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce94</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.94</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 56&#8211;58; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I,
                        p. 210 [in part; 1 paragraph, where it is dated 12 June 1794].Dating
                        note: The letter is probably written over several days in June
                    1794.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="94" type="letter">
        <head>94. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1794-06-12">12 [&#8211;?] June
                        1794</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: June 22<hi rend="sup">nd</hi>/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/
                        Westminster./ Single<lb />Stamped: OXFORD<lb />Postmark: [partial] AJU/
                        9<lb />Endorsements: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. June 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.
                        1794. Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> June 24. 1794/ and send same day; First
                        mention of/ Coleridge<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c.
                        22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 56&#8211;58; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I,
                        p. 210 [in part; 1 paragraph, where it is dated 12 June 1794].<lb />Dating
                        note: The letter is probably written over several days in June
                    1794.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1794-06-12">Thursday. June 12. 1794.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>Balliol.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your last letter is now with <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, he purposes answering it
                    himself, but whether or no that purpose is yet accomplished I am ignorant. I
                    wish much to see you. cannot you contrive to come speedily to Oxford? we leave
                    it very early in July &#8212; about the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> or fifth, &amp;
                    time lags sadly till that period. I could explain more fully why this college
                    life is so irksome to me, were you here, &amp; more clearly convince you of
                    the propriety of my wishes. your last was calculated to raise my hope<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> tis a tormenting phantom which I fear to
                    indulge.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> my poor trullibubs are empty. a dose of salts yesterday &amp;
                    another this morning has been scouring out my tripes. this may possibly remove
                    indisposition for a little while, but I am not fool enough to hope it will
                    remove the cause. continual anxiety will wear out a stronger frame than mine &#8212;
                    oh that gripe &#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> one week has elapsed since my letter was so unpleasantly
                    interrupted. in the interim the salts have worked &amp; your last arrived.
                    at present my situation <del rend="strikethrough">my situation</del> resembles
                    that of a poor devil executing for high treason, at the interval when he is cut
                    down from the gallows to have his heart torn out &#8212; for I am delaying the
                    pickling of my tripes again till the departure of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">a Cantab</ref> one whom I very
                    much esteem &amp; admire tho two thirds of our conversation be spent in
                    disputing on metaphysical subjects. the latter part of your letter leads to a
                    wide &amp; interesting subject &#8212; I am as far from pleading the cause of
                    incontinence as you. yet the philosopher should pardon in another what he would
                    not pardon in himself. the passions are not vicious &#8212; tis society makes the
                    indulgence of them so. they resemble an assemblage of waters destructive if they
                    run wildly over the country, but the source of abundance if properly guided.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> has started an objection to
                    the plan on which I presumed too much. &#8212; they will enquire &amp; find me a
                    Republican. right. they ought to enquire &amp; they must know. perish every
                    hope of life rather than &lt;that&gt; I should forfeit my integrity. I
                    am a Republican &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">thxx</del> did wrong in even
                    thinking of the situation. twas a fallacious reasoning that said &#8212; there is no
                    criminality in accepting a situation where for a certain salary I give up a
                    certain portion of time. &#8212; the false hopes which deceived me are gone &amp;
                    it is but turning adventurer at last. or be villain enough to take orders
                    &amp; grow fat in ease indolence &amp; iniquity. blessed be God that my
                    principles are notorious enough to keep me necessarily in integrity. who can
                    answer for his perseverance in rectitude when every passion of the human heart
                    prompts him to dissimulation?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> they will enquire &amp; find me a Republican. even at the
                    moment of disappointment &#8212; when every delightful hope melted away like the
                    shadows of a dream &#8212; I exulted in the reflection. my practice flows from my
                    principle. if the one be wrong the other must be so. if my first principles are
                    vicious the actions resulting from them must be vicious likewise &#8212; &amp;
                    where is the being who shall throw the first stone? I am already too much the
                    victim of affection &#8212; my heart is too often consulted where the head should have
                    determined, &amp; it is better to sacrifice happiness than integrity. had my
                    situation been like yours tis more than probable that my theoretical principles
                    had been the same. but I am too notorious to be tempted &#8212; &amp; when from
                    the triumph of affections over honesty I had placed myself in the way of
                    temptation &#8212; the character of Republican man saved me the trial.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So be it. I will hasten nothing. as I am I may yet remain two
                    years &#8212; should any thing devolve to me then it will be well. &amp; if not
                    why the same world will still lie before me, &amp; whether I linger out
                    existence in England in America or among the convicts of New Holland is a matter
                    of indifference. thus much (&amp; too much) for self.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> is gone, AB. I have
                    quarrelld with <ref target="people.html#CollinsJeremiah">J Collins</ref> so my
                        <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref> friends are reduced to
                        <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref>. but he is
                    worth an hundred. Allen is with us daily &amp; his friend from Cambridge &#8212;
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> whose poems
                    you will oblige me by subscribing to either at Hookhams or Edwards&#8217;s.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to Samuel Taylor
                        Coleridge&#8217;s projected &#8212; but unrealised &#8212; subscription volume, &#8216;Imitations
                        from the Modern Latin Poets&#8217;, which had been advertised in the <title level="j">Cambridge Intelligencer</title> on 14 June 1794. Hookham&#8217;s:
                        the London booksellers Thomas Hookham and James Carpenter of Old Bond
                        Street. Edwards&#8217;s: the London booksellers Edwards &amp; Sons of Pall
                        Mall, headed by James Edwards (d. 1816).</note> he is of most uncommon merit
                    &#8212; of the strongest genius the clearest judgment &amp; the best heart. my
                    friend he already is &#8212; &amp; must hereafter be yours. tis I fear impossible
                    to keep him till you come but my efforts shall not be wanting. <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> you will see. &amp; as <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> most probably will be in London
                    in the Long Vacation I trust you will find &lt;in&gt; him as I have done
                    &#8212; a <hi rend="ital">good friend</hi>. to me he is similar in every respect. from
                    you he differs only where I differ. the constant society of <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> has rendered many hours
                    delightful which would otherwise have passed in the destructive day dreams of
                    solitude. him I lose from Oxford when I depart but tis my wish never to reside
                    again &amp; I shall grasp at any situation of independance during the next
                    six months. were not the vacation so near &#8212; I would try the press &amp;
                    print my Botany Bay Eclogues with my name in the title page. <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey published four &#8216;Botany-Bay Eclogues&#8217; in
                        his <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797). One, &#8216;Elinor&#8217;, had previously
                        appeared anonymously in the <title level="j">Morning Chronicle</title> (18
                        September 1794). A fifth, &#8216;Edward and Susan&#8217;, was published in the <title level="j">Monthly Magazine,</title> 5 (January 1798). He may have
                        attempted to print the &#8216;Botany-Bay Eclogues&#8217; himself, as a few printed
                        sheets of &#8216;Humphrey and William&#8217;, reputedly set up by Southey, survive in
                        the Beinecke Library, OSB MSS File, Folder 14213.</note> &#8220;the world is all
                    before me&#8221;,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">An adaptation of John Milton
                        (1608&#8211;1674; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Paradise
                            Lost</title>, (1667&#8211;1678), Book 12, line 646.</note> &amp; a wide
                    &amp; wearying world it is when I cast my eyes around &amp; see no haven
                    of shelter! let me see you very shortly. write &amp; fix the day. I depart
                    early in July &#8212; possibly sooner if <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my
                        brother</ref> gets leave of absence. I have much to tell you but neither
                    room or time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> what attaches you to King?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac King (1776&#8211;1832), educated at Westminster School and Trinity College,
                        Cambridge. He was later chaplain to the Prince Regent.</note> there is a
                    something in my nature repugnant to that man. your pun is good. your moralizing
                    good. God bless you &amp; save you from that eternal anxiety which preys
                    upon me.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent4">yours sincerely.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> why Esquire one who loathes titles? my name needs no
                        addition.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> is very
                        indolent. tell him to write. my remembrances to your friends. particularly
                            <ref target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Harry</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace ... Harry: Written parallel to
                            address.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>