<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce273</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.273</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 323&#8211;324 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="273" type="letter">
        <head>273. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1797-11-19">19 November 1797</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ Grosvenor Charles Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster./ Single<lb />Stamped: BATH<lb />Postmark: NO/ 20/ 97<lb /> Watermark: J Smyth/ 1796<lb />Endorsement: 19 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1797<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title level="m">Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 323&#8211;324 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1797-11-19">Sunday. 19 Nov. 97.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	Grosvenor I have found out a better fence for our Eutopia than <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisles</ref> plantation of vipers &amp; rattle snakes. it is to surround it with a Vacuum. for you know <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> this would so puzzle the philosophers on the other side; &amp; we might see them making experiments upon the atmosphere &#8212; to the great annoyance of dogs whom they would scientifically torture. besides &#8212; if we had any refractory inmate we might push him into the void.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	But how could you blunder about Tuesday so egregiously. did not I say expressly dine at Grays Inn with me? look you. I am <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John Mays</ref> guest for some 24 hours. now in common civility I must dine one day with him; &amp; we hope to be lodged on the Wednesday. so I hold myself engaged to the blackguard mess on Tuesday &amp; the next day to him. you do not know him &#8212; but he is one whom I greatly respect &#8212; &amp; I should like to have him on the right side of the vacuum. I have written to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to explain this &amp; call you an ideot. &amp; now remember to meet me at his rooms on Tuesday as soon after three as you please.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I hate the journey &#8212; &amp; yet going to London I may say with Quarles</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	My journey&#8217;s better than my journeys end. <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Francis Quarles (1592&#8211;1644; <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Divine Fancies</title> (1632), no. 24 &#8216;On a Pilgrim&#8217;, line 8.</note> a little home &#8212; <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> &#8212; near the sea &#8212; or in any quiet country where there is water to bathe in &#8212; &amp; what should I wish for in this life? &amp; how could I be so honourably or happily employed as in writing?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	If Buonaparte should come before I look like Sir John Comyns<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Comyns (1667&#8211;1740; <title level="m">DNB</title>), judge and legal writer.</note>  &#8212; oh that fine chuckle head was made for the law. I am too old to have my skull moulded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> is coming to London with me &#8212; &amp; means to lodge in the same house. how all this chanced is a long &amp; odd story. I could wish you to know him well &#8212; but it would be an effort to give his character &#8212; &amp; I love not exertion. thus much however I will say &#8212; his feelings are too susceptible of neglect or kindness. they are not so blunt as we could wish them or as they should be for his own happiness. &amp; a little attention to him in conversation, <del rend="strikethrough">will</del> &amp; any trifling mark of kindness will highly gratify him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	And now God bless you. <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del> give my love to <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> &amp; to <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Your letter is arrived. why not trust the settled quietness to which my mind has arrived? it is wisdom to avoid all violent emotions. I would not annihilate my feelings &#8212; but I would have them under a most Spartan despotism. <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> Inveni portum. spes &amp; fortuna valete.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin can be translated as &#8216;I have reached the port, hope and fortune farewell.&#8217; It is a Latin version of a Greek original and in this form was used in Alain-Rene Lesage&#8217;s (1668&#8211;1747), <title level="m">Gil Blas</title> (1715&#8211;35), Book 9, as the inscription over the hero&#8217;s door on his retirement.</note>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">Tu quoque, si vis </l>
          <l rend="indent2">Lumine claro</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Cernere rectum,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Gaudia pelle</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Pelle timorem</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Spemque fugato</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Nec dolor adsit.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Anicius Manlius Severinus Boethius (c. 475&#8211;525), <title level="m">De Consolatione Philosophi&#230;</title>. The passage is translated in Boethius, <title level="m">The Consolation of Philosophy</title>, trans. Victor Watts (Harmondsworth, 1969; rev. edn 1999), p. 21, as: &#8216;If you desire/ To look on truth/ And follow the path/ With unswerving course,/ Rid yourself/ Of joy and fear,/ Put hope to flight,/ And banish grief.&#8217;</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>I have laid up the advice of Boethius in my heart &#8212; &amp; prescribe it to you &#8212; so fare you well</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>