<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce187</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.187</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 116&#8211;118.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="187" type="letter">
        <head>187. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1796-11-11">[started before 11 November 1796; continued 17 November 1796]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: For/ G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster.<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: ANO/ 18/ 96<lb />Watermark: [Obscured by MS binding]<lb />Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 18 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1796<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 22<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title level="m">New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 116&#8211;118.</note>
        </head>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">	Well Grosvenor we shall be settled when we get <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> an apartment in the church yard however. so you too are about to waste the five best years of existence in acquiring a detestable jargon unpleasant to acquire, unprofitable to the head &amp; the heart when obtained. why not physic? but you must know best, for were that useful science equally eligible as to worldly concerns you would certainly prefer it. allons! would the journey were over! &#8212; would it were begun!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	You want me at London &amp; I want to be there as much as you can wish to have me. what hinders? there needs no Oedipus to solve that question! <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In classical mythology, Oedipus solved the riddle of the Sphinx.</note> &#8212; nothing but the neighbourhood of you &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> could render a London residence bearable &#8212; I abhor that diabolical city!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	have you seen Bob Banyards Review of Joan of Arc?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Banyard&#8217; is possibly a nickname for <ref target="people.html#NaresRobert">Robert Nares</ref>. An anonymous review of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> (1796) had appeared in the <title level="j">British Critic</title>, 8 (October 1796), 393&#8211;396.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	&#8220;a professional man must not step too much out of his way.&#8221; granted &#8212; ergo I abjure <hi rend="ital">public</hi> poetry. but a professional man must have a house &amp; furniture ergo I must write a book first. poor Madoc! if he will buy me chairs tables beds linen &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c it will be worth more than an eternity of posthumous credit &#8212; <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> is &lt;it&gt; not damnd hard <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> that the booksellers should make so much of that poem when I am rotten, &amp; that I should make so little? it will be in twenty books. a thirty shilling volume. the sale of one edition would make me happy. two hundred copies would indemnify the publication &amp; the remaining three put me in possession of about three hundred guineas, which would furnish a house, &amp; leave enough to risk in an octavo edition. a pretty scheme <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> &#8212; &amp; easy for one who has a wide circle of acquaintance. but I am &#8212; RS!</p>
        <p rend="indent11">										after all</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1796-11-11">Friday</date>. I am just returned from Bath where I walked yesterday. you will not therefore &lt;wonder&gt; that the above &#8220;after all&#8221; appears as unconnected to me as to you. oh <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> that your plan may be feasible &#8212; &amp; you &amp; I study together &amp; break our meditations ever &amp; anon by cursing the trash that employs them! I have a companion to cheer the hours of employment. ah <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &#8212; <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> is in the right &#8212; we shall shame you into it &#8212; or more probably tempt you to make the experiment I have succeeded so well in. your worldly-wise resolutions &#8212; nonsense! go into company with the &#8220;parfaits aimable&#8221; &amp; if you find her such &#8212; o one idea of money comes into your head &#8212; go cut it off &#8212; for it is not worth keeping upon your shoulders.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I wish much to see &#8212;&#8212;. if I were but intimate with her. &#8212; do you believe the persuadability of the Beast? of the better order I do. no more of this: your determination concerning your future life must be regulated by the choice you shall make between the high delights &amp; many anxieties of marriage &#8212; <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> negation of both in the heart</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent7">	no more diseasd</l>
          <l rend="indent2">By the quick ague fits of Hope &amp; Fear,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">Quietly cold. <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Sappho&#8217;, lines 11&#8211;13, published in his <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797).</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>I have always followed my feelings instead of my judgement &#8212; &amp; they have led me right.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1796-11-17">Thursday.</date> I have met with a <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Losh</ref>. he carries with him one of the most open manly democratic faces I ever saw: he mentioned <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>. I enquired what were Carlisles opinions upon religious subjects: he told me atheistical. now <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> who am I to believe? that his sentiments as given in conversation if not avowedly atheistical, lead immediately to atheism from the testimony of <ref target="people.html#AllenRobert">Allen</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">Losh</ref> appears certain; they are both accustomed to metaphysical reasonings &amp; could hardly both be deceived. moreover, the part which <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> wrote in one of your letters to me, appeared most clearly to be the production of an Atheist. mark you &#8212; his speculative <del rend="strikethrough">fancies</del> &lt;tenets&gt; will neither make him rise or fall in the barometer of my opinion: but as you have so positively assured me that he thinks otherwise &amp; as he is by others who know him, Christians as well as Atheists, considered as a disbeliever of Deity &#8212; you will do well. if you are right, in telling him how his opinions are mistaken, &amp; warning him, if he be indeed a Theist, not to give his sanction to principles, which, to say the best of them, can produce no good. you may, if you like it, show him what I have written.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	St Pierres book is entitled Etudes de la Nature.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques-Henri Bernardin de Saint-Pierre (1737&#8211;1814), <title level="m">Etudes de la Nature</title> (1784).</note>  &#8212; the observations of a man of real genius &amp; real piety upon the harmonies of nature. I hesitate not to pronounce it one of the most interesting works ever produced: &amp; that heart must be a bad one that is not deeply delighted by the perusal. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	I remove to Bath on Tuesday next, to remain with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> till I fix my tent<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> among you. I do not expect to make any friends in London. &amp; the fewer acquaintance the better. As I cannot cage the Beast I must cage myself. I think of your club with the determination of declining it. tell me <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> &#8212; after nine hours law which will make me happiest &#8212; the company of half a dozen men &#8212; or the continuing Madoc? God bless you. direct your next to <ref target="places.html#WestgateBath">Westgate Buildings Bath</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">		Yrs sincerely</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">				R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>