<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce151</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.151</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2009-02-20">March 15, 2009</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>National Library of
                        Wales, MS 4811D.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 25–29 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.26.1.names"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.26.1.places"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-03-10" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-03-02" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2009-02-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2009-02-20" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>TEI Encoding</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="151" type="letter">
<head>151. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1796-04-23">23–27 April 1796</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: Charles Watkin Williams
                        Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 5 Stone Buildings/
                        Lincolns Inn/ London<lb/> Postmark: [partial] MA/ 13<lb/>Watermark: Crest/ J
                        LARKING<lb/>Endorsement: Southey April 23 1796<lb/>MS: National Library of
                        Wales, MS 4811D<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title level="m">Selections From the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 25–29 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="left">
<address>
<placeName>Lisbon.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1796-04-23">Satur. Apr. 23. 1796</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> It depends upon Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Benjamin Norwood<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Benjamin Norwood (dates unknown), Master
                        of the ship that took Southey home from Portugal in 1796.</note> of the
                    Swift of New York — bound from this port to Hull — whether or no I shall
                    breakfast with you ten days after the receipt of this. if he lands me at the
                    Isle of Wight I shall of course take the shortest road to Bristol. if at Dover
                    or Ramsgate my way lies thro London. I shall in that case sleep there one night.
                    breakfast with you — see <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Bedford</ref> —
                    &amp; get into the mail on the next evening. we sail on Wednesday or
                    Thursday next. so that if the weather be tolerably favourable I shall not be
                    long after my letter. — of Joan of Arc the accounts are more favourable than I
                    expected. the aristocrats are as much pleased as the democrats — &amp; some
                    of them of the most intolerant order — have even thankd me by proxy for the
                    pleasure they derived from it. as it is most probable a second edition will soon
                    be wanted — do you turn public accuser &amp; bring all obnoxious passages
                    before the revolutionary tribunal of my writing desk. I will engage to condemn a
                    great many — tho you must not be surprized if a few favourites should be
                    spared.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Marq. Pombal<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebastiao
                        José de Carvalho E Melo, Marquis of Pombal (1699–1782), chief minister (and
                        effective ruler) of Portugal under King José I (1714–1777; reigned
                        1750–1777).</note> displaced the Franciscans from Mafra because they
                    impoverishd the country, &amp; gave that superb convent to the regular
                    Canons of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Austin who could support themselves by their
                    own revenues. the Confessor of the present Prince of Brazil<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The title given to the heir to the throne of
                        Portugal. In 1796 it was held by John (1767–1826), the future John
                        VI.</note> is a Franciscan, &amp; he assured this sapient sprig of
                    royalty, that he would never have a child till the Franciscans were
                    reestablished in Mafra. the Prince had faith — &amp; in nine months after
                    his marriage an heir was born — no doubt by miraculous assistance. Antonio
                    Francisco Caetano Christofero. these the four first names of the young Prince of
                        Beira<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The title given to the
                        second-in-line to the Portuguese throne. In 1796 it was held by Francisco
                        António (1795–1801), eldest son of John, Prince of Brazil.</note> were
                    chosen by his father for their mystical signification. Antony he is called in
                    honour of the tutelary Saint of Lisbon. Francisco in grateful acknowledgement of
                    that saints assistance — &amp; Caetano because the Confessor who gave him
                    that advice respecting Mafra &amp; so enabled him to be a father, bore that
                    name. but of Christofer nobody could discover the secret wisdom. somebody
                    however asked the Prince — admiring the wisdom that had directed his choice of
                    the other — &amp; begging an explanation of this. ah — said his Serene
                    Highness — you cant find out the meaning of Christofer! — why it was upon S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Christoffers day that I first thought of having a child.
                    this anecdote is literally true. is it not strange that the reigning Sovereigns
                    of Europe should be so very despicable? &amp; that the rising generation of
                    Princes should be worse than their parents? such pillars will but ill prop the
                    tottering temple of royalty. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> what you say of repeated attacks upon the Kings life<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Attempts to assassinate George III (1738–1820;
                        reigned 1760–1820).</note> surprizes me. I have always laughed at the
                    stories. for in the first place I believe there are no men in England <del rend="strikethrough">who</del> &lt;wicked enough to&gt; entertain so
                    black a design — <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> if they were atrocious
                    enough to intend assassination — fools enough to attempt it so clumsily. I have
                    been inclined to think with many others that William Pitt<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Prime Minister William Pitt, the Younger
                        (1759–1806; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</note> might have had the marble
                    &amp; the stones flung at the Kings coach — in order so to alarm the people
                    that they might gladly submit to any of his measures.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The stoning of the royal coach on 29 October 1795 provided
                        the pretext for the government’s ‘Two Acts’ to suppress radical
                        activity.</note> I am inclined to adopt this opinion because it is less
                    improbable than that a regular system should be formed of killing the King.
                    —</p>
<p rend="indent1"> the Poetry of Spain &amp; Portugal wants taste, &amp;
                    generally, feeling. I should have thought Camoens<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis Vaz de Camoëns (c. 1524–1580), author of <title level="m">The Lusiad</title> (1572).</note> deficient in feelings if I
                    had only read his Lusiad — but the Sonnets of Camoens are very beautiful. those
                    given by Hayley in his notes to the Essay on Epic P.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley (1745–1820; <title level="m">DNB</title>),
                            <title level="m">An Essay on Epic Poetry</title> (London, 1782), pp.
                        272-277.</note> tho
                    among the best are but a wretched specimen to the English reader. the
                    translations are detestable — &amp; the originals so printed as to be
                    unintelligible. I bought some ballads in Spain in remembrance of Rio Verde<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">An old English ballad, see Thomas Percy
                        (1729–1811: <title level="m">DNB</title>), <title level="m">Reliques of
                            Ancient English Poetry</title>, 2nd edn, 3 vols (London, 1767), I, pp.
                        335–342.</note> — but they prove bad enough. but six months after my return
                    I will tell you more. of Hanbury<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to John Hanbury (1775–1796), a contemporary of
                        Southey’s at Oxford (matric. 1792).</note> I knew nothing but that he was
                    the victim of his own irregularities as well as his friend Harvey<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to John Augustus Hervey,
                        Lord Hervey (1757–1796).</note> whom I saw. of Spanish society I saw nothing
                    good, tho I had letters to Cornide<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cornide de Saavedra (1737–1803), a member of the Royal Academy of
                        History.</note> one of their luminaries — as stupid a fellow as ever eat
                    college commons. I should perhaps have had a better opinion of it if
                        Gimbernatts<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Either the Spanish
                        geologist Carlos de Gimbernat (1768–1834), or (though less likely) his
                        father, the physician Antonio de Gimbernat (1734–1816).</note> letter had
                    arrived in time — that is if I had delivered it &amp; I should have had some
                    scruples of conscience upon that head — as on the one hand I should have thought
                    it right to deliver a letter entrusted to me, &amp; on the other had but
                    little ambition of appearing as the luminary of Great Britain &amp; the
                    greatest Poet Politician &amp; Philosopher of the present day!!! &amp;
                    all this upon second hand knowledge too — for Gimbernatt &amp; I never met
                    tho we lived in the same circle.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Aikin</ref> wrote the
                    critique on Joan in the Analytical R.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title level="j">Analytical Review</title>, 23 (February 1796),
                        170–177.</note> so my letters tell me. who was my friend in the Critical I
                    have not heard. — you talk of nine hours daily study — I could like less —
                    &amp; yet would undertake more. the day will never be less than fifteen — so
                    that six will still be my own. but must those nine hours be spent
                    &lt;all&gt; from home? or do you allow a certain portion of them to the
                    comfortable study. in a great chair by the fire side? of all this when we meet.
                    — poor <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharlesJohn">Bunbury</ref>! of all
                    professions what could make &lt;him&gt; chuse the army? after all your
                    hum-drum plodding fellows stand the best chance in the world. imagination is a
                    kind of mettled horse that will most probably break the riders neck when a
                    donkey would have carried slow &amp; sure to the end of the journey. if I
                    should ever be a father I shall find little time for any thing but the education
                    of my children, what might <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharlesJohn">Bunbury</ref> have been at this &lt;day. &amp;&gt; if his heart
                    had &lt;not&gt; been so early corrupted! <del rend="strikethrough">rather xxxxld xxxxxxxxxxx his life — with such abilities?</del> Radji<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">A revised version of the account of Radji
                        appeared in Southey’s <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short
                            Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797).</note> is the son of an
                    Arabian woman &amp; an Italian Physician settled at Bagdat. he was sent when
                    about fifteen to his Uncle at Bombay — but his Uncle kept two or three black
                    mistresses, &amp; lived so dissolutely as to disgust Radji — for he had had
                    a religious education. the boy ran away &amp; entered on board a ship. he
                    was as little pleased with the morality of a sailors life, &amp; when the
                    vessel entered Lisbon — he took his cloaths — left his pay behind him, &amp;
                    went for shelter to the English college. the singularity of the boys story
                    &amp; the uncommon simplicity &amp; goodness of his character made him
                    friends — &amp; tho the Portuguese noblemen who promised to protect him —
                    neglected it with their usual sincerity — an English student took care of him,
                    &amp; procured him among other friends the patronage of the Grand
                    Inquisitor. How are those chaps? — said he one day speaking of two English
                    Protestants here. they are fine looking chaps — but they are like all you
                    English — they think about eating &amp; drinking but I believe they don’t
                    think much about saving their souls. why do’nt you talk to them about their
                    souls — &amp; convert them? if I lived with them as much as you do I should
                    talk of nothing else. do you pray for them Radji — said Bramstone<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Bramstone (first name and dates unknown), an
                        English convert to Catholicism who was studying at the Irish College in
                        Lisbon.</note> — yes — replied the boy — I have never neglected that
                    &amp; I never will. — is not this a singular story? he will be made a priest
                    — &amp; live useless &amp; happy.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Wed. Apr 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I cannot yet learn whether we
                    go tomorrow Friday or Saturday. where we land is equally uncertain — but if the
                    sea runs high when the boats come out I shall certainly go on to Hull. I have
                    two children under my care.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have no time to proceed as we dine out &amp; I have the
                    pleasant job of dropping cards TTL.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> did <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> shew you the fable of <hi rend="ital">Dapple</hi> playing the
                        flute?<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had sent a
                        translation of Tomás de Iriarte (1750–1791), ‘El Burro Flaustista’ to
                        Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [December 1795–] 20 February [1796], (Letter
                        145). Bedford’s nickname was Dapple, probably a reference to the ass in
                        Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616), <title level="m">Don
                            Quixote</title> (1605–1615).</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Why shall I be like a pigeon when I land?</p>
<p rend="indent1"> there is a little fellow here whose equestrian exploits would
                    make [MS torn] good third volume for Bunburys Gambadoniana.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to the satirical prints of horse
                        riders and their antics produced by Henry William Bunbury (1750–1811; <title level="m">DNB</title>), under the pseudonym Geoffrey Gambado, such as
                            <title level="m">Hints to Bad Horsemen</title> (1781), and <title level="m">An Academy for Grown Horsemen</title> (1787).</note> sometimes
                    his [MS torn] chuses to leap — then he either leaves his rider behind [MS torn]
                    him over first. one day he rode out with a Lady [MS torn] stranger to the
                    country. off went his horse — &amp; the poor &lt;woman&gt; was left
                    at a cross road unable to enquire her way. ignor[MS torn] where he went —
                    &amp; obliged to wait there till the horse chose to come back again. once
                    the horse chose to look over a high wall &amp; claps his fore legs on the
                    top of it — the rider bellowing most manfully all the while. once he threw the
                    little man over his head — &amp; he alighted on his legs in direct
                    opposition to the law of gravitation.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent3"> farewell.</salute>
<signed rend="indent5"> RS.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
