<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2009-03-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">people</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2009-03-15">March 15, 2009</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>Lynda Pratt</author>
            <title>Biographies</title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/people" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1: 1791-1797 </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
              <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
              <pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#g21" scheme="#genre" />
        <catRef target="#EEd.26.1.names" scheme="#people" />
        <catRef target="#EEd.26.1.places" scheme="#places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change n="4" when="2009-03-10" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="3" when="2009-03-02" who="#AB">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="2" when="2009-02-20" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="1" when="2009-02-20" who="#AB">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="paratext" xml:id="EEd.26.1.names">
        <head>Biographies</head>
        <p>These pages provide information about contemporaries to whom Southey was connected, in particular, correspondents, family and
					friends. </p>
        <p>Information about minor acquaintances and about contemporaries whom Southey did not meet or correspond with can be found in the
					editorial notes to individual letters.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="ital">DNB</hi> indicates that further information can be found in the new Oxford <title level="m">Dictionary of National
						Biography</title>.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="ital">Hist P</hi> indicates that further information can be found in <title level="m">The History of Parliament</title>. </p>
        <lb />
        <list type="simple">
          <item n="1">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Adderley">Adderley:</term>
            <gloss target="#Adderley"> A friend of Southey&#8217;s during his time at Westminster School, his precise identity is not clear. He
							could be one of: Edward Hale Adderley (1771&#8211;1870), admitted 1784; George Augustus Adderley (dates unknown), admitted 1785;
							or Richard Boyle Adderley (dates unknown), admitted 1785.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="2">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="AikinJohn">Aikin, John (1747&#8211;1822; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#AikinJohn"> physician, author and brother of Anna Letitia Barbauld (1743&#8211;1825; <title level="m">DNB</title>).
							In the mid-1790s, Southey and Aikin moved in the same circles in London. Aikin was a regular contributor to periodicals
							and his review of <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> appeared in the <title level="m">Analytical Review</title> in 1796.
							In 1797 Aikin and his son, Arthur Aikin (1773&#8211;1854; <title level="m">DNB</title>), translated the first volume of Necker&#8217;s
								<title level="m">On the French Revolution</title>. Southey translated the second. In the mid-1790s, Southey (using a
							variety of pseudonyms) corresponded with Aikin in the latter&#8217;s capacity as literary editor of the <title level="m">Monthly
								Magazine</title>.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="3">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="AllenRobert">Allen, Robert (1772&#8211;1805):</term>
            <gloss target="#AllenRobert"> surgeon and journalist. Educated at Christ&#8217;s Hospital (where he was a contemporary of Samuel
							Taylor Coleridge and Charles Lamb) and University College, Oxford (BA 1796, MA 1803, MB and MD 1803). He first met
							Southey, who was flirting with a career in medicine, at the Anatomy School in Oxford in early 1794. They became firm
							friends, Southey later describing how in 1794 Allen had been his &#8216;bosom-companion&#8217; and had &#8216;rendered many hours delightful
							which would otherwise have passed in the destructive daydreams of solitude&#8217;. Allen wrote poetry and, in Oxford in June
							1794, introduced Southey to Coleridge. In 1794&#8211;1795, Allen was possibly a convert to Pantisocracy. In 1796, he enrolled at
							the Westminster Hospital and married a wealthy widow, Catherine, daughter of Nathaniel Forster (1726&#8211;1790; <title level="m">DNB</title>). She died within a year. In 1797, with the encouragement of Anthony Carlisle, he became deputy
							surgeon with England&#8217;s Second Royals, then stationed in Portugal. He was back in Britain by 1802 and from 1803 until his
							death worked as a journalist, writing for (according to Charles Lamb) the London newspapers the <title level="j">Oracle</title>, <title level="j">True Briton</title>, <title level="j">Star</title> and <title level="j">Traveller</title>.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="4">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BarnesFrederick">Barnes, Frederick &#8216;Ginger&#8217; (1771&#8211;1859):</term>
            <gloss target="#BarnesFrederick"> clergyman. A friend of Southey&#8217;s during his time at Westminster School and Oxford. In later life, Barnes held several livings in Devonshire.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="5">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BeddoesThomas">Beddoes, Thomas (1760&#8211;1808; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#BeddoesThomas"> chemist and physician. Born at Shifnal, Shropshire, son of Richard Beddoes and Ann Whitehall.
							Educated at Bridgnorth Grammar School, by private tutor, and at Pembroke College, Oxford (matric. 1776, BA 1779, MB and MD
							1786), and Edinburgh. Reader in Chemistry at Oxford from 1788. In the early 1790s, a growing reputation as a radical led
							to his surveillance by Home Office spies and failure to gain the Regius Chair in Chemistry. He left Oxford for Bristol in
							1793 and married Anna Edgeworth (1772&#8211;1824), sister of the novelist Maria (1768&#8211;1849; <title level="m">DNB</title>), in
							the following year. Beddoes was involved in the political protest movements of the mid-1790s and possibly first met
							Southey in 1795, during the latter&#8217;s immersion in Bristol politics. In 1799, Beddoes opened the Pneumatic Institute (from
							1802 the Preventive Medical Institution for the Sick and Drooping Poor) in Hotwells, Bristol. Southey participated in the
							experiments with gases carried out by Beddoes and Humphry Davy, and recorded in <title level="m">Notice of Some
								Observations made at the Medical Pneumatic Institution</title> (1799). Beddoes was a prolific writer on medical,
							political and educational reform. He was also a poet: author of <title level="m">Alexander&#8217;s Expedition</title> (1792) and
							a contributor to Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title> (1799). Southey respected Beddoes&#8217;s medical judgment,
							consulting him on more than one occasion. In 1809 he recorded that &#8216;From Beddoes I hoped for more good to the human race
							than from any other individual&#8217;. However, disagreements about poetry ensured that their personal relationship was not
							warm. Southey dismissed Beddoes as a &#8216;hypercritic of the Darwin school&#8217; and was furious when his &#8216;Domiciliary Verses&#8217; (a
							parody of Samuel Taylor Coleridge, William Wordsworth and Southey) found its way into the first volume of the <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title>. Joseph Cottle, who was responsible for the poem&#8217;s inclusion, was ordered by
							Southey not to solicit any further contributions from Beddoes.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="6">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Bedfordfamily">Bedford family:</term>
            <gloss target="#Bedfordfamily"> the Bedford family lived at Westminster and Brixton. The household consisted of the parents,
							Charles and Mary Bedford, three sons (Grosvenor, Horace and Harry) and a cousin, Mary Page. Southey was on good terms with
							the entire family. He made use of the library in their Westminster home and wrote the first draft of <title level="m">Joan
								of Arc</title> during an extended stay at their house in Brixton in summer 1793. Southey corresponded with Grosvenor
							and Horace.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="7">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford, Grosvenor Charles (1773&#8211;1839):</term>
            <gloss target="#BedfordGrosvenorCharles"> civil servant and miscellaneous writer. The son of Charles Bedford (Deputy Usher of
							the Exchequer, as Horace Walpole&#8217;s substitute). Educated at Westminster (adm. 1784), but did not attend university.
							Assistant clerk in the Exchequer Office, 1792&#8211;1803; clerk of the cash book, 1803&#8211;6; clerk of the registers and issues,
							1806&#8211;22; chief clerk in the auditor&#8217;s office, 1822&#8211;34. Admitted to Gray&#8217;s Inn, 26 January 1797. Bedford did not marry,
							despite regularly seeking Southey&#8217;s advice on his love affairs. Bedford and Southey met at Westminster School and their
							friendship endured for the remainder of their lives. Bedford had literary inclinations. He was involved in the ill-fated
								<title level="m">Flagellant</title> (1792), contributed poems to the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title> (1797)
							and the first volume of the <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title> (1799), and privately published his translation of
							Musaeus, <title level="m">The Loves of Hero and Leander</title> (1797). He worked with Southey on <title level="m">Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807) and contributed an unsigned notice of Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814) to the <title level="m">Quarterly Review</title>. His other
							publications included <title level="m">A Letter to the Right Hon. William Pitt on his Political Experiments</title> (1804,
							anonymous) and a <title level="m">Memoir</title> of Barr&#233; Charles Roberts (1814).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="8">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BedfordHenry">Bedford, Henry (&#8216;Harry&#8217;) (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#BedfordHenry"> the younger brother of Grosvenor and Horace Bedford.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="9">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BedfordHoraceWalpole">Bedford, Horace Walpole (c. 1776&#8211;1807):</term>
            <gloss target="#BedfordHoraceWalpole"> civil servant and miscellaneous writer. The younger brother of Grosvenor Charles
							Bedford and named after his father&#8217;s patron. He was educated at Westminster School (adm. 1784), where his nickname was
							&#8216;the Doctor&#8217; or &#8216;Dr. Johnson&#8217;. He did not attend university and later held a post at the British Museum. Like his older
							brother, he did not marry. Southey&#8217;s friendship with Horace began at school and their correspondence (though occasionally
							intermittent) lasted until at least 1797. Southey&#8217;s relationship with Horace was slightly different from that with
							Grosvenor Charles Bedford. He treated Horace as a younger brother: encouraging him and worrying about his tendency to
							laziness. He also fostered the younger man&#8217;s literary ambitions. Horace&#8217;s poems appeared in the <title level="m">Monthly
								Magazine</title> (1797) and the <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title> (1799).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="10">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe, Charles (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#BiddlecombeCharles"> neighbour and friend. Biddlecombe met Southey in summer 1797 when the latter moved to the
							village of Burton in Hampshire. Southey described him as &#8216;rich enough to buy books, and very friendly, all that a
							neighbour should be&#8217;. Biddlecombe married in summer 1798. His wife had died in childbirth by April 1799, leaving him with
							an infant daughter. During Southey&#8217;s numerous absences, Biddlecombe appears to have looked after the cottage at Burton and
							when it was finally given up in 1802 arranged for a sale of part of the furniture and stored some of Southey&#8217;s
							possessions, including books, for a number of years. During his 1817 visit to France, Southey ran into Biddlecombe, whom
							he had not seen for several years, and his invalid daughter, describing the latter as &#8216;short and plethoric, with a
							countenance of prepossessing good nature&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="11">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BiggsNathaniel">Biggs, Nathaniel (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#BiggsNathaniel"> a printer and stationer in Bristol. He printed books, including works by Beddoes, Coleridge,
							Estlin and Southey, for congeries of publishers in London and the South-West of England. In the mid-late 1790s, he entered
							into a business partnership with Joseph Cottle, printing the Bristol edition of Coleridge and Wordsworth&#8217;s <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> (1798), and the revised editions of 1800 and 1802.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="12">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BunburyCharlesJohn">Bunbury, Charles John (1772&#8211;1798):</term>
            <gloss target="#BunburyCharlesJohn"> soldier. Educated at Westminster School, where he was a friend of Southey&#8217;s, and Trinity
							College, Cambridge. In 1789, Bunbury presented Southey with a copy of Thomas Warton&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (3rd
							edn, 1779), see <title level="m">A Catalogue of the Printed Books Bequeathed by John Forster, Esq., LL.D.</title> (London,
							1888), p. 525. Their friendship did not last. In 1793, Bunbury tried to avoid Southey when the latter was visiting
							Cambridge. Southey, in turn, claimed that Bunbury&#8217;s &#8216;debauchery&#8217; was the direct result of his public school education.
							Bunbury joined the army and died at the Cape of Good Hope. Bunbury&#8217;s father, the artist Henry William Bunbury (1750&#8211;1811;
								<title level="m">DNB</title>), and his younger brother, Sir Henry Edward Bunbury (1778&#8211;1860; <title level="m">DNB</title>), later became close friends of Southey&#8217;s and members of his circle in Keswick.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="13">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="BurnettGeorge">Burnett, George (c. 1776&#8211;1811; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#BurnettGeorge"> writer. The son of John Burnett, a farmer, of Huntspill, Somerset. Educated at Balliol
							College, Oxford (matric. 1793). His varied career included time spent as a student at a dissenting academy in Manchester,
							pastor to a Unitarian congregation in Great Yarmouth, medical student at the University of Edinburgh, assistant to John
							Rickman, domestic tutor to the sons of Lord Stanhope, assistant surgeon to a militia regiment and (in Poland) tutor to the
							family of Count Zamovski. Burnett was also a professional writer, whose works included <title level="m">View of the
								Present State of Poland</title> (1807; from essays originally published in the <title level="m">Monthly
								Magazine</title>), <title level="m">Specimens of English Prose Writers</title> (1807; a companion to George Ellis&#8217;s
								<title level="m">Specimens of the Early English Poets</title>) and <title level="m">Extracts from the Prose Works of
								Milton</title> (1809). Southey met Burnett at Balliol and the two became friends. Burnett was one of the originators
							of Pantisocracy and in true Pantisocratic spirit proposed to Martha Fricker, who turned him down. In 1795, he shared
							lodgings with Southey and Coleridge in Bristol. From 1797&#8211;1798, he was minister to a Unitarian congregation in Great
							Yarmouth, Norfolk, where he also tutored Henry Herbert Southey. Burnett moved in metropolitan literary circles and was
							friendly with Charles Lamb and John Rickman. His relationship with Southey and Samuel Taylor Coleridge became deeply
							ambivalent &#8212; by 1803 he was accusing both of treating him badly. Burnett was an opium addict and his last years were
							probably spent in poverty. He died in the Marylebone Infirmary.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="14">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="ButtJohnMarten">Butt, John Marten (1774&#8211;1846):</term>
            <gloss target="#ButtJohnMarten"> clergyman and author. Only son of George and Mary Martha Butt and brother of Mary Martha
							Sherwood (1775&#8211;1851; <title level="m">DNB</title>), author of <title level="m">The Fairchild Family</title>. Educated
							Westminster (adm. 1788) and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1792, BA 1796, MA 1799). Curate of Witley, Worcestershire;
							Rector of Oddingley, Worcestershire from 1806 and Vicar of East Garston, Berkshire from 1806. Author of <title level="m">The Last Vision of Daniel</title> (1808) and other works. His first wife was Mary Ann Congreve; his second, Jemima
							Hubbal. Butt was a friend of Southey&#8217;s at Westminster School and Oxford.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="15">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="CampbellHenry">Campbell, Henry &#8216;Horse&#8217; (1774&#8211;?):</term>
            <gloss target="#CampbellHenry"> clergyman. Educated at Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1792). A university friend of Southey&#8217;s, they
							did not keep in touch in later life. Their last meeting was at Falmouth in 1801, when Campbell was on his way to take up a
							living in Antigua.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="16">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle, Anthony (1768&#8211;1840; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#CarlisleAnthony"> surgeon and anatomist. Born at Stillington, Durham, the third son of Thomas Carlisle and his
							first wife Barbara (d. 1768). Studied medicine in York, Durham and London, and was appointed surgeon to the Westminster
							Hospital in 1793. He married Martha Symmons in 1800 and in the same year was one of the founding members of the Royal
							College of Surgeons, serving as its president in 1829 and 1839. He moved in metropolitan literary and scientific circles,
							attending Mary Wollstonecraft on her death-bed in 1797. He was elected a Fellow of the Royal Society in 1804, held the
							post of Professor of Anatomy at the Royal Academy from 1808 and later that of surgeon-extraordinary to the Prince Regent.
							Carlisle was knighted when George IV acceded to the throne. Carlisle and Southey met in c. 1795, probably through their
							mutual friend Grosvenor Charles Bedford. In c. 1798 Carlisle, Southey and John May collaborated on a scheme for a
							convalescent asylum to assist the poor after their discharge from hospital. Although Carlisle and Southey corresponded,
							their letters to one another seem not to have survived.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="17">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="ColeridgeGeorge">Coleridge, George (1764&#8211;1828):</term>
            <gloss target="#ColeridgeGeorge"> clergyman and schoolmaster. The older brother of Samuel Taylor Coleridge. Southey and George
							Coleridge were &#8212; especially later in life, when the latter acknowledged Southey&#8217;s services to Samuel Taylor Coleridge&#8217;s
							family &#8212; on terms of mutual respect.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="18">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge, Samuel Taylor (1772&#8211;1834; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor"> poet, critic, philosopher and Southey&#8217;s brother-in-law. His complex &#8212; at times
							passionate &#8212; four decade relationship with Coleridge had a major impact both on Southey&#8217;s life and on his critical
							posterity. It began in Oxford in summer 1794 when Robert Allen introduced Southey to a visitor from Cambridge &#8212; Coleridge.
							It was a fateful meeting, leading to the failed scheme of Pantisocracy, literary collaboration, and &#8212; eventually &#8212; mutual
							disenchantment. As Southey later recorded: &#8216;that meeting fixed the future fortunes of us both ... Coleridge had at that
							time thought little of politics, in morals he was as loose ... as men at a university usually are, but he was a Unitarian.
							my morals were of the sternest Stoicism ... that same feeling which made me a poet kept me pure ... Our meeting was
							mutually serviceable, &#8212; I reformed his life, &amp; he disposed me toward Xtianity&#8217;. Although they corresponded from
							summer 1794, none of Southey&#8217;s letters to Coleridge for 1794&#8211;1797 have survived.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="19">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="CollinsCharles">Collins, Charles (c.1777&#8211;1806?):</term>
            <gloss target="#CollinsCharles"> school friend. The son of William Collins and his wife Sarah Astell of Maize Hill, Greenwich,
							Kent. Educated at Westminster and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. Jan 1793). Married Jane Forman, by whom he had one son.
							Died c. 1806. Collins&#8217;s biography is difficult to reconstruct as <title level="m">Records of Old Westminsters</title> and
								<title level="m">Alumni Oxoniensis</title> both confuse him with his son, also named Charles Collins, and give a later
							date of death. A note, now in the Huntington Library, written by an eponymous descendant confirms that he died young. In
							1815, Southey referred to Collins&#8217;s widow and in 1828 described him as long dead. Southey met Collins at Westminster and
							later described him as &#8216;one of my most intimate school and college friends&#8217;. However, by early 1794 their friendship had
							cooled and they seem to have had no contact with one another after Southey&#8217;s departure from Oxford later that
							year.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="20">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="CollinsJeremiah">Collins, Jeremiah (1774&#8211;?):</term>
            <gloss target="#CollinsJeremiah"> clergyman. Educated at Balliol College, Oxford (BA 1794). He eventually returned to his
							native Cornwall, where he became chaplain of the Truro Infirmary. He and Southey were friends for a short time in Oxford,
							but by mid-1794 they were permanently estranged.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="21">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="CombeEdward">Combe, Edward (c. 1773/4&#8211;1848):</term>
            <gloss target="#CombeEdward"> clergyman. Son of Richard Combe of Harley St. Educated at Westminster (adm. June 1785) and
							Christ Church, Oxford (matric. October 1792, BA 1796, MA 1803). Admitted to Lincoln&#8217;s Inn, January 1795. Perpetual Curate
							of Barrington, Somerset, 1810; Rector of Earnshill from 1821 and of Donyatt, from 1821. Southey met Combe at Westminster
							and later described him as one of his &#8216;most intimate acquaintances&#8217; during his years at school. Combe was known by the
							nicknames &#8216;His Majesty&#8217; or the &#8216;King of Men&#8217;. Although their friendship did not outlast Oxford, Southey did visit Combe in
							1824.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="22">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Cottlefamily">Cottle family:</term>
            <gloss cRef="#Cottlefamily"> the children of Robert Cottle, an unsuccessful Bristol tailor and draper. The family included
							Amos, Joseph and Robert (?1780&#8211;1858), a painter and founder of his own religious sect (&#8216;the Cottlelites&#8217;), and three
							sisters Ann, Martha and Mary, though there were possibly as many as eight siblings in total. Southey seems to have been
							acquainted with the entire Cottle family. After their secret marriage in November 1795, his wife Edith lived with the
							Cottle sisters for some of the time Southey was absent in Spain and Portugal.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="23">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="CottleAmos">Cottle, Amos Simon (1768?&#8211;1800; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#CottleAmos"> poet and translator. Elder brother of Joseph Cottle. Educated at the school run by Richard
							Henderson (1736/7&#8211;1792) at Hanham, near Bristol, and Magdalene College, Cambridge (matric. 1795, BA 1799). He then
							embarked on a legal training. He spent the final year of his life in London, where he was a friend of George Dyer and
							Charles Lamb, and died in his chambers at Clifford&#8217;s Inn. Author of <title level="m">Icelandic Poetry, or, The Edda of
								Saemund, translated into English verse</title> (1797; published by Joseph Cottle and with dedicatory poem by Southey).
							Several of his other poems were collected posthumously in the 1829 fourth edition of Joseph Cottle, <title level="m">Malvern Hills, with Minor Poems and Essays</title>. Southey probably met Amos Cottle through his younger brother
							Joseph. The two shared an interest in Scandinavian literature and mythology and it was Southey who encouraged Amos to
							produce a verse, rather than prose, translation of the <title level="m">Edda</title> and who reviewed it in the <title level="m">Critical Review</title>.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="24">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="CottleJoseph">Cottle, Joseph (1770&#8211;1853; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#CottleJoseph"> Bristolian author, bookseller and publisher. Although Coleridge&#8217;s biographer James Dykes
							Campbell joked &#8216;I never heard of ... [Cottle&#8217;s] having ... any [parents], and think it very doubtful. I should think he
							was found under a booksellers counter wrapped in Felix Farley&#8217;s newspaper&#8217;, Joseph was in fact the second child of Robert
							and Sarah Cottle. He was educated at the school run by Richard Henderson (1736/7&#8211;1792) at Hanham, near Bristol. In 1791 he
							opened a shop as a printseller, stationer, binder and bookseller in Bristol. Cottle abandoned bookselling in 1798 but
							continued publishing. Between 1791&#8211;1800, he sold, printed or published 114 works, in congeries with Joseph Johnson,
							Benjamin Flower, H. D. Symons and others. In 1800 he began to sell his copyrights to the London firm of Longman. A poet
							and prose writer, his works included: <title level="m">Poems</title> (1795), <title level="m">Malvern Hills</title> (1798;
							with a prefatory poem by Southey), <title level="m">Alfred</title> (1800), <title level="m">The Fall of Cambria</title>
							(1808), <title level="m">Early Recollections, Chiefly Relating to the Late Samuel Taylor Coleridge, During his Long
								Residence in Bristol</title> (1837) and <title level="m">Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert
								Southey</title> (1847). Cottle and Southey were introduced by Robert Lovell in 1794. Although not wealthy, Cottle
							provided generous financial help to Southey throughout the 1790s, even lending him money for his wedding ring. He
							published <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title> and the majority of Southey&#8217;s earliest works, including <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797) and <title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>
							(1797). His professional collaboration with Southey also included contributing poems to the <title level="m">Annual
								Anthology</title> and co-editing the works of their fellow Bristolian Thomas Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title level="m">DNB</title>). What Cottle did not know, was that Southey viewed his poetry with a merriment that verged on contempt.
							The two men met less frequently after Southey&#8217;s move to Keswick in 1803, but maintained their correspondence. Southey&#8217;s
							final tour of the West Country in 1836&#8211;1837 included a visit to Cottle in Bristol. After Southey&#8217;s death, Cottle was a
							central figure in the successful campaign to erect a monument to his memory in Bristol cathedral. He recorded his
							association with Southey for posterity in his controversial <title level="m">Reminiscences</title> (1847), itself a
							reworking of the equally contentious <title level="m">Early Recollections</title> (1837).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="25">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="DanversCharles">Danvers, Charles (d. 1814):</term>
            <gloss target="#DanversCharles"> Bristol wine merchant, trading under the name Danvers and White. He was distantly related to
							the regicides Sir John Danvers (1584/5&#8211;1655; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and General Thomas Harrison (c. 1616&#8211;60; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and to the diarist Celia Fiennes (1662&#8211;1741; <title level="m">DNB</title>). (Southey possessed
							a manuscript of Fiennes diary which he had been given by the Danvers family and included unacknowledged excerpts from it
							in his and Coleridge&#8217;s <title level="m">Omniana</title> (1812)). Danvers&#8217; father had &#8216;been a person of some property&#8217;,
							though the family&#8217;s fortunes had since declined. Danvers seems to have had two brothers and two sisters. He never married.
							A dissenter, he died in London &#8216;during a short tarriance there&#8217; and was buried in Asplands Burial Ground, Hackney. Danvers
							knew Southey from childhood. In 1797, their friendship flourished when Southey and his wife lodged in a house in
							Kingsdown, next door to Danvers and his mother. In 1799, Southey finished the fifteen book version of <title level="m">Madoc</title> in Mrs Danvers&#8217; &#8216;parlour on her little table&#8217;. When Southey went to Portugal in 1800&#8211;1, he left a copy
							of his poetic magnum opus with Danvers and also delegated the task of collecting materials for the third <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title> to him and Davy. This volume did not appear. Danvers visited Southey at Keswick in summer
							1805 and kept a journal of his tour, now in the British Library, Add MS 30,929. Extracts from this were published in
							Kenneth Curry, &#8216;A note on Wordsworth&#8217;s &#8220;Fidelity&#8221;&#8217;, <title level="m">Philological Quarterly</title>, 32 (1953),
							212&#8211;214.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="26">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="DaveyJohn">Davey, John (d. 1798):</term>
            <gloss target="#DaveyJohn"> master of Balliol College, Oxford 1785&#8211;1798.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="27">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="DeaconKate">Deacon, Kate:</term>
            <gloss target="#DeaconKate"> a friend of Grosvenor Charles Bedford and his family. Daughter of Mr and Mrs Deacon.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="28">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Deaconfamily">Deacon, Mr and Mrs:</term>
            <gloss target="#Deaconfamily"> friends of Grosvenor Charles Bedford and his family.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="29">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="DoddJamesWilliam">Dodd, James William (?1759/60&#8211;1818):</term>
            <gloss target="#DoddJamesWilliam"> an Usher at Westminster School from 1784.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="30">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="DolignonLouisa">Dolignon, Louisa (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#DolignonLouisa"> the widowed Mrs Dolignon and her sisters, the Misses Delamere, were friends of Southey&#8217;s aunt
							Elizabeth Tyler. Southey spent time at the Delamere home (Theobalds) in Hertfordshire, and Louisa Dolignon seems to have
							acted as his guardian during his time at Westminster School. William Vincent wrote to her (and not to Southey&#8217;s parents)
							regarding his involvement in <title level="m">The Flagellant</title>. Southey, in turn, went from Westminster to the
							Delameres&#8217; house after his suspension from school. Southey later recorded his &#8216;utmost reverence and affection&#8217; for
							Dolignon.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="31">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Doyly">Doyly:</term>
            <gloss target="#Doyly"> an acquaintance of Southey&#8217;s during his time at Westminster School. Kenneth Curry identified him as
							Thomas D&#8217;Oyly (1772&#8211;1855). However, the contexts in which he figures in Southey&#8217;s correspondence suggests that a more
							likely candidate is Sir John D&#8217;Oyly (1774&#8211;1825; <title level="m">DNB</title>), King&#8217;s Scholar at Westminster. Whilst at
							Cambridge, he won Sir W. Browne&#8217;s Medal for a Latin Ode (1795) and the Chancellor&#8217;s Second Medal (1796). An excellent
							linguist, he later worked as a civil servant in Ceylon.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="32">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="DuppaRichard">Duppa, Richard (c. 1768&#8211;1831; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#DuppaRichard"> writer (mainly on botany, art, literature and politics) and draughtsman. Son of William and
							Susannah Duppa. Educated (late in life) at Trinity College, Oxford (matric. 1807); entered Middle Temple 1810; graduated
							LLB Trinity Hall, Cambridge in 1814. His publications included: <title level="m">A Brief Account of the Subversion of the
								Papal Government in 1798</title> (1799), <title level="m">A Selection of Twelve Heads from the Last Judgment of
								Michael Angelo</title> (1801), <title level="m">Memoirs of a Literary and Political Character</title> (1803), and
								<title level="m">The Life and Literary Works of Michael Angelo Buonarotti, with His Poetry and Letters</title> (1806).
							The latter contained translations by Southey and William Wordsworth. Southey and Duppa were introduced by Edmund Seward in
							Oxford in 1793. Duppa was related to Seward and, according to family lore, distantly related to Southey. Part of Southey&#8217;s
							circle, he was at one time engaged to Mary Page, the cousin of Grosvenor Charles and Horace Walpole Bedford. In the 1790s,
							Southey sought Duppa&#8217;s advice about projected illustrated editions of his poems. Later, Duppa provided the material on art
							in Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Letters from England</title> (1807).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="33">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="DyerGeorge">Dyer, George (1755&#8211;1841; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#DyerGeorge"> author and advocate of political reform. Son of John Dyer, a shipwright of Bridewell, London.
							Educated at Christ&#8217;s Hospital and Emmanuel College, Cambridge (BA 1778). From the late 1780s to mid 1790s he was active in
							reformist causes, a member of the Constitutional Society and author of <title level="m">An Inquiry into the Nature of
								Subscription to the Thirty-Nine Articles</title> (1789, second revised edn 1792), <title level="m">Complaints of the
								Poor People of England</title> (1793) and <title level="m">A Dissertation on the Theory and Practice of
								Benevolence</title> (1795). After 1795, he abandoned active politics, turning instead to scholarship and literature.
							He was a prolific poet whose works included, <title level="m">Poems, Consisting of Odes and Elegies</title> (1792), <title level="m">The Poet&#8217;s Fate</title> (1797), and <title level="m">Poetics</title> (1812). Dyer met Southey in c.
							1794&#8211;1795, probably through Coleridge. He was enthusiastic about Pantisocracy and encouraged the publication of <title level="m">The Fall of Robespierre</title> (1794). He seems to have corresponded with Southey from the mid 1790s, but
							none of these early letters survive, making it difficult to judge the actual extent of their friendship. It is, however,
							fair to say, that this has probably been underestimated. A handful of letters written by Southey to Dyer from later
							periods do exist. Dyer&#8217;s close connections with Southey&#8217;s literary circle are evidenced in a letter sent to him by Joseph
							Cottle, 22 April 1797 now in the Houghton Library (Autograph File: Cottle, Joseph).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="34">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="EgertonThomasJohn">Egerton, Thomas and John (both, dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#EgertonThomasJohn"> London publishers and booksellers. Southey and his collaborators Bedford and Wynn,
							employed the Egertons as printers for the first five numbers of the schoolboy magazine <title level="m">The
								Flagellant</title>, which appeared between 1&#8211;29 March 1792. The fifth issue contained a controversial essay denouncing
							flogging as an invention of the devil. Under pressure from Dr William Vincent, the Head Master of Westminster School, the
							Egertons revealed that Southey was its author. Southey was expelled and the Egertons&#8217; involvement with <title level="m">The Flagellant</title> ceased. The remaining four issues, 5&#8211;26 April 1792, were printed by the Pall-Mall bookseller
							and printer Edward Jeffrey (dates unknown).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="35">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley, Peter (1774&#8211;1825; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#ElmsleyPeter"> classical scholar. Son of Alexander Elmsley. He was named after his uncle, the famous London
							bookseller Peter Elmsley, from whom he inherited a considerable fortune. Educated at Westminster and Christ Church, Oxford
							(matric. 1791, BA 1794, MA 1797, BD and DD 1823), he was described as &#8216;the fattest undergraduate of his day&#8217; (<title level="m">DNB</title>). Ordained and presented to the living of Little Horkesley, Essex, on his uncle&#8217;s death in 1802
							he relinquished his duties and income to a curate, though he continued to hold the living until 1816. He made a brief move
							to Edinburgh, where he met the founders of the <title level="m">Edinburgh Review</title>, to which he became a
							contributor. He returned to London and in 1807 moved to Kent, where he lived with his mother until 1816. During this time
							he produced editions of Aristophanes, Sophocles and Euripides and a number of learned papers on classical subjects,
							published in the <title level="m">Quarterly Review</title> and other periodicals. He travelled at length in Europe c.
							1816&#8211;1818 and settled in Oxford in 1818. In 1823 (having been unsuccessfully proposed for the Regius Chair of Divinity at
							Oxford and having turned down the See of Calcutta) he was elected Camden Professor of Ancient History and Principal of St
							Alban Hall, Oxford, offices he held until his death in 1825. Southey and Elmsley met at Westminster School and remained
							lifelong friends, though relatively little of what seems to have been an extensive correspondence survives. Elmsley was
							also a great friend of Charles Watkin Williams Wynn and the latter erected a memorial tablet to him in Christ Church
							Cathedral, Oxford.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="36">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="EstlinJohnPrior">Estlin, John Prior (1747&#8211;1817; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#EstlinJohnPrior"> Unitarian minister, at Lewin&#8217;s Mead Chapel, Bristol, and school master. Educated at the
							Warrington Academy, he moved to Bristol in 1771. Married Mary Coates (1753&#8211;1783) and then Susanna Bishop (d. 1842). He was
							on good terms with a number of writers, including Southey (whom he had taught briefly when he took over Mr Foot&#8217;s school,
							Bristol), Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Anna Laetitia Barbauld (1743&#8211;1825; <title level="m">DNB</title>). His publications
							included <title level="m">The Nature and Causes of Atheism</title> (1797).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="37">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="EstlinMrs">Estlin, Mrs:</term>
            <gloss target="#EstlinMrs"> Susanna Bishop (d. 1842), the second wife of John Prior Estlin.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="38">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="FavellRobert">Favell, Robert (1775&#8211;1812):</term>
            <gloss target="#FavellRobert"> soldier. Educated at Christ&#8217;s Hospital, where he was a friend of Samuel Taylor Coleridge.
							Obtained an army commission, fought in the Peninsular War and was killed at the battle of Salamanca. There is some
							confusion over Favell&#8217;s first name &#8212; with some sources citing it as Joseph or Samuel &#8212; see C. A. Prance, <title level="m">Companion to Charles Lamb. A Guide to People and Places 1760&#8211;1847</title> (1983), pp. 112&#8211;113 and Duncan Wu,
							&#8216;Unpublished drafts of sonnets by Lamb and Favell&#8217;, <title level="m">Charles Lamb Bulletin</title>, n.s. 75 (1991),
							100.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="39">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Frickerfamily">Fricker family:</term>
            <gloss target="#Frickerfamily"> Stephen Fricker and his second wife Martha Rowles and their six surviving children: Sarah,
							Mary, Edith, Martha (b. 1777), Eliza (b. 1778) and George (b. 1785). The failure of his business speculations (including
							the manufacture of sugar pans) contributed to Stephen Fricker&#8217;s early death and to a sharp decline in the fortunes of his
							family. The family home was sold, Mrs Fricker moved into lodgings in Bristol and opened a dame school, and her three
							eldest daughters became seamstresses, whose clients included Southey&#8217;s mother and aunt, Elizabeth Tyler. Southey knew the
							Frickers from childhood and was &#8216;partly educated&#8217; with the three eldest girls. The similarity between their situation and
							his own (Southey&#8217;s father was also a bankrupt) was perhaps an important factor in what was to be a lifelong
							relationship.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="40">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerEdith">Fricker, Edith (1774&#8211;1837; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#FrickerEdith"> Southey&#8217;s first wife. The third surviving child of Stephen Fricker and Martha Rowles. Southey
							and Edith met as children in Bristol. They married in secret on 14 November 1795 at St Mary Redcliffe, Bristol. As her
							sister Sarah later explained, Southey &#8216;left ... [Edith] at the Church door&#8217; and the following day departed for Spain and
							Portugal. Edith spent the early days of her marriage living with the Cottle sisters and using her maiden name, only
							reverting to &#8216;Southey&#8217; when the secret became public in early 1796. Recent biographers of Southey have questioned the
							state of his marriage, particularly given his lively &#8212; even flirtatious &#8212; friendships with Mary Barker and Caroline
							Bowles, who became his second wife in 1839. Compared to these other women, or to her sister Sarah, Edith is a relatively
							shadowy figure, plagued by physical and mental illness. The deaths of four of her eight children, in particular that of
							her daughter Isabel in 1826, hastened her decline. She suffered a complete collapse in 1834 and was taken to The Retreat,
							the pioneering, Quaker-run asylum in York, where she was diagnosed as of &#8216;unsound mind&#8217; and treated with &#8216;purgatives,
							remedies, [and] leeches&#8217;. She was released in 1835 &#8216;as admitted&#8217; &#8212; that is, uncured and incurable. Edith spent her final
							years at her home, Greta Hall, where she was cared for by Southey and her daughters Bertha and Kate. Southey described her
							death as a release from &#8216;a pitiable state of existence&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="41">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerMary">Fricker, Mary (1771&#8211;1862):</term>
            <gloss target="#FrickerMary"> Southey&#8217;s sister-in-law. The second surviving child of Stephen Fricker and Martha Rowles. In the
							early 1790s she worked as an actress in Bath and Bristol theatres. She married Robert Lovell in January 1794, in spite of
							the disapproval of his family. Their son, also called Robert, was born in 1795. After Lovell&#8217;s death in 1796, Southey
							tried to persuade his family to provide for his widow and child. He was only partially successful. The Lovells gave Robert
							Lovell Junior the occasional gift (for example, &#163;20 in 1802) and made some contribution to the boy&#8217;s early education, but
							they did not provide consistent, long-term support. As a result, Mary and her son were dependent upon Southey. They lived
							with or near to the Southeys for the rest of the 1790s and early 1800s and in 1803 accompanied them to their new home,
							Greta Hall. Robert Lovell Junior had few prospects (significantly less than those of Samuel Taylor Coleridge&#8217;s children,
							whose paternal relations were capable of greater generosity). By 1803, the money paid by the Lovell family for the child&#8217;s
							education was about to cease, so Southey and John May tried to get Robert Lovell Junior into Christ&#8217;s Hospital. They
							failed. The boy was apprenticed to a London printer and effectively separated from his mother and family in Keswick. The
							impact of this on his character seems to have been profound. In 1836 his first cousin Sara Coleridge described Robert
							Lovell Junior&#8217;s lack of social skills: &#8216;From nine years old he has had to shift and scramble a good deal for himself, to
							bear up against a hard world which would have crushed &lt;or injured&gt; the frame it did not render to a certain
							degree tough &amp; unyielding ... [he] never had the opportunity of acquiring a taste for domestic, scarcely even for
							social enjoyment: we ought not to wonder that he is deficient in many qualities which can only be fostered thereby.&#8217; Mary
							remained at Greta Hall after her son&#8217;s departure for London, finally moving out when it was given up after Southey&#8217;s death
							in 1843. She spent her final years living with Kate, Southey&#8217;s unmarried daughter, and died on 10 August 1862. She was
							buried in the Southey grave in Crosthwaite churchyard, on the outskirts of Keswick. Robert Lovell Junior predeceased his
							mother. He disappeared whilst on a European walking tour in 1841.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="42">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="FrickerSarah">Fricker, Sarah (1770&#8211;1845):</term>
            <gloss target="#FrickerSarah"> Southey&#8217;s sister-in-law. The eldest surviving child of Stephen Fricker and Martha Rowles. Sarah
							and Southey were childhood friends and it was through her that Southey met Robert Lovell in late 1793. Sarah married
							Samuel Taylor Coleridge on 4 October 1795. Her relationship with Southey, who provided her with advice and support during
							her later marital difficulties, was affectionate, and at times jokey and rumbustious. Indeed, Sarah&#8217;s daughter and
							namesake recorded that Southey had been romantically interested in Sarah Fricker first, only later turning his attentions
							to her sister Edith.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="43">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="GilbertWilliam">Gilbert, William (1763&#8211;c. 1825; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#GilbertWilliam"> poet and astrologer. Born in Antigua, son of Nathaniel Gilbert, speaker of the Antiguan House
							of Assembly. In 1788 he came to England to work as a lawyer, but suffered a mental collapse and was placed in an asylum
							run by Richard Henderson (1736/7&#8211;1792) at Hanham near Bristol. (In an earlier career as a schoolmaster, Henderson had
							numbered Joseph Cottle among his pupils.) Gilbert was released after a year and went to London, where he worked as an
							astrologer and maker of magic talismans. In 1795 he went to Bristol, where he became friends with Southey and Coleridge.
							In 1796 he published <title level="m">The Hurricane: a Theosophical and Western Eclogue</title>. He disappeared in 1798.
							It was thought he had left Bristol in search of the &#8216;Gilberti&#8217;, an African tribe with whom he believed he had a spiritual
							affinity. Southey made enquiries after him, but to no effect. Although by 1820 Southey spoke of Gilbert as long dead, he
							was in fact probably still alive, dying c. 1825.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="44">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="GodwinWilliam">Godwin, William (1756&#8211;1836; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#GodwinWilliam"> philosopher and novelist. Southey was an early enthusiast for his <title level="m">An Enquiry
								Concerning Political Justice</title> (1793), which he read shortly after its publication. He met Godwin in London in
							1797 and disliked him.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="45">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="HillHerbert">Hill, Herbert (1750&#8211;1828):</term>
            <gloss target="#HillHerbert"> Southey&#8217;s maternal uncle. Hill was the product of a second marriage, and after his father&#8217;s
							death was left short of money (even having to &#8216;pay his own school bills when it was in his power&#8217;) and on extremely bad
							terms with his older half-brother. Hill was educated at Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1772, MA 1774). From 1792&#8211;1807, he was
							chaplain to the British factory at Lisbon. On his return to England, Hill took up a living he owned at Staunton-Upon-Wye,
							remaining there until 1810 when the Duke of Bedford presented him to a living in Streatham. In 1808 Hill married a woman
							twenty-five years his junior, Catherine Bigg (b. c. 1775), a friend of Jane Austen (1775&#8211;1817; <title level="m">DNB</title>). The marriage produced six surviving children, all of whom were on good terms with Southey and his
							family. Hill&#8217;s son and namesake, Herbert Hill Junior (1810&#8211;1892), married Southey&#8217;s daughter Bertha in 1839. Hill took a
							paternal interest in his nephews, and helped finance Southey&#8217;s education. Hill&#8217;s concern about Southey&#8217;s refusal to take
							the path mapped out for him (a path leading to ordination), his relationship with Edith Fricker, and his politics, led him
							to visit England in 1795. He returned to Portugal with Southey in tow. Oblivious to the fact that his nephew had married
							Edith the day before their departure, Hill used every opportunity to introduce Southey to more suitable women.
							Nevertheless, the time Southey spent with his uncle in 1795&#8211;1796 greatly strengthened their relationship, which remained
							close until Hill&#8217;s death in 1828. Hill encouraged his nephew&#8217;s interests in Spanish and Portuguese history and literature,
							and later bought books and manuscripts on his behalf. Southey dedicated his <title level="m">Colloquies</title> (1829) to
							his uncle.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="46">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="HillMargaret">Hill, Margaret (&#8216;Peggy&#8217;) (d. 1801):</term>
            <gloss target="#HillMargaret"> Southey&#8217;s cousin, probably the daughter of his mother&#8217;s brother Joseph Hill.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="47">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="HookJames">Hook, James (c. 1772&#8211;1828; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#HookJames"> Dean of Worcester and brother of the writer and hoaxer Theodore Hook (1788&#8211;1841; <title level="m">DNB</title>). Educated at Westminster School and St Mary Hall, Oxford (his admission to Christ Church was blocked in
							1792 because of his involvement in &#8216;acts of insubordination&#8217; whilst at school). Hook was one of the editors of the
							schoolboy magazine, <title level="m">The Trifler</title>, and a keen musician and artist. He was a friend of Southey&#8217;s
							during his time at Westminster, but their friendship did not last beyond schooldays.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="48">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="HorsemanJohn">Horseman, John (1776&#8211;1844):</term>
            <gloss target="#HorsemanJohn"> clergyman. The son of an Oxfordshire cleric, he was educated at Corpus Christi, Oxford (BA
							1795), where he remained as a fellow from 1795&#8211;1819. He was Rector of Heydon and Little Chishill from 1810. He was a
							university friend of Southey&#8217;s. Although they lost touch in the mid 1790s, in 1835 after a gap of &#8216;one and forty years&#8217;
							Horseman wrote to Southey recalling their old acquaintance. At the time of their reunion, Southey was not aware that at
							the height of the <title level="m">Wat Tyler</title> controversy in 1817, a &#8216;John Horseman&#8217; &#8212; presumably the same one &#8212;
							had sent his political opponent William Smith (1756&#8211;1835) a transcript of another production of the Poet Laureate&#8217;s
							radical youth &#8212; &#8216;To the Exiled Patriots&#8217;. Horseman&#8217;s letter is now in the William R. Perkins Library, Duke
							University.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="49">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="HoweThomas">Howe, Thomas (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#HoweThomas"> clergyman. Possibly the son of John Howe of Honiton, Devon. Educated at Emmanuel College,
							Cambridge and Balliol College, Oxford. Howe was Rector of Huntspill, Somerset 1804&#8211;1823. He was Southey&#8217;s tutor at Oxford
							in 1793&#8211;1794.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="50">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="HucksJoseph">Hucks, Joseph (1772&#8211;1800):</term>
            <gloss target="#HucksJoseph"> writer. Educated at Cambridge, Hucks accompanied Samuel Taylor Coleridge on his 1794 tour,
							publishing an account &#8212; <title level="m">A Pedestrian Tour Through North Wales, in a Series of Letters</title> &#8212; the
							following year. Southey &#8212; and Coleridge &#8212; renewed their acquaintance with him during their visit to Exeter in 1799 and
							Hucks contributed three poems to Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title> (1800). He died of consumption in
							1800. In an unpublished preliminary notice to his <title level="m">Specimens of the Later English Poets</title> (1807)
							Southey recalled the &#8216;many pleasant &amp; rememberable hours&#8217; he and Hucks had spent together.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="51">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="JardineAlexander">Jardine, Alexander (d. 1799; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#JardineAlexander"> army officer and author. He was appointed to the post of Consul in Galicia in 1791. He was
							a friend of William Godwin and Joel Barlow (1754&#8211;1812; <title level="m">DNB</title>), and his writings included <title level="m">Letters from Barbary, France, Spain, Portugal &amp;c.</title> (1788). He and Southey met during the
							latter&#8217;s 1795&#8211;1796 visit to the Iberian peninsula. He figures in both Southey&#8217;s correspondence from this period and in
								<title level="m">Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (1797).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="52">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="JenningsJames">Jennings, James (1772&#8211;1833; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#JenningsJames"> writer. Born in Huntspill, Somerset, son of a village shopkeeper, John Jennings, and his wife
							Elizabeth Fear. Educated locally and at North Petherton School. Apprenticed to a Bristol apothecary in 1786. He
							contributed poems to the <title level="m">European Magazine</title> and in 1794 published <title level="m">The
								Times</title>, a satire. Jennings moved to London shortly after his marriage to Charlotte Sawier, probably the only
							daughter of Southey&#8217;s landlady Mary Sawier, in 1795. He returned to work in his family&#8217;s shop in 1801 and remained in
							Huntspill until the mid-1810s, when economic depression led to the failure of the business. He continued with his literary
							pursuits, contributing to the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title> (from 1807) and publishing <title level="m">Poems,
								Consisting of the Mysteries of Mendip, the Magic Ball</title> (1810). He returned to London in 1817 and worked as a
							professional writer, with some support from Sir William Paxton, a wealthy banker. His works included the <title level="m">Family Cyclopaedia</title> (1821), <title level="m">Observations on Some of the Dialects of the West of
								England</title> (1825) and <title level="m">Ornithologia</title> (1828). He founded the short-lived Metropolitan
							Literary Institution in 1823 and was editor of the <title level="m">Metropolitan Literary Journal</title> (1824). Jennings
							met Southey (and Coleridge) in Bristol in c. 1794. Although they were not close friends, he and Southey corresponded (the
							correspondence has not survived) and remained in contact until c. 1828. Jennings was a great admirer of Southey&#8217;s writing,
							but the admiration was not reciprocated. Southey nicknamed him &#8216;poor Trauma&#8217; and &#8216;the traumatic poet&#8217;, though he admired
							Jennings&#8217;s &#8216;moral character&#8217;. Jennings shared Southey&#8217;s interest in educational methods, and in 1813, in collaboration
							with the local rector at Huntspill, established a school conducted on Lancaster and Bell&#8217;s monitorial system. Jennings
							included anecdotes of Southey and Coleridge&#8217;s early careers in the <title level="m">Metropolitan Literary Journal</title>
							(1824).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="53">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="KellyMontague">Kelly, Montague Henry (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#KellyMontague"> educated at Westminster School (adm. 1786). A friend of Southey&#8217;s during his
							schooldays.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="54">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="KiddJohn">Kidd, John (1775&#8211;1851):</term>
            <gloss target="#KiddJohn"> doctor and author of medical treatises. Educated at Westminster School and Christ Church, Oxford
							(matric. 1793, BA 1797). A friend of Southey&#8217;s during his time at Oxford, and possibly a school friend as well.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="55">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LambCharles">Lamb, Charles (1775&#8211;1834; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#LambCharles"> essayist. Educated at Christ&#8217;s Hospital, where he was a friend of Samuel Taylor Coleridge, he
							was later a clerk at the East India Company. Lamb and Southey met in 1795. Their relationship started to blossom in 1797,
							when Lamb &#8212; accompanied by Charles Lloyd &#8212; paid Southey an unexpected visit. Southey and Lamb shared an interest in
							Francis Quarles (1592&#8211;1644; <title level="m">DNB</title>). They quarrelled briefly &#8212; and publicly &#8212; in 1823, but were
							reconciled. Although they corresponded, Southey&#8217;s letters to Lamb have not survived.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="56">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LambThomasDavis">Lamb, Thomas Davis (1775&#8211;1818; <title level="m">Hist P</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#LambThomasDavis"> politician. The eldest son of Thomas Phillipps Lamb and his wife Elizabeth Davis. Educated
							at Westminster (adm. 1788); Edinburgh University (1792) and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. Dec 1793). Lamb&#8217;s family were
							wealthy, politically influential and well-connected. His father was the government manager at Rye, Sussex. Lamb&#8217;s career
							benefited from the patronage of Lord Liverpool (1727&#8211;1808; <title level="m">DNB</title>) and his eldest son, Lord
							Hawkesbury (1770&#8211;1828; <title level="m">DNB</title>), a future Prime Minister. Lamb was private secretary to Hawkesbury,
							then Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, 1801&#8211;1802, and in 1802 was offered but rejected the consulship at Lisbon, a
							post worth between &#163;2000&#8211;2500 per year. He sat as an M.P. for Rye from 1802&#8211;1806, though he seems never to have spoken in
							the House of Commons. He vacated his seat when appointed to the post of Law Clerk at the Home Office by the Ministry of
							&#8216;Talents&#8217;. Following in the footsteps of his grandfather and father, he was Mayor of Rye from 1803&#8211;1804, 1809&#8211;1810 and
							1816&#8211;1817. He never married. Southey described Lamb as &#8216;one of my oldest &#8212; &amp; once one of my most intimate
							friends&#8217;. The two met whilst pupils at Westminster and Southey stayed with Lamb&#8217;s family in Rye on more than one occasion.
							They drifted apart (though, Southey later noted, &#8216;without dissention&#8217;) during Southey&#8217;s time at Oxford. Lamb seems to have
							made an effort to renew their acquaintance, seeking Southey out in London in 1802. In later years, however, Southey&#8217;s
							opinion of him soured. He described him as one who had &#8216;discarded decency&#8217; and on reading of Lamb&#8217;s death in a newspaper
							admitted that he had: &#8216; ... thought more of him, poor fellow, in consequence, than I had done for the last four-and-twenty
							years ... [He] had become a mere idle heir of fortune, and not having his estates to manage while his father lived, had
							not even that occupation to keep him from frivolities. He was an old man at thirty, and that too being of a family in
							which it is degeneracy to die at an age short of fourscore.&#8217;</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="57">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LambThomasPhillipps">Lamb, Thomas Phillipps (?1752&#8211;1819; <title level="m">Hist P</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#LambThomasPhillipps"> politician. The father of Thomas Davis Lamb. He was married to Elizabeth Davis and lived
							at Mountsfield Lodge, near Rye. By the mid-eighteenth century the Lamb family had become the dominant force on Rye
							corporation and wielded great political influence in the borough. Lamb was the government agent in Rye and sat as an M.P.
							for the town 1812&#8211;1816 and 1819, though (like his son) he is not known to have spoken in the House of Commons. He was
							Mayor of Rye some 18 times between 1775&#8211;1817. Southey twice visited the Lambs home in Rye in 1791 and 1792 and was on
							excellent terms with Thomas Phillipps Lamb, perhaps seeing him as a surrogate father-figure. Their correspondence lapsed
							during Southey&#8217;s time at Oxford and was briefly renewed in 1798.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="58">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LeGriceSamuel">Le Grice, Samuel (1775&#8211;1802):</term>
            <gloss target="#LeGriceSamuel"> soldier. The younger brother of Coleridge&#8217;s school fellow, Charles Valentine Le Grice
							(1773&#8211;1858). Educated at Christ&#8217;s Hospital, where he was a contemporary and friend of Charles Lamb, and Trinity College,
							Cambridge. He obtained an army commission and died in Jamaica.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="59">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LewisRichard">Lewis, Richard (1771&#8211;1843):</term>
            <gloss target="#LewisRichard"> clergyman and schoolmaster. Educated at Balliol and Corpus Christi Colleges, Oxford (matric.
							1792, BA 1796). He became a curate and master of the grammar school in Honiton, Devon. A friend of Southey&#8217;s at Oxford,
							they lost touch in later years.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="60">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot, Nicholas (c. 1771/2&#8211;1847):</term>
            <gloss target="#LightfootNicholas"> clergyman and schoolmaster. Son of Nicholas Lightfoot of Moretonhampstead, Devon. Educated
							at Balliol College, Oxford (matric. 1790, BA 1794). Perpetual curate for Churcheton, Devon from 1795 and Rector of
							Stockleigh Pomeroy from 1831&#8211;1847. Southey met Lightfoot at Balliol and their friendship endured until his death. Southey
							considered sending his brother Edward Southey to be educated by Lightfoot (though didn&#8217;t do so) and in later life stayed
							with him during visits to the south west of England.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="61">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LloydCharles">Lloyd, Charles (1775&#8211;1839; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#LloydCharles"> poet. Eldest child of Charles, a wealthy Quaker banker, and his wife Mary. He matriculated at
							Caius College, Cambridge in 1798 but did not take his degree. He married Sophia Pemberton in 1799 and they moved to
							Ambleside in 1800. His works included: contributions to Samuel Taylor Coleridge&#8217;s <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797),
								<title level="m">Blank Verse</title> (1798) (co-authored with Charles Lamb), the controversial roman a clef <title level="m">Edmund Oliver</title> (1798), <title level="m">Nugae Canorae</title> (1819), <title level="m">Desultory
								Thoughts in London</title> (1821), <title level="m">Poetical Essays on the Character of Pope</title> (1821), and
								<title level="m">The Duke d'Ormond</title> (1822),. Lloyd&#8217;s later life was clouded by mental illness, he was briefly
							confined in Quaker-run asylum The Retreat, York and died in a sanatorium near Versailles. Lloyd met Southey at Burton in
							August 1797, when he and Charles Lamb unexpectedly turned up on Southey&#8217;s doorstep. Lloyd remained with Southey and his
							family for several months. Southey recognised in him a fellow man of strong emotions, a kindred &#8212; yet also unlike &#8212;
							spirit, and worried that Lloyd&#8217;s &#8216;feelings ... are not so blunt as we could wish them &#8212; or as they should be for his own
							happiness&#8217;. Indeed Lloyd&#8217;s continued presence was increasingly unwelcome and in 1798 his tale-telling led to a major
							quarrel between Southey and Coleridge which was not healed until 1799. After Southey moved to Keswick in 1803, Lloyd was
							on the fringes of his circle. In his edition of Cowper (1836&#8211;1837), Southey made his final public observations on Lloyd&#8217;s
							tragic history: &#8216;[his] intellectual powers were of a very high order ... when in company with persons who were not
							informed of his condition, no one could descry in him the slightest appearance of a deranged mind.&#8217;</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="62">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LoshJames">Losh, James (1763&#8211;1833; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#LoshJames"> barrister. Second son of John Losh. Born at Woodside, Carlisle, he was educated at Trinity
							College, Cambridge (BA 1786) and Lincoln&#8217;s Inn (called to the Bar 1789). He visited Paris in 1792 and on his return to
							England moved in a circle of metropolitan and Cambridge-based radicals and reformers that included George Dyer, William
							Godwin, John Horne Tooke (1736&#8211;1812; <title level="m">DNB</title>), John Tweddell (1769&#8211;1799; <title level="m">DNB</title>), Felix Vaughan (dates unknown), and William Wordsworth. In 1795&#8211;1796, ill-health forced his relocation to
							Bath, where he moved in the same circles as Southey. Losh was amongst the earliest readers of the manuscript of the first
							complete version of <title level="m">Madoc</title> and had literary ambitions of his own, publishing an edition of
							Milton&#8217;s <title level="m">Areopagitica</title> (1791) and a translation of Benjamin Constant&#8217;s <title level="m">Observations on the Strength of the Present Government in France</title> (1797). He married Cecilia Baldwin in
							February 1798 and moved permanently to Newcastle at the end of the same year. In later life he was a successful lawyer,
							businessman and local politician.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="63">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Lovellfamily">Lovell family:</term>
            <gloss target="#Lovellfamily"> a family of Bristol-based Quakers and manufacturers. It consisted of a father (d. 1803) (about
							whose name there is some confusion &#8212; it is recorded variously as Robert and Joseph), and numerous children. His first
							marriage to Edith Bourne (1741&#8211;1781) had produced at least two sons, Joseph and Robert, and two daughters, whose names are
							not known. Mr Lovell also had a substantial family by a second marriage. Southey was on reasonable terms with all the
							Lovells, but their relationship was clouded by struggles over adequate financial provision for the son and widow of Robert
							Lovell.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="64">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="LovellRobert">Lovell, Robert (1771&#8211;1796; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#LovellRobert"> poet. Born in Bristol, the son of a wealthy Quaker manufacturer (initially of cabinets and
							later of pins), and his first wife Edith Bourne, a Quaker minister. Lovell possibly entered the manufacturing business (on
							his death he was described as a pin manufacturer) but was ill at ease in the commercial world. In 1794 he married Mary
							Fricker. His family disapproved of the match as she was not a Quaker and had worked as an actress. Their son, also named
							Robert, was born in 1795. Lovell died at Bristol on 3 May 1796 of a fever contracted on a trip to Salisbury and
							exacerbated by refusing to take medical advice before returning home. One of his final letters to his wife is in the
							Huntington Library, San Marino. Lovell&#8217;s father was reluctant to provide regular financial support for his widow and child
							and both became part of Southey&#8217;s extended household. Lovell and Southey were introduced by Sarah Fricker in Bristol in
							late 1793. Lovell was also a poet, his <title level="m">Bristol: a Satire</title> appeared in 1794, and he and Southey
							embarked on a period of collaboration: planning two co-authored collections, only one of which was published under the
							pseudonyms &#8216;Bion&#8217; [Southey] and &#8216;Moschus&#8217; [Lovell] in late 1794. Lovell was also involved in the 1794 revisions to
							Southey&#8217;s <title level="m">Joan of Arc</title>. The advent of Coleridge in summer&#8211;autumn 1794 seems to have led (at least
							temporarily) to a reorientation of literary relationships. Lovell was pushed to the margins. His contribution to <title level="m">The Fall of Robespierre</title> was dropped and Coleridge was openly critical of his poetry. Lovell was,
							however, involved in Pantisocracy and it was through him that Southey and Coleridge were introduced to Joseph Cottle.
							After Lovell&#8217;s death, Southey tried &#8212; and failed &#8212; to produce a subscription edition of his poems, to raise money for his
							widow and child. However, Lovell&#8217;s writings were included in the <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title> (1799 and 1800)
							and <title level="m">Specimens of the Later English poets</title> (1807). In a notice published in <title level="m">Literary Memoirs of Living Authors of Great Britain</title> (1798), David Rivers described Lovell&#8217;s poetry as being
							&#8216;entitled to considerable distinction&#8217;. Southey described receiving the news of Lovell&#8217;s death as &#8216;the most sudden check I
							ever experienced&#8217;. The full extent of their relationship is difficult to gauge because of the survival of only two letters
							from what must have been an extensive correspondence.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="65">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="MaberGeorgeMartin">Maber, George Martin (d. 1844):</term>
            <gloss target="#MaberGeorgeMartin"> clergyman. Educated at St Paul&#8217;s School, London and then at Cambridge. He was personal
							chaplain to Lord Bute and from 1795 Rector of Merthyr Tydfil. Maber and Southey met during a voyage to Portugal in
							November 1795.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="66">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="MayJohn">May, John (1775&#8211;1856):</term>
            <gloss target="#MayJohn"> merchant, financier and business agent. A member of a wealthy family, both his father (Joseph) and
							grandfather were successful wine merchants in Lisbon. He was educated at Newcome&#8217;s Academy, Hackney, where he was taught
							by George Coleridge, with whom he became lifelong friends. May went to Lisbon in 1793, in order to learn the family trade,
							returning to England in 1796. May married Susannah Frances Livius in 1799. The marriage produced four children. May and
							Southey met in Portugal in 1796. Their friendship was to last until the latter&#8217;s death. May acted as a financial adviser
							and agent to Southey, lending him money &#8212; including sums to finance Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s education &#8212; and purchasing
							goods on his behalf. Southey reciprocated when May experienced a severe financial crisis in 1821 by lending him his life
							savings of &#163;620. May visited the Southeys on several occasions and acted as godfather to Southey&#8217;s two eldest children &#8212;
							Margaret Edith (1802&#8211;1803) and Edith May (1803&#8211;1871), the latter named in his honour. <title level="m">The Poet&#8217;s
								Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816) was dedicated to him &#8216;in testimony of the highest esteem and affection&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="67">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="MoreHannah">More, Hannah (1745&#8211;1833; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#MoreHannah"> writer and philanthropist. Southey and More met in October 1795, when he visited her house at
							Cowslip Green, just outside Bristol.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="68">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="MorganJohnJames">Morgan, John James (d. 1820):</term>
            <gloss target="#MorganJohnJames"> businessman. His friendship with Southey dated from their time as pupils at Williams&#8217;
							School, Bristol. From 1810&#8211;1816, Morgan and his wife took in Samuel Taylor Coleridge and attempted to cure him of his
							opium addiction. When Morgan&#8217;s finances collapsed in 1813, Southey, Charles Lamb and other friends contributed to an
							annuity for him.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="69">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="MorganMary">Morgan, Mary (b. 1782):</term>
            <gloss target="#MorganMary"> the wife of one of Southey&#8217;s oldest friends, John James Morgan.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="70">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="NaresRobert">Nares, Robert (1753&#8211;1829; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#NaresRobert"> philologist, clergyman and reviewer. From 1779&#8211;1783 Nares was tutor to Charles Watkin Williams
							Wynn and his older brother, Watkin. He was Usher at Westminster School from 1786&#8211;1788, where he continued his tutoring of
							the Wynn boys and where he undoubtedly met Charles Wynn&#8217;s friend Southey. In 1793, Nares was the founder-editor of the
							pro-government review the <title level="m">British Critic</title>.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="71">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="PalmerMiss">Palmer, Miss:</term>
            <gloss target="#PalmerMiss"> a close friend of Southey&#8217;s aunt, Elizabeth Tyler. Her father was John Palmer (1702/3&#8211;1788),
							proprietor of the Theatre Royal, Bath, and her only brother the theatre proprietor and postal reformer John Palmer
							(1742&#8211;1818; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="72">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Peacockunknown">Peacock (first name and dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#Peacockunknown"> Southey lodged with Peacock and his wife in Newington Butts in 1797. Peacock was involved in
							the book trade, possibly as a travelling salesman. The Peacocks were unhappily married and later in life Mrs Peacock was
							central in having her husband committed to a private asylum. On at least two occasions, Peacock wrote to Southey from his
							&#8216;place of confinement&#8217; and in 1816 Southey made enquiries about his case.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="73">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="PeckwellRobertHenry">Peckwell, Robert Henry (later Blosset; 1776&#8211;1823):</term>
            <gloss target="#PeckwellRobertHenry"> lawyer. Eldest son of Rev. Henry and Bella Peckwell. In 1811, he assumed his mother&#8217;s
							surname. Educated Westminster (adm. 1785) and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1792, BA 1796, MA 1799). Admitted to
							Lincoln&#8217;s Inn 1795, called to the Bar 1801; Serjeant-at-Law 1809. Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Bengal, 1821;
							knighted 1822. Author of <title level="m">Cases on Controverted Elections in the Second Parliament of the United
								Kingdom</title> (1805&#8211;1806). He never married. Peckwell was a friend of Southey&#8217;s during his time at Westminster
							School and Oxford.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="74">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="PeggeChristopher">Pegge, Christopher (d. 1822):</term>
            <gloss target="#PeggeChristopher"> a fellow of Christ Church, Oxford and from 1790 Lees Reader in Anatomy. He was elected a
							Fellow of the Royal Society in 1795 and was knighted in 1799.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="75">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="PembertonSophia">Pemberton, Sophia (d. 1830):</term>
            <gloss target="#PembertonSophia"> daughter of a Birmingham manufacturer, she married Charles Lloyd on 24 April 1799. They
							moved to Old Brathay, near Ambleside, in 1800. The Lloyds had nine children and Thomas De Quincey (1758&#8211;1859; <title level="m">DNB</title>) claimed that &#8216;as a wife and mother&#8217; Sophia was &#8216;unsurpassed&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="76">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="PhillimoreJoseph">Phillimore, Joseph (1775&#8211;1855; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#PhillimoreJoseph"> lawyer. Educated at Westminster School and Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1793, BA 1797,
							BCL 1800, DCL 1804). He won prizes at Christ Church for Latin verse (1793) and prose (1798), and the university English
							essay prize (1798) for his dissertation, &#8216;Chivalry&#8217;. Southey and Phillimore met at Westminster School, and their
							friendship lasted until the end of Southey&#8217;s time at Oxford. When Southey returned to Oxford in 1820 to receive an
							honorary DCL, Phillimore, by then Regius Professor of Civil Law, participated in the degree ceremony. Phillimore was not
							very tall, hence his nickname &#8216;little Joe&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="77">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="ProbyJohnCarysfort">Proby, John Joshua, 1st Earl of Carysfort (1751&#8211;1828; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#ProbyJohnCarysfort"> politician and writer. Educated at Westminster School and Trinity College, Cambridge. In
							the mid 1790s, Carysfort developed an interest in Southey&#8217;s poetry, communicating with him through his cousin and
							Southey&#8217;s patron Charles Wynn. Southey arranged for Carysfort to be sent copies of his books, though any letters he wrote
							to the peer have not survived. Carysfort&#8217;s critiques of &#8216;The Retrospect&#8217; and <title level="m">Madoc</title> are in
							National Library of Wales, NLW MS 4819E. Carysfort&#8217;s own <title level="m">Dramatic and Narrative Poems</title> were
							published in 1810.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="78">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="PugheWilliamOwen">Pughe, William Owen (1759&#8211;1835; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#PugheWilliamOwen"> lexicographer, grammarian, editor, antiquarian and poet. The son of John Owen, he adopted
							the surname Pughe in 1806 after inheriting property from a relative. A leading member of the Society of Gwyneddigion and
							the Society of the Cymmrodorion. His publications included: <title level="m">The Heroic Elegies of Llywarch Hen</title>
							(1792), <title level="m">The Myvyrian Archaiology</title> (1801, 1807) and <title level="m">The Cambrian Biography</title>
							(1803). In 1796&#8211;1797, Southey and Pughe engaged in a (pseudonymous) debate about the Welsh language in the pages of the
								<title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title>. Later in 1797, Southey consulted Pughe about details for his Welsh-American
							poem <title level="m">Madoc</title>.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="79">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="RickmanJohn">Rickman, John (1771&#8211;1840; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#RickmanJohn"> statistician. Only son of Thomas Rickman, vicar of Newburn, Northumberland. Educated at
							Guildford Grammar School (1781&#8211;1785) and Oxford (matric. Magdalen Hall, 1788, and migrated to Lincoln College, BA 1792).
							After graduation he joined his father, who had retired to live in Christchurch, Hampshire. Rickman worked as a private
							tutor and read widely in economics. He edited the <title level="m">Commercial, Agricultural and Manufacturer&#8217;s
								Magazine</title> (until 1801). In 1796 he wrote a private paper in which he argued for the benefits to the nation of a
							census. George Rose, an M.P. for Christchurch, showed this to Charles Abbot and in March 1801 the latter steered the
							census bill into law. Rickman was responsible for the first four censuses (1801, 1811, 1821 and 1831) and paved the way
							for the fifth (1841). In 1801 he became Abbot&#8217;s personal secretary whilst the latter was Chief Secretary for Ireland. On
							Abbot&#8217;s election to the post of Speaker of the House of Commons, Rickman became the Speaker&#8217;s secretary. In 1820 he became
							Clerk Assistant to the Commons with a salary of &#163;2500 per year. He married Susannah Postlethwaite (d. 1836) in 1805. His
							friendship with Southey began at Burton in 1797 and endured for the rest of their lives. Shortly after their first
							meeting, Southey described him as &#8216;rough, coarse, well informed on all subjects, believing nothing, jacobinical&#8217;. Later in
							life Rickman became high tory, anti-Malthusian and anti-semitic. He regularly provided ideas and information (especially
							statistics) for Southey&#8217;s articles in the <title level="m">Quarterly Review</title> and authored the majority of Southey&#8217;s
							April 1818 <title level="m">Quarterly</title> essay on the Poor Laws. Southey and Rickman planned to collaborate on a
							sequel to the <title level="m">Colloquies</title> (1829) but this was prevented by John Murray&#8217;s (1778&#8211;1843; <title level="m">DNB</title>) financial problems.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="80">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Robinsonfamily">Robinson family:</term>
            <gloss target="#Robinsonfamily"> London booksellers and publishers. George Robinson (1736&#8211;1801; <title level="m">DNB</title>)
							and his brothers James Robinson (d. 1803/4; <title level="m">DNB</title>), John Robinson (1753&#8211;1813; <title level="m">DNB</title>), and possibly Henry Robinson (d. in or after 1813; <title level="m">DNB</title>).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="81">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="RosserRobert">Rosser, Robert (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#RosserRobert"> Bristol-based printer.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="82">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="RoughWilliam">Rough, William (1772/3&#8211;1838; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#RoughWilliam"> lawyer and poet. Only son of William Rough. Educated Westminster (adm. 1786, King&#8217;s Scholar
							1789) and Trinity College, Cambridge (matric. 1792, BA 1796, MA 1799). Entered Gray&#8217;s Inn 1796, and called to the Bar at
							the Inner Temple 1801. Married Harriet (1778&#8211;c. 1820), an illegitimate daughter of John Wilkes (1725&#8211;1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>). He served in the judiciary in Demerara and Essequibo and later Ceylon and was knighted in
							1837. His literary works included <title level="m">Lorenzo di Medici</title> (1797), <title level="m">The Conspiracy of
								Gowrie</title> (1800), and <title level="m">Lines on the Death of Sir Ralph Abercromby</title> (1800). He was also a
							contributor to the <title level="m">Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title> and the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title>. He and
							Southey were friends whilst at Westminster School and remained in contact in later life. He was rumoured to have
							contributed to <title level="m">The Flagellant</title> (1792).</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="83">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SawierMrs">Sawier, Mrs (d. before April 1798):</term>
            <gloss target="#SawierMrs"> Mary Sawier was the widow of a Bristol accountant and Southey&#8217;s landlady in College Street,
							Bristol in 1795. Her daughter married James Jennings.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="84">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="Sewardfamily">Seward family:</term>
            <gloss target="#Sewardfamily"> a Worcestershire family consisting of four brothers and three sisters. The death of Southey&#8217;s
							close friend Edmund Seward in 1795 was followed by that of his brother John (educated at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge, MB
							1795, and physician to the Worcester infirmary) in December 1797. Some time afterwards, the eldest brother, William (a
							lawyer, based in Ledbury, Herefordshire) shot himself. A fourth brother, whose name Southey does not record, was a &#8216;mere
							farmer&#8217; of a &#8216;methodistical turn&#8217;. Of the sisters, one married Mr Severn (a clergyman) and two remained unmarried. In the
							mid 1790s, Southey was on good terms with most &#8212; if not all &#8212; of the siblings and corresponded with at least Edmund and
							one of the Seward sisters.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="85">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SewardEdmund">Seward, Edmund (c. 1770/71&#8211;1795):</term>
            <gloss target="#SewardEdmund"> the youngest son of John Seward of Sapey, Worcestershire. Educated at Balliol College, Oxford
							(matric. 1789, BA 1793). Seward was one of Southey&#8217;s closest friends at Oxford, and an important influence on him. An
							early enthusiast for Pantisocracy, Seward later withdrew from the scheme and felt himself partly to blame for what he
							described as &#8216;having contrived to bring [Southey] ... into ... a calamitous &amp; ruinous ... adventure, from which I
							might at first perhaps have diverted him&#8217;. Southey was deeply shocked by Seward&#8217;s death from a &#8216;fever&#8217;, and later
							addressed his elegy &#8216;To the Dead Friend&#8217; to him. In a letter to James Montgomery, 6 May 1811, Southey recalled him as &#8216;an
							admirable man in all things, whose only fault was that he was too humble ... In his company my religious instincts were
							strengthened ... Sick of the college-chapel &amp; of the church, we tried the meeting house, &#8212; &amp; there we were
							disgusted too. Seward left College, meaning to take orders; &#8212; I who had the same destination, became a Deist after he left
							me&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="86">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyEdward">Southey, Edward (1788&#8211;1847):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyEdward"> Southey&#8217;s youngest brother, he spent much of his childhood in the household of Elizabeth
							Tyler. Southey was much preoccupied with arranging Edward&#8217;s education, though plans to send him to St Paul&#8217;s School did
							not work out. It is not certain where he was educated. Southey despaired, noting &#8216;I never saw a lad with a better capacity
							or with habits more compleatly bad&#8217;. Edward was to lead an increasingly rackety, disreputable life, trying his hand at
							being a sailor, soldier and, eventually, a provincial actor.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="87">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyEliza">Southey, Eliza (1776&#8211;1779):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyEliza"> Southey&#8217;s younger sister.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="88">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyHenryHerbert">Southey, Henry Herbert (1783&#8211;1865; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyHenryHerbert">physician. Southey&#8217;s younger brother. With the help of his uncle Herbert Hill, Southey
							provided money for Henry Herbert&#8217;s education at Norwich and Edinburgh. His concerns about his younger brother&#8217;s lack of
							application proved &#8212; eventually &#8212; to be ill-founded, and in later life the two enjoyed a close friendship.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="89">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyJohn">Southey, John (d. 1806):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyJohn"> the eldest brother of Southey&#8217;s father. His work as a lawyer led to him accumulating a
							substantial fortune of &#163;100,000. Although he was unmarried, he refused to help either Robert Southey Senior, thus ensuring
							the latter&#8217;s imprisonment for debt in 1792, or his nephews, to whom he left nothing in his Will. Southey visited his uncle
							in 1802, describing his miserly existence to John May. In 1806, he recorded that his uncle &#8216;had thanked God upon his death
							bed that he had cut me off&#8217;. Southey retaliated by writing a poem attacking the deceased.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="90">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyMargaret">Southey, Margaret (1752&#8211;1802):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyMargaret"> Southey&#8217;s mother. Born Margaret Hill, she married Robert Southey Senior in 1772. The
							marriage produced nine children, of whom five died young. She was dominated by her older half-sister, Elizabeth Tyler,
							with whom Southey spent a great deal of his childhood. After the bankruptcy and death of her husband in 1792, Margaret
							moved to Bath, running a boarding house in Westgate Buildings. Her continued financial difficulties &#8212; possibly exacerbated
							by the extravagance of her half-sister &#8212; caused Southey great anxiety. Margaret died on 5 January 1802 after a long
							illness.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="91">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyMary">Southey, Mary (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyMary"> Southey&#8217;s paternal aunt, also referred to as &#8216;Aunt Maria&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="92">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyRobertSnr">Southey, Robert, Senior (1745&#8211;1792):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyRobertSnr"> Southey&#8217;s father. A failed Bristol linen-draper, he was briefly imprisoned in 1792 &#8216;for a
							bill endorsed for a deceitful friend&#8217;. His release was secured by Elizabeth Tyler. He died in December 1792, after what
							his eldest son described as a &#8216;long&#8217; decline.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="93">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyTom">Southey, Thomas (&#8216;Tom&#8217;) [brother] (1771&#8211;1838):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyTom"> sailor and farmer. Southey&#8217;s younger brother and the one to whom he was in the 1790s closest. Tom
							entered the navy as a midshipman at the age of 12, saw action in several major battles of the French revolutionary wars
							(including Cape St Vincent and Copenhagen), was captured on one occasion, wounded on several others, and was made a
							lieutenant as reward for his bravery in the fight between <hi rend="ital">Mars</hi> and <hi rend="ital">L&#8217;Hercule</hi> on
							21 April 1798. He made Captain in 1811, but never commanded a ship. After he retired from the navy, he tried his hand at
							farming and as a customs officer. His last posting was at Demerara, British Guiana, and he died on shipboard on the return
							voyage to England. He married Sarah Castle in 1810 and produced a large family. Tom&#8217;s lack of financial stability meant
							that some of the burden of supporting him fell on his brothers Robert and Henry Herbert Southey. Tom&#8217;s knowledge of the
							navy and seafaring, and his observations of foreign climes, provided important information for many of Southey&#8217;s writings,
							including his poetry and <title level="m">The Life of Nelson</title> (1813). Tom&#8217;s only publication was <title level="m">A
								Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1828), written with his brother Robert&#8217;s encouragement.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="94">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="SoutheyThomas">Southey, Thomas [uncle] (d. 1811):</term>
            <gloss target="#SoutheyThomas"> younger brother and at one time the business partner of Southey&#8217;s father, Robert Southey
							Senior. He spent his later years in Taunton, Somerset. Although unmarried, childless, and wealthy Thomas Southey was on
							distant terms with his brother Robert&#8217;s sons. Thomas Southey&#8217;s Will held no surprises &#8212; it cut his nephews off without a
							penny, &#8216;his last boast being ... that no one of his own name should ever be a shilling the better for him&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="95">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="StracheyGeorge">Strachey, George (1776&#8211;1849):</term>
            <gloss target="#StracheyGeorge"> officer of the East India Company. Son of John Strachey. Educated at Westminster (adm. 1787)
							and Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1795; MA 1822). Writer EICS (Madras) 1796; Assistant in the Military, Secret and
							Political Department, 1798; Joint Assay Master, 1807; Private Secretary to the Governor, 1808; Judge and Magistrate of the
							Zillah of Cuddapah, 1809; Junior Secretary to Government, 1812; Chief Secretary, 1813; retired 1824. Strachey was
							Southey&#8217;s &#8216;substance&#8217; (an older boy assigned to induct a new pupil into school rules and rituals) at Westminster School.
							During their schooldays, Strachey (perhaps in response to the scandal surrounding <title level="m">The Flagellant</title>)
							was one of many acquaintances who treated Southey &#8216;like a scabby sheep&#8217;, dropping him. They were later only partially
							reconciled, but enough for Southey to commemorate Strachey&#8217;s departure for India in 1798 with a sonnet (&#8216;Fair be thy
							fortunes in the distant land&#8217;) published in the <title level="m">Morning Post</title>. Southey attempted to maintain their
							correspondence, but it had lapsed by April 1805 when he confessed that as Strachey had not replied to his letters, he
							would &#8216;not ... write to him again, nor in any way force myself upon him.&#8217;</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="96">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="TaylorWilliam">Taylor, William (1765&#8211;1836; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#TaylorWilliam"> reviewer and translator. Born in Norwich, the only child of William and Sarah Taylor. Taylor&#8217;s
							interest in German culture culminated in his <title level="m">Historic Survey of German Poetry</title> (1828&#8211;1830). He was
							also a prolific contributor to the <title level="m">Annual Review, The Athenaeum, Monthly Magazine</title>, and <title level="m">Monthly Review</title>. Southey and Taylor met in 1798, whilst the former was on a visit to Great Yarmouth,
							where his brother Henry Herbert Southey was being tutored by George Burnett. Taylor introduced Southey to his great friend
							Frank Sayers (1763&#8211;1817; <title level="m">DNB</title>) &#8212; whose 1792 collection <title level="m">Poems</title> had
							influenced Southey&#8217;s early work &#8212; and also to radical and dissenting circles in Norwich. Taylor gave Southey the idea for
							the <title level="m">Annual Anthology</title> and was an acute, if frequently blunt, critic of his work. From 1803&#8211;1804,
							he edited the Norwich newspaper <title level="m">The Iris</title>, to which Southey contributed poetry. Southey described
							Taylor as &#8216;one of the three great men of my acquaintance ... the more I know him and the longer I know him, the more do I
							admire his knowledge and love his moral character.&#8217;</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="97">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas, William Bowyer (d. 1802):</term>
            <gloss target="#ThomasWilliamBowyer"> a native of Hereford, Thomas was the business agent for Herbert Hill, Southey&#8217;s uncle.
							His job also involved him in the tangled finances of Elizabeth Tyler, Hill&#8217;s half-sister and Southey&#8217;s aunt. Thomas met
							Southey during the latter&#8217;s 1795&#8211;1796 visit to Portugal. Southey stayed with him in Hereford in 1798 and through Thomas
							gained access to the cathedral library. In 1800 Thomas married a cousin, a woman Southey greatly admired. Thomas died
							suddenly in 1802.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="98">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="ThorpMr">Thorp, Mr (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#ThorpMr"> Thorp and his son were friends of Southey&#8217;s during his time at Oxford. Thorp was a resident of the
							town or its environs and seems to have been a man of some social standing. He was possibly the William Thorp named as an
							assistant to the city&#8217;s aldermen in a 1794 directory of Oxford.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="99">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="TylerElizabeth">Tyler, Elizabeth (1739&#8211;1821):</term>
            <gloss target="#TylerElizabeth"> the older, unmarried half-sister of Southey&#8217;s mother. She had spent her early life looking
							after an elderly relative and on his death received an inheritance which she then spent on living the high life. Her
							extravagance was a source of great worry to her relatives, in particular her half-brother Herbert Hill. Elizabeth Tyler
							was painted by Joshua Reynolds and moved in cultural circles in Bath and Bristol, counting amongst her friends the
							Palmers, owners of the Theatre Royal, Bath. Southey was largely brought up in her household, an experience he later
							described in a series of autobiographical letters to John May. Southey quarrelled with his aunt over his relationship with
							Edith Fricker and involvement in Pantisocracy, and on a wet night in 1794 she threw him out. They never saw or spoke to
							one another again. Southey later speculated that Elizabeth Tyler, whose grandmother had died &#8216;in confinement&#8217;, suffered
							from a form of insanity, noting that &#8216;her habitual violence of temper is now increased by long indulgence absolutely to a
							state of derangement&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="100">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="VincentWilliam">Vincent, William (1739&#8211;1815; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#VincentWilliam"> Head Master of Westminster School 1778&#8211;1802 and later Dean of Westminster. A Tory, in 1792 he
							used a public sermon at St Margaret&#8217;s, Westminster, to defend the constitution and the prevailing social order. He
							published works on the geography and commerce of the classical world.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="101">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="WeeksShadrach">Weeks (also spelled &#8216;Weekes&#8217;), Shadrach (dates unknown):</term>
            <gloss target="#WeeksShadrach"> childhood friend of Southey. A servant of Elizabeth Tyler, Southey&#8217;s aunt, and a recruit to
							Pantisocracy.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="102">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="WingfieldJohn">Wingfield, John (c. 1757&#8211;1825):</term>
            <gloss target="#WingfieldJohn"> Under-Master at Westminster School 1788&#8211;1802.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="103">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="WollstonecraftMary">Wollstonecraft, Mary (1759&#8211;1797; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#WollstonecraftMary"> author. Southey was a great admirer of Wollstonecraft and dedicated his &#8216;The Triumph of
							Woman&#8217; (published in his <title level="m">Poems</title> (1797)) to her. They met in London in 1797, where they moved in
							the same radical circles. Southey mourned her death in his 1797 poem &#8216;To A. S. Cottle&#8217;.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="104">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="WordsworthDorothy">Wordsworth, Dorothy (1771&#8211;1855; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#WordsworthDorothy"> writer. She and Southey probably met in 1795 but their relationship only flourished after
							Southey and his family moved to Keswick in 1803.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="105">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth, William (1770&#8211;1850; <title level="m">DNB</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#WordsworthWilliam"> poet. Wordsworth and Southey met in Bristol in 1795. Their relationship became closer
							after the Southeys moved to Keswick in 1803 and particularly after the death of John Wordsworth in 1805.</gloss>
          </item>
          <lb />
          <item n="106">
            <term rend="bold" xml:id="WynnCharlesWW">Wynn, Charles Watkin Williams (1775&#8211;1850; <title level="m">DNB</title>, <title level="m">Hist P</title>):</term>
            <gloss target="#WynnCharlesWW"> politician. The second son of Sir Watkin Williams Wynn, 4th Baronet, and his second wife
							Charlotte Grenville. He was educated at home by a tutor, the Rev. Robert Nares, and later at Westminster (adm. 1784) and
							Christ Church, Oxford (matric. 1791, BA 1795, MA 1798, DCL 1810). Entered Lincoln&#8217;s Inn in 1795 and was called to the Bar
							in 1798. He married Mary Cunliffe, daughter of a baronet, in 1806. Wynn had excellent family and political connections,
							his maternal grandfather was the Prime Minister George Grenville (1712&#8211;1770; <title level="m">DNB</title>). He served as
							an M.P. for Old Sarum (1797&#8211;1799) and for Montgomeryshire (1799&#8211;1850). From 1806&#8211;1807, he served in the Ministry of
							Talents (led by his uncle Lord Grenville) and secured a pension for Southey, which he described as &#8216;the only benefit I
							reap from 12 months of office&#8217;. From 1822&#8211;1828, he held a cabinet post as President of the Board of Control. Wynn met
							Southey at Westminster and the two remained friends for rest of their lives. He contributed to <title level="m">The
								Flagellant</title> (1792) under pseudonyms which included &#8216;St Pardulph&#8217;. Wynn (who was not personally wealthy) gave
							Southey an annuity of &#163;160 from 1797, and Southey dedicated <title level="m">Madoc</title> (1805) to him.</gloss>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>