<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.62</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Memorandum for a letter; BL
                        Add. MS 28268, ff. 66–67</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="62" type="letter"><head>62. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel
                        Lofft</ref>, <date when="1801-10-29">29 October 1801</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Memorandum for a letter; BL
                        Add. MS 28268, ff. 66–67</note></head><lb/><p rend="right">Night, dark night, and a dark subject</p><p rend="center">Memorandum for a letter to <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref></p><p>Just returnd the first proof of the Quartos; found that the subject as stated in
                    the headline was thrown out of the arrangement by the different size of the
                    paper; all else correct. — Was asked by Mr Knight at the Office whither I had
                    seen <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref>? No — because Mr Bentley
                    had been to <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hoods</ref>, who had
                    expressd a wish to see me on the subject of the engravings which cannot be got
                    from Mr Nesbit and on the subject of placing the notes.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield is referring to proofs of his <hi rend="ital">Rural Tales</hi>, which was to include engravings by
                        Charlton Nesbit (1775-1838), a pupil of Thomas Bewick. The illustration used
                        as a headnote for the poem 'Rosy Hannah' is pictured <ref target="../images/image10.html">here</ref>.</note> — Told him I had just written myself to <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref> without communication with the
                    Bookseller. — had my situation pitied. — Nothing new to me — A box of Nuts and
                    Apples from Mrs Newman, Midhurst — perhaps <ref target="people.html#BurnsRobert">Bob Burns</ref> had some such crossgraind vexations as these, and strove to
                    cure them by drinking — Difficult to speak my mind without appearing vain — Sure
                    to be blamed at last — Never to attempt to write to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> again on such matters — Rose
                    by favour, must expect trouble — Destress of mind — Fame is a bubble — Would
                    this instant stop the publication, and all destressing desputes with it, were it
                    possible to be done — What use to burn the MS? — Those who envy the reputation I
                    may have acquired should have a relish of what it is to hear my friend censured
                    and then not allowd to tell him so — Deviations in opinion ascribed to mercenary
                    motives — What shall I say to <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref>
                    — What power have I — No kind friend to take my place a moment between
                    contending parties, to mount the pedestal and kick away the Rubbish from around,
                    that hides and involves my actions in obscurity — I must look base and criminal
                    — How can I engage in a quarrel which I have studiously avoided, Between
                    Bookseller and Editor? — Was ever poor poet fixt as I am! — But fretting will
                    bring sickness, not conviction to others; so says <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">my Wife</ref> — Truth is in a Fogg —
                    How can I send the Quarto proofs to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr
                        Lofft</ref>; denied — The <hi rend="ital">place</hi> and not the <hi rend="ital">matter</hi> of the notes disputed — Is not <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> a lover of peace? ——</p><p><date when="1801-10-29">Oct 29 Noon</date> Sir Thus far I had prepared for a
                    further explanation and as I have not spirits to enlarge on the above subjects I
                    send it thus unfinish’d. Mr Waine called this morning, bringing a letter from
                    you, and another from my Brother. Mr Wayne will bring a line with him but I send
                    this in haste by the post, still endeavouring to throw off the mental load that
                    oppresses me. Your letter of yesterday I must reply to, but realy know not how.
                    To clear myself from the imputation of disrespect and dissatisfaction is more
                    than I have now hopes of doing. And when the prospect of placing my actions in
                    their true light ceases, the wish allmost ceases with it. I would rather sink
                    into oblivion again and nurse my sick soul with calm reflection, than even
                    attempt to persist in my self-defence against those who did not formerly think
                    so of me. One sentence inadiquately expressd through my own ignorance, involves
                    me in accumulating difficulties; your suspicion of <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref> was <hi rend="ital">groundless</hi> only in that you intimated that I had acted by his
                    influence and advice. That he as an individual will object to the situation of
                    the notes I now know, and shall soon hear I doubt; but how I am to act, God only
                    knows. What you have written on the old subject of the preface &amp;c to the
                    Farmer’s Boy includes a paragraph which is most likely true. That, ‘you know
                    what is calld the publick Better than I do.’ But Sir, the following I absolutely
                    disclaim, without endeavouring to offer one word more that might sound like
                    exculpation. ‘My remarks on my removal as a Justice were treated I must say
                    neither with delicacy, nor I think with good judgment. I was justly sick of all
                    this. And it required nothing less than the intrepid zeal of a very sincere
                    friendship to write any thing for a future Edition after so unpleasant reception
                    of what I had written. Reception, <hi rend="ital">not from the publick</hi>, nor
                    from Reviewers in general who appear’d well contented, but from <hi rend="ital">the Author and from some of his acquaintance</hi>’ &amp;c</p><p rend="indent1"> Sir, I enter my protest against this conclusion, as to its truth:
                    its consequences I must bear. My letters would not warrant such a conclusion. My
                    situation is singularly delicate. But I have had great pleasure; great benefit;
                    it is fit I should feel great trouble.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have said positively that as to the notes now in question in
                    this Vollm that as an individual <hi rend="ital">I have no objection to
                        them</hi>. If this declaration is disbelieved, as my former declarations
                    have evidently been, what more can I do or say? I submit to the rod of an angry
                    friend, I will bear <hi rend="ital">his</hi> chastizement rather than <hi rend="ital">my own</hi>. And smother the justification of myself which
                    cannot be urged without widening every breach and mending my broken character by
                    unwise means. Time perhaps will heal all wounds, and clear all foggs. — </p><p rend="indent1"> The overlooking of the Quarto proofs having thus fallen upon
                    myself I shall have to give an answer directly to the printers; and I shall not
                    vote for the exclusion of the notes. How can I if I would? When the consequence
                    would be what every one of my friends would deplore, the loss of my first
                    friend!</p><p rend="indent1"> The matter stands thus — let me act which way I will, censure
                    must ensue. — If I remain neuter, and give no answer should the subject of the
                    notes be broachd by <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref>; that
                    silence will give consent. If I say ‘you shall not omit them,’ how can I follow
                    up the injunction? Should I say, ‘leave them out,’ <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> is no more amongst my
                    correspondents!</p><p rend="indent1"> The harshness you complain of in my last I cannot discover. We
                    all have our feelings and propensities. I am alive to strong feelings, and hope
                    I shall never be otherwise. I may loose my friends perhaps as fast as I gaind
                    them. But whither I am favourd with your thoughts or honourd with your
                    correspondence or not, in future, I shall remain, Sir, your once-respected, and
                    unfortunate</p><closer><signed rend="right">Bloomfield</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>