<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.186</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        216–17</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="186" type="letter"><head>186. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1806-06">[after May 1806]</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        216–17</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><date when="1806-06">Thursday Night</date></dateline><salute>Dear George</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The delay of the parcel has enabled me to send you a letter from
                    sister <ref target="people.html#HingstonElizabeth">Bet</ref> received Thursday
                    in a packet from cousin Isaac to his friends.</p><p rend="indent1"> You say that you and I did not think <hi rend="ital">just</hi>
                    alike as to the preface, very likely not. But we thought alike on the subject of
                        <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L’s</ref> eternal additions, and you
                    knew <hi rend="ital">then</hi> and was witness in some degree to the dislike of
                    the readers to certain parts of the preface. Of this you and I talked much
                    during the short intercourse we had at <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> and at <ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref>. I
                    had <hi rend="ital">assured you</hi>, as one who would hear it though <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L</ref><hi rend="ital"> would not</hi>, that in <hi rend="ital">all companies</hi>
                    wherein the subject had been mentioned, the sentiment was the <hi rend="ital">same</hi>, invariably the <hi rend="ital">same</hi>. I have never <hi rend="ital">seen</hi> nor <hi rend="ital">heard</hi> the man or woman who,
                    speaking of the subject did not applaud his zeal for me, and at the same time
                    either condemn with anger, or ridicule his want of judgment, his arrogance, or
                    his vanity; just which they happen’d to hit upon, as in their opinion the most
                    applicable. I have several letters by me from unknown hands abusing him for
                    going too far, in particular for his notes at the foot of the page in the Rural
                    Tales, his ‘simply pleasing’ was to my knowledge a bye word among the young
                    ladies at a boarding school. What ideas they attached to it to make them giggle
                    may easily be divined. I know two high authorities in the Literary world, one of
                    them cut out the notes with his pen knife, and the other would not suffer the
                    copy to enter his library, but destroy’d it when he could procure one that had
                    them not. The former is a <hi rend="ital">friend</hi> of <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">CL</ref>, and lives at Stamford, and was the
                    man who wrote the Review of my Wild Flowers in the Mirror.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Presumably Octavius Gilchrist, an admirer of
                        Bloomfield’s work, regular contributor to journals and, in later years, a
                        promoter of John Clare’s writing.</note> I have had conversations with at
                    least a dozen Gentlemen in different lines of connection at Edenborough who
                    describe the same sentiments strongly expressed there, and as universally as in
                    England. Archer the Great Bookseller at Dublin told me the very same tale of the
                    Literati of the Sister Country, and Stansbury, late a Bookseller at New York
                    gave (voluntarily) the same evidence exactly respecting the people of America,
                    and in the editions of the Rural Tales printed there the notes were left out. I
                    have seen a Gentleman lately from the North of Germany (now in your town) who
                    mentioned to me with peculiar disgust the same hacknied worn out subject. They
                    all cry ‘why dont you tell the man he is doing too much?’ or something to that
                    effect. Now <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> what does
                    the little man say to me when I would broach this. Why he says, truly, that I
                    have nothing to do with it! here he is egregiously wrong. Does he forget that I
                    have constantly to hear him ridiculed and abus’d and is this nothing? I do not
                    pretend to assert that two years ago you knew just as well as I did how strong
                    the outcry was against him, but this I assert, that you know a great <hi rend="ital">deal indeed</hi> of it, and therefore when your Note* stated to
                    him that the opposers of him and his tyranny were only a few of the ‘hangers on’
                    of that <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Bookseller</ref> with whom you <hi rend="ital">knew</hi> he had an inveterate
                    quarrel you did, (I hope) more mischief than you intended. that man would listen
                    to Tom Cat if he could flatter him, so dont pretend that you are too obscure and
                    too humble to be able to do mischief. (whether intended or not.) Were I to take
                    it as a risible subject, there is abundance of room for can anyone conceive a
                    poor fellow more universally loaded with hangers on! There is something in that
                    same letter of yours respecting <ref target="people.html#WindhamWilliam">Windham</ref>, which from <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nats</ref> and my own sentiments differ so horribly that I think I shall
                    one day send it you with a few notes, that you may see if I have understood it
                    right or wrong’d you when I deem’d you a turntail and a shufler, and that at <hi rend="ital">a pinch</hi>, you would swallow professions by pailfulls and
                    glory in the unhappiness you had wrought. Whatever blame you might have heap’d
                    upon <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Hood</ref> at that time (or this)
                    would be sure to be wellcome at <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref>.
                    You will perceive by the tone of this letter that it will be well to send it me
                    again. I am only speaking in it to <hi rend="ital">you</hi>, and send the
                    enclosed** too, at any time convenient.</p><closer><signed rend="right">R. B.</signed></closer><postscript><p>* I have sought in vain for the letter I meant to send, it is in my
                        wilderness void. I have no more time</p><p>**letter to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">CL</ref> about May 1805</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>