<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.399</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 30809, ff.
                        66–67</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="399" type="letter"><head>399. <ref target="people.html#ClareJohn">John Clare</ref> to <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Joseph Weston</ref>, <date when="1825-03-07">7 March 1825</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 30809, ff.
                        66–67</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>Helpstone</placeName></address><date when="1825-03-07">March 7. 1825</date></dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> In answer to yours of the third I am sorry to say that I posses
                    but little of the corespondence of my departed ‘brother bard’ what I do posses
                    you are welcome too &amp; as to my letters to him you may do with them just
                    as you please &amp; make what use of them you like</p><p rend="indent1"> I deeply regret that ill health prevented our corespondence
                    &amp; that death prevented us from being better acquainted I sincerely loved
                    the man &amp; admired his Genius &amp; had a strong anxiety to make a
                    journey to spend a day with him on my second visit to London &amp; I
                    intended to have stopt at Biggleswade on my return home for that purpose but my
                    purse got too near the bottom for a stoppage on the road &amp; as it was too
                    great a distance to walk home this with other matters prevented me from seeing
                    him as one of my family was very ill at the same time &amp; hastened my
                    return—Whatever cause his friends may have to regret the death of the Poet—Fame
                    is not one [of] them for he dyed ripe for immortality &amp; had he written
                    nothing else but ‘Richard &amp; Kate’<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Richard and Kate: or, Fair-Day. A Suffolk Ballad’, published in
                            <title>Rural Tales</title>, pp. 1–14.</note> that fine picture of Rural
                    Life were sufficient to establish his name as the English Theocritus &amp;
                    the first of rural Bards in this country &amp; as Fashion (that feeble
                    substitute for Fame) had nothing to do in his exaltation its neglect will have
                    nothing to affect his memory it is built on a more solid foundation &amp;
                    time will bring its own reward to the ‘Farmers Boy’—I beg you will have the
                    kindness to take <hi rend="ital">care of the M.S. &amp; return it</hi> when
                    you have done with it as I wish to preserve a scrap of his handwriting—the Copy
                    on the other side is a note which accompanied his present of ‘Mayday with the
                    Muses’ I gave the origional to Allan Cunningham the Poet<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Clare wrote to this effect on 9 September 1824 to his friend
                        Cunningham, the labouring-class rural poet. See <title>The Letters of John
                            Clare</title>, ed. Mark Storey (Oxford, 1985), pp. 321–24. For
                        Bloomfield’s note to Clare, see Letter 359 of the present edition.</note>
                    who has a high respect for Bloomfields genius &amp; whose request on that
                    account to posses a scrap of his writing) I was proud &amp; happy to
                    gratifye—soon after the Poets death I wrote in a mellancholy feeling 3 Sonnets
                    to his memory.</p><p rend="indent1"> I was not aware that his ‘Remains’ woud have had such insertions
                    or I shoud have sent them to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">his
                        daughter</ref>—I shall fill this sheet with them for your perusal tho I
                    expect they will come out in the Volume now in the press that will be published
                    this Spring: with my best wishes that your kindly labours for the memory of the
                    departed Poet may meet with the success it deserves</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I remain yours very faithfully </salute><signed rend="right"><ref target="people.html#ClareJohn">John Clare</ref></signed></closer><postscript><p>Three Sonnets on Bloomfield</p><p rend="indent4"> 1.</p><lg type="stanza"><l>Some feed on living fame with conscious pride </l><l>&amp; in that gay ship popularity</l><l>They stem with painted oars the hollow tide </l><l>Proud of the noise which flatterys aids supply </l><l>Joind with to days sun gilded butterflye</l><l>The breed of fashion haughtily they ride </l><l>As tho her breath was immortality</l><l>Which are but bladder puffs of common air </l><l>Or water bubbles that are blown to dye </l><l>Let not their fancys think tis muses fare </l><l>While feeding on the publics gross supplye </l><l>Times wave rolls on—mortality must share </l><l>A mortals fate—&amp; many a fame shall lye</l><l>A dead wreck on the shore of dark posterity</l></lg><lb/><p rend="indent4"> 2.</p><lg type="stanza"><l>Sweet unasuming Minstrel not to thee</l><l>The dazzling fashions of the day belong</l><l>Natures mild pictures field &amp; cloud &amp; tree </l><l>&amp; quiet brooks far distant from the throng </l><l>In murmurs tender as the toiling bee</l><l>Make the sweet music of thy gentle song</l><l>Well, nature owns thee let the crowd pass bye</l><l>The tide of fashion is a stream too strong </l><l>For pastoral brooks that gently flow &amp; sing </l><l>But nature is their source &amp; earth &amp; sky </l><l>Their annual offerings to her current bring</l><l>Thy injurd muse &amp; memory need no sigh</l><l>For thine shall murmur on to many a spring </l><l>When their proud streams is summer burnt &amp; dry</l></lg><lb/><p rend="indent4"> 3.</p><lg type="stanza"><l>The shepherd musing oer his meadow dreams</l><l>The mayday wild flowers in the summer grass</l><l>The sunshine sparkling in the valley streams</l><l>The singing ploughman &amp; hay making lass</l><l>These live the summer of thy rural themes</l><l>Thy green memorials these &amp; they surpass</l><l>The cobweb praise of fashion—every May</l><l>Shall find a native ‘Giles’ beside his plough</l><l>Joining the skylarks song at early day</l><l>&amp; summer rustling in the ripened corn</l><l>Shall find thy rustic loves as sweet as now</l><l>Offering to Mary’s lips ‘the brimming horn’</l><l>&amp; seasons round thy humble grave shall be</l><l>Fond lingering pilgrims to remember thee<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Mark Storey, the editor of <title>The Letters of John
                                    Clare</title> (Oxford, 1985), notes (p. 322) that Weston, with a
                                view to publishing the sonnets, asked Clare, in a letter of 20
                                April, to make some alterations. Clare noted in his journal for 30
                                April ‘I shall not agree with either way Editors are troubled with
                                nice amendings &amp; if Doctors were as fond of Amputation as
                                they are of altering &amp; correcting the world woud have
                                nothing but cripples’. Storey notes further that the sonnets
                                appeared in <title>The Scientific Receptacle</title>, 1 (1825),
                                306–7, with variants. The second was included in Clare’s collection
                                    <title>The Rural Muse</title> (London, 1835). All three are in
                                his <title>Midsummer Cushion</title> manuscript
                            collection.</note></l></lg></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Jos Weston</ref> Esqr</name> / <placeName>12 Providence Row / Finsbury Square / London</placeName> / <date>March 8t</date></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>