<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.225</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        249–50</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="225" type="letter"><head>225. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd
                        Baker</ref>, <date when="1808-01-22">22 January 1808</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        249–50</note></head><opener><dateline><address rend="right"><placeName>City Road, London</placeName></address></dateline><dateline rend="right"><date when="1808-01-22">Jan 22. 1808</date></dateline><salute>Dear Madam</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Thanks for your excellent letter.</p><p rend="indent1"> I think that amongst all the pleasures we derive from Biography
                    that there is manifestly a great injustice done to the correspondents of those
                    who happen to have their letters collected and published. The poor poets
                    epistles are exhibited, but the epistles he <hi rend="ital">receives</hi> are
                    kept out of sight, though such epistles perhaps were the chief agents in
                    eliciting the very thoughts and diction of his own. I am led into these
                    reflections from recently perusing <ref target="people.html#SoutheyRobert">Southey’s</ref> ‘Remains of <ref target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">H.
                        K.White</ref>’.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Remains of
                            H. K. W. With an Account of his Life by R. Southey</title>, 3 vols.
                        (London, 1808–22), including some of the private correspondence of another
                        labouring-class poet closely associated with <title>The Monthly
                            Mirror</title>.</note> If you have not seen this masterly memoir and
                    contemplated the character of the person it celebrates you have a treat to come
                    which I should be sorry you should miss.</p><p rend="indent1"> I lent <ref target="people.html#GrantAnne">Mrs Grant’s</ref>
                    poems to <ref target="people.html#AnsteadMiss">Miss Ansted</ref> who returned it
                    with the note and memorandum which you will find in the volum. I esteem the
                    notes to the poems, and the fine picture of Highland manners exhibited through
                    the work.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Grant’s <title>The
                            Highlanders: and Other Poems</title>. See Letter 224.</note> Though, as
                    her letters are so good, I am not certain that her poetry will set her in a new
                    light to you, who have relished the prose first.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your account of <ref target="people.html#CooperCharlotte">Miss
                        Cooper</ref> is indeed a subject on which I have allmost got ‘the horrors’.
                    You will see that I have ventured to write to her: having promised a tune which
                    I cannot get. Hers is a dangerous age, and liable to the seeds of decline. I
                    hope for all their sakes she will escape this bout, and take care of herself.
                    N.B. I have mentioned in my letter to her, nothing of you (<hi rend="ital">cause</hi> of her illness). I have sent her a song &amp;c.—</p><p rend="indent1"> And now for the accompanying packet &amp;c—I have already
                    said that your book has given me much pleasure and amusement and I return it, I
                    hope, undamaged. With respect to what I have done from it, I wish to remind you
                    again that I never did but <hi rend="ital">one</hi> copy in Indian Ink before I
                    had your Book, and therfore had some trouble, and found perseverance a highly
                    necessiry quality.* I have done them all by candlelight. You will find two or
                    three in your book which for different reasons I did not attempt, that of the
                    upstream end of Chepstow Castle I thought I never could do so as to satisfy
                    myself. The view in the Wye meadows is my worst—but it being but the second on
                    the list, and the view of Mitchel Dean the last, I keep up my courage boldly.
                    Have mercy on <hi rend="ital">my own</hi> scratches from fancy, and be as
                    favourable as you can towards the two that I have done from <hi rend="ital">my</hi> drawings on the spot. They are both erroneous in point of
                    perspective, and I have in many instances made the distances too dark.</p><p rend="indent1"> The prose journal might be materially amended as to a <hi rend="ital">whole</hi>, but I set no store by it but as a string of
                    memorandums. Some parts are obscure and some too much in <hi rend="ital">immediate</hi> relation to yourself and friends, to be read <hi rend="ital">generally</hi>. These I think are necessary provisos between you and I,
                    that you may not think that I have aimed at perfection. If you judge that my
                    book could give a moments pleasure to the Lasses of <ref target="places.html#FerneyHill">Ferney Hill</ref> let them see it, for the
                    more criticism I have on my attempts, the better I can feel my own ground. </p><p rend="indent1"> The frost is intensely severe and we are hovering over the fire
                    at the close of day. All well. I could, methinks, moralise over the situation of
                    those who have a scarcity of food and fuel!—You mention the pitiable situation
                    of such as spend sleepless hours in bed. This seldom falls to my lot, but my
                    sleep is, as I have often told you, full of the most hideous workings of fancy
                    whenever I am disturbed by vexation, or unwell. I am now happily free from
                    both.</p><p rend="indent1"> I rather think that when this letter is gone I shall recollect
                    somthing or other which I meant to have said, but as it will not come to hand
                        <hi rend="ital">now</hi>, I only add my respects to all your house, and
                    particularly to the younger objects of your affection. What would you think of
                    having a ride in Powels Cart<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Powell’s
                        cart: a reference to the ascent of the Sugar Loaf mountain, near
                        Abergavenny, in the cart of their local guide.</note> such a day as this?
                    May you be allways happy up hill and down dale, is the wish of your</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Much honour’d and oblidged</salute><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>*recollect that I did not attempt my own until I had practised by copying
                        more than twenty of yours.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>