<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.339</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Northumberland Record Office,
                        ZAN M12, Brook Autographs, II, 62</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="339" type="letter"><head>339. Robert Bloomfield and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref> to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldJames">James
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1819-07-27">27 July 1819</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Northumberland Record Office,
                        ZAN M12, Brook Autographs, II, 62</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>Shefford,</placeName></address><date when="1819-07-27">July 27 1819</date></dateline><salute>Dear James<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In a later hand,
                            probably James Bloomfield’s: ‘my father had been dead eight years the
                            day this was written.’</note></salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The new spectacles enable me to write this and will do as well as
                    glasses can do with my eyes, which, I am now convinced have some ailment beyond
                    the power of the Opticians. If it grows much worse farewell to writing and
                    reading. You must then look me out a good tempered Dog and a string,* and I will
                    sing <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">your fathers</ref>
                        Anthems<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Bloomfield's anthems
                        had been published as <title>Six Anthems for the Use of Choirs Where There
                            Is No Organ</title> (London, 1807).</note> and my own songs round
                    Grosvenor Square, and live like a prince. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> thanks you for his
                    watch ribond, and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah</ref> sends
                    her love and says you shall have your Books by the first parcel we send without
                    putting you to further expense, We are all well, and two or three more lazy then
                    myself are tumbling on the new made Rug on our grass-plot. I sincerely thank you
                    for the trouble you have taken, and am quite relieved.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your Old Nunck, R. Bloomfield</p><p>Turn over</p><p>*And I’ll hold the hat and will come amongst the ‘<hi rend="ital">Hyeana’s</hi>’
                    in Eastern lane and will gather a fortune in no time—</p><p>For fear this should not be full enough I’ll grumble again, to induce you to pity
                    the sorrows of the aged, I have really got a touch of the old Fiend Rheumatism,
                    he has laid hold of my shoulder and the back of my neck, and I am now prouder
                    and more stiffneckd than ever [illegible phrase]</p><p rend="right"><date when="1819-07-27">Tuesday evening, July 27 1819</date></p><p>Dear <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldJames">James</ref>,</p><p rend="indent1"> I don’t know whether second thoughts are best always, but it
                    occurs to me that you will not object to the expense of a parcel now, containing
                    the ‘Lecture on Heads’<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Lecture
                            on Heads</title>, a satirical piece mocking fashion and physionomy by
                        George Alexander Stevens (1764).</note> and two letters, (though in one,),
                    any more than you would to wait, you would not <hi n="ital">know</hi> how long,
                    nor I neither, for the chance of sending you it free,—besides I am anxious to
                    prove that I am not <hi rend="ital">quite</hi> so lazy but I can hold a pen,
                    notwithstanding what my Father has told you, and I have a mortal objection to
                    seeing anything in the shape of a letter with so much blank space as there would
                    have been in this, but for the <hi rend="ital">sense</hi> which <hi rend="ital">I</hi> am now putting into it, and another reason, my Father has not said
                        <hi rend="ital">all</hi> he intended, he wishes you, when next you write, to
                    say what you gave for the spectacles that he may give you the money for them
                    (when he gets it) or pay you when he comes to Town. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> would <hi rend="ital">write</hi> to you his thoughts, but he has two lame fingers
                    ocasioned by—not making Craft Bows—but by spining tops.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am glad that <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">your father</ref> prefer’d the story I sent you last to the ‘sonnet’ which
                    I still think above ‘middling’ but the <hi rend="ital">sense</hi> is exquisite
                    and I agree with you in thinking it one of his best. I herewith return you <ref target="people.html#MooreThomas">Moores</ref> Book<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The first and second volumes of Thomas Moore’s <title>Irish
                            Melodies</title> appeared in 1808. Hannah copied out one of Moore’s song
                        in Letter 331.</note> with thanks for the pleasure it has given me, I have
                    marked with pencil those pieces which I have copy’d as my favourites, and those
                    mark’d double are <hi rend="ital">particular</hi> favorites, so you may condemn
                    or applaud my taste, as in your judgement seemeth meet—if you have the other
                    volume (for this I see is the second) will you let it me? Make haste and win
                    your 1/16th of 30000.—You say I have said nothing about coming to town—very
                    true, but I am far even thinking about it,—for time, even at <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>, never hung so heavily as now.
                    I verily think it stands right still sometimes,—and yet, so inconsistent am I,
                    that I shall regret to leave the <hi rend="ital">place</hi>, although for want
                    of that sort of society that I could enjoy, I can never considder it as a <hi rend="ital">home</hi>—but I tormented you with this stuff when you was
                    here—My father will be in town he thinks in about a month, but he must stay till
                    he has done his poems, which now with the assistance of the new spectacles he
                    hopes to be able to complete soon; at all events he <hi rend="ital">must</hi> be
                    in town before Michaelmass to find some hole to put our heads in, but now I
                    must, I fear, stay here till such hole is found. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Chas’</ref> is dull from want of
                    employment and for want of the <hi rend="ital">hope</hi> of future
                    employment,—when you write again, if Sarah is returned, let me know if <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamCousin">Mr Austin</ref><hi rend="ital">has</hi> worried Jenny out of her nest for we have yet had no
                        reply;—<ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacNephew">Isaac</ref> has had a
                        <hi rend="ital">short</hi> excursion has’nt he?—I am very glad to find by
                    your letter to father that your situation is less irksome than formerly, the
                    worst part of your information is the fluctuating state of your health, I wish I
                    could send you a little Bedfordshire air, and two or three wheatfields for your
                    private enjoyment, for such a treat is too good for the groveling—body’s (I was
                    going to say <hi rend="ital">souls</hi>) that surround you. Our scenery will
                    soon be embellish’d by Irish reapers for ‘sure’ a great number of them have been
                    here for this fortnight.</p><p>Fortnight past in readiness begun—My father has this minute put a conclusion to
                    his Oakly Hall,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e.
                            <title>Hazelwood-Hall: a Village Drama</title>.</note> he has now to go
                    back and polish a bit,—this lovely weather inspired him, in spite of his fears
                    for his eyesight, which I am sorry to say are by no means groundless, for it has
                    become rapidly worse during these last few months:—<ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobertHenry">Robert</ref> are gone
                    fishing,—You will have this medley of nonsense, and grumbles, a few houres after
                    the arrival of <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteShot">my sister</ref>
                    here. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> and I have
                        <hi rend="ital">such</hi> duets on our flageolets sometimes, I mean <hi rend="ital">had</hi>, before he was fumble-finger’d, it would make your hair
                    stand on end to hear us. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> does not like the tune of ‘The Manly heart’<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Manly Heart’, a ‘favourite duet’ adapted
                        from Mozart by T. Latour and published by Bland and Wellers, c. 1800.</note>
                    nor ‘To use this well’. either he or I want taste,—good night—your affectionate
                    Cousin <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah Bloomfield</ref> —</p><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldJames">Mr Jam[e]s Bloomfield</ref></name> / <placeName>Sowerby Co’s / Forster Lane / London</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>