<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.70</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 74–77.
                        Extract in Suffolk Record Office, Bury St. Edmunds, 317/3, ff. 43–44;
                        published in Hart, p. 18</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="70" type="letter"><head>70. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1801-11-30">30 November 1801</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 74–77.
                        Extract in Suffolk Record Office, Bury St. Edmunds, 317/3, ff. 43–44;
                        published in Hart, p. 18</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London.</placeName></address><date when="1801-11-30">Novm 30. 1801.</date></dateline><salute>Dear George </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> With ink from the India-House and good pen, I set about informing
                    you of some of the many particulars that have ocupied my whole attention lately.
                    I have written largely to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft</ref>
                    since our last communication, and hope that all will go on smooth yet: he still
                    insists on my leaving out all mention of him in the preface of the large copies;
                    and I (though I dare not tell him so) as certainly mean to disobey the order.
                        <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft</ref> accuses me of want of
                    firmness. I have had to exert my firmness in a matter and in a manner which with
                    him cannot procure me credit because he is not likely to know it. In this sixth
                    edition of the Farmer’s Boy a plan was laid by Mr ___, principaly, and by <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref>, to strike out some matters
                    from the Appendix. this task was undertaken, with a considerable degree of
                    vanity, by Mr ___, who himself, in a copy of Giles markd out a great deal of
                    matter which certainly have been much disapproved; I mean the political notes of
                        <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>, and what he introduced
                    relative to his dismissal from office; but he did not strike out the high
                    compliment paid by <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L</ref> to himself,
                    though he did the whole of what was written by <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Swan</ref> as to my manner of composition.
                    All this was bold assumption on the part of Mr ___ and I disliked it. At that
                    moment I stood so with <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref>, that
                    had I permitted it to go on, the blame would have fallen on <hi rend="ital">me</hi>, and not on <hi rend="ital">them</hi>. <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. Lofft</ref> would have said (perhaps
                    publickly) that I had not only offended in relation to the new Vollm but had
                    most ungratefully set him aside in the original publication. In this situation I
                    had to <hi rend="ital">act,</hi> not merely to <hi rend="ital">wish</hi> my
                    part. the consequence was weighty; and I had never tried my power before. I
                    wrote on Friday to <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref>, stating
                    that any omission <hi rend="ital">now</hi>, as my correspondence stood with <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L</ref>, would involve me in censures,
                    which however innocent I might be, would stick to my publick character and damn
                    my reputation; adding that the ensuing Edition by <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Swan</ref> should be a copy of the last
                    Edition, &amp;c. I mentiond nothing about money, but you see his answer
                    (inclosed) mentions it; and is in all points highly satisfactory. The 5th and
                    6th edition of Giles comprize together 10,000 copies, the new work 7,000, so
                    that I have at any rate to share the profits of 17,000 books, for which (at full
                    price) the publick, if they are goodnaturd enough to buy them, will pay no less
                    than £36,025! I have felt sad, and uncommon trouble of mind; and I doubt it is
                    not over yet. I am writing a fair copy of the Farmer’s Boy exactly as you saw it
                    in MS., and marking the alterations made by <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>; and adding notes of information, &amp;c., this I do
                    that as I have not the original, something in <hi rend="ital">my own hand</hi>
                    may be found hereafter, and I do it too to improve my handwriting: I shall have
                    it bound carefully.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">This manuscript is
                        now in the Houghton Library, Harvard University.</note> I have by me the
                    real original MSS. of the new Vollm, and shall bind them too. The printers say
                    now that it will not be out before Christmas; but I think that it will. I send
                        <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my Mother</ref> a piece of cheese
                    such as she could not get at Honington if she had money. No dying lover in a
                    romance ever longd for the bridal-day more sincerely or fervently than I do for
                    the birth of my Vollm. you can hardly conceive how great a relief it will be to
                    my mind when I can throw it down to them and say; ‘there it is’ I shall hope to
                    send books in next month’s parcel. I have a rhumatick attack in the shoulder
                    which requires patience. I have felt something of my stomach complaint, but of
                    short duration; if they would let one alone I might live as long as any of them;
                    but they place me awkwardly in their quarrells: Genious is not wanted to work my
                    extrication, but jockyship, constituional vigor, and impudence. And in these
                    matters I feel myself a bad match for ——— Send me <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Hoods</ref> letter again, at ——— A pocket
                    book for next year entitled the ‘Pocket Atlas’ contains twenty-four beautiful
                    engravings from Giles, designed by Stothard<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Royal Engagement Pocket Atlas</title> was a yearly
                        diary and almanac featuring, for each month, engravings after Stothard’s
                        drawings of scenes from a literary work. That for 1802 featured designs from
                            <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title>; that for 1805 was illustrated by scenes
                        from Goldsmith’s <title>The Vicar of Wakefield</title>.</note> ——— The
                    letter to Mrs Chinery contains about 8 Guineas you will mind who cary it.</p><p rend="indent1"> I send you my story of <ref target="../HTML/imagination.html">‘Imagination’</ref><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Another of
                        Bloomfield’s references to this aborted poem.</note> I have copied it, and
                    copied what <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L</ref> would have added and
                    withdrawn. I think you will not wonder at my rejecting it. I wish you may find
                    patience to look it through, and return it. — </p><p rend="indent1"> I think the last money you had of me was out of a Bill for £27 —
                    odd — of which you returnd about £17, to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">my Wife</ref> while I was at <ref target="places.html#Towcester">Towcester</ref>. but how much tis all
                    together I do not pretend to know. perhaps £30 or more. If I had ever had it in
                    my power to advance that sum in a lump it might have done you good. What must
                    the Quaker be paid just at Christmas?? Tell him to Dunn some of your Customers,
                    and mind, if, as Christmas is so near and my mony melts here with a Wife and 4
                    of them, if you find that your own £90 cannot be brought forward to meet this 20
                    of the Quakers, don’t do nothing rashly in it, I by no means despair of helping
                    you again. My partner is so interested in your success since poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> faild; that her
                    consent will not be wanting. I loose much time in going to the printers dayly. I
                    can do but little work if my mind was happy enugh to try. My present amusement
                    is writing a Child’s Book ‘the History of Little Davy’s new hat,’ dedicated to
                        <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my Mother</ref>, but have sent
                        <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> the remaining
                    profit on Rosy Hannah, I hope it will come seasonably.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The History of Little Davy’s New Hat</title> was not
                        published until 1815; the profits on ‘Rosy Hannah’ were for sales of the
                        musical setting of the poem devised by Isaac and published as <title>Rosy
                            Hannah; a Song Written by R. Bloomfield</title> (London, 1801).</note> I
                    had better defer my ‘triumphant letter’ till the Reviewers have done with me;
                    but I have now no material fears. ———</p><p rend="indent1"> My determination to becoming somthing or other to procure a
                    permanent income, somtimes wavers; my prospect is so good that I doubt the
                    propriety of <hi rend="ital">asking any thing at all.</hi> I have no objection
                    to shoemaking, but though I now use it allmost as a cloak for I can do nothing
                    at it; I firmly believe that 2 or three years hence I shall have somwhere or
                    other several hundred pounds even if I live upon the Books entirely; and perhaps
                    if the edge of public curiosity should wear off, I may have more uninterrupted
                    leisure; though by my daily increasing popularity I ought not to reason so. I
                    try to select my acquaintance, and there is need of it. You can hardly judge how
                    great a difference there is to be found even amongst professd admirers of me and
                    my Tales. <hi rend="ital">Pedants</hi> who dive and peep as a crow would after a
                    Grubb. <hi rend="ital">Labouring poets</hi>, who insist that nothing good was
                    ever produced without labouring at it, writing and rewriting, and writing over
                    and over again. <hi rend="ital">Grammaerians</hi> who judge more of points and
                    constructions that of sence and spirit and animation; with a dozen other queer
                    fellows and characters, who would plague me confoundedly if I was once to <hi rend="ital">begin to mind them</hi>. These I keep in the back ground, and
                    oppose nothing to argument, but fact. When they talk of <hi rend="ital">labour</hi>, I produce them Old Kate and her children<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Richard and Kate: or, Fair-Day. A Suffolk
                        Ballad’, published in <title>Rural Tales</title>, p. 1–14.</note> if they
                    were to set about labouring them into elegance I doubt they would rub off their
                    polish, the same polish that you see when you break a flint; its Natural
                    colour.</p><p rend="indent2"> I must leave abruptly. </p><p rend="indent3"> Good night</p><closer><salute rend="indent4"> Yours</salute><signed rend="right">Robert</signed><dateline rend="right"><date when="1801-11">Nov 1801</date></dateline></closer><postscript><p>Monday Night</p><p>Yours, enclosing one for Mrs Phillips came this morning. — It is curious that
                        I only told <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> that I would
                        apply to <ref target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Mr Rogers</ref> for a
                        labourer’s place in the India warehouses, and he directly understood that
                            <ref target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Mr Rogers</ref> had <hi rend="ital">proposed</hi> it, and said as much to the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke</ref>. <ref target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Mr Rogers</ref> dont know one word
                        about the matter. thus it is I stand at present, and have many doubts as to
                        the wisdom of seeking it. I must determine for myself and a previous
                        determination may be affected by fresh circumstances, such as the unbounded
                        success of the new vollm. — </p><p>Read <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my Mothers</ref> and seal and
                        Despatch as usual, I doubt I have set you a task in <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft’s</ref> Budget, Read it if you
                        can — </p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>