<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.236</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 265–66</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="236" type="letter"><head>236. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd
                        Baker</ref>, <date when="1809-03-25">25 March 1809</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 265–66</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>City Road.</placeName></address><date when="1809-03-25">Friday Night</date><time> half past ten</time></dateline><salute>My Dear Madam</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> You will wonder, I know you will, at my silence and perhaps
                    ascribe it to ill-health, but I thank God I have no such current coin to offer
                    as an apology. I am indeed much better, and have even begun to sing, I don’t
                    mean sing in rhyming composition, but, as the children say ‘right earnest
                    singing’. My back behaves pretty decently within the last fortnight, and don’t
                    you see the buds coming? I congratulate you with a <hi rend="ital">true
                        heart</hi> on your arrival with the Bairne, and you will jog the elbow of
                        <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr B.</ref> with my respects
                    even though he should be pondering on Saxon architecture. By the bye, Storer and
                        <ref target="people.html#GriegJohn">Greig</ref>, the engravers, have given
                    me four little volms, the ‘Topographical Cabinet’ which show in very highly
                    finished miniature some of the best remains in the island.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Antiquarian and Topographical Cabinet,
                            Containing a Series of Elegant Views [engraved by J. S. Storer and John
                            Greig] of the Most Interesting Objects of Curiosity in Great Britain.
                            Accompanied with Letter-Press Descriptions</title>, 10 vols. (London,
                        1807–11).</note> My daughter has written out Robin Grey which I formerly
                    mentiond and here it is if you turn the paper. I think <hi rend="ital">now</hi>
                    that I shall be able to see you on Thursday next, perhaps not, I have several
                    things to accomplish first, and the more I write here the less I shall have to
                    talk, so good night, Catherine and Mary Ann are now fast asleep, and ditto,
                    three of mine. I am not bent upon Thursday, and therefore open to remonstrance
                    from you.</p><closer><signed rend="right">R Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent4"> Continuation of Auld Robin Grey</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> The spring it was past, it was summer, nae mair,</l><l rend="indent3"> And thinly were scatter’d the leaves in the air:</l><l rend="indent3"> Oh winter, says Jenny, we kindly agree,</l><l rend="indent3"> For the sun he looks wae, when he shines upon me.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Nae langer she grat, for her tears were a spent,</l><l rend="indent3"> Despair it was come, and she thought it content:</l><l rend="indent3"> She thought it content, but her cheek it look’d pale,</l><l rend="indent3"> And she droop’d like the snowdrops broke down by the
                            hail.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Her mither was vex’d and her father was wae;</l><l rend="indent3"> What ails you my bairn? They would oftentimes say;</l><l rend="indent3"> Your wheel ye turn round and ye cause little speed,</l><l rend="indent3"> Your hand it grows feeble, and weak is your thread.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> She smiled when she heard them, to banish their fear;</l><l rend="indent3"> But sad looks the smile, that is seen through a tear</l><l rend="indent3"> And bitter the tear that is forc’d by a love,</l><l rend="indent3"> Which virtue and honour can never approve.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Her father was vex’d and her mither was wae,</l><l rend="indent3"> But dowie, and silent sat auld Robin Grey;</l><l rend="indent3"> He spake not a word, and his cheek it grew lean,</l><l rend="indent3"> Like the side of a brae where the torrent had been.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Nae questions he ask’d her concerning her health,</l><l rend="indent3"> He look’d at her often, but aye ’twas by stealth;</l><l rend="indent3"> Then his heart it grew grit, and after he figur’d</l><l rend="indent3"> To gang to the door, to see if it rain’d</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Syne he took to his bed, no physick he sought:</l><l rend="indent3"> He ordered his neighbours around to be brought,</l><l rend="indent3"> While Jenny supported his head in its place,</l><l rend="indent3"> Her tears trickled down, and fell on his face.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Oh! Kill me not, Jenny, said auld Robin grey,</l><l rend="indent3"> I have not deserved this—I have something to say:</l><l rend="indent3"> I knew not, dear Jenny, I knew not your vow;</l><l rend="indent3"> In mercy forgive me,—’twas I stole the cow.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> I valued not Crummy, I thought best of thee,</l><l rend="indent3"> I thought it was her stood between you and me</l><l rend="indent3"> While she fed your parents, oh! Did nae ye say,</l><l rend="indent3"> Ye never would marry that auld Robin Grey</l></lg><p>Taken from the Censura Literaria for December 1808,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Egerton Brydges, <title>Censura Literaria: Containing
                                Titles, Abstracts, and Opinions of Old English Books, with Original
                                Disquisitions, Articles of Biography, and other Literary
                                Antiquities</title>, 10 vols (London, 1805–9). ‘The Continuation of
                            Auld Robin Grey’ text:<lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> The spring had pass’d over, ’twas summer nae mair, </l><l rend="indent3"> And trembling were scatter’d the leaves in the air: </l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Oh winter!’ said Jenny, ‘we kindly agree, </l><l rend="indent3"> For wae looks the sun when he shines upon me.’</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Nae langer she wept, her tears were a’ spent—</l><l rend="indent3"> Despair it had come, and she thought it content; </l><l rend="indent3"> She thought it content, but her cheek was grown pale, </l><l rend="indent3"> And she droop’d like a lily bent down by the hail.
                            </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Her father was sad, and her mother was wae, </l><l rend="indent3"> But silent and thoughtfu’ was Auld Robin Gray; </l><l rend="indent3"> He wander’d his lane, and his face look’d as lean </l><l rend="indent3"> As the side of a brae where the torrents have been.
                            </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> He gaed to his bed, but nae physic wou’d take, </l><l rend="indent3"> And often he said, ‘It is best, for her sake.’ </l><l rend="indent3"> While Jenny supported his head as he lay, </l><l rend="indent3"> Her tears trickled down upon Auld Robin Gray. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> O, greet nae mair, Jenny,’ said he, wi’ a groan; </l><l rend="indent3"> ‘I’m no worth your sorrow—the truth maun be known! </l><l rend="indent3"> Send round for our neighbours; my hour it draws near, </l><l rend="indent3"> And I’ve that to tell that it’s fit a’ should hear.
                            </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> ‘I’ve wrong’d her,’ he said, ‘but I kent it o’er
                                late;</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘I’ve wrong’d her, and sorrow is speeding my date. </l><l rend="indent3"> But a’s for the best, since my death will soon free </l><l rend="indent3"> A faithfu’ young heart, that was ill match’d wi’ me.
                            </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> ‘I loved and I courted her mony a day; </l><l rend="indent3"> The auld folks were for me, but still she said nae. </l><l rend="indent3"> I kentna o’ Jamie, nor yet of her vow; </l><l rend="indent3"> In mercy forgive me!—’twas I stole the cow! </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> ‘I cared not for Crummie; I thought but o’ thee! </l><l rend="indent3"> I thought it was Crummie stood ‘twixt you and me. </l><l rend="indent3"> While she fed your parents, oh! did you not say, </l><l rend="indent3"> You never would marry wi’ Auld Robin Gray? </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> ‘But sickness at hame, and want at the door, </l><l rend="indent3"> You gied me your hand, while your heart it was sore. </l><l rend="indent3"> I saw it was sore—why took I her hand? </l><l rend="indent3"> Oh! that was a deed to cry shame o’er the land.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> ‘But truth, soon or late, it comes ever to light; </l><l rend="indent3"> For Jamie came back, and your cheek it grew white. </l><l rend="indent3"> White, white grew your cheek, but aye true unto me; </l><l rend="indent3"> Oh, Jenny, I’m thankfu’—I’m thankfu’ to dee! </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> ‘Is Jamie come here yet?’ and Jamie they saw. </l><l rend="indent3"> ‘I’ve injured you sair, lad, so leave you my a’; </l><l rend="indent3"> Be kind to my Jenny, and soon may it be! </l><l rend="indent3"> Waste nae time, my dauties, in mourning for me.’</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> They kiss’d his cauld hands; and a smile o’er his
                                face </l><l rend="indent3"> Seem’d hopefu’ of being accepted by grace: </l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Oh, doubtna,’ said Jamie, ‘forgi’en he will be; </l><l rend="indent3"> Wha wou’dna be tempted, my love, to win thee?’ </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> The first days were dowie while time slipp’d awa; </l><l rend="indent3"> Though saddest and sairest to Jenny of a’, </l><l rend="indent3"> Was fearing she cou’dna be honest and right,</l><l rend="indent3"> Wi’ tears in her ee, while her heart was sae light.
                            </l></lg><lb/><lg><l rend="indent3"> But nae guile had she, and her sorrows away. </l><l rend="indent3"> The wife of her Jamie—the tears cou’dna stay. </l><l rend="indent3"> A bonnie wee bairn—the auld folks by the fire;— </l><l rend="indent3"> O now she has a’ that her heart can
                                desire.</l></lg></note></p><p>* I find that I have been writing on the right and not on the wrong side of
                        the sheets and I acknowledge it thus that the Song should retain <hi rend="ital">some</hi> meaning at least; And now I have taken up ‘Stumpy’
                        again I will add that <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">my
                            boy</ref> is every way as well as he was before.—I told <ref target="people.html#SharpWilliam">your Father</ref> that I had got a man
                        to attend him who bears the name of the ‘honest Doctor’, (no reflections)
                        And I believe I shall find him such, for, whether from the apparent
                        attatchment to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref>
                        or his Father’s name, or from his own conscience I know not, I find that his
                        whole share is A Guinea !!!!!! </p><p rend="indent1"> God Bless you All.—— </p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>