<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.216</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        242–43</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="216" type="letter"><head>216. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd
                        Baker</ref>, <date when="1807-10-02">2–5 October 1807</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        242–43</note></head><opener><dateline><address rend="right"><placeName>City Road. London.</placeName></address></dateline><dateline rend="right"><date when="1807-10-02">Oct 2. 1807</date></dateline><salute>Mrs T Baker</salute><salute>Dear Madam</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> My Coat came safe to town, and tho’ no letter accompanied it, I
                    was certain from the direction being in your hand, that I should soon hear from
                    you. Thanks for your friendly account of your amiable neighbours, and late
                    fellow travellers. Do be so good as to make my respects to them, and say that I
                    have not forgot any of my promises to them, but shall at some future time send
                        <ref target="people.html#CooperRobert">Mr Cooper</ref> the ‘Illustrations’
                    and return his Voll<hi rend="sup">ms.</hi> of <del rend="strikethrough">Daubney</del> Daubeny’s Guide to the Church.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Charles Daubney’s <title>Eight Discourses on the
                            Connection between the Old and New Testament considered as two parts of
                            the same divine revelation and demonstrative of the great doctrine of
                            atonement : accompanied with a preliminary discourse addressed to the
                            younger clergy containing some remarks on the Late Professor Campbell’s
                            Ecclesiastical History</title>, (London, 1802).</note> I likewise hope
                    to send that exceedingly <hi rend="ital">petulant, arrogant</hi> and <hi rend="ital">illnature’d Girl</hi>, <del rend="strikethrough">my</del><ref target="people.html#CooperCharlotte">Charlotte C.</ref><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">my Brother’s</ref> tune to my
                    Highland Drover.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">We have found no
                        published version of Isaac’s musical setting of the poem from <title>Rural
                            Tales</title>.</note> But of all this I will write more in due time. And
                    you will here probably ask yourself, what does he mean by due time? Why I mean
                    that when you have fulfilld <hi rend="ital">your</hi> promise, and sent me your
                    Wye Scetches to copy, and the said copying is done. I mean to have the pleasure
                    of exhibiting to you and them my whole triple-page’d Journal, Drawings, prose,
                    and rhime.</p><p rend="indent1"> Since my return I have spent an evening at <ref target="places.html#Fulham">Fulham</ref>, very delightfully. <ref target="people.html#OwenRobert">Mr and Mrs Owen</ref>, and a Sweedish
                    Gentleman, <hi rend="ital">the <ref target="people.html#DeGeerGerard">Baron De
                            Gear</ref></hi>, contributed to make me forget that, I was from home,
                    and <ref target="people.html#SharpWilliam">your Father</ref> to forget that he
                    was old. The latter, I assure you, <hi rend="ital">in appearance</hi>, gives me
                    less apprehensions of <hi rend="ital">speedy</hi> dissolution than I was
                    prepare’d to expect. The Sweed talkd of the scenery of the Baltic, Mr O talk’d
                    of the Alps, and of the passage of mount St Gotherd &amp;c, —and I—What
                    could I talk about?—The <hi rend="ital">Wye</hi>, to be sure!</p><p rend="indent1"> I have made a Harp for <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Catharine</ref>, and carried it to <ref target="places.html#ClareHall">Clare Hall</ref>, and there met <ref target="people.html#CrotchWilliam">Dr
                        Crotch</ref> and family. They are all as jovial as music can make them, And
                    all well. During this visit I was favourd with a copy of your <hi rend="ital">Blank Verse</hi> tribute to the Queen’s Oak, and shewd a Sonnet besides on
                    the same Subject, which Sonnet brought <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Kate-te</ref> and I as near to a quarrel <hi rend="ital">as ever we
                        were</hi> in our lives; for I could not for the life of me call to mind that
                    I had ever heard it before. The <hi rend="ital">Blank</hi> Verse I rememberd to
                    have heard, or read in the garden at <ref target="places.html#Fulham">Fullham</ref>, and If I then saw or heard the other, I think you must have
                    read it to me and smuggled up the name of the writer, in which case I find a
                    tolarable hole to creep out at. You have allso dresst Wake’s Oak in rhime, And
                    if you go any further in personal compliments to your H. S. I shall begin to
                    suspect what I would not have true for two or three such <hi rend="ital">working
                        day worlds</hi> as this, Either that you rather exceed the sober rating of
                    my performances; or, that you are contented to pull the reins of your fancy, and
                    to <del rend="strikethrough">quench</del> check superior abilities, and to come
                    in second by choice, perhaps because you don’t like to be stare’d at; Hey!—Well
                    well, take your way Lady; take your way.!</p><p rend="indent1"> I have not yet found that <ref target="people.html#GrantAnne">Mrs
                Grant’s</ref> poems are publishd. I will not loose sight of them.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Lloyd Baker had previously asked Bloomfield if he could procure her a copy of Anne Grant’s poems (see Letter 210).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Having now transcribed my <del rend="strikethrough">pose</del>
                    prose Journal and made some <hi rend="ital">matchless</hi> drawings from memory,
                    I wait with real anxiety for the time when you can send me <hi rend="ital">yours</hi>, and I will take as much care of them as I would of you. I mean
                    seriously to get some command of the pencil during the next year or two, so
                    remember that I am at school.</p><p rend="indent1"> To <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr T Baker</ref> I
                    beg to be particularly rememberd and hope that when he has news to tell of <hi rend="ital">you</hi> that I may not be wholly left out of the
                    Post.—Blessings attend you All, and with true respects to Mr. &amp; Mrs
                    Baker, and to the wee things.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I am Madam yours truly,</salute><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p><ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr. B,</ref></p><p>By Monday Night’s post,</p><p><date>ye 5th of Oct.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>