<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.4</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 30809, ff. 42–44;
                        published in Remains, I, pp. 11–12 and Works, pp. 297–98</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="4" type="letter"><head>4. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#ChurchJoseph">Joseph
                        Church</ref>, <date when="1791-12-28">28 December [17]91</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 30809, ff. 42–44;
                        published in <title level="m">Remains</title>, I, pp. 11–12 and <title level="m">Works</title>, pp. 297–98</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right">Wednesday-night, <date when="1791-12-28">Dec. 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 91</date></dateline><salute>Honrd Father,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It would have been a great pleasure to us both to have met you at
                    Mr Wyatts this time, and we [were] only prevented by visitors, who came quite
                    unexpected. You would have like to have seen <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">our little one</ref>; and I hope you
                    will yet before long. We thank you for all your kindness, and as I am
                    endeavouring to get into business for myself, I sincerely hope to have it in my
                    power to entertain you better when you come, I have an undeniable chance, I have
                    some good customers, and might have enuff immediately, to provide a genteel
                    living for my <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">wife</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">child</ref>, if I could take advantage
                    of it soon, if I could get three months credit at my leather-cutters for five or
                    six pounds only, it would enable me to give credit to that amount, as my custom
                    lays amongst such, as are able and willing to improve it — but I am determined
                    to carry it on as well as I can.</p><p rend="indent1"> The underwritten lines<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield’s verses ‘On seeing the launch of the Boyne’ were published in
                        the first volume of <title level="m">Remains</title> (pp. 13–16).</note>
                    contain the sentiments which allways occur to my mind when I come to <ref target="places.html#Woolwich">Woolwich,</ref> and as I put them into metre
                    when the Boyne was launched and they are still perfect on my mind, I write them
                    now because I think you have a relish for such things, particularly the
                    devotional parts of them, before I was married I often amused myself with such
                    compositions, and had several pieces published in newspapers, magazines,
                    &amp;c. — but I find other employment now that is of equal pleasure to me — </p><p rend="indent1"> My <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">Polly</ref> and
                        <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">the child</ref> are in good
                    health, and we hope to hear from you soon; and remain yours, in duty and
                    affection,</p><closer><signed rend="right">Rt Bloomfield</signed></closer><lb/><postscript><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Whence springs the joy that longest warms the heart,!</l><l rend="indent3"> Can mutual Love, can Friendship’s self impart,</l><l rend="indent3"> Rapture unmix’d, thoughts constantly the same</l><l rend="indent3"> Like those that feed Devotions sacred flame;</l><l rend="indent3"> When glows the breast with more than mortal fire,</l><l rend="indent3"> And boundless Gratitude to Heaven aspire.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Through the wide field of Arts with true delight,</l><l rend="indent3"> Unceasing wonders croud upon the sight</l><l rend="indent3"> There, a vast Pile<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Identified in <title level="m">Remains</title> as Greenwich
                                Hospital.</note> for no blest ends supply’d,</l><l rend="indent3"> Majestic greets the slowly rising tide;</l><l rend="indent3"> There, less in bulk, a greater wonder far,</l><l rend="indent3"> View in its infant state the ship of war.</l><l rend="indent3"> Who from the hills the boundless prospect sees</l><l rend="indent3"> Must silent praise, or utter words like these.</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Sweet child of Heaven, thee, Gratitude we bless,</l><l rend="indent3"> Through life how lovely in whatever dress,</l><l rend="indent3"> Thou chears our path, with care and perill trod</l><l rend="indent3"> Thou lifts the soul, and points the way to God</l><l rend="indent3"> The shapely columm and the doom it bears,</l><l rend="indent3"> Man sees with pleasure and exulting rears,</l><l rend="indent3"> Whilst here confin’d we view with conscious heart</l><l rend="indent3"> The striking symmetry of every part</l><l rend="indent3"> But ’scap’d the walls and look to earth and sky</l><l rend="indent3"> To all the wonders half revealed on high</l><l rend="indent3"> Where the charm’d soul contemplates her abode</l><l rend="indent3"> And matchless order speaks the eternal God.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> On the fam’d Hill where Flamsteads vigorous mind,</l><l rend="indent3"> By midnight meditations taught mankind;</l><l rend="indent3"> When gleam’d the Moon, and silence reign’d around,</l><l rend="indent3"> The scene was awful, and the thought profound;</l><l rend="indent3"> Heavens shining orbs that gild the peaceful night,</l><l rend="indent3"> To him were clear, were intimately known,</l><l rend="indent3"> And all his pleasure was a God to own;</l><l rend="indent3"> Yet one step more improves the glorious thought,</l><l rend="indent3"> God made that man, and made the stars he sought.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Show the enquiring mind that seeks to know</l><l rend="indent3"> Objects where art her utmost efforts show,</l><l rend="indent3"> Show him where Thames her swelling bosom heaves</l><l rend="indent3"> The towring vessel destin’d to the waves;</l><l rend="indent3"> See! Fix’d astonishment seaze every power</l><l rend="indent3"> Like a short moment flies the favour’d hour,</l><l rend="indent3"> Then admiration every thought attend,</l><l rend="indent3"> The vast design, the purpose, and the end:</l><l rend="indent3"> The forest mourns his largest stateliest trees,</l><l rend="indent3"> Here hewn and fashiond with the greatest ease,</l><l rend="indent3"> Anormous limbs of season’d solid oak</l><l rend="indent3"> Yield there rough sides to labours sturdy stroke,</l><l rend="indent3"> Exact proportion rules in height and length,</l><l rend="indent3"> The first great principal, amazing strength;</l><l rend="indent3"> Strength well required when o’er the watery deep</l><l rend="indent3"> The dauntless mariner his reckoning keep;</l><l rend="indent3"> Behold her prow the opposing billow cleave,</l><l rend="indent3"> And far behind the land of freedom leave,</l><l rend="indent3"> Triumphantly she bears to distant shores,</l><l rend="indent3"> A thousand men with all their ponderous stores,</l><l rend="indent3"> Amazing thought, yet more amazing still,</l><l rend="indent3"> This complicated proof of human skill,</l><l rend="indent3"> When storms arise is like a feather tost,</l><l rend="indent3"> Her monstrous bulk comparatively lost;</l><l rend="indent3"> Waves roll her over, terrors fill the sky,</l><l rend="indent3"> She bursts asunder, every creature dies.</l><l rend="indent3"> O God by winds thou canst destroy or save,</l><l rend="indent3"> O Lord of Life thy Ocean is their grave.</l><l rend="indent3"> What e’er is great or awful from Thee springs</l><l rend="indent3"> We by imperfect, judge of perfect things,</l><l rend="indent3"> If works of Art our admiration raise</l><l rend="indent3"> Thine be the Worship, thine the sacred Praise.</l></lg><p rend="indent8"> Christmas Day. 1791 </p></postscript><lb/><closer><address><rs>Address:</rs><name><ref target="people.html#ChurchJoseph"> Mr
                        Church</ref></name><placeName> at Mrs Woodgates / near the Post Office / <ref target="places.html#Woolwich">Woolwich</ref> 1791</placeName></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>