<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.245</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        275–76</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="245" type="letter"><head>245. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd
                        Baker</ref>, <date when="1809-10-31">31 October–1 November 1809</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        275–76</note></head><opener><dateline><address rend="right"><placeName>London.</placeName></address></dateline><dateline rend="right"><date when="1809-10-31">Oct 31. 1809.</date></dateline><salute>Dear Madam,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I should indeed be sadly ashamed of this long disrespectful
                    silence had I not unfortunately a tolerable excuse to urge, which, though I
                    write in extreme pain, shall not make its appearance until the fag end of the
                    epistle.</p><p rend="indent1"> The first thought that came across my mind on the receipt of
                    yours was, a glow of self approbation, for having by some means or other so far
                    obtain’d your good wishes as to induce you in hurry, and on business, and in the
                    midst of a journey to think of me and to steal time to write. You must certainly
                    take a pleasure in oblidging, and that is the very essence of all that is good
                    upon earth, as far as earth is concernd.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Cheddar Cliffs have taken up a nook in my heart, and
                    imagination scratches a picture of her own, like an old Hen in a garden.</p><p> I had taken a momentary dislike to Old Scoop,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In the MS <title>The Banks of Wye a Poetical Journal. A
                            Poetical Journal. Aug. 17. 1807</title> [BL Add. MS 28265 ff. 48–49],
                        the opening lines of the poem read <lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> When Time’s young curls embower’d his brow</l><l rend="indent3"> And infant streams began to flow,</l><l rend="indent3"> Huge giant Scoop with spade in hand, </l><l rend="indent3"> And all the Island at command,</l><l rend="indent3"> With puffing breath and monstrous stride</l><l rend="indent3"> Came thundering on by Severn’s side.</l><l rend="indent3"> Fancy still hears his foot rebound,</l><l rend="indent3"> When <hi rend="ital">Stinchcombe</hi> trembled at the
                                sound.</l><l rend="indent3"> Here Cambrian mountains caught his eye</l><l rend="indent3"> Towring to meet the distant sky</l><l rend="indent3"> Jealous he mark’d them one by one</l><l rend="indent3"> And dreading <del rend="strikethrough">much to
                                    be</del> sore the work out-done</l><l rend="indent3"> ‘Out-done’ he cried, ’Tis true I’m warm’</l><l rend="indent3"> But this bright prospect nerves my arm</l><l rend="indent3"> I too the mountain pile can rear</l><l rend="indent3"> Outdone, there shall be just such here.’</l><l rend="indent3"> Then stript at once to set about it,</l><l rend="indent3"> (Look at the spot and who can doubt it,)</l><l rend="indent3"> But, at the moment he was speaking</l><l rend="indent3"> His limbs were stiff, his back was aching,</l><l rend="indent3"> For <hi rend="ital">Mendip</hi>, and the western
                                shore,</l><l rend="indent3"> The marks of recent labours bore:</l><l rend="indent3"> Weary he rested, full of pain,</l><l rend="indent3"> By <hi rend="ital">Nympsfield</hi>, on the upland
                                plain,</l><l rend="indent3"> And with a gnashing envious smile</l><l rend="indent3"> There stuck his spade upright the while,</l><l rend="indent3"> And chang’d his mind.—Then sprewing first,</l><l rend="indent3"> O’er Severn’s Vale a cloud of dust,</l><l rend="indent3"> Again he pluck’d it from the ground,</l><l rend="indent3"> The crumbling earth flew wizzing round;</l><l rend="indent3"> Then dashing sternly to and fro,</l><l rend="indent3"> He cut a casual hole or two;</l><l rend="indent3"> In one of which (a sweet one truly)</l><l rend="indent3"> Some modern pigmies built up Uley</l><l rend="indent3"> And <hi rend="ital">Owlpen</hi>, by the dark wood
                                side,</l><l rend="indent3"> Which none can find without a guide.</l><l rend="indent3"> And here, the happy natives stroll</l><l rend="indent3"> Around their green illshapen Bowl,</l><l rend="indent3"> A Bowl all zigzagg’d round about</l><l rend="indent3"> With one large gap to let them out.</l></lg></note>* but you strengthen my original feeling and I begin to think
                    that He may be a personage not <hi rend="ital">altogether</hi> to be ridiculed.
                    I have a great mind to keep him alive.</p><p rend="indent1"> Have you ever seen two or three local publications by Mr Heath a
                    printer at Monmouth? A fund of information may be glean’d from them all
                    immediately relating to our late expidition to paradice. Historical and minute
                    descriptions relative to Kyrle, to Ross, Willton Castle, Goodrich, Coldwell,
                    &amp;c &amp;c told in a plain <hi rend="ital">tradesman</hi> like
                        stile.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably <title>Monmouthshire:
                            historical and descriptive accounts of the Ancient and present state of
                            Chepstow Castle: ... Interpersed with curious biographical anecdotes
                            relating to the life and public character of Henry Marten, one of the
                            judges of King Charles I: Confined twenty years in this castle:
                            Collected from original papers and unquestionable authorities</title>
                        (Monmouth, 1801).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><date when="1809-11-01">Nov. 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi></date> I have no summer
                    excursions to relate, No Rocks to describe but the rocks of expenditure and
                    taxation, and I’ll be bound for it they are not so sublime or picturesque as
                    those of Cheddar.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">My eldest Daughter</ref> has just
                    return’d from an eight weeks residence in Suffolk at the very Farm that employ’d
                    me in my childhood. She has seen the Harvest, and was present at the ‘Horkey’
                    and with many of the persons who figured there thirty years ago when I was 13
                    years old. There is a fund of gossip cut out for me during the winter coming.
                    She return’d on the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, the next day you may recollect is
                    sacred to our <hi rend="ital">Leather Saint,</hi> and is besides her
                        birthday.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">St. Crispin is the patron
                        saint of shoemakers.</note> It was a high holiday in London as a Jubilee,
                    and to crown it all my brother’s family postponed on her account the celebration
                    of a Christning. Thus, by having a family meeting we beat all the Doctors for we
                    killd more than two birds with one stone.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have been <hi rend="ital">forced</hi> to read a large Volumn
                    which has in the end given me much pleasure. Dr Parkinson’s ‘Organic Remains of
                    the Antediluvian World,’ treating of the transformation of vegetable substances
                    into stone and Cole &amp;c.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">James
                        Parkinson, <title>Organic Remains of a Former World. An Examination of the
                            Mineralized Remains of the Vegetables and Animals of the Antediluvian
                            World; Generally Termed Extraneous Fossils</title>, 3 vols. (London,
                        1804–11).</note> I have besides borrowed old Stowe<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Stowe’s <title>Survey of London</title> was first
                        published in 1598 and reprinted several times.</note> and been diving into
                    the former state of this great city with very great satisfaction. When I last
                    wrote to your <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Cousin Catherine</ref> I
                    told her I could not read; it was true but I have greatly got over it since. I
                    have even, (being inspired by Heath’s books) new modelled my journal, and hope
                    to fetch up what I have lost by idleness or by indisposition, and to make a
                    somthing of it yet. I am better pleased with it than I ever have been
                    before.</p><p rend="indent1"> What joy it must be to you to come home to your children and find
                    them well! For yourself it appears that travelling agrees with you, and you
                    should take the remedy upon all possible occasions.</p><p rend="indent1"> One day in the <del rend="strikethrough">Winter</del> Summer when
                    for a long time I had heard nothing from <ref target="places.html#ClareHall">Clare Hall</ref> or from <ref target="places.html#Fulham">Fullham</ref>, I
                    trudged to the latter place and found that <ref target="people.html#SharpMrs">Mrs Sharp</ref> had much recoverd, and that the family were then at <ref target="places.html#WickenPark">Wicken</ref>. While on the bridge I saw a
                    most beautiful sight. A Rain bow of most singular strength and breadth of
                    colours; it appeared in the east, the right foot resting on the surry shore,
                    just on the bank, so that the tide being full, and the water unruffled, its
                    shadow was <hi rend="ital">quite</hi> as perfect as itself and form’d nearly a
                    circle, thus. [sketch of a circle]. The house on the right bank has a white
                    front which the prismatic colours renderd more striking than any thing I ever
                    observed of the kind. I have had a very kind letter from <ref target="people.html#CooperRobert">Mr Cooper</ref> pray put in a word for me
                    there if I should be mention’d. I look with much anxiety towards the health of
                        <ref target="people.html#CooperCharlotte">Charlotte</ref>. And how is <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr Baker</ref>? Will he change his
                    Gout for my Rhumatism? You see here that grumbling must come in at last.
                    November is a trying month to me. I have been a week totally disabled from work,
                    or from resting above ten minutes in a place. I hope nevertheless to tell you a
                    better story soon. My sincere respects are due to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mrs Baker</ref>, and tell Catharine and
                    Mary Ann that if my back does not mend shortly I shall for a certainty forget
                    all my dancing. And with welsh scenery in my imagination and welsh [word
                    deleted] flannel to my skin I am, Dear Madam your very much oblidged, but tardy
                    friend,</p><closer><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>P. S. I have this minute been reading your letter to my daughter and she
                        naturally ask’d on the mention of your <ref target="people.html#SharpMrs">Aunt James S</ref>. ‘which Mrs S. is that’. I reflected for the first
                        time, and that for the <hi rend="ital">first time</hi> carried me to <ref target="places.html#ClareHall">Clare Hall</ref>, for I had fixd the
                        reference to Durham, and your friends there—It may be possible that <ref target="people.html#SharpMrs">Mrs Sharp</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Catharine</ref> are now with you. If
                        they are what a most brilliant figure I should make at an apology at the
                        table! I have rather wonderd that I have heard nothing from <ref target="places.html#Barnett">Barnett</ref>, and been sadly unwilling to
                        believe that any other cause for it than absence could have been found,
                        where people write so frankly as we do, This is however a hole in a dark
                        staircase; a light thrown on the subject. I therefore charge you with my
                        love to All <del rend="strikethrough">tog</del> together — </p><p>* See the beginning of the original MSS of Banks of Wye <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">T J Ll B</ref> [note added by
                            <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">T. J. Lloyd Baker</ref>]</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>