<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.1</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, f. 15</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="1" type="letter"><head>1. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamCousin">William
                        Austin</ref>, <date when="1788-04-11">11 April 1788</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, f. 15</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London,</placeName></address><date when="1788-04-11">April 11th 1788</date></dateline><salute>To Mr Wm Austin</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is so long since I wrote to you that I ought to begin with
                    half a sheet full of apoligys, but I intend to persue quite a different plan and
                    begin bluntly thus,</p><p rend="indent1"> I am inform’d that you have seen Cambridge, Norwich, &amp;c.
                    now I think the same desire that led you to see Norwich, would make you wish to
                    see London, and if you have a friends house to come to where you might be used
                    just as if you was at home, it would doubtless be most agreeable to you, but if
                    you are not provided in this respect and have any inclination to see the town, I
                    should be most heartily rejoiced if you and your Brother will accept my
                    invitation, here you will begin to think how I can entertain you, Ill tell you
                    how exactly; and if you think it will not do you can tell me so and there will
                    be no harm done — In the first place, I will provide you a genteel private
                    lodging for as long a time as you intend to stay, and when you are at my lodging
                    you must expect such treatment as is in my power to give, and when we are out
                    you must have no objection to dine at a decent Cook-shop, where there is good
                    choice, and if you dont like porter we can get good ale, in short, London is
                    like other great places, allmost any thing may be had for money and when we are
                    out, whatever the expence may be for living or for seeing the public buildings,
                    &amp;c, my scheme is, that each bear his own charges, you know how <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> and others of our trade
                    live, but <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> have the
                    honour of living in a street, but I cannot Get into a street from my lodgings
                    without going through some such crook of a hole as between your near-barn and
                    the hay-house, but take notice you are not to lodge in such a place as this, you
                    have boath had the small-pox and I think I remember that your sister Judith have
                    had it too, here is a letter enclosed from my sister to Judith and I hope to see
                    you all soon, I hope it will not be thought disrespectful for me to mention only
                    you and your brother, the reason is, I could not procure a suitable accomodation
                    for any woman whatever, a single man have no chance to do it half so well as my
                    sister have, if you all come (as I hope you will) you and your brother must
                    lodge near me, and the street where your sister will live, lead into Berkley
                    Square, just by where my sister live, and we are about three miles apart, so you
                    will have a good chance to see the town in going backwards and forwards, I shall
                    be allways with you and we must be very particular and not be out late of night,
                    nor frequent any low lived places, and as long as we do so, there is no danger
                    to be feard, if you consider the whole expense I belive it will be found a cheap
                    way of seeing London, you may all come by the <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> Stage, and if either of you
                    chuse to ride in the dust outside it will cost only 9.<hi rend="sup">s</hi>
                    each, inside double, and you will be here by breakfast if you come in the night,
                    or by two o clock if you start in the morning, I think <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamUncle">my Unkle</ref> can have no objection
                    to such a Scheme, as the time is short, and you know your company — If you will
                    promise to come, I promise on my part to do all in my power to spend the time
                    agreeably and to the best advantage, and secondly, not to pretend to do any work
                    while you are hear; and lastly, I dont intend to quit your company till we are
                    all safly landed at <ref target="places.html#Sapiston">Sapiston</ref>; this is
                    what I have often thought of, but I should not have declared myself so soon if
                        <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> had not wrote to
                    know whether I would come this Sumer or not, as to the time of your coming you
                    must go by what my sister have write, and I shall expect you in June. — </p><p rend="indent1"> But be so kind as to write soon and let us know whether you will
                    come or not, and if you do I should like to hear from you just before you set
                    out, to know what inn you will come to, and at what time, and I will be there to
                    meet you, give my duty and respects to all the family, I am very thankful for
                    the great favours and respect shown me by <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamUncle">my Unkle</ref> and all of you, and
                    will endeavour still to deserve them, we are all well, and desire to be
                    remembered to all frends,</p><closer><signed rend="right">Rt. Bloomfield</signed><address><rs>Address:</rs><name><ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamCousin"> Mr Wm Austin</ref></name></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>