<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.76</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 83–84;
                        extract published in Hart, p. 22</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="76" type="letter"><head>76. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Elizabeth
                        Glover</ref>, <date when="1802-01-31">31 January 1802</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 83–84;
                        extract published in Hart, p. 22</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName>London</placeName></address><date when="1802-01-31">Jany 31st 1802</date></dateline><salute>Dear Mother</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> When I sent the Books to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref>, I could not write to you
                    or to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Kitty</ref>. I have been full
                    employ’d, and I have written down the principle occurrence of each day in the
                    enclosed Diary where if you can read hasty and bad writing, you will find that I
                    had little time to make shoes. But it realy takes so much time to copy letters
                    that I don’t see it possible to make you so fuly acquainted with my affairs as I
                    wish I could. I have Letters from <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Mr
                        Fox</ref>, and from <ref target="people.html#BuchanLord">Lord Buchan</ref>,
                    which I hope you will one day see.—From <ref target="people.html#DrakeNathan">Dr
                        Drake</ref> of <ref target="places.html#Hadleigh">Hadleigh</ref>, Mr Smith,
                    and Mr Mills of <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>, <ref target="people.html#GilchristOctavius">Mr Gilchrist</ref> of Stamford and
                    others, all relating to my new vollumn, and all in high commendation. I sell a
                    great many books myself, on which I have a good profit. I yesterday received
                    from Mrs. Philips £3.11s. for Books she has sold for me; and left with her
                    others to the amount of £8 and upwards; and, calling on Mr. Stonhewer, he
                    insisted on paying me for a large copy by giving me a £5 note. The publick
                    interest and admiration seems to be as much raised by this publication as by the
                    first; and in my own mind, and in the common and moderate way of reconing, I
                    shall at least have to receive in the next 2 years, 8 or 9 hundred pounds. I
                    have left near 2 Hundred due to me on the Books, arising from the first 4
                    Editions, and I have to receive the half profits of ten thousand copies of the
                    Farmer’s Boy, being the 5th and 6th editions; the last is now printed; to which
                    must be added my whole expectations on this second work, of which 7000 copies
                    are printed and an other Edition will certainly be wanted. this statement though
                    true I do not wish to be made publick, which you and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Kitty</ref> and all of you will
                    remember. God grant that you may live long enough to be essentialy benefited by
                    a part of it. this is not counting any chickens before they are hatched; they
                    actually are hatched, but not all brought to market.—</p><p rend="indent1"> I send you a One pound Note. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> will buy you a Bottle of
                    Rum or Brandy at <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>, and send
                    you the change.—</p><p rend="indent1"> I can say no more now, I must write largely to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref>, and to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>, and to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Kitty</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Our best respects to <ref target="people.html#GloverJohn">my
                        Father</ref></p><p rend="indent1"> We have the satisfaction of saying that we are all well <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nats</ref> family the same</p><p rend="indent1"> And remain with true affection Dear <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref> Yours</p><closer><signed rend="right">R Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p><label>PS</label> If my last Northamton Journal be with you, pray let <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> have it to send to
                        me, I want it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">This journal is not
                            extant; to judge by Bloomfield’s many enquiries of different relatives,
                            he never recovered it.</note></p><p rend="right">Monday night</p><p>Since writing the above, I have had a letter from <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> at Yarmouth; it contained
                        a one pound note for me, a present from Mr Green of Ipswich, for the
                        pleasure he found in reading Richard and Kate. This identical note I send
                        for you, so that its ride from Ipswich to Yarmouth and from Yarmouth to
                        London, and from London to you, only proves that, as a Suffolk Ballad made
                        it mine, it ought to be spent in Suffolk. </p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mrs Glover</ref></name> / <placeName><ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref></placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>