<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.234</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        261–62</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="234" type="letter"><head>234. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerMary">Mary Lloyd
                        Baker</ref>, <date when="1808-12-21">21 December 1808</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        261–62</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><date when="1808-12-21">The shortest day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> year
                            1808</date></dateline><salute>To Mrs Baker,</salute><salute>Dear Madam.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> This, I hope will find you in your place at the fire side, and
                    all who are dear to you, in the same circle, or a similar one. How does <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr B.</ref> &amp; the boy? the
                    little girls, and the elders of <ref target="places.html#StoutsHill">Stouts
                        Hill</ref>? When I reflect on the times which have past since I wrote last I
                    feel vex’d, and lower’d in my own estimation, and therefore I will proceed
                    without reflection, at least without that of the retrospective kind, which I can
                    least bear. Your venerable parents honourd me with a call twice, by whom I
                    learnd that you were in health &amp;c, and obtaind an address to <ref target="people.html#SharpCatherine">Miss Sharp</ref> then on a visit, and of
                    which I have made no use, but <hi rend="ital">now</hi> write to her at her home.
                    This is the way I treat my friends. <ref target="people.html#SharpWilliam">Your
                        father</ref> has been helping me with his advice as to the treatment of <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">my boys</ref> knee, so as to
                    obtain strength by degrees, he is healthy and strong except his lameness, and
                    the rest are as I wish them, except when they give the rein to their tongues,
                    and croud round the fire. And now you will exclaim ‘but how are you yourself?’
                    Then honestly my dear friend I am but so so, I have now and then a staunch,
                    stupendous WindCliff* of a headache, that leaves me as weak and worthless as if
                    I had been in a hot bath for a fortnight. Out of these fits I rise with a spirit
                    that lasts——5 hours! or a day and half! I believe you know that I have not
                    budg’d an inch after the Muses since April, but I have a strong notion that we
                    shall be friends in the spring.</p><p rend="indent1"> Many thanks for ‘Marmion;’ It comes, when compared with The Lay,
                    like a round of beef after a Sirloin;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Scott’s second verse romance, <title>Marmion: a Tale of Flodden
                            Field</title> was published in 1808, following the runaway success of
                            <title>The Lay of the Last Minstrel</title> (London and Edinburgh,
                        1805).</note> it is not quite so tender, but it is right good stuff. In the
                        2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Canto I lookd and expected that he would, at least
                    poetically, rescue the poor girl from the dungeon; and when I left her there I
                    felt a burning indignation, A little of it was for the past, and the rest for
                    the [word obscured] old lumps of iniquity who are saddled with the crime, or in
                    case they call off, for the historians who have told the Tale! I think the
                    passage of Marmion through the Scottish Camp is a masterly description; many
                    other parts strike like lightning in a dark night, but I question if the local
                    tales of superstition add <hi rend="ital">here</hi> the interest they do in the
                    Lay, and that for reasons I must leave you to find out.</p><p rend="indent1"> I must now give you another proof of my great inattention of late
                    to what would have spurd me once to immediate action. I had long ago, a letter
                    from <ref target="people.html#CooperCharlotte">Miss Cooper</ref>, and I have
                    never answerd it! I know many months ago that there were Songs for me at <ref target="people.html#CrotchWilliam">Dr Crotch’s</ref>, and I never went for
                    them untill the night before last. I know that <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Mr Baker</ref> beat me hollow at
                    expedition and galantry for <ref target="people.html#CooperCharlotte">Miss
                        C</ref> had the song at the time of its publication, and very glad was I to
                    hear it. And now will you for me give them the essence of this letter, and all
                    the apology you can pick out of it, saying moreover that I am above ground, and
                    with a lively remembrance of pleasures and events, never more than now their
                    humble servant.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">my
                        Musical brother</ref> in town for a while, and we are making Harps by the
                    dozen.</p><p rend="indent1"> With regard to Books, the first Vol of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                    Steriotype Edition has past my hands, but not publishd; and the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> vol is in great forwardness.</p><p> You will know that continuations or additions to popular Songs of acknowledged
                    merit and pathos are not often successful, but I have lately been delighted with
                    one on the subject of ‘Robin Gray’. It work’d effectually at sensibility’s pump,
                    and did me a deal of good, and at some future lucky hour I will certainly copy
                    it for you.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield’s daughter copies
                        the continuation of Anne Lindsay’s ‘Auld Robin Grey: a Ballad’ out in Letter
                        236. Lindsay’s ballad (1772):<lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> When the sheep are in the fauld, when the cows come hame, </l><l rend="indent3"> When a’ the weary world to quiet rest are gane, </l><l rend="indent3"> The woes of my heart fa’ in showers frae my ee, </l><l rend="indent3"> Unken’d by my gudeman, who soundly sleeps by me. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Young Jamie loo’d me weel, and sought me for his bride; </l><l rend="indent3"> But saving ae crown-piece, he’d naething else beside, </l><l rend="indent3"> To make the crown a pound, my Jamie gaed to sea; </l><l rend="indent3"> And the crown and the pound, oh! they were baith for me!
                        </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Before he had been gane a twelvemonth and a day, </l><l rend="indent3"> My father brak his arm, our cow was stown away; </l><l rend="indent3"> My mother she fell sick—my Jamie was at sea—</l><l rend="indent3"> And Auld Robin Gray, oh! he came a-courting me. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> My father cou’dna work—my mother cou’dna spin; </l><l rend="indent3"> I toil’d day and night, but their bread I cou’dna win; </l><l rend="indent3"> Auld Rob maintain’d them baith, and, wi’ tears in his ee, </l><l rend="indent3"> Said, ‘Jenny, oh! for their sakes, will you marry me?’
                        </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> My heart it said na, and I look’d for Jamie back; </l><l rend="indent3"> But hard blew the winds, and his ship was a wrack: </l><l rend="indent3"> His ship it was a wrack! Why didna Jenny dee? </l><l rend="indent3"> Or, wherefore am I spared to cry out, Woe is me! </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> My father argued sair—my mother didna speak, </l><l rend="indent3"> But she look’d in my face till my heart was like to
                            break: </l><l rend="indent3"> They gied him my hand, but my heart was in the sea; </l><l rend="indent3"> And so Auld Robin Gray, he was gudeman to me. </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> I hadna been wife, a week but only four, </l><l rend="indent3"> When mournfu’ as I sat on the stane at my door, </l><l rend="indent3"> I saw my Jamie’s ghaist—I cou’dna think it he, </l><l rend="indent3"> Till he said, ‘I’m come hame, my love, to marry thee!’
                        </l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> O sair, sair did we greet, and mickle say of a’; </l><l rend="indent3"> Ae kiss we took, nae mair—I bad him gang awa. </l><l rend="indent3"> I wish that I were dead, but I’m no like to dee; </l><l rend="indent3"> For O, I am but young to cry out, Woe is me! </l></lg><lb/><lg><l rend="indent3"> I gang like a ghaist, and I carena much to spin; </l><l rend="indent3"> I darena think o’ Jamie, for that wad be a sin. </l><l rend="indent3"> But I will do my best a gude wife aye to be. </l><l rend="indent3"> For auld Robin Gray, oh! he is sae kind to me.</l></lg></note></p><p rend="indent1"> Once again pray speak to the good folks at <ref target="places.html#FerneyHill">Ferney-Hill</ref>, and believe me whither
                    well or ill, [word deleted] sad or foolish, musical or out of tune, with true
                    love to your self and family, Your sincere, but sulky friend and servant</p><closer><signed rend="right">Robert Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>* Windcliff is <hi rend="ital">most stupendous</hi> cliff on the Wye near
                        Chepstow [note added by <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">T. J.
                            Lloyd Baker</ref>]</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>