<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.354</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        421–23</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="354" type="letter"><head>354. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">Thomas
                        John Lloyd Baker</ref>, <date when="1821-05-31">31 May–1 June 1821</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        421–23</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>, Beds.</placeName></address><date when="1821-05-31">May 31. 1821</date></dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am glad that your remaining scruples have thus enabled me to
                    say a word on this important subject, for important it is and must be to me; but
                    you must let me have my own <hi rend="ital">stile</hi> of writing or I can do
                    nothing. Put up with vulgarisms and take me as you find me.—I am realy glad that
                    you approve of my original plan to silence, or keep at a distance <hi rend="ital">all party</hi>, but I shall have to recur to this subject
                    again—when I was first known in London I met, (without my seeking) a man related
                    to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Lofft</ref>, who, I soon found was
                    not only a deist but a writer in their cause. I soon found the shocking
                    inconsistency of keeping <hi rend="ital">him</hi> company and others his betters
                    of different principles at the same time. I therefore dropd him, he thinking me
                    a silly young fool who wanted a ring in my nose and he to hold the string, and I
                        <hi rend="ital">knowing</hi> him to be a boasting fellow whom I would not
                    trust three hours.—From that time came to me people of all descriptions—the
                    Unitarians were very busy. It is known that the late <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">D of Grafton</ref> often attended
                    the chapple in Essex Street, and a busy friend of mine thought perhaps that I
                    too might make a pretty little Unitarian, He therefore wrote the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">D</ref> without my knowledge an
                    intimation that I would attend there, but feard that my attendance would look
                    like truckling to my great patron who sat in the gallery?—When I saw the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">D</ref> again he askd me if I
                    knew a man of the name of ——? For he had recieved a letter respecting me
                    &amp;c. the good old man then said with an emphasis almost peculiar to
                    himself, ‘I never wish to exert either power of persuasion over the wills or
                    opinion of any one living, I have never done so with my <hi rend="ital">own</hi>
                    children, nor ever will.’ Now the man who took this great liberty to write,
                    never to this days knows that I am acquainted with the affair!! What did he want
                    with me I wonder? It is not usual to get money out of poets! No, no it is not
                    the search after guineas, but proselites.—</p><p rend="indent1"> You have lately been amused and perhaps grieved by a report. Now
                    I will try to give you some of old date concerning myself.</p><p>1. The Morning Chronicle once said ‘Bloomfield has a <hi rend="ital">lucrative</hi> place in the Temple,’ adding, ‘thus it seems he has not
                    courted the Muse unsuccessfully’<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">See
                        Letter 103. The <title>Morning Chronicle</title> report on Bloomfield’s
                        lucrative place at the Seal office appeared on 19 February 1803.</note>—This
                    was copied into the American papers and most likely read by <ref target="people.html#HingstonElizabeth">my sister</ref> in Virginia,—yet the
                        <hi rend="ital">place was not</hi> lucrative, and I never recieved but
                    twenty pounds. Twice to our knowledge I have been reported to be dead. I have
                    been advertised once to know if I was dead or alive!</p><p>2d Mr Cobbet has ventured to tell his readers that I have been ‘taken in tow’ by
                    government to prevent me from writing in favour of the people <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See Cobbett’s <title>Political Register</title>
                        of 24 April 1819, where, on pp. 980–81, Cobbett writes ‘the cause of the
                        people has been betrayed by hundreds of men, who were well able to serve the
                        people, but whom a love of ease and of the indulgence of empty vanity have
                        seduced into the service of the bribing usurpers, who have spared no means
                        to corrupt men of literary talent from the authors of folios to the authors
                        of baby-books and ballads. . . . None have escaped. BLOOMFIELD, the
                        Farmer’s-Boy author was <hi rend="ital">taken in tow</hi>, and was pensioned
                        for fear he should write for the people’. In a later work, Cobbett used
                        Bloomfield as an example of the personal dangers run by men who abandoned
                        their trades to depend on literature and, consequently, on the patronage of
                        the aristocracy. See William Cobbett, <title>Advice to Young Men and
                            (Incidentally) to Young Women in the Middle and Higher Ranks of Life. In
                            a Series of Letters, Addressed to a Youth, a Bachelor, a Lover, a
                            Husband, a Father, a Citizen, or a Subject</title> (London, 1829),
                        Letter 1, ‘To a Youth’, paragraph 42: ‘Stick, therefore, to the shop; rely
                        upon your mercantile or mechanical or professional calling; try your
                        strength in literature, if you like; but, rely on the shop. If BLOOMFIELD,
                        who wrote a poem called the FARMER’S BOY, had placed no reliance on the
                        faithless muses, his unfortunate and much-to-be-pitied family would, in all
                        probability, have not been in a state to solicit relief from charity. I
                        remember that this loyal shoemaker was flattered to the skies, and (ominous
                        sign, if he had understood it) feasted at the tables of some of the great.
                        Have, I beseech you, no hope of this sort; and, if you find it creeping
                        towards your heart, drive it instantly away as the mortal foe of your
                        independence and your peace’.</note></p><p>3d—I once met with a painter in London who absolutely insisted that I had a place
                    of three hundred a year in the Stamp Office! I thought then that I knew better,
                    and my pocket has confirmd it since</p><p rend="indent1"> See to what lengths <hi rend="ital">party spirit</hi> will
                    go!!!</p><p rend="indent1"> But to the point,—I say then there is not a man or woman living
                    who would or could say to <hi rend="ital">my face</hi> that I have renounced the
                    doctrines of Christ or his Miracles.—There is not a soul upon earth to say ‘you
                    are an enemy to the government of your country’ Fools, cannot they see that the
                        <hi rend="ital">form</hi> of government of a country is rather different to
                    the administration of it? Pray remember me to Mrs Baker and all who have
                    patience to hear of me. Yours dr Sir most respectfully</p><closer><signed rend="right">Robt Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p><label>P.S.</label> June 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> 1821</p><p>Dear Sir,</p><p rend="indent1"> My eyes will let me say a few words more on the subject which
                        I hope will afterwards sleep for ever.—</p><p rend="indent1"> Cobbett and Hunt<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry
                            Hunt, the orator present at the Peterloo Massacre and the Spa Fields’
                            ‘riots’, whose supporters Bloomfield feared encountering on the street
                            in Letter 343.</note> are men whom I would not trust with power; they
                        are too eager to obtain it.—Universal suffrage is an impracticable piece of
                        nonscense;—Republicanism will only do in <hi rend="ital">new</hi> establishd
                        countrys: not in those which have been govern’d by Kings for a thousand
                        years.—</p><p rend="indent1"> It is the natural bent and practice of <hi rend="ital">party</hi> to go to extreems. Thus they could not let me rest even on
                        the intermediate shelf of Scepticism but made me a Deist at once!!—I have
                        been in the presence of great and <hi rend="ital">good</hi> men, the Bishops
                        Watson and Porteous,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Bishops Watson
                            and Porteous: the Rt Rev Richard Watson (1737–1816) was a clergyman and
                            academic, who served as the Bishop of Llandaff from 1782 to 1816. His
                            1796 <title>An Apology for the Bible</title>, a work written in response
                            to the 1795 publication of the second part of Thomas Paine’s <title>Age
                                of Reason</title>, defended orthodox Christianity and the
                            established church. In return, Wordsworth wrote (but did not publish)
                            his ‘Letter to the Bishop of Llandaff’, attacking Watson and supporting
                            Paine. Bishop Porteous: the Rt. Rev. Beilby Porteous, Bishop of London,
                            notable preacher, supporter of the Evangelical movement and the
                            Anti-Slavery campaign, opponent of Paine and revolutionary radicalism.
                            Died 1809.</note> but then it is equally true that I have taken snuff
                        with Horne Tooke,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Horne Tooke
                            (1736–1812) was, by 1800, already a veteran campaigner for parliamentary
                            reform. Initially radicalised by the establishment efforts to exclude
                            newly-elected John Wilkes from parliament, Horne Tooke became an
                            organiser of societies dedicated to widening suffrage—including the
                            Society for Constitutional Information. He was arrested and charged with
                            treason in 1794 when, in alliance with the London Corresponding Society,
                            he attempted to organise a radical convention. Acquitted, despite the
                            bias of the judge, he continued to argue for parliamentary reform,
                            though in more moderate form.</note> and have held conversation with
                        Hardy* the Boot maker, who was tried for high treason!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Hardy (1752–1832), like Bloomfield a
                            London shoemaker, was a campaigner for parliamentary reform and the
                            extension of the franchise. As an organiser of the London Corresponding
                            Society he, like Horne Tooke, was tried for treason in 1794. Although
                            acquitted, he lost his wife and unborn child—both died in childbirth
                            brought on prematurely by the stress of fleeing from a pro-government
                            mob. After his release from custody, Hardy gave up politics and carried
                            on his trade in Covent Garden.</note>—Yea, more than all this, I had the
                        misfortune to be born only six miles from the birthplace of Tom Paine!!
                        This, to some ears would be horrible!—I shall go to worship again when I am
                        well enough; and when my dear <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Daughter</ref> and Sons<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles
                            Bloomfield and Robert Henry Bloomfield.</note> can leave me in the
                        company of <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">a Woman</ref> whom
                        you know little about, they will go too. </p><p>*(on his visit to this County, where I was obliged to meet him, and from him
                        came the report that ‘I was writing a poem on <ref target="places.html#Southill">Southill</ref> and <ref target="people.html#WhitbreadSamuel">Whitbread</ref>.’</p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#LloydBakerThomasJ">T. J. L. Baker</ref> Esq,</name> / <name>Rev’d Mr Ross’s,</name> / <placeName>Maulden. / Ampthill, / Beds.</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>