<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.103</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 116–17;
                        extract published in Hart, p. 31</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="103" type="letter"><head>103. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1803-03-01">29 February 1803</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 116–17;
                        extract published in Hart, p. 31</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London.</placeName></address><date when="1803-03-01">Feb 29th 1803.</date></dateline><salute>Dear George,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Last week was remarkable for a combination of vexations and
                    unexpected troubles. My own health very midling amongst the rest <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">My Wife</ref> and the 3 elder
                    Children ill with bad colds, <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">my
                        poor Boy</ref> had early last week an unusual swelling come on his right
                    knee, and the surgeon tells me that it is in a fair way to be a White swelling
                    if the means he takes do not stop it. We apply night and morning a large
                    poultice of Vinegar, Water, and Oatmeal, which draws it full of pimples, and
                    those pimples are to subside, and then to have them raised again by the same
                    means: he gives me no hope of its speedy ammendment. this is one of my serious
                    troubles. I had two holidays last week but was too ill to make my visits which
                    had been defer’d or to write, or any thing else but think. On Friday, the day
                    after the Holidays, I expected a busy day at the <ref target="places.html#SealOffice">Seal Office</ref>; and so I found it with a
                    vengeance. I had eat no breakfast, and the Mob of Lawyers made me perfectly
                    savage: at One o’clock we shut the Office, but shut in between 40 and 50 people,
                    and did not get through the Work for 3 quarters of an hour after one. I then
                    grew faint, and knew if I walkd home to the City Road that my Wind and
                    indigestion would get the upper hand of my Stomach, and should eat no dinner; so
                    I put into the Cook’s in Salsbury Court and eat heartily. by this time there was
                    no time to go home and then to Temple Bar again by 4; so I sulkd away the time
                    in St George’s Fields, and then took another 3 hours’ Mobbing at the Office,
                    having seald during the day nearly 1100 Writs! by far the busiest day (if <ref target="people.html#AllenWilliam">Mr A</ref> is to be credited) that have
                    occurrd for eight years past. Returnd to my sick house, tired and insufferably
                    disgusted. At home I found a Letter from <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref>, not quite the thing and your most melancholy tidings, and—to
                    crown all, a young Man in the neighbourhood fourced on me a M:S. book of poems
                    for me to read and to give my judgment of, which accorded with the feelings of
                    the moment, being a doleful string of Elegies as black as midnight—This I shall
                    call Black Friday—Another trifle had displeased me. I had found in the Morning
                    Chronicle a bit of news put there by some fool or other that ‘Bloomfield the
                    poet has been recently appointed to a <hi rend="ital">handsome</hi> situation in
                    the <ref target="places.html#SealOffice">Seal Office</ref> in the Temple, thus
                    he has not courted the Muses unsuccessfully!’<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield quotes verbatim the notice of his appointment to
                        the Seal Office printed in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title> on 19
                        February 1803.</note> Your letter made it still worse by shewing me that
                        <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Peter</ref> had either <hi rend="ital">originally</hi> printed this wonderfull piece of news,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The notice also appeared in Peter Gedge’s
                            <title>Bury and Norwich Post</title> in early 1803.</note> or else had
                    made it worse by adding to it what is as false as the Chronicle’s ‘<hi rend="ital">handsome</hi> appointment’ is ridiculous. This story has served
                    the Herald <hi rend="ital">two</hi> days, the first to say I was there, and the
                    next to say I had resignd it!!—tis useless to be angry, but if the Asses that
                    meddle with another mans business before they know it were buried three times as
                    deep as your poor Wife, I would not were [i.e. wear] black for them.—What <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">G</ref> says in his paper is false, thus,
                    because <hi rend="ital">confinement</hi> is not my objection, and I hope and
                    trust that it is well known to the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke</ref>. Extreem publicity
                    begins to be more and more disgusting to my feelings, and these boobys make it
                    worse.—The Good Man at <ref target="places.html#EustonHall">Euston</ref> will be
                    here soon, and then I shall know how I am to proceed. His last letter said that
                        ‘<hi rend="ital">he was sorry I was going to leave it at all</hi>.’
                    circumstances made it absolutely necessary to reply that I would not leave it,
                    at least untill I see him—thus we stand now—<ref target="people.html#JennerEdward">Dr Jenner</ref> is in Town, and has
                    written to me. <ref target="people.html#PerkinsBenjamin">Dr Perkins</ref>
                    plagued me by publishing my name with his Tractors, till I wrote to him to
                    forbid it. my cough plagues me, and I have no time to write down my Rhimes, I
                    have enough on my mind to craze a saint, but I feel my soul soar above it all—I
                    know that I shall triumph—and ‘that Spring will come and Nature smile
                        again’.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield quotes the last
                        line of ‘Autumn’ from his own <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title>.</note> God
                    grant that I could say or do any thing that would give a new spring to your
                    resolution under your present trials—<ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Kitty</ref> must commence Mother with all her might, and I have a high
                    opinion of her sobriety and steadiness. <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">My Mother</ref> need not be uneasy on
                    my account; my troubles are such as I must expect, even with <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">my Boy</ref>, for he never was
                    well long together, Love to all friends, </p><closer><signed rend="right">Robert Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>Robt</p><p>Tuesday Afternoon—The Surgeon says <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">the Boys</ref> Knee is
                        mending. Perhaps the others will soon be well—Sickness is allmost
                        universal.</p></postscript><closer><signed>R B—</signed><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">G. Bloomfield</ref></name></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>