<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.253</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 290–91</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="253" type="letter"><head>253. Robert Bloomfield and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryDaughter">Mary Bloomfield</ref> to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1810-08-05">5 August 1810</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 290–91</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1810-08-05">Aug 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1810</date></dateline><salute>My dear Girl</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">	I am writing on Sunday morning before breakfast. I came from <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> to this place on Tuesday evening and was prevaild on to promise to stay here on the Wednesday; but in the Afternoon of that day an express came from Ipswich to fetch <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> on particular business as a Councellor. <ref target="people.html#LofftSarah">Mrs L</ref> and Miss Finch wanted to go, and here again I was drawn into a fresh scrape, for I had not fulfilld my visit as to time, and so I agreed to go with them, The distance is 26 miles <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L</ref> and I rode on the Dickey, they drive their own Carriage, and hire horses. We arrived there at eleven at night, and returnd on Friday night. Yesterday (Saturday, and the day on which I first proposed to be home) <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr L</ref> walkd with me to <ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref>, there I found your letter, a most wellcome one, as <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> had sent it to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref>. I find them all well, but have not been to <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamCousin">Mr Austins</ref> yet. I am going <hi rend="ital">now</hi> when I have had breakfast, and shall dine at <ref target="people.html#MothersoleMr">Mothersoles</ref> —From this statement you will perceive that I have no news yet as to your proposed visit to Suffolk, I only learn that M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Austins Father being dead, and having left <hi rend="ital">her</hi> part of his property at the disposal of her Husband, has render’d her a more silly and ungovernable devil that before. Their case is a desperate one, and he is much to be pitied. We have dreadful thunder storms allmost dayly, how will you get home?—<ref target="people.html#LofftSarah">Mrs L</ref> has offerd to be my Banker, and I have accordingly sent relief to our fortress in the City Road. When I got to <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> I saw <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> going cross the Angel hill, he was then going to the post Office with his wife’s letter for two pound as Usual!! and yesterday at <ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref> I found that <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> had just written to me in Town, somthing perhaps concerning Mrs Austin. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> set out at 5 in the morning of saturday from London and reachd <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> by ten the next morning! so much for good legs. With respect to my coming round your way I doubt that is now impossible. I never saw Cambridge and [line obscured] there; besides, If you [words obscured] at all, it will not be before I could get to you, which would not be earlier than Friday next, and then we could not reach Town till Tuesday I believe, if this finds you at <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston’s</ref>, you may be sure of my recieving your letter should you write again before Thursday, but not later. You must not expect me in Bedfordshire, And yet should you realy be induced or have allready agree’d to stay till tomorrow week, of course I should find you there if I come; And thinking that you may not be there, I will before starting for home on either road, write to <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston</ref>. Your last letter does you credit, all but in the writing. I will endeavour to see <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldKitty">Aunt Kitty</ref>. And when I have visited the Farmers, will in a day or two return to <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> and go a ‘how d doing’ there, and then write to <ref target="places.html#Shefford">shefford</ref> and then ride home, and then tell you all about it and both then and now I am your Affectionate Father.</p><closer><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>I am glad to find that <ref target="people.html#InskipThomas">Mr Inskip</ref> is still with you. It is so old fashiond to say give my remembrances so; tell them they are two Noble fellows and give my love to Miss W.—</p><p>Dear <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah</ref>, </p><p rend="indent1">	Here is A Letter properly full for you it is from father to you, and as it Came to us first I took the oppertunity of writing a few words, though I have not much to say, except that we are all Very well, and that we Received this letter this morning which is to be sent to you. I am Almost that our juant to suffolk will not be this summer, we hear by the news paper that <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Mr Swans</ref> House is quite Down but the printing office has escaped, the Chickens grow very fast, thats is all so good bye to you your affectionate sister</p><p rend="right"><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryDaughter">Mary</ref></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>