<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.45</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 45–48,
                        extract in BCB, p. 81</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="45" type="letter"><head>45. Messrs <ref target="people.html#VernorThomas">Vernor</ref> and <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Hood</ref> to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Lofft</ref>, copy of a letter not
                    sent, with annotations in Bloomfield's hand, <date when="1800-11-26">26 November
                        1800</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff. 45–48,
                        extract in BCB, p. 81</note></head><opener><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It is an old saying and a true one that wonders will never cease.
                    This reflection is occasioned by seeing your letter to Mr Bloomfield wherein you
                    assert that no right or title in the Farmers Boy belongs to us. — We could
                    hardly think that you was serious in this after all that has pass’d Between you,
                        <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Mr Hill</ref>, and us. But we percieve
                    that you are not given to joke, and therefore we shall think that you mean to
                    consider it seriously as you say. In this situation we are very sorry to say
                    that the Harvest that promised the Author will be blasted by a contest which
                    neither he, any of his friends here, nor us expected. We have no fear of the
                    issue of the contest if it is your determination to persist in it as our proofs
                    are ready to come forward whenever you are pleased to bring it forward. But we
                    are sorry to say that whatever be the issue of it the poor Author will
                    ultimately suffer as wel as us, by the stop that will take place in the sale —
                    for we only wait your determination to guide our conduct. Thus far we assert our
                    property — but, as fair liberal Tradesmen (a character we never have forfeited)
                    we shall reason the matter with <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr
                        Lofft</ref>.——In the first place then is it at all probable that we, or any
                    Bookseller (or <hi rend="ital">Gentleman</hi> we will add) would undertake to
                    print a poem, (which had been handed about to 4 booksellers and offer’d for
                    nothing) &amp; whose merits were not known, (and to this day contested pro
                    &amp; con by the literary world), at the enormous expence of £190 without we
                    had some <hi rend="ital">interest</hi> in it — that we should print it at our
                    own risque, stand the chance of loss, and engage to give the Author 20 guineas
                    [i] whither it succeeded or not, Or that we should put another Edition to press
                    before half the first was sold off (259 Quartos are <hi rend="ital">still</hi>
                    in hand) It is not very probable that a <hi rend="ital">selfish</hi> Bookseller
                    should do this, (which no Gentleman of fortune would have done) when he can
                    every day lay out his money to a good advantage, without risque at all, perhaps
                    not inferior to what we shall get by the Farmer’s Boy. — Thus far it is not
                    reasonable to suppose — Another consideration for <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> is — that the benefit does
                    not arise to the Author from the <hi rend="ital">merit</hi> of the poem merely,
                    but as much so from the merits of the Booksellers, <hi rend="ital">in bringing
                        it forward with every advantage in its favour, of ornaments and printing, of
                        his pushing over England, Scotland, Ireland &amp; America at his own
                        risque and expense and influence</hi>. His selling a large quantity to
                    Ireland at a reduced price (considerably under what he shall account for) in
                    order to prevent it from being printed there, and running away with the market.
                    Of his being oblidged to give credit to the trade to the amount of 11–12ths of
                    the whole (for we have not received above 1/12 in cash for all the Editions)
                    and, of course have several Bankrupts accounts in the Book [ii] — That we should
                    be at this moment £550 out of pocket for a work in which we have no right,
                    (except the first Edition as you say) and only a commission on what we sell,
                    when we could lay out that money with the advantage of 25 or 50 pr cent in our
                    own business — These are ideas that no man acquainted with business would say
                    were any way probable — It is also necessary to inform <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> that the <hi rend="ital">universal custom of trade</hi> is against him. No Bookseller what ever
                    prints another mans property &amp; pays for it <hi rend="ital">himself</hi>
                    upon the meer profits of commission, <hi rend="ital">the Author pays for
                        it,</hi> the Bookseller sells, and pays for what he sells at the end of the
                    year, deducting 10 P Cent for selling. If this does not refer to the first
                    Edition (suposing the copyright out of the case) it must refer to the other
                    agreeable to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>’s ideas — We
                    therefore should not have been presumed to print a second, third and fourth
                    Edition unless we had not been assured that one half of the copyright of the
                    Farmer’s Boy was ours, &amp; no one could expect us to do it.</p><p rend="indent1"> We think it necessary to notice what you say respecting the offer
                    that we made on behalf of another Bookseller (<ref target="people.html#LongmanThomasN">Longmans</ref> and <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref>) we wrote you that a Bookseller
                    would give £100 for <hi rend="ital">Mr Bloomfields copy-right</hi> in the
                    Farmer’s Boy after the second Edition; but you cannot surely from that wrest out
                    a meaning that we considerd the<hi rend="ital"> whole</hi> copyright as his,
                        <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomasN">Longmans</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> will set you right in this respect
                    by informing you of the matter of our conversation — And I have to say that I
                    thought their offer not unworthy of mentioning to you, and I promised them as
                    much as to mention it, although I told them I would not advise it to be sold. </p><p rend="indent1"> Now Sir we will be free to say that after what has been done by
                    us — After giving the Author £100 — which he could not expect or demand, we
                    think ourselves <hi rend="ital">most unhandsomely used</hi> by his friends; for
                    we find that <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Mr Swan</ref> has been rather
                    medling, more than his <hi rend="ital">literary knowledge</hi> gave us reason to
                    expect for however honest a man he may be, we are confident his knowledge of
                    literary bargains cannot entitle his opinion to much consideration. Other
                    friends of the Author were perfectly satisfied with what we had done, we were
                    satisfied in our own minds that we had done only what was right, and the Author
                    was so far satisfied [iii] of it, that he said it was beyond what he had any
                    right to expect, and <ref target="people.html#SwanJames">Mr Swan</ref> was
                    present upon the occasion. — Now Sir, <hi rend="ital">we will maintain our
                        right</hi> as agreed to by the Author, and in the meantime till this is
                    settled, we shall hold ourselves bound to act with the Book as heretofore <hi rend="ital">as one half of our property</hi>, and sell accordingly, as we
                    are unwilling that a worthy man should suffer from an Idle despute Between us. </p><p rend="indent1"> The receipt or assignment which we gave Mr B to copy <hi rend="ital">is a meer matter of form</hi> used by Booksellers in conveying
                    copyright from one to another. We can assure <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> that were the copyright <hi rend="ital">a thousand times</hi> more valuable than it is we should not be
                    guilty of such a piece of <hi rend="ital">Villainy</hi> as he is afraid of and
                    if he will take the trouble to enquire we think that he will find that we have
                    done more than we were oblidged to perform in our engagements with Authors, and
                        <hi rend="ital">never</hi> less — One thing we are determined to do in
                    future, and that is, that we shall have no concern with any Author’s work <hi rend="ital">that is not our own property</hi>. For we find that if we were
                    to give <hi rend="ital">all</hi> there is still some cause for dissatisfaction. </p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> We are Sir </salute><salute rend="indent2"> Your Obed Servants</salute><signed rend="indent7"><ref target="people.html#VernorThomas">Vernor</ref>
                        &amp; <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Hood</ref></signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName>London</placeName></address><date when="1800-11-26"> 26, Nov 1800</date></p><p>[In Bloomfield’s hand]:</p><p>[i] This part of the agreement I never heard of till now. R. Bloomfield</p><p>[ii] An Author situated like myself suffers nothing from Bankrupts, but
                        receives his full share of profits on all Books sold, by his publisher
                        whither they be paid for or not. R.B.</p><p>[iii] Take notice, that at this crisis of the business the question of
                        copyright was not started!! Therefore a <hi rend="ital">Gift</hi> of £100
                        was what I had no right to expect R.B.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>