<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.106</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        121–23</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="106" type="letter"><head>106. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1803-04-17">17 April 1803</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        121–23</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London,</placeName></address><date when="1803-04-17">April 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1803</date></dateline><salute>Dear George </salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I promised you some account of my short excursion to Dorking
                    during the late vacant days of my employment; and I must abridge my plan I
                    perceive before I begin, as I have other letters to write. Having been harrassd
                    by too much thinking and too many trivial engagements, and an employment that I
                    shall never like, I determined that I would respire one mouthfull of real
                    country air if possible and I know at the same time that pollution of smoke
                    reaches ten miles round the Metropolis. I had heard much of Leithe Hills and of
                    Box Hill in the neighbourhood of Dorking. This was the time to see them. I
                    started from the Spread Eagle, GraceChurch Stt. at 3 in the afternoon of Monday
                    and soon rode away from the gay Bonnets and red faces that made a perfect
                    current towards Greenwich. The road is like all others within ten miles of town,
                    much too spruce and too full of inhabitants for my fancy. Epsom is a pretty
                    little town and the country round it open and flat; but 3 or four miles beyond
                    it assumes a quite different aspect, becoming more hilly than I had ever before
                    seen. Remember that I am no Welshman, therefore to me these Hills are Cader
                    Idris’s and Snowdens.—</p><p rend="indent1"> Evening drew on as we approached the old town of Dorking, and the
                    prospect to me was delightful; but to prove that enjoyment is often dashd with a
                    strange and unexpected kind of naucia, we had behind us on the Coach two Lasses,
                    the one going to join the Thunderer on her arrival at Portsmouth from Chatham,
                    and the other to meet a party of Marines passing through Dorking; they drank
                    Brandy all the way, and then work’d off the fumes by songs of a description
                    which were new to me, so that you see that the school of poetry has many stages.
                    I supt and insured a lodging for two nights at the 3 Tons [i.e. Tuns] where the
                    Coach put up, and on Tuesday morning set off with a determination to reach Leith
                    Hill; but though I had a good map of the County in my pocket I took the wrong
                    rout, and as the place of my destination was about 6 miles and my attention and
                    inclination drawn to other and nearer objects I made for the top of a Hill which
                    is planted with about 8 or ten Fir Trees which are very conspicuous at a great
                    distance; this Hill the inhabitants denominate with no small share of pride
                    ‘Dorking’s Glory.’ It affords certainly a most delightfull view on every side;
                    here I could discover that had I kept on nearly in the direction in which I
                    started that I might have passd over Boar Hills to Leith Hills which here appear
                    eminently conspicuous, having a square tower on one summit and being much higher
                    and of greater extant than any other in sight. Being alone and in the pure
                    unadulterated spirit of Idleness and Gratitude mix’d, I cut on an oak bench</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> ‘From the smoke of London free</l><l rend="indent4"> I bless thee, Rural Liberty.’</l></lg><p>Box Hill which I had passd the foregoing evening in the way from town lay
                    southward from ‘Dorkings Glory’ and made a noble appearance but it did not
                    appear to me to be higher than that on which I stood;—</p><p rend="indent1"> Return’d into the town to dinner, which by the by was a poets
                    dinner, Bread and Cheese.</p><p rend="indent1"> Set off again for Leith Hill, many doubts on my mind as to having
                    time for the completion of my design, proceeded in the heat of the day out of
                    the town and kepd winding along the valley with that branch of the River Mole on
                    which Dorking stands, till I found that I was all wrong and all behind—Returnd a
                    little disappointed—but I reflected that as I must at all events return to
                    London next day that I might as well ensure a good ramble over Box Hill before
                    the night came on. I therefore came back through Dorking and crossing the Mole
                    at the bridge on the road leading to Rygate I clim’d up the Hill on its south
                    side; it is composed entirely of chalk and its southern front steep enough to
                    tire any one with a tolerable stock of perseverance: they have contrived to
                    cultivate part of its declivity which I should not suppose would answer
                    ploughing. Box Wood in the greatest abundance grows on its top and Western
                    declivity being planted originally by the Earl of Arundel in the reign of
                    Charles ye 2d—but whither it was planted where it now grows on the west side
                    over the Mole, is to me a curious question, for that whole side is allmost
                    fearfully steep; so much so that it somtimes requires a deviation from the road
                    on the top to be able to gain a sight of the river Mole that runs (I think) most
                    strongly and romantically under the chalky side of the Hill at I know not what
                    distance beneath.—the Hill I have allready said is a premontory of chalk, its
                    west side bending inwards leaving a most charming piece of ground surrounded
                    allmost by the Mole and looking in its highly finishd state the very picture of
                    care and opulence; being the residence of a London merchant named Barclay. to
                    make a woman’s simily, his gravel walks look like a red tape winding on a green
                    ground. We look down on his slate roof and into his Rooks’s nests, and with my
                    pocket glass could see them bear their materials for building: from this
                    charming eminence the southEast of Surry for forty miles is laid open, and
                    southwest, Leith Hills rise with much more effect than from ‘Dorkings Glory’ for
                    this last hill is here seen to be much lower than Leith or Box Hill, and looks
                    like a toy between two men, Box Hill is certainly the glory of Dorking.—</p><p rend="indent1"> Immediately west of it, and on the other side of the valley formd
                    by the Mole, the Hills are as high and are composed of chalk; but they decline
                    nobly towards the meadows, bearing on their tops two fine seats that overlook
                    half the county. One I find belongs to a stock-broker. The whole spot is Hills
                    and dales, the roads in places steep and overhung with wood, in short I can say
                    with certainty the scene is such a one as your Suffolk neighbours are
                    unacquainted with, and such a one as I never saw before. I have no means of
                    judging of its true elevation; I wish I had. but on descending the Hill and
                    passing on the London road which may be somthing less than a quarter of a mile
                    from the Base, I found that the tall trees around the House of Mr Barclay on
                    which the Rooks build, and which may be forty yards from the River and
                    consequently from the foot of the Hill, left over their heads to the top of the
                    Hill nearly 3 times their own height. What height such an angle would give I
                    know not.—At the sign of the Cock a little country pot house at the foot of the
                    Hill on the London road I was tempted by a bench that invited me kindly to sit
                    down, I did so, and drank a pint of Ale. Somthing was rudely painted by way of
                    inscription across the window shutter – I was much pleased to find it contained
                    the following lines which certainly possess some humour, and suited me, and my
                    random expidition to a nicety.</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent6"> ‘probonopublico’</l><l rend="indent4"> ‘To those who cannot summer’s thirst endure</l><l rend="indent4"> Clark’s brown Elixa is a certain cure</l><l rend="indent4"> In winter too some doses are supplied</l><l rend="indent4"> Which may be taken at this fire side;</l><l rend="indent4"> And when the symptoms are not very bad</l><l rend="indent4"> Relieve for twopence only may be had’</l></lg><p>Reachd my lodging at night well pleas’d.—I could not find a Bookshop in the town
                    worthy of the name of a shop. Visited the Churchyard in the morning before the
                    Coach started, found it very full of inscriptions and barren of sence and
                    poetry. Return’d to London very unwillingly; and as I have no Latin to finish
                    with, take English,</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Let me study Law upon Box Hill; </l></lg><p><label>P.S.</label> Remember that the chief and most striking circumstance
                    belonging to the Hill is its sudden declivity. Its entire command of the small
                    river Mole and the beautiful valley beneath. You know richmond, but I prefer the
                    former very much, because it partakes greatly of that quality which I should
                    find, no doubt, in larger Hills is denominated sublime. It is highly worthy of
                    remark that Mr Barclay’s House must for ever be destitute of the Morning Sun.
                    The Fog at seven in the morning hung thick over the Mole; yet the greater part
                    of the low ground was clearing fast, and brightening into sunshine; but in this
                    nook immediately under the Hill, one unbroken mass of Fog cover’d Mr B’s grounds
                    House and Trees completely; not an object could be seen; but far above the
                    morning Sun shot over the ridge of the Hill and illuminated the clouds of fog as
                    they rose; and a brisk gale carried them off in quick succession, forming a
                    striking and truly beautiful appearance. I imagine that the Sun would make his
                    way into this spot by passing the southwest point of the Hill, at about nine in
                    the morning. A boiling Cauldron is no bad comparison in this cave: the Merchant
                    and his paradise were immersed; and could be found only by the means used by
                    Cooks; blowing away the steem. We are told that the Mole runs under ground; but
                    though it is just by Box hill on the London side I had not time to examine it. I
                    promise myself another excursion to Dorking if I have life and Health, and by
                    that time may be able to take draughts.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Yours</salute><signed rend="right">Robert</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>