<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.16</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS
                        28268, ff. 19–23; extract published in Hart, p. 1</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="16" type="letter"><head>16. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1799-09-08">8 September–6 October
                        1799</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS
                        28268, ff. 19–23; extract published in Hart, p. 1</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName>London.</placeName></address><date when="1799-09-08">Sepm y. 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1799</date></dateline><salute>Dear George,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I am very much in your debt with regard to writing. I received
                    your parcell in June, and am every way gratifiy’d and oblidged by its contents;
                    you seem to express so much good will and earnest solicitude about my poetical
                    welfare, that I think it incumbent on me to say a few words on that subject
                    first.——</p><p rend="indent1"> You know that I have naturally (in common with the rest of the
                    family) an inclination for Music, and that I was formerly a beginer in the
                    practice of it; and you likewise know that when I am at work I often indulge
                    myself in whistling and singing; now if I leave off the practical part of music,
                    as I have done years ago; and then again can find something to amuse my mind
                    with as much as by singing, or perhaps more; I reckon it but amusement still.
                        <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">My wife</ref> and I agree that
                    during the two years that I was breeding with Giles<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield’s pet name for <title level="m">The Farmer’s
                            Boy</title> and for his fictionalised younger self, its main
                        character.</note> we got on smoother than before, our girls were both out of
                    hand, our rest was sound, &amp;c, but it unfortunately happened that by the
                    time I was brought to Bed with my Boy, my wife was breeding another;! We some
                    times see a ball of wax with so small a portion of the buoyant quality that it
                    knows not whither to sink or swim; if you put your finger on it when at the
                    surface, it will dive deep and be a long time in rising again; so it was with my
                    Boy <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref>, he dived me
                    into some debts this time twelvemonth, from which I am not yet free, but I have
                    great hopes I shall be free by the end of November. It is true we are none of
                    the shining part of the community. — [three lines deleted] they go to market
                    with the fruit of other people’s labour, and then with a double chalk score it
                    up to their own industry and hard striving; Last midsummer twelfth’s month I was
                    out of debt with respect to rent; I had hired a little house in an alley in Grub
                    Street, (a bad place for a poet) but being disappointed we continued at <ref target="people.html#HortonMr">Horton’s</ref> a year longer, and a groaning,
                    and a long Winter have thrown us behind; this Sumer <ref target="people.html#HortonMr">Horton’s</ref> House was going to be repaird,
                    we left them by consent leaving some rent unpaid, after living there seven years
                    and a quarter, and paying most part of the time seven pound pr year. — We now
                    hired on the spot, a dining room, bed room, kitchen, washhouse, nursery,
                    workshop, &amp;c; that is to say, a large two pair stairs room with two
                    north windows, and one south, at <ref target="places.html#MulberryCourt">No. 1
                        Mulbery Court</ref>, our north prospect is terminated by a high range of
                    chimney pots in Coleman Street buildings, but here is a throrough air (cockney
                    air) and excellent light. All our endeavours are to get clear, and to live
                    happy, and to hope humbly, and thereby blunt the edge of disappointments. —
                    perhaps your Wife when she speaks of ‘doubts that I should be unsettled’ have
                    entertaind notions as to the reputation and profit too; to be coming from my
                    book, such as never can be realized. If you yourself have doubts of my
                    discretion, I know it is from the kindest motives, if it should bring me five
                    pound you would be glad to hear that I had made <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">my Wife</ref> and Children happy.
                    Perhaps after all you only mean, for fear I should slacken my hand now at
                    shoemaking, that I may make poetry the faster; this is a groundless fear: If I
                    had leisure hours I should read, but in this I debar myself as much as I
                    possibly can; the only extravagance I have been guilty of in this way is the
                    purchase of 2 Numbrs. of the ‘Monthly Magazine,’ and I am not a little pleased
                    to find <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref> a well-known
                    correspondent of theirs. ——</p><p rend="indent1"> I suspected <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref> was
                    concerned in the new Review, from his friend saying (the ‘respectable Gentleman
                    in London to whom he had communicated his sentiments respecting the poem’) — he
                    says, ‘I read that part of your letter to Messrs <ref target="people.html#VernorThomas">Vernor</ref> and <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Hood</ref>, my publishers,’ and in <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L’s</ref> letter to you he expressed it,
                    our publishers. — </p><p rend="indent1"> I thank you for the account of <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">Dyer</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George Dyer was an early admirer of <title level="m">The
                            Farmer’s Boy</title> (see Letters 37, 50 and 86), and a friend of
                        Bloomfield’s supporters, Lofft and Granville Sharp, as well as Coleridge and
                        Lamb.</note> Dr. Johnson, I think, is a ‘Thwackum’<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thwackum: Henry Fielding’s <title level="m">The Histroy of
                            Tom Jones</title> (London, 1749).</note> amongst criticks; I allways
                    look at him and his abilities with a mixture of reverence and anger. — </p><p rend="indent1"> I have read Gay’s ‘Trivia;’<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Gay, <title level="m">Trivia: or, the Art of Walking the
                            Streets of London</title> (London, 1716).</note> it decends to minute
                    descriptions of London, more minute than mine do of the country; his minutia
                    must be more subject to change than mine, less dependant on Nature. — </p><p rend="indent1"> From the many letters I have recieved from you on poetical
                    subjects, I find that our taste of those things agrees surprisingly, even to
                    little particulars, I can allways, therefore, speak to you with the confidence
                    of being understood; and when I find you and <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref>, use the same high epithets of
                    praise for my poetry, I am oblidged to believe you, from knowing and observing
                    that though some would read or hear Ramsay’s piece<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Allan Ramsay’s <title level="m">The Gentle Shepherd,
                            A Scots Pastoral Comedy</title> (Edinburgh, 1725); see Letter 15.</note>
                    unmovd, I cannot. — An Ear for Music, and a Voice, are by Nature somtimes given
                    jointly, somtimes separately, and more frequently totally withheld. Dr Johnson
                    was unmoved by the powers of Music, the ‘concord of sweet sounds,’<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Shakespeare, <title level="m">The Merchant of
                            Venice</title>, act 5, scene 1.</note> and yet could write musical
                    poetry! If you feel the same pleasure in reading mine which I and you and all of
                    us feel in reading other poetry, you have a right to use what expressions you
                    please without being accused of flattery. — </p><p rend="indent1"> I often thought of ‘Hail, May,’<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Hail, May’ refers to the opening lines of ‘The Milk-Maid, On
                        The First Of May’, one of the earliest poems Bloomfield had published in a
                        magazine, and included in the preface of the first edition of <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>: ‘Hail, MAY! lovely MAY! how
                        replenish’d my pails!’</note> and whether <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref> would ever see it, and
                    determined not to speak of such things till I was forced; but it is now, with
                    its accompanying information, got into his hands; in the best manner it could
                    have gone; and though I dont think so highly of it as you seem to do, I am
                    convinced it will do me no hurt. — </p><p rend="indent1"> I shall see in what manner the Farmer’s Boy is advertised, not in
                    the papers but on the covers of the monthly publications from that house, the
                    ‘Monthly Mirror,’ ‘Ladies’ Museum,’ &amp;c. — they insert their
                    advertisements in the Chronicle, &amp;c. — Relative to its ornamental part,
                    the Cuts, I send the following from the ‘Monthly Magazine.’ I write this letter
                    at different opportunities; it is now Oct. ye 6th, and I have lent the magazine
                    to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>, which contains my intended
                    extract. It is to this effect, ‘That the art of engraving on Woodden Blocks,
                    which formerly constituted the only ornaments for Books; have lately been
                    revived by the “<ref target="people.html#BewickThomas">Bewicks</ref>” of
                    Newcastle; one of them is dead, but the art is not dead; for we understand that
                        <ref target="people.html#AndersonJohn">a son of Dr. Anderson</ref>, and
                    several other young men have carried the art to very great perfection; their
                    performances rival in brilliancy and spirit the finest productions on copper.
                    Every one acquainted with the trouble and delays of printing with plates of
                    Copper is sensible of the advantages and convenience of this way, as the prints
                    are impressed at the same time with the letter-press.’<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Bewick (1753–1828) and his younger brother John
                        (1760–1795), revived the art of woodcut illustration, with animals, birds
                        and rural scenes their speciality. The Bewicks illustrated editions of poems
                        by Gay and by Goldsmith. Bloomfield admired Thomas’s <title level="m">A
                            General History of Quadrupeds</title> (Newcastle upon Tyne, 1790). Here,
                        Bloomfield is quoting <title level="j">The Monthly Magazine</title>, 8.2
                        (September 1799). <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title> was first
                        published with woodcuts by Thomas Bewick’s former apprentice John Anderson
                        (1775–?). On illustrations of the poem see Bruce Graver, ‘Illustrating
                            <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>’, in <title level="m">Robert
                            Bloomfield: Lyric, Class, and the Romantic Canon</title>, eds. Simon
                        White, John Goodridge and Bridget Keegan (Lewisburg, 2006), 49–69.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Not long after you left London, Buckler; or, as we called him,
                    Buckle, the shoemaker of Pitcher’s Court, impertuned me repeatedly to write out
                    for him my scraps of poetry which had been inserted in the papers, I did it, and
                    I remember that he approvd most ‘an Harvest scene’, in blank verse; but this,
                    and all the rest, but that which you have sent to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref>, I have forgot, and if you have
                    any more by you should be particularly oblig’d to you if you will put your thumb
                    upon them and not let them see the daylight again. Buckle was a poetical
                    enthusiast, he went to America, and I heard that he carried on a roaring trade
                    at New York, but broke during the first visitation of the fever, wrote to
                    Charles Jones since, that he was going to purchase land in the back settlements
                    and turn farmer, since which, accounts have come that he is dead, and left a
                    Wife and 2 or 3 children.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#DillyCharles">Mr. Dilly’s</ref> is nearly opposite to
                    Vernor and Hoods, (perhaps he will rather wonder how I came by the patronage of
                    a critick,) the name of <ref target="people.html#VernorThomas">Vernor</ref> you
                    may perhaps remember in Fore Stt, Between the Castle and the end of Coleman Stt,
                    when we lived at <ref target="people.html#SimmsMr">Syms’s</ref>; he was here
                    only a Bookseller; he moved to Birchin Lane and opend a Circulating Library, and
                    I afterwards found the name of <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Hood</ref>
                    added to his; from hence they moved to their present situation and became
                    publishers; but I see nothing of <ref target="people.html#VernorThomas">Mr
                        Vernor</ref>. I imagine him to be old, for <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref> is the acting partner — he
                    seems about 40, and with what we call a gentlemanlike carriage; he seems
                    naturally good-naturd, and perhaps would have told me more particulars if I had
                    found heart enuff to ask them. I doubt we shall never know who the ‘Respectable
                    Gentleman’ is, to whom <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref> wrote
                    his first sentiments of the poem; I judge it was the same Gentleman who borrowed
                    it to read before it went to the designer and engraver, &amp;c. — <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Thomas Hill</ref>.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> You may perhaps sometimes wish to know whither when it comes out
                    it will be a sudden surprise to my London acquaintance, or whether they know it
                    allready? you may remember I told you that <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr Hood</ref> told me to call again in a month and I should see some of it
                    printed; this was last February. — as <ref target="people.html#HortonMr">Horton</ref> and my shopmates did not recon me close and uncommunicative, I
                    did not like that they should; <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">my
                        wife</ref> and I consulted about it, that as it was to come so soon, we had
                    Better tell them now, and not let them say we were close &amp;c., and
                    perhaps more, that I wanted to cut the greater shine over them; I therefore told
                        <ref target="people.html#HortonMr">Horton</ref>, and he carried it to the
                    Blew Last, and I soon found myself obliged to explain to Robinson, &amp;c.,
                    but, as it has been detaind so long, I have often repented of devulging it at
                    all, as it is, I must take all that follows. — </p><p rend="indent1"> If the piece is really ever so intrinsically good, and my
                    reputation raised by it to public notice, there are thousands who would still
                    cry ‘what do he get by it’ to these ‘lovers of gain,’ gain is the sum total of
                    all other arguments and considerations. To silence those it is no small triumph
                    to me that <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref> has ensured to me
                    half the profits, if profits should arise from it; and if no profits arise, <ref target="people.html#HoodThomas">Mr. Hood</ref> will make a worse job of it
                    than I. </p><p rend="indent1"> It must be obvious to you what a great advantage we gaind, or
                    rather you gaind, by showing the book to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref>. As every book applys itself more or less to the experience and
                    judgment of its readers, so does this, perhaps neither <ref target="people.html#BentWilliam">Mr Bent</ref> nor <ref target="people.html#DillyCharles">Mr Dilly</ref> ever saw a spring morning
                    in the country; or if they did, not with the eyes, and the feelings of <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr. L</ref>, to whom</p><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Say, ye that know, ye who have felt and seen,</l><l rend="indent3"> Spring’s morning smiles, and soul-enlivning green;</l><l rend="indent3"> Say, did you give the thrilling transport way?</l><l rend="indent3"> Did your eye brighten, when young Lambs, at play,</l><l rend="indent3"> Leapd oer your path?’ &amp;c.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Lines 309–313 of ‘Spring’ from <title level="m">The
                                Farmer’s Boy</title>.</note></l></lg><lb/><p>These images being familiar to him gave him patience to read it through, and I
                    consider myself highly indebted to you as well as him — </p><p>I have long promised myself the pleasure of writing to you some notions of mine
                    on ‘Originality of composition’ comparing it with music, and other things, but I
                    shall never find time I doubt to do it, — I sometimes think of a criticism and
                    remarks on some well known songs, &amp;c. proverbial sayings &amp;c at
                    other times I think if you and I was to keep a journal of the weather we might
                    find whither you have more thunder than we. But I have no leisure for any thing
                    but thinking.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have lately been sadly troubled with the Rhumatism and other
                    complaints, I have not been right well since the beginning of August, — We are
                    happy to hear that your affectionate pertner was spar’d for your future comfort,
                    and that of your children, to whom we wish to be mentiond with Love and good
                    wishes</p><closer><signed rend="right">R. Bloomfield — </signed></closer><lb/><postscript><p><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">my Son</ref> looks a very
                        promising boy, but he has got but one tooth, in cutting which he had four
                        very strong fitts, we are apprehensive they may continue, at least with the
                        rest of his teeth</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>