<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.20</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Quoted in the first edition
                        (London, 1800) of The Farmer’s Boy, pp. iii–vii;
                        Capel Lofft’s paraphrases selectively included in square
                    brackets</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="20" type="letter"><head>20. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George Bloomfield</ref> to <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Lofft</ref>, <date when="1800-03-01">before 1 March 1800</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Quoted in the first edition
                        (London, 1800) of <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>, pp. iii–vii;
                        Capel Lofft’s paraphrases selectively included in square
                    brackets</note></head><lb/><p rend="indent1">As I spent five years with the Author, from the time he was
                    thirteen years and a half old till he was turned of eighteen, the most
                    interesting time of life (I mean the time that instruction is acquired, if
                    acquired at all), I think I am able to give a Better account of him than any one
                    can, or than he can of himself: for his Modesty would not let him speak of his
                    Temper, Disposition, or Morals.</p><p rend="indent1"> Robert was the younger Child of George Bloomfield, a Taylor, at
                        <ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref>. His Father died when he
                    was an infant under a year old. His <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref> was a Schoolmistress, and instructed her own Children with the
                    others. He thus learned to read as soon as he learned to speak.</p><p rend="indent1"> Though the <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref>
                    was left a Widow with six small Children, yet with the help of Friends she
                    managed to give each of them a little schooling.</p><p rend="indent1"> Robert was accordingly sent to Mr. Rodwell,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Lofft adds a note: ‘This respectable Man is
                        senior Clerk to the Magistrates of the Hundred of BLACKBOURN, in which
                        Honington is situated, and has conducted himself with great propriety in
                        this and other public employments.’</note> of <ref target="places.html#IxworthThorpe">Ixworth</ref>, to be improved in Writing:
                    but he did not go to that School more than two or three months, nor was ever
                    sent to any other; his <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref>
                    again marrying when Robert was about seven years old.</p><p rend="indent1"> By her second husband, <ref target="people.html#GloverJohn">John
                        Glover</ref>, she had another family.</p><p rend="indent1"> When Robert was not above eleven years old, the late <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamUncle">Mr. W. Austin</ref>, of <ref target="places.html#Sapiston">Sapiston</ref>, took him. And though it is
                    customary for Farmers to pay such Boys only 1s. 6d. per week, yet he generously
                    took him into the house. This relieved his <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref> of any other expence than
                    only of finding him a few things to wear: and this was more than she well knew
                    how to do.</p><p rend="indent1"> She wrote, therefore to me and my brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> (then in London), to assist
                    her; mentioning that he, Robert, was so small of his age that <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamUncle">Mr. Austin</ref> said he was not
                    likely to be able to get his living by hard labour.</p><p rend="indent1"> [Mr. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">G.
                        Bloomfield</ref> on this informed his <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref> that, if she would let him
                    take the Boy with him, he would take him, and teach him to make shoes: and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> promised to clothe him. The
                        <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref>, upon this offer,
                    took coach and came to London, to Mr. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">G. Bloomfield</ref>, with the Boy: for she said, she never should have been
                    happy if she had not put him herself into his hands.]</p><p rend="indent1"> She charged me as I valued a <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother’s</ref> Blessing, to watch over
                    him, to set good Examples for him, and never to forget that he had lost his
                    Father.</p><p rend="indent1"> [Mr. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">G.
                        Bloomfield</ref> then lived at <ref target="people.html#SimmsMr">Mr.
                        Simm’s</ref>, No. 7, Fisher’s-court, <ref target="places.html#BellAlley">Bell-alley</ref>, Coleman-street.] It is customary in such houses as are
                    let to poor people in London, to have light Garrets fit for Mechanics to work
                    in. In the Garret, where we had two turn-up Beds, and five of us worked, I
                    received little Robert.</p><p rend="indent1"> As we were all single Men, Lodgers at a Shilling per week each,
                    our beds were coarse, and all things far from being clean and snug, like what
                    Robert had left at <ref target="places.html#Sapiston">Sapiston</ref>. Robert was
                    our man, to fetch all things to hand. At Noon he fetched our Dinners from the
                    Cook’s Shop: and any one of our fellow workmen that wanted to have any thing
                    fetched in, would send him, and assist in his work and teach him, for a
                    recompense for his trouble.</p><p rend="indent1"> Every day when the Boy from the Public-house came for the pewter
                    pots, and to hear what Porter was wanted, he always brought the yesterday’s
                    Newspaper. The reading of the Paper we had been used to take by turns; but after
                    Robert came, he mostly read for us,... because his time was of least value.</p><p rend="indent1"> He frequently met with words that he was unacquainted with: of
                    this he often complained. I one day happened at a Book-stall to see a small
                    Dictionary, which had been very ill used. I bought it for him for 4d. By the
                    help of this he in little time could read and comprehend the long and beautiful
                    speeches of <ref target="people.html#BurkeEdmund">Burke</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref>, or <ref target="people.html#NorthFrederick">North</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> One Sunday, after an whole day’s stroll in the country, we by
                    accident went into a dissenting Meeting-house in the <ref target="places.html#OldJewry">Old Jewry</ref>, where a Gentleman was
                    lecturing. This Man filled little Robert with astonishment. The House was
                    amazingly crowded with the most genteel people; and though we were forced to
                    stand still in the Aisle, and were much pressed, yet Robert always quickened his
                    steps to get into the Town on a Sunday evening soon enough to attend this
                    Lecture.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Preacher lived somewhere at the West End of the Town... his
                    name was <ref target="people.html#FawcettJoseph">Fawcet</ref>. His language was
                    just such as the Rambler<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title level="m">The Rambler</title> (1750–52) was the magazine with which Samuel
                        Johnson made his name as a critic and rhetorician.</note> is written in; his
                    Action like a person acting a Tragedy; his Discourse rational, and free from the
                    Cant of Methodism.</p><p rend="indent1"> Of him Robert learned to accent what he called <hi rend="ital">hard</hi> words; and otherwise improved himself; and gained the most
                    enlarged notions of Providence.</p><p rend="indent1"> He went sometimes with me to a Debating Society at
                        Coachmaker’s-hall,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Debating societies
                        met at Coachmakers’ Hall throughout the 1780s and early 1790s. See Mary
                        Thale, ‘London Debating Societies in the 1790s’, <title level="j">The
                            Historical Journal</title>, 32.1 (March 1989), 57–86.</note> but not
                    often; and a few times to Covent-garden Theatre. These are all the opportunities
                    he ever has to learn from Public Speakers. As to Books, he had to wade through
                    two or three Folios, an <title level="m">History of England</title>, <title level="m">British Traveller</title>, and a <title level="m">Geography</title>. But he always read them as a task, or to oblige us who
                    bought them. And as they came in sixpenny numbers weekly, he had about as many
                    hours to read as other boys spend in play.</p><p rend="indent1"> I at that time read the <title level="j">London Magazine</title>;
                    and in that work about two sheets were set apart for a Review... Robert seemed
                    always eager to read this Review. Here he could see what the Literary Men were
                    doing, and learn how to judge of the merits of the Works that came out. And I
                    observed that he always looked at the Poet’s Corner. And one day he repeated a
                    Song which he composed to an old tune. I was much surprised that a boy of
                    sixteen should make so smooth verses: so I persuaded him to try whether the
                    Editor of our Paper would give them a place in Poet’s Corner. And he succeeded,
                    and they were printed. And as I forget his other early productions,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">B. C. Bloomfield has identified some of these
                        early magazine verses: ‘A Village Girl’, <title level="j">The Gazetteer and
                            New Daily Advertizer</title> (May 24, 1786), p. 4; ‘An Harvest Scene’,
                            <title level="j">The General Advertizer</title> (October 5, 1786); ‘The
                        Soldier’s Return’, <title level="j">The General Advertizer</title> (November
                        11, 1786). See B. C. Bloomfield, ‘Robert Bloomfield: A Provisional Checklist
                        of His Published Work, with Some Bibliographical Notes and a Record of Later
                        Editions’, in <title level="m">Robert Bloomfield: Lyric, Class, and the
                            Romantic Canon</title>, eds. Simon White, John Goodridge and Bridget
                        Keegan (Lewisburg, 2006), pp. 288–301.</note> I shall copy this.</p><lb/><p rend="indent6"> THE MILK-MAID, </p><p rend="indent5"> ON THE FIRST OF MAY.</p><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Hail, MAY! lovely MAY! how replenish'd my pails!</l><l rend="indent4"> The young Dawn overspreads the East streak'd with gold!</l><l rend="indent3"> My glad heart beats time to the laugh of the Vales,</l><l rend="indent4"> And COLIN'S voice rings through the woods from the fold.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> The Wood to the Mountain submissively bends,</l><l rend="indent4"> Whose blue misty summits first glow with the sun!</l><l rend="indent3"> See thence a gay train by the wild rill descends</l><l rend="indent4"> To join the glad sports:... hark! the tumult's begun.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Be cloudless, ye skies!... Be my Colin but there,</l><l rend="indent4"> Not the dew-spangled bents on the wide level Dale,</l><l rend="indent3"> Nor Morning's first blush can more lovely appear</l><l rend="indent4"> Than his looks, since my wishes I could not conceal.</l><lb/><l rend="indent3"> Swift down the mad dance, while blest health prompts to
                        move,</l><l rend="indent4"> We’ll count joys to come, and exchange Vows of truth;</l><l rend="indent3"> And haply when Age cools the transports of Love,</l><l rend="indent4"> Decry, like good folks, the vain pleasures of youth.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lofft added the following stanza in
                            the Preface to <title level="m">The Farmer’s Boy</title>:<lg><l rend="indent3"> No, no; the remembrance shall ever be dear!</l><l rend="indent4"> At no time LOVE with INNOCENCE ceases to
                                    charm:</l><l rend="indent3"> It is transport in Youth... and it smiles through
                                    the tear,</l><l rend="indent4"> When they feel, in their children, its first soft
                                    alarm.</l></lg></note></l></lg><lb/><p>[...] I remember a little piece which he called the Sailor’s Return: in which he
                    tried to describe the feelings of an honest Tar, who, after a long absence, saw
                    his dear native Village first rising into view. This too obtain’d a place in the
                    Poet’s Corner.</p><p rend="indent1"> And as he was so young it shews some Genius in him, and some
                    Industry, to have acquired so much knowledge of the use of words in so little
                    time. Indeed at this time myself and my fellow workmen in the Garret began to
                    get instructions from him, though not more than sixteen years old.</p><p rend="indent1"> About this time there came a Man to lodge at our Lodgings that
                    was troubled with fits. Robert was so much hurt to see this poor creature drawn
                    into such frightful forms, and to hear his horrid screams, that I was forced to
                    leave the Lodging, We went to Blue Hart-court, <ref target="places.html#BellAlley">Bell-alley</ref>. In our new Garret we found
                    a singular character, James Kay, a native of Dundee. He was a middle-aged man,
                    of a good understanding, and yet a furious Calvinist. He had many books,... and
                    some which he did not value: such as the <title>Seasons</title>, <title>Paradise
                        Lost</title>, and some Novels. These Books he lent to Robert; who spent all
                    his leisure hours in reading the <title>Seasons</title>, which he was now
                    capable of reading. I never heard him give so much praise to any Book as to
                        that.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">James Thomson’s <title level="m">The Seasons</title> (1726–30). For a discussion of the
                        relationship between Bloomfield’s and Thomson’s poems, see John Strachan,
                            ‘“<hi rend="ital">That</hi> is true fame”: A Few Words about Thomson’s
                        Romantic Period Popularity’, <title level="m">James Thomson: Essays for the
                            Tercentenary</title>, ed. Richard Terry (Liverpool, 2000), pp.
                        247–70.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I think it was in the year 1784 that the Question came to be
                    decided Between the journeyman Shoemakers; whether those who had learn’d without
                    serving an Apprenticeship could follow the Trade.</p><p rend="indent1"> The Man by whom Robert and I were employ’d, Mr. Chamberlayne, of
                    Cheapside, took an active part against the lawful Journeymen; and even went so
                    far as to pay off every man that worked for him that had joined their Clubs.
                    This so exasperated the men, that their acting Committee soon looked for <hi rend="ital">unlawful men</hi> (as they called them) among Chamberlayne’s
                    workmen.</p><p rend="indent1"> [They found out little Robert, and threatened to prosecute
                    Chamberlayne for employing him, and to prosecute his Brother, Mr. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">G. Bloomfield</ref>, for teaching him.
                    Chamberlayne requested of the Brother to go on and bring it to a Trial; for that
                    he would defend it; and that neither <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> nor Robert should be hurt.</p><p rend="indent1"> In the mean time <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> was much insulted for having refused to join upon this
                    occasion those who called themselves, exclusively, the <hi rend="ital">Lawful
                        Crafts</hi>. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref>, who
                    says he was never famed for patience, took his pen, and addressed a letter to
                    one of the most active of their Committee-men (a man of very bad character). In
                    this, after stating that he took Robert at his <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother’s</ref> request, he made free as
                    well with the private character of this man as with the views of the
                    Committee.]</p><p>This was very foolish; for it made things worse: but I felt too much to
                    refrain.</p><p rend="indent1"> Robert naturally fond of Peace, and fearful for my personal
                    safety, begged to be suffered to retire from the storm.</p><p rend="indent1"> He came home; and <ref target="people.html#AustinWilliamCousin">Mr. Austin</ref> kindly bade him take his house for his home till he could
                    return to me. And here, with his mind glowing with the fine Descriptions of
                    rural scenery which he found in <hi rend="ital">Thomson’s Seasons</hi>, he again
                    retraced the very fields where first he began to think. Here, free from the
                    smoke, the noise, the contention of the City, he imbibed that Love of rural
                    Simplicity and rural Innocence, which fitted him, in a great degree, to be the
                    writer of such a thing as the <hi rend="ital">Farmer’s Boy</hi>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Here he lived two Months:... at length, as the dispute in the
                    trade still remained undecided, Mr, Dudbridge offered to take Robert Apprentice,
                    to secure him, at all events, from any consequences of the Litigation.</p><p rend="indent1"> [He was bound by Mr. Ingram, of <ref target="places.html#BellAlley">Bell-alley</ref>, to Mr. John Dudbridge. His
                    Brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref> paid five
                    shillings for Robert, by way of form, as a premium. Dudbridge was their
                    Landlord, and a Freeman of the City of London. He acted most honourably, and
                    took no advantage of the power which the Indentures gave him. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George Bloomfield</ref> staid with
                    Robert till he found he could work as expertly as his self.]</p><p rend="indent1"> When I left London he was turned of eighteen; and much of my
                    happiness since has arisen from a constant correspondence which I have held with
                    him.</p><p rend="indent1"> After I left him, he studied Music, and was a good player on the
                    Violin,</p><p rend="indent1"> But as my brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> had married a <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteAunt">Woolwich woman</ref>, it happened that Robert took a fancy to a comely
                    young woman of that Town, whose Father is a boat-builder in the Government yard
                    there. His name is <ref target="people.html#ChurchJoseph">Church</ref>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Soon after he married, Robert told me, in a Letter, that ‘he had
                    sold his Fiddle and got a <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">Wife</ref>’. Like most poor men, he got a <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">wife</ref> first, and had to get
                    household stuff afterward. It took him some years to get out of ready furnished
                    Lodgings. At length, by hard working, &amp;c., he acquired a Bed of his own,
                    and hired the room up one pair of stairs at 14, <ref target="places.html#BellAlley">Bell-alley</ref>, Coleman-Street. The
                    Landlord kindly gave him leave to sit and work in the light Garret, two pair of
                    stairs higher.</p><p rend="indent1"> In this Garret, amid six or seven other workmen, his active Mind
                    employed itself in composing the <title>Farmer’s Boy</title>.</p><p rend="indent1"> In my correspondence I have seen several poetical effusions of
                    his; all of them of a good moral tendency; but which he very likely would think
                    do him little credit: on that account I have not preserved them.</p><p rend="indent1"> Robert is a Ladies Shoemaker, and works for Davies,
                    Lombard-street. He is of a slender make; of about 5 F. 4 I. high; very dark
                    complexion... His <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">Mother</ref>, who is
                    a very religious member of the Church of England, took all the pains she could
                    in his infancy to make him pious: and as his Reason expanded, his love of God
                    and Man increased with it. I never knew his fellow for mildness of temper and
                    Goodness of Disposition. And since I left him, universally is he praised by
                    those who know him best, for the best of Husbands, an indulgent Father, and
                    quiet Neighbour. He is about thirty-two years old, and has three Children.</p><p rend="indent1"> [<ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George</ref>
                    concludes in praying]: ... that God, the Giver of thought, may, as mental light
                    spreads, raise up many who will turn a listening ear, and not despise</p><p rend="indent1"> The short and simple Annals of the Poor.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Line 32 of Thomas Gray’s <title level="m">Elegy in a Country
                            Churchyard</title> (London, 1751).</note></p></div></body></text></TEI>