<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.423</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Suffolk Record Office, Bury St
                        Edmunds 406/2</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="423" type="letter"><head>423. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George Bloomfield</ref> to W.
                    Weston, <date when="1830">[c. 1830]</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Suffolk Record Office, Bury St
                        Edmunds 406/2</note></head><epigraph><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Example <hi rend="ital">draws, where</hi> precept
                            fails</l><l rend="indent4"><hi rend="ital">And</hi> Sermons <hi rend="ital">are less read then</hi>
                            Tales</l></lg><p rend="indent6"> ——————— prior<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Matthew
                            Prior, ‘The Turtle and the Sparrow’ (1725), lines 190–91.</note></p></epigraph><opener><salute>To Mr W Weston<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Presumably the son
                            of Bloomfield’s friend and the family’s supporter Joseph
                        Weston.</note></salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> To say I was pleased with the lines you affixed to <title>Banks
                        of Wye</title> is but faintly to express my feelings. I am astonished at the
                    command of language you possess when I consider your youth; Oh how grateful you
                    ought to be to providence and to your excelant parents for your education!!—the
                    mastery of language may be acquired by <hi rend="ital">Education</hi> but the
                    poets <hi rend="ital">art</hi> canot be <hi rend="ital">taught</hi>. the <hi rend="ital">allusions, Similes</hi>, and all the decorations of poetical
                    composition, can be employ’d but by a few, I could point out 6 or 7 very happy
                    poetical strokes in that little poem (or at least such they appear to me) but I
                    forbear, to you I am an entire stranger you know not but I may wish to <hi rend="ital">praise</hi>, whereas at 3 score and 10 I feel it my Duty to deal
                    in <hi rend="ital">truth</hi> only you have heard no doubt that <hi rend="ital">grey-beards</hi> will prate, I claim the priviledge of a <hi rend="ital">Grey-beard</hi> to be allow’d to advise you to be very <hi rend="ital">cautious</hi> how you indulge your bent for poetical composition I said
                    above how grateful you ought to be to your parents for your Education &amp;c
                    your gratitude ought to evince itself, in your steady, active, persute of <hi rend="ital">Business</hi>, I mean you ought not to let the charms of poesy
                    allure you from what we terms the <hi rend="ital">main chance</hi> I should not
                    have been guilty of such freedom had I not been quite certain you are possessed
                    of poetical powers, <hi rend="ital">The marks are</hi> upon you</p><p>The proverbs of Threescore Affectionately Addrest to Eighteen<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The poem was published in Nathaniel Bloomfield’s
                        volume <title>An Essay on War, in Blank Verse; Honington Green, a Ballad . .
                            . and Other Poems</title> (London: Hurst, Vernor and Hood, 1803), pp.
                        85–88.</note> p85 <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">N
                    Bloomfield</ref>’s poems</p><p rend="indent7"> 1</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Have you seen the delightful abode</l><l rend="indent5"> Where penury nursed despair,</l><l rend="indent4"> Where comfortless life is a load</l><l rend="indent5"> Age wishes no longer to bear?</l><l rend="indent4"> And who in that lazerhouse pent</l><l rend="indent5"> His lone wailings sends up to the skies</l><l rend="indent4"> ’Tis the man whose young prime was misspent</l><l rend="indent5"> ’Tis he that so bitterly sighs</l></lg><lb/><p rend="indent7"> 2</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> His youth, sunk in profligate waste,</l><l rend="indent5"> Left no comforts lifes evening to cheer</l><l rend="indent4"> He must only its bitterness taste</l><l rend="indent5"> No friend no kind relative near</l><l rend="indent4"> The children by want forced to roam,</l><l rend="indent5"> Are aliens wherever they are,</l><l rend="indent4"> They have long left his desolate home,</l><l rend="indent5"> Have left him alone to despair</l></lg><lb/><p rend="indent7"> 3</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Have you seen the delectable place</l><l rend="indent5"> Where honourd age loves to abide</l><l rend="indent4"> With virtue and wisdom reside,</l><l rend="indent5"> Autumns fruits he has carefully stored</l><l rend="indent4"> His herds willing tributes abound</l><l rend="indent5"> By his Childrens children are crown’d</l></lg><lb/><p rend="indent7"> 4</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> And his is the Godlike delight</l><l rend="indent5"> The power to relieve the distressd.</l><l rend="indent4"> Who can contemplate prospects so bright</l><l rend="indent5"> And not wish to be equally blessd,</l><l rend="indent4"> Then let not the means be forgot</l><l rend="indent5"> Remember and mark this great truth</l><l rend="indent4"> ’Twas not chance fix’d his prosperous lot</l><l rend="indent5"> ’Twas the Virtues of provident youth</l></lg><lb/><p rend="indent7"> 5 </p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> If such a bright prospect can charm,</l><l rend="indent5"> If you feel emulation arise</l><l rend="indent4"> If your juvenile bosom is warm</l><l rend="indent5"> With the hope to be wealthy and wise</l><l rend="indent4"> O cherish the noble design</l><l rend="indent5"> The maxims of prudence persue</l><l rend="indent4"> Application and industry join</l><l rend="indent5"> ’Tis the way fickle fortune to woo,</l></lg><lb/><p rend="indent7"> 6</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Early cultivate virtues rich seeds</l><l rend="indent5"> These will fruits in lifes winter display</l><l rend="indent4"> Ne’er defer till to mo-row good deeds</l><l rend="indent5"> That as well might be finished to day</l><l rend="indent4"> For Age and Experience can tell</l><l rend="indent5"> And you’l find when you are an old man</l><l rend="indent4"> Though tis never too late to do well</l><l rend="indent5"> You will wish you had sooner began—</l></lg><p>If Sir, you are tired, (as I dare say you are) of this string of proverbs, I beg
                    leave to say I am not going any farther that way; the proverbs are from a small
                    voloumn of poems, which that excelant man the late <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Mr Peter Gedge</ref> so kindly printed <hi rend="ital">at his own risque</hi> for my Brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nathaniel</ref>; proverbs are very good
                    things in their way, <hi rend="ital">example</hi> is better than precept, a few
                    particulars of my <hi rend="ital">misspent</hi> life I think may warn you, In
                    early life like you I had a great bent for reading soon had read all the Books
                        <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my mother</ref> possessed, it
                    happened we had a relation in the village who had many Books and who took great
                    delight in putting me forward as he termed it,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Perhaps George and Robert’s maternal grandfather Robin Manby
                        who lent the family books including Goldsmith’s <title>The Deserted Village:
                            A Poem</title> (London, 1770) and Gray’s <title>Elegy Written in a
                            Country Church-Yard</title> (London, 1751).</note> there were at that
                    time but two papers read herebouts (ie) the Norwich, and the Ipswich, By
                    constantly seeing the Ipswich I could talk very finely about the first William
                    Pit, Beckford, Sawbridge, John Wilks, Dr Price <ref target="people.html#PriestleyJoseph">Dr Priestly</ref> &amp;c
                        &amp;c<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A list of the principal
                        Whig and radical politicians and writers of the second half of the
                        eighteenth-century. The elder Pitt was the minister who led Britain to
                        success in the Seven Years’ War but who later, ennobled as Lord Chatham,
                        presided over the unpopular refusal to let John Wilkes take the seat in
                        parliament to which he had been elected. Alderman William Beckford was a
                        wealthy plantation owner who, in 1770, when Lord Mayor of London, became a
                        Whig political hero by supporting John Wilkes’s campaign to be allowed to
                        take his seat. Wilkes, journalist, pornographer, campaigner for the
                        extension of the franchise was the centre of popular protest, culminating in
                        London-wide riots, when he was excluded from the House of Commons although
                        elected by a majority. Alderman John Sawbridge, also a Lord Mayor of London,
                        was one of Wilkes’s coterie. Drs Richard Price and Joseph Priestley were
                        Unitarian theologians and political writers who supported Whig campaigns for
                        the reform of parliament and, in 1789, welcomed the French Revolution, both
                        as a model for the revolution they hoped would occur in Britain and as a
                        sign of the coming millennium.</note> In short by the time I was 12 my
                    vanity was wonderously improved, I was apprenticed at Thetford, where I saw <hi rend="ital">both</hi> the papers, and still indulged my favorite persuit,
                    reading all the Books I could borrow, I started off to London as soon as my time
                    came out, and happening to lodge in a family who were Wesleyan Methodists I went
                    with them to their class and prayer meetings &amp;c, I read every thing I
                    could borrow on the subject of <hi rend="ital">Religion</hi>, but curiosity led
                    me to the Tabernacle to hear Witfields preachers roaring away under the banners
                    of <hi rend="ital">Calvin</hi>, tearing the poor <hi rend="ital">Arminians</hi>
                    to rags,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Witfield’s preachers: at the
                        Moorfields Tabernacle, George Whitfield’s (1714–70) Calvinistic Methodists,
                        asserting the doctrine of predestination, attacked the Arminian doctrines of
                        Anglicans and Wesleyan Methodists, who asserted that salvation was possible
                        for any faithful person.</note> and often went to hear the famous Mr Romaine
                    on the same side,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Romaine
                        (1714–95), a leading Anglican evangelical associated, like Whitfield, with
                        the Countess of Huntingdon’s movement. Also like Whitfield, a Calvinist
                        famed for his public preaching in London and beyond.</note> Thus I was
                    plunging in the mists and fogs of Theological controversy, still vainly
                    conceipting I should find it all out, but an accident happened that at once set
                    me free, the Will-with-a-wisp I had been chasing so many years, I now gave up,
                    French America had been conquered, and the great Dispute about the <hi rend="ital">Quebeck Bill</hi> came on, I saw 30000 Methodists march in
                    martial order under Lord Gordon, to try to over awe parliament<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George Gordon led mass protests over the
                        relaxation of laws placing restrictions on Catholics made in the wake of the
                        acquisition of Quebec, with its population of French Catholic colonists. The
                        protests culminated in days of bloody rioting and looting in June
                        1780.</note> &amp;c this <hi rend="ital">intolerant</hi> army disgusted
                    me so I <hi rend="ital">bad</hi> adieu to Methodism of <hi rend="ital">both</hi>
                    sorts for ever,—but it happened I was soon provided with a new <hi rend="ital">Hobby-horse</hi><ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">My mother</ref> brought up to London
                    my Little Brother Bob, who proved an excelant companion to me 10 years younger
                    then my self, yet with as strong prejudices against <hi rend="ital">strange
                        faces</hi> as I had my self, as fond of Books, but his turn for poetry
                    displayed it self, <hi rend="ital">poets corner</hi> in our Dayly paper caught
                    his attention, to indulge him I bought Milton, <ref target="people.html#ThomsonJames">Thompson</ref>, Young<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">George refers to James Thomson’s <title>The
                            Seasons</title> (London, 1726–30) and Edward Young’s <title>Night
                            Thoughts</title> (London, 1741).</note> and many other standard works in
                    short bought, hired, or borrowed every thing I could to oblige him took him to
                    the Theatres when I had money to the debating societys at Coachmakers Hall<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Debating societies met at Coachmakers’
                        Hall throughout the 1780s and early 1790s. See Mary Thale, ‘London Debating
                        Societies in the 1790s’, <title>The Historical Journal</title>, 32.1 (March
                        1989), 57–86.</note> &amp;c &amp;c to Give him a chance of learning
                    to accent words &amp;c but neither my self or him ever learned a rule of
                    grammer, five happy years I spent with him in Garrets in London, I was on the
                    wrong side 30 when I left him, and had not acquired money enough to bring me
                    down to <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref> I stopd at <hi rend="ital">safron Walden</hi> a fortnite, to raise a wind to bring me home,
                    I had now spent the prime of Life from 21 to 30 without bettering my condition,
                    but I hit upon an excelant Expedient to improve my Fortune, I soon met a young
                    woman, we were soon married lived some years in Skiners Lane, had 7 children,
                    the times were then good and we might have still got on as well as our
                    neighbours, but my Brothers in London were <hi rend="ital">poets</hi> and both
                    so shy, <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> never came down attal,
                    have not been here these 40 years, Bob came two or three times but slip’d about
                    so slyly few persons saw him, ad to this they were both extreemly averse to
                    corrisponding <hi rend="ital">except with me</hi>, so that their great friends
                    here applied to me for any information they wish’d for, as those great men the
                        <hi rend="ital">poets</hi> were so extreemly cautious of commiting
                    themselves on <hi rend="ital">paper</hi> I actualy became a corrispondant of
                        <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharles">Sir C Bunbury</ref> Esq and 20
                    others, I do not mean that these persons wrote to me (they did not except <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>) but were often sending
                    queries by servants &amp;c which as I never would be seen if I could help it
                    caused me to lose much time and slur a great deal of beautiful white paper, the
                    private friendship and assistance I received from Bob amply paid me for my loss
                    of time &amp;c. and when they prevailed on me to be a <hi rend="ital">Master</hi> (in that which is now Mrs Armstrong the Hatters shop) my <hi rend="ital">Sheepishness</hi> increased so as to inspissate me, And besides
                    it pleased God to take from me my Excelant wife. The Gentlemen the Great friends
                    of my Brothers rais’d a subscription for me Mr Wright (once Recorder of this
                    Borough) set it of,) <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Mr Gedge</ref>, <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharles">Sir C Bunbury</ref>, <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Lofft</ref> Esq &amp;c joind
                    raised upwards of 30 pounds, still I was wretched, I had lost all my fireside
                    comforts It was soon discovered I was going to marry a young widow with 4
                    childrens!! And as I had 5 we had 9 to begin the world with, this imprudent step
                    displeased some of my great friends, But Mr Smith <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharles">Sir C Bunbury</ref>, <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Mr gedge</ref> and many others continued to
                    be my Benefactors while they lived. In my second marriage I have had 3 children,
                    have (to late) been brought to my senses, In the 20 years that have past in my
                    present marriage I have seen most of my Brothers great friends removed by Death,
                    it is one of the great trials of those who live to be old, they outlive those
                    they love, and those who were able and wiling to help in Time of Need, were that
                    excelant man <ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Mr Gedge</ref> or William
                    Smith Esq <ref target="people.html#BunburyCharles">Sir C bunbury</ref>, Sir C
                    Davers, <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Lofft</ref> &amp;c now
                    alive old age would to me be disarmed of half its terrors here are none to blame
                    or to accuse, it is the lot of all the aged to out live their friends and
                    benefactors, I am truly grateful to kind providence, still <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesBury">Charles Bloomfield</ref> Esq
                    lives, a man who did not know there were such a man as me in the world, who on
                    my Brothers account have been my sure protector and unwearied Benifactor for 30
                    years, but for whome I must have been in a workhouse years ago; still how
                    precarious is my condition should providence remove him though Mr Hasted and
                    other Gentlemen have often befriended me yet I am at this instant, a poor feeble
                    old man <hi rend="ital">allmost</hi> wholly dependant on Charity, I have Grand
                    Children whom I dearly love often nearly naked and bearfoot, and have not the
                    power to help them, And my Self in rags, for though I have clothes given me, my
                    necessities send them up the <hi rend="ital">Spout</hi>, my natural Shyness
                    makes me a recluse, for squallid poverty soon pall the beholder, and seldom do I
                    have a second visit from any one unless it is Brassy faced pretenders to poesy,
                    such as <hi rend="ital"><ref target="people.html#ServiceDavid">David Service</ref></hi><hi rend="ital"><ref target="people.html#PrestonEdward">Ned Preston</ref></hi> &amp;c &amp;c who would willingly count up how many patches are on
                    my old <hi rend="ital">Breeches</hi> (I beg pardon) I mean my <hi rend="ital">Small Clothes</hi>,—now had I been wise and prudent from 21 to 50 should I
                    have been a poor Despicable being, without the power of Doing any creature on
                    Earth good!!! I had continued health have not kep’d my bed for a single Day
                    since I had the small pox in the year 1765, was a good workman and found the
                    greatest friendship from the wealthy part of society, my present distresses
                    arrise entirely from my too Eager persute of information, and what did the
                    little superficial knowledge I glanend [sic] avail!! True it gratified my vanity
                    while my Brothers lived, with whom I corrisponded, (I never had other <hi rend="ital">confidential</hi> correspondents than them) <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> &amp; Bob are
                    Dead, And poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> is near my own
                    Age, O how Vain appears to me, now the waste of time, the waste of Lifes prime,
                    to acquire that which is altogether Vanity my mind I hope is prepared, though I
                        <hi rend="ital">feel</hi> my present Dificulties like a man, I hope to <hi rend="ital">bear</hi> them like a man, I have no other motive for mentioning
                    them, then as a hint to you to avoid my folly, I am aware of the Dissimilarity
                    of the cases, you have been bless’d with <hi rend="ital">education</hi> and have
                    a prospect of succeeding to property I was born at the bottom of the <hi rend="ital">Lowest</hi> class of Society, Fielding had a curious
                    Classification of Society, but allowed it was Dificult to Distinguish the <hi rend="ital">top</hi> of the bottom class, from the <hi rend="ital">bottom</hi> of the top class,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        passage to which Bloomfield refers occurs in Book 2, Chapter 13 of Henry
                        Fielding’s <title>Joseph Andrews</title> (London, 1742), ‘A Dissertation
                        concerning high People and low People. . .’: ‘these two Parties, especially
                        those bordering nearly on each other, to-wit the lowest of the High, and the
                        highest of the Low, often change their Parties according to Place and Time;
                        for those who are People of Fashion in one place, are often People of no
                        Fashion in another’.</note> but it is easy to see the distinctions in our
                    case I have stated that I have no doubt on my mind but you are one of those
                    Distinguished minds that we disignate a <hi rend="ital">Genius</hi> I suppose
                    because we have no terme that will suit better, thus we call Cowper A <hi rend="ital">Genius,</hi> he could not succeed as a man of Business, But
                    shone as A <hi rend="ital">Genius</hi>, And I believe it is a prevelent oppinion
                    that men of Genius are impressed by their leading propensity into a particular
                    persute, <hi rend="ital">disregarding</hi> their worldly Interest For instance
                    Lord Byron declares my unfortunate Brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> A <hi rend="ital">madman</hi>,
                    now there is doubtless A cause for this malignant Censure of his Lordship, <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> published but one small Voloumn
                    wheras <hi rend="ital"><ref target="people.html#ServiceDavid">David Service</ref></hi>, <hi rend="ital"><ref target="people.html#PrestonEdward">Ned Preston</ref></hi>, <hi rend="ital"><ref target="people.html#HollowayWilliam">Holloway</ref></hi>, <hi rend="ital"><ref target="people.html#PrattSamuel">Pratt</ref></hi> and 50 others he never censured at all though they published 10 times more
                    than <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> did of whom he thus
                    express himself:</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> ‘Him to the mania not the muse has seized</l><l rend="indent4"> Not inspiration, but a Mind diseased’<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron, <title>English Bards and Scotch
                                Reviewers</title> (London, 1809), lines 765–94. <lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> When some brisk youth, the tenant of a stall, </l><l rend="indent3"> Employs a pen less pointed than his awl, </l><l rend="indent3"> Leaves his snug shop, forsakes his store of
                                    shoes, </l><l rend="indent3"> St. Crispin quits, and cobbles for the muse, </l><l rend="indent3"> Heavens! how the vulgar stare! how crowds
                                    applaud! </l><l rend="indent3"> How ladies read, and literati laud!</l><l rend="indent3"> If chance some wicked wag should pass his jest, </l><l rend="indent3"> ’Tis sheer ill-nature—don’t the world know best? </l><l rend="indent3"> Genius must guide when wits admire the rhyme, </l><l rend="indent3"> And Capel Lofft declares ’tis quite sublime. </l><l rend="indent3"> Here, then, ye happy sons of needless trade!</l><l rend="indent3"> Swains! quit the plough, resign the useless
                                    spade!</l><l rend="indent3"> Lo! Burns and Bloomfield, nay, a greater far, </l><l rend="indent3"> Gifford was born beneath an adverse star, </l><l rend="indent3"> Forsook the labours of a servile state, </l><l rend="indent3"> Stemm’d the rude storm, and triumph’d over fate; </l><l rend="indent3"> Then why no more? if Phoebus smiled on you, </l><l rend="indent3"> Bloomfield! why not on brother Nathan too? </l><l rend="indent3"> Him too the mania, not the muse, has seized; </l><l rend="indent3"> Not inspiration, but a mind diseased; </l><l rend="indent3"> And now no boor can seek his last abode, </l><l rend="indent3"> No common be enclosed without an ode. </l><l rend="indent3"> Oh! since increased refinement deigns to smile </l><l rend="indent3"> On Britain’s sons, and bless our genial isle, </l><l rend="indent3"> Let poesy go forth, pervade the whole, </l><l rend="indent3"> Alike the rustic, and mechanic soul! </l><l rend="indent3"> Ye tuneful cobblers! still your notes prolong, </l><l rend="indent3"> Compose at once a slipper and a song; </l><l rend="indent3"> So shall the fair your handywork peruse,</l><l rend="indent3"> Your sonnets sure shall please—perhaps your
                                    shoes. </l></lg>Byron added a footnote on Nathaniel’s poem: ‘See Nathaniel
                            Bloomfield’s ode, elegy, or whatever he or any one else chooses to call
                            it, on the enclosure of “Honington Green.”’ See <ref target="../HTML/elegy.html">here</ref> for the text of ‘Honington
                            Green’.</note></l></lg><p>As <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> wrote against <hi rend="ital">Common Stealing</hi> at the time that Common Stealing was all
                    the rage, how probable it is, the Noble Lords family had acquired some Thousand
                    Acres of Land in that way, consequently he would feel sore, Honington Green is
                    most severe upon Common Stealers,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">By
                        ‘Common stealing’ George refers to the enclosure of common land. Nathaniel
                        Bloomfield’s, ‘Elegy on the Enclosure of Honington Green’ was published in
                            <title>An Essay on War, in Blank Verse; Honington Green, a Ballad . . .
                            and Other Poems</title> (London, 1803).</note> Miss Quince the Lady who
                    enclosed the spot into her Croft actually scolded <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref>,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Miss Quince, the encloser in this case, probably resented
                        Lofft because he wrote the preface to Nat’s volume, extolling the virtues of
                        his anti-enclosure poem.</note><ref target="people.html#GedgePeter">Mr P Gedge</ref> &amp;c she actually
                    placed the Voloumn on the little shelf in the Garden privy to be reserved for
                    very <hi rend="ital">particular</hi> occasions would it not naturally appear to
                    the Noble Lord a species of Madness in <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> to censure so unmercifully that very Class of Society who alone
                    possess wealth sufficient to promote the sale of such works of amusement to any
                    extent!!—Again poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> blundered
                    upon a theme which led him to <hi rend="ital">advocate</hi> the Christian
                    Religion!!—In his <title><ref target="../HTML/culprit.html">Culprit</ref></title>, p 51</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Yea who the lore of distant climes</l><l rend="indent5"> Canvas, latent truth to find</l><l rend="indent4"> Who hail our philosophic times</l><l rend="indent5"> And mans emancipated mind</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Oh ye who boast the enlightened age</l><l rend="indent5"> Who boast your right of thinking free,</l><l rend="indent4"> If ere ye learn the lessons sage,</l><l rend="indent5"> Taught in Afflictions school like me,</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> Should you ere a Culprit stand,</l><l rend="indent5"> You’ll wish mankind all christians then,</l><l rend="indent4"> If ere you raise the Culprits hand</l><l rend="indent5"> You’l wish the Jurors Christian Men</l></lg><p rend="indent9"> Culprit p 51<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The
                        Culprit’ also appears in Nathaniel’s <title>An Essay on War, in Blank Verse;
                            Honington Green, a Ballad . . . and Other Poems</title> (London: Hurst,
                        Vernor and Hood, 1803), pp. 43–59.</note></p><p>Now though this is I think perfectly in character in the Culprit, yet certain it
                    is, that to plead for any <hi rend="ital">particular</hi> Religion is esteemed
                        <hi rend="ital">Vulgarism</hi> A publication that treats of the veneration
                    and piety that all Religions <hi rend="ital">profess</hi> to feel towards the
                        <hi rend="ital">Supreme Being</hi>, will pass, but not when we Descend to
                    particulars,—</p><p>Some 60 years ago there were some young Gentlemen at Oxford who used to meet in
                    their Rooms to expound the Scriptures to sing psalms and pray &amp;c
                    &amp;c, now this seems to be harmless But they were admonished by the higher
                    powers in the university to desist, and as they still continued the practice
                    they were at length expelled the university!!! This gave rise to A well written
                    pamphlet called <hi rend="ital">The Shaver</hi>—this shews that the <hi rend="ital">great</hi> World disapprove of what they sneeringly terme <hi rend="ital">enthusiasm Methodism</hi> &amp;c &amp;c,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">George refers to the trial and expulsion of
                        so-called ‘Methodistical’ evangelical students from St Edmund Hall, Oxford
                        in 1768. The students were sons of tradesmen, rather than gentlemen, and
                        they were defended in the press by George Whitfield and by Baptist minister
                        John Macgowan, ‘the Shaver’, whose satirical pamphlet <title>Priestcraft
                            Defended</title> saw 25 editions and was being re-printed as late as
                        1813.</note> There is a Gentleman at Great Gransden Vicarage, the <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Revd Mr Plumtre</ref>, This Gentleman
                    took unusual pains to get my Brother Bob from his retirement thinking that his
                    health sufferd from the confinement: he often wrote to Bob inviting him to
                    Gransden, take his house for his home and breath the free Air &amp;c
                    &amp;c but could not draw him from <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref>, but <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr P</ref> is
                    not a man that give up a point easily, he visited Bob at <ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref> and contrived to get a promise
                    from him to go to Gransden &amp;c poor Bob though in bad health and low
                    spirits felt compeld to keep his word, he visited <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr P</ref>, and while he staid slep’d in
                    a chamber at the corner of the house, <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr
                        P</ref> gave the Room the name of <hi rend="ital">poets corner</hi> and it
                    will long retain that Name, Bobs account of this parson to me is that he
                    appear’d to him, the best of human beings, so kind, so charitable, and so every
                    way amiable, I was charmed with the picture, when Bob sent me <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr Ps</ref> works to read, I thought them
                    excelant, I mentioned them to a gentleman who has been very kind to me, the
                    gentleman seemd to be acurately acquainted with the parsons manner of writing,
                    But said <hi rend="ital">he is a Methodist</hi>, told me a tale, of how a young
                        <hi rend="ital">Cantab</hi> affronted <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr P</ref>, <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr Plumtre</ref> sent a voloumn of his,
                    as a present to a young student at Cambridge, the youth instead of reading it
                    wrote on the cover and returned it unopened</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent4"> There was an Old Woman Lived at Dundee</l><l rend="indent4"> Out of her B-tt-m there grew a plumbtree</l></lg><p>Now I cannot conceive a more gross vulgar and unfeeling insult than this, or one
                    that could more deserve to be phisiced with a stout crab-stick, to such usage
                        <ref target="people.html#PlumptreJames">Mr P</ref> is exposed for advocating
                    the Christian religion!!—and it ought to be a warning to those who do not wish
                    to offend the <hi rend="ital">great</hi> world, it is the <hi rend="ital">great</hi> world that are the <hi rend="ital">masters</hi> of the Great
                    Booksellers in London, and those booksellers are the <hi rend="ital">masters</hi> and commanders of the Critics from the Great London packs;
                    down to the little country kennels,</p><p>As Sir, I consider you as a youth of real genius, consequently think it probable
                    you will be led on from little to much, I therefore think poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nats</ref> failure may lead you to be
                    very cautious in the choice of your themes &amp;c for as it is the <hi rend="ital">great</hi> world who alone can <hi rend="ital">pay</hi> for
                    Books a writer should avoid as much as he can giving them unnecessary
                    offence.</p><p>Poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> was very unfortunate in
                    his choice of subjects to write upon, his <ref target="../HTML/lovestriumph.html">Loves Triumph</ref><note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Love’s Triumph’: another poem from
                        Nathaniel’s <title>An Essay on War, in Blank Verse; Honington Green, a
                            Ballad . . . and Other Poems</title> (London, 1803).</note> make <hi rend="ital">Love</hi> and <hi rend="ital">poverty</hi> despise wealth and
                    the wealthy mans grandure &amp;c and even his <ref target="../HTML/essayonwar.html"><hi rend="ital">essay</hi> on <hi rend="ital">War</hi></ref><note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The increase of population is discussed
                        in Nathaniel’s ‘Essay on War’ from <title>An Essay on War, in Blank Verse;
                            Honington Green, a Ballad . . . and Other Poems</title> (London,
                        1803).</note> is conducted on what was then believed to be a false principle
                    (ie) he maintained that the population of the country was too Great!! Hence war
                    is a <hi rend="ital">necessary</hi> evil &amp;c Goldsmith makes his vicar of
                    Wakefield say... when I look round on my Children, all blooming around me, I
                    consider my Country my deptor, for presenting it with such a present!! Goldsmith
                    makes the parson urge the lads and lasses to early marriage., The notion that in
                    the <hi rend="ital">population of a state, consisted its wealth</hi>, writers of
                    all descriptions entertained this idea 50 years ago, when <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">nat</ref> wrote the Idea was still in
                    fashion consequently he offended the <hi rend="ital">great</hi> World by what
                    their packs of critics stiled <hi rend="ital">ignorance</hi> of the
                        subject,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The Revd. Thomas Malthus’s
                            <title>Essay on the Principle of Population</title>, first published in
                        1798 and repeatedly reworked over the next twenty years, gradually changed
                        the climate of opinion and persuaded the public and parliament that
                        population was in fact too large and becoming larger. Previously, the
                        position espoused by Oliver Goldsmith in chapter one of his 1766 novel
                            <title>The Vicar of Wakefield</title> was the norm—and William Pitt, as
                        Prime Minister, had been concerned to introduce measures tending to increase
                        national population.</note> I wish Dear Sir, if (as I think you will) you
                    should be forced by your Genius into a serious attempt at poetry, you may study
                    to give as little offence to the great world as possible, and with unfeigned
                    wishes for your health and prosperity, remain yours <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">Geo Bloomfield</ref></p><p><label>P.S.</label> If Sir you ever find time or patience to read my long long
                    scrawl, you will find my advice is <hi rend="ital">not</hi> to follow the
                    allurements of poesy, to the detriment of business &amp;c there are
                    circumstances in my family which if known to youth, might teach them caution,
                    there are other things besides the <hi rend="ital">leading</hi> foly, that may
                    be injurious to a man, thus it happen’d that the late <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke of Grafton</ref> was prime
                    minister, I loved and revered the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke</ref>, many a day I followed
                    on foot after the good <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke</ref> and his hounds, and when Junius<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Junius: the Whig pamphleteer, whose real identity has never
                        been determined, who attacked the Duke of Grafton and others in his
                        ministry.</note> and 50 others abused him I felt as much as if he had been
                    my father, hence arrose my mad attachment to political reading hence my Brothers
                    laughing stiled me the politician &amp; but I too had a second <hi rend="ital">hobby</hi> my Brothers and Sisters were all <hi rend="ital">Song-smiths</hi> all wrote occasional Verses on particular occasions and I
                    too you may laugh if you will, wrote Verses for the Universal, the London, and
                    the Mirror Mag<hi rend="sup">ns</hi><note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">George Bloomfield’s poems ‘Lines to a
                        Young Woman’ and ‘Quatduorzain to the new-born Daughter of Capel Lofft Esq.’
                        appeared in <title>The Monthly Mirror</title>, 15 (1803), 50 and 413.</note>
                    and have sometimes actually received the <hi rend="ital">thanks</hi> of the
                    editors, but I assure you on the Veracity of an Historian I never got any thing
                    more (a forlorn trade this) how many hours of valuable time in Lifes prime have
                    I misspent, and besides I was allways rhyming on passing local occurrences
                    &amp;c this brought me a notoreity that often gave me pain, as people choose
                    to see me, and like all my family I had an avertion to <hi rend="ital">strange
                        faces</hi> But I never had patience or talents to attempt seriously at
                    poetical compositions or to write any but short pieces, this turn of mine have
                    when I least expected it, and when I most wanted it, been beneficial to me, I
                    had left Thetford more then 50 years, but I love the old Town some are still
                    living there rememberd me, and when the Spa was discovered, I was sent for to
                    the Angel here at <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>, <ref target="people.html#FauxJames">J Burrell Faux</ref> Esq was there, he told
                    me in few words, if I wrote a few verses, he would endeavour to get them
                    printed, promote their sale &amp;c he had with him a jolly man the picture
                    of good nature, I have found out since it was Mr Smith the printer from
                    Cambridge the Gentleman who so charitably printed <ref target="../HTML/thetford.html">my lines on the Spa</ref>,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">George refers to his <title>Thetford Chalybeate
                            Spa. A Poem by a Parishioner of St. Peter’s</title> (Cambridge,
                        1820).</note> but I dared not let my Name appear, I remembered too well how
                    the Dogs of Critics worried poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> from first to last <ref target="people.html#FauxJames">Mr
                        Faux</ref> sold so many I reciev’d upwards of 40 pounds in my years of old
                    age which was a great blessing to me while it lasted,: John Wright Esq of
                    Kilverston Hall<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The Wrights of
                        Kilverstone Hall, Thetford, Norfolk were an ancient and powerful local
                        landowning dynasty: it would have been in their interest to have a
                        labouring-class writer lament the rick-burning by which starving rural
                        labourers were protesting at the price of grain (kept artificially high by
                        the interest of landowners in Parliament).</note> in 1822 advised me to
                    write some <ref target="../HTML/friendlyhints.html">verses on stack burning
                        &amp;c</ref><note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">George’s verses on rick-burning were
                        issued as a broadside ‘Friendly Hints Affectionately Addressed, by an Old
                        Man to the Labouring Poor of Suffolk and Norfolk’.</note> this brought me
                    considerable benefit. Mr Dutton like Mr Smith had the charity to print them
                    gratis I inclose you coppys not because of any merit in them but to shew how
                    kind these gentlemen have been to me—as you see my <hi rend="ital">Dapper
                        hobby</hi> by <hi rend="ital">accident</hi> brought me profit while my great
                    hobby had brought me rags for <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>
                    the next brother to me whose great leading hobby was poetical composition was
                    hunted down by the dogs of critics and his 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> poney was as
                    unprofitable he studied machinery, invented a horse, the riders weight was to
                    have impeld it along, but as this horse would never move I can give no account
                    of his movements, poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> the next Brother (a bricklayer) lived at <ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref>, his great hobby was music,
                    he wrote music to a great variety of songs, he published 12 anthems and cleard
                    15 or 16 pounds profit, he to had a second hobby he invented a self-working pump
                    this hobby he studied for 7 years, <ref target="people.html#BoysJohn">Mr
                        Boys</ref>, (a gentleman in London) advanced him 10 pounds to go on with,
                    and an ingenious smith, Mr Burrell of Thetford assisted him, <ref target="people.html#BoysJohn">Mr Boys</ref> advanced him a second 10 pounds,
                    and he made 2 journeys to London on the business, but died suddenly and left it
                    unfinished,!!—It happened luckily for us all that Bob too my youngest Brother
                    had his hoby, descriptive poetry was his grand <hi rend="ital">hobby</hi> but to
                    read of the Drama, &amp;c Dramatist &amp; was his and he was at the
                    expense of reading Hunts Examiner<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Leigh
                        and John Hunt’s <title>Examiner</title> (1808–21) featured regular articles
                        on contemporary and Shakespearian drama.</note> for that sole purpose, so
                    that we had [MS ends, remaining sheets lost]</p></div></body></text></TEI>