<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.302a</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS in private hands. Published by permission of the owner. The editors thank Angus
                  Whitehead for bringing this letter to light: see Whitehead, ‘“A relish for hedge-row poetry”:a newly discovered letter from Robert
                  Bloomfield to Sir Charles Bunbury’, Notes and Queries, 61 (2014), 76–80.</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="302a" type="letter"><head>302a. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BrydgesSamuelEgerton">Sir Samuel Egerton Brydges</ref>, <date when="1816-06-12">12 June 1816</date><note place="foot" type="headnote" resp="editors">MS in private hands. Published by permission of the owner. The editors thank Angus
                  Whitehead for bringing this letter to light: see Whitehead, ‘“A relish for hedge-row poetry”:a newly discovered letter from Robert
                  Bloomfield to Sir Charles Bunbury’, <title>Notes and Queries</title>, 61 (2014), 76–80.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName>Shefford. Bedd’s</placeName></address><date when="1816-06-12">June 12 1816</date></dateline><salute>To Sir Egerton Brydges, Bart</salute><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">Perhaps I greatly presume when I thus address you by letter, but you are strictly and truly a litterary Character, and
               love poetry. This is quite enough for me to know at present, and the attentions you have formerly bestow’d upon me are at the same time
               not forgotten. <note n="1" resp="editors"> place="foot"&gt;For Brydges’ services to Bloomfield, literary and financial, see Letters 236,
                  303 and 317.</note></p><p rend="indent1">My Suffolk friends after hearing of some of my misfortunes, and my very precarious health, have, for a third time,
               seemingly determined to assist me by some means or other, and the last and best determination is, to publish for my benefit a
               subscription Edition of <hi rend="ital">all that I have written</hi>, in a splendid way, to bear the price of 2 Guineas! <note n="2" resp="editors"> place="foot"&gt;See Letters 301 and 302 for further details of this scheme, which did not find sufficient subscribers
                  to come to fruition. Brydges then launched a plain subscription for Bloomfield’s relief, with no luxury edition promised, and
                  personally helped Bloomfield with money. See Letters 303, 304 and 305. After Bloomfield’s death, his daughter again appealed to
                  Brydges for assistance, but he had by then left Britain to escape his creditors: see Letter 305.</note> Publick notice of this
               undertaking will soon be given; but in the interem, and as a previous step, I am calld upon to sound my friends, for the purpose of
               giving my Booksellers, Messrs <ref target="people.html#BaldwinRobert">Baldwin</ref> Craddock &amp; Joy, some idea of the probable
               success and extent of the undertaking.</p><p rend="indent1">With this short view of the subject Sir, and impertinent as it may appear, I venture to ask for your name, and
               <del>xxxx</del> the names of your friends who have a relish for hedge-row poetry, <note n="3" resp="editors"> place="foot"&gt;Angus Whitehead observes of this
                  phrase that it appears to be Bloomfield’s self-deprecating coinage, though the <title>OED</title> defines ‘hedge-poet’ as a poet
                  ‘born, brought up, habitually sleeping, sheltering or plying their trade under hedges, or by the road-side (and hence used generally
                  as an attribute expressing contempt)’. See Whitehead, ‘“A relish for hedge-row poetry”:a newly discovered letter from Robert
                  Bloomfield to Sir Charles Bunbury’, <title>Notes and Queries</title>, 61 (2014), 76–80 (p. 80).</note> and I want more particularly
               to hear if you approve of such a plan, and how many names you may be able to collect by the end of this month, &amp; when, if you will
               honour me with an answer, or send your reply through my friend <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">T. Park</ref> Esq. of Hampstead, I
               shall feel greatly obliged, for I am far from well, as my writing too plainly shows. </p><p rend="indent1">Persons and places will be appointed where money will be received—I have now no power to recieve any thing but
               names,—but of these, the more, and the more honourable, the greater will be the glory to those who have started the measure, and who
               claim me as their Countryman. . .</p><closer><salute>With Grt Respect I am Sir your most</salute><salute rend="indent1">Humble serv<hi rend="sup">t</hi></salute><signed rend="indent3">Rob<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bloomfield.</signed></closer><postscript><p>In all likelihood names will be recieved untill September at least, but this &lt;present&gt; is a previous measure.—No more copies
                  will be printed than are actually subscribed for.—I write now to <ref target="people.html#JennerEdward">Dr Jenner</ref>, and other
                  Gloucestershire friends—to the ‘Good <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Fitzroy</ref>’ family, and to all I can muster.
                  Mr Park is in some degree apprised of the affair, and my neighbour Sir George Osborn, and Lady, <note n="4" resp="editors">
                     place="foot"&gt;Sir George Osborne (1742–1818), 4th Baronet of Chicksands Priory, near Shefford, Bedfordshire, and his wife Heneage,
                     née Finch (1741–1820).</note> are my sure friends. <del>xxxx</del></p><p>R.B.</p><p>I have this fair opportunity of returning thanks for your prompt and kind reply to my Dover request when I wanted to see the
                  Heights, and the Castle. I saw Mr Fector, and was not dissappointed in any thing but time. <note n="5" resp="editors" place="foot">See Letter 290, 14 June 1814, in which Bloomfield describes how a letter of introduction from Brydges enabled him to
                     gain from John Minet Fector, a Dover banker and later MP, a pass to the Heights and Citadel that formed part of the fortified
                     cliffs. Bloomfield had hoped he might be introduced to the Tsar Alexander, one of the European monarchs who had arrived in Dover
                     en route to the celebrations, in London, of the abdication of Napoleon.</note></p></postscript><closer><address><addrLine><rs>Address: </rs><name> To/ Sir Egerton Bridges M.P.</name>/ <placeName><del>Hynde St/ Manchester Square/
                  London</del> [in another hand:] &lt;Lee Priory/ near/ Wingham/ Kent&gt;</placeName></addrLine></address><dateline><address><addrLine><rs>Postmark:</rs> Shefford/ Biggleswade/</addrLine></address>address&gt;<date when="1816-06-18">&gt;18 June
                     1816</date></dateline></closer></div></body></text></TEI>