<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.55a</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Tipped in to a copy of George
                        Gordon, Lord Byron, English Bards and Scotch Reviewers: A Satire,
                            vol. II. Illustrated, Collected and Arranged by Arnold Wood. New
                        York: Charles B. Richardson, 1865. This book is located at the James Smith
                        Noel Collection, Louisiana State University in Shreveport.</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="55a" type="letter"><head>55a. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Thomas
                        Hill</ref>, <date when="1801-09-11">11 September 1801</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Tipped in to a copy of George
                        Gordon, Lord Byron, <title>English Bards and Scotch Reviewers: A Satire,
                            vol. II.</title> Illustrated, Collected and Arranged by Arnold Wood. New
                        York: Charles B. Richardson, 1865. This book is located at the James Smith
                        Noel Collection, Louisiana State University in Shreveport.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName>City Road</placeName></address>, <date when="1801-09-11">Sep 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1801</date></dateline><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1">Probably you may have heard of the great loss sustained by your correspondent,
                    and my friend, at <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref>—Mrs Lofft died
                    on Tuesday morning <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Lofft, née
                        Emlyn, married to Capel Lofft since 1778, died on 9 September. Her widower
                        married again in spring 1802.</note> just after a painfull illness.</p><p rend="indent1">In a letter to me by <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> on the
                    preceeding Sunday is this passage; which I thus fully state to you to discharge
                    myself of as much of the request as appears for me to fulfill.—</p><p rend="indent1">‘I mentioned some months back that there was a young man of the name of Hole of
                    whose abilities as a young engraver on wood I had seen some promising specimens,
                    and who would be soon out of his apprenticeship to <ref target="people.html#BewickThomas">Mr Bewick</ref>. The apprenticeship will
                    expire this month. His name is Henry Hole, <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Hole (1782-1852): born in Newcastle, Hole was
                        apprenticed to Bewick from 24 March 1794 until autumn 1801. Hole engraved
                        cuts for the 1808 edition of Felicia Dorothea Browne (later Mrs Hemans),
                            <title>Poems</title>. He retired from the profession on inheriting a
                        landed estate in Derbyshire.</note> a sister of mine was his Godmother. I
                    wish him to come to Town if he could have a safe and beneficial introduction to
                    business. Will you mention this to <ref target="people.html#HillThomas">Mr
                        Hill</ref>, <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Mr Park</ref>, and others
                    of our friends. I think he seems likely to be a modest, sober, and industrious
                    youth, and that he has shown both ingenuity and application. Any reference that
                    might be thought nessisary would, of course be made to Mr Bewick in case there
                    should be an opening where there is so much employment for this art.’</p><p rend="indent1">Mr Lofft did not by his letter of Sunday, seem to think Mrs L in more danger than
                    for some time before, but I yesterday had the statement from his own hand, of
                    her death.—</p><p rend="indent1">If the Poetical department of the Mirror is not overstocked perhaps the following
                    lines would not disgrace it. <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield’s ‘Song for a Highland Drover’ was published in <title>The
                            Monthly Mirror</title>, which Hill edited, in 12 (September 1801),
                        197–98. It was collected in <title>Rural Tales</title>.</note> If my
                    blemishes appear to you, be so kind as return it to me that I may insert it in
                    the pending Vollon, where Mr Lofft expects to see it, as it has his approbation
                    already.</p><p rend="indent1"> Song.</p><p rend="indent1"> For A Highland Drover, returning from England.</p><p rend="indent1"> By Robert Bloomfield, author of the Farmer’s Boy.</p><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> Now fare-thee-well England, no further I’ll roam,</l><l rend="indent3"> But follow my shadow that points the way home;</l><l rend="indent3">Your gray southern shores shall not tempt me to stay,</l><l rend="indent3">For my Maggy’s at home, and my children at play;</l><l rend="indent3">Tis this makes my Bonnet set light on my brow,</l><l rend="indent3">Gives my sorrows their strength, and my bosom its glow.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">Farewell Mountaineers! My companions adieu!.</l><l rend="indent3">Soon, many long miles when I’m severed from you,</l><l rend="indent3">I shall miss your white Horns on the brink of the Bourne,</l><l rend="indent3">And o’er the rough Heaths where you’ll never return;</l><l rend="indent3">But in brave English pastures you cannot complain,</l><l rend="indent3">While your drover speeds back to his Maggy again.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">O <hi rend="ital">Tweed</hi>! gentle <hi rend="ital">Tweed</hi>, as I pass
                        your green vales,</l><l rend="indent3">More than life, more than love, my tired spirit inhales;</l><l rend="indent3">There, <hi rend="ital">Scotland</hi>, my darling lies full in my view, </l><l rend="indent3">With her barefooted Lasses and Mountains so blue;</l><l rend="indent3">To the Mountains away! My heart bounds like the Hind;</l><l rend="indent3">For home is so sweet, and my Maggy so kind.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">As day after day I still follow my course,</l><l rend="indent3">And in fancy trace back every Stream to its source,</l><l rend="indent3">Hope cheers me up Hills, where the road lies before</l><l rend="indent3">O’er Hills just as high, and o’er tracks of wild Moor;</l><l rend="indent3">The keen polar Star nightly rising to view;</l><l rend="indent3">But Maggy’s my Star, just as steady and true.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">O Ghosts of my Fathers! O Heroes, look down;</l><l rend="indent3">Fix my wandering thoughts on your deeds of renown,</l><l rend="indent3">For the glory of <hi rend="ital">Scotland</hi> reigns warm in my breast,</l><l rend="indent3">And fortitude grows both from toil and from rest;</l><l rend="indent3">May your deeds and your worth be for ever in view,</l><l rend="indent3">And may Maggy bear sons not unworthy of you.</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">Love, why do you urge me, so weary and poor?</l><l rend="indent3">I cannot step faster, I cannot do more;</l><l rend="indent3">I’ve pas’d silver <hi rend="ital">Tweed</hi>; e’en the <hi rend="ital">Tay</hi> flows behind:</l><l rend="indent3">Yet fatigue I’ll disdain;--my reward I shall find;</l><l rend="indent3">Thou sweet smile of innocence, thou art my prize,</l><l rend="indent3">And the joy that will sparkle in Maggy’s blue eyes</l></lg><lb/><lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">She’ll watch to the southward; . . . perhaps she will sigh,</l><l rend="indent3">That the way is so long, and the Mountains so high;</l><l rend="indent3">Perhaps some huge Rock in the dusk she may see,</l><l rend="indent3">And will say in her fondness, ‘that surely is he.’!</l><l rend="indent3">Good Wife you’re deceiv’d; I’m still far from my home;</l><l rend="indent3">Go, sleep, my dear Maggy; tomorrow I’ll come.</l></lg><lb/><closer><salute rend="indent1">Your Obedien Servt</salute><signed rend="indent1">Robert Bloomfield.</signed><address><addrLine rend="indent1"><rs>Address:</rs><name>Thos Hill Esq</name></addrLine><addrLine rend="indent2">	No. 7</addrLine><addrLine rend="indent2">	Henrietta St Covent Garden</addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>