<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.268</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        309–310</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="268" type="letter"><head>268. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1811-08-28">28 August 1811</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        309–310</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1811-08-28">Wednesday morning, Aug 28. 1811</date></dateline><salute>My Dear Girls</salute></opener><p> I feel myself unusually well this morning, and I have this moment finishd the
                        Song<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bloomfield was adding words to
                        the melodies given in Hook’s <title>Guida di Musica</title>. The resultant
                        poems were published in the first volume of <title>Remains</title> (pp.
                        51–56). Hook himself set a Bloomfield poem to music: <title>Rosy Hannah, A
                            Much Admired Song, with an Accompaniment, for the Harp or Pianoforte,
                            Composed for Mr. Braham, by Mr. Hook (The Words from Bloomfield’s
                            Poems)</title> (London, [? 1810]).</note> to my liking. (The Book says
                    ‘Allegro’, but to these words it must not be so).</p><p rend="indent6">XIV</p><table cols="3" rows="19" width="740" border="0"><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"><hi rend="ital">Rondo</hi>,</cell><cell width="620">To sleep my dear, to sleep my dear,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">The march is oer, the fight is done,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">To sleep my dear, you need not fear,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">We’re safe, the Field is won. D.C</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620"/></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">Rest thy troubled bosom,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">And rest thy weary head,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">Comrades watch around thee,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">Thy Husband guards thy bed, D.C. To sleep
                            &amp;c.</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620"/></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">No piercing Trumpet</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">Shall tell of death and terrors,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">No thundering Cannon</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">Shall fill thee with dismay; — To sleep &amp;c</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620"/></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">Broad the vanguard shows its front,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">Our brave Commander knows his ground,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">And faintly roll their doubling drums,</cell></row><row><cell width="40"/><cell width="80"/><cell width="620">The conquer’d foe is far away. D.C. To Sleep.</cell></row></table><p>You will perceive the words ‘No piercing Trumpet’ are set to that part of the
                    tune which so much resembles a passage in the Forest song, and on the word
                    dismay I mean you to sing it thus. [Some musical notation] Dis<hi rend="ital">may</hi> must finish on the c. and the 4 notes I have inclosed will be
                    symphony.</p><p> On Monday I waited anxiously for your letter untill One, and then took <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteShot">Charlotte</ref> to <ref target="people.html#ParkThomas">Mr Parks</ref>,—<ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> walkd nobly all the
                    journey with only a small lift up the <hi rend="ital">mountain</hi> on our
                    return from Battle-Bridge to the Belvedere,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Battle-Bridge: the London area now known as King’s Cross; the
                        Belvedere: a pub on the Pentonville Road, London, now called <hi rend="ital">Clockwork</hi>.</note> but I must leave the particulars to themselves,
                    you will find them in a parcel at the begining of the week, which (with money) I
                    will direct for you at <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Loffts</ref>. I
                    write to him now to beg that you may be there on Monday, or sooner. I have
                    mentiond Friday. Therefore, if you have no previous intimation from thence
                    before Friday teatime, I advise you by all means to go in the evening, and take
                    with you such articles of cloathing as you judge will be wanted for two or three
                    days. Your letter was most wellcome; I should have liked to see <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryDaughter">Mary</ref> mounted on a Donkey.
                    She is just the weight for them. Repeat it at <ref target="places.html#Troston">Troston</ref> if you can.—I miss your company, both of you, sadly. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldMaryAnn">Your Mother</ref> has a very bad
                    cold, but the rest are well and as usual are a compound of noise, childishness
                    and sense. We went to Hampstead by way of Primrose Hill, and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> in particular was in
                    his glory. I have a scrabble from Canterbury, and one from Mr Pollard, and his
                    friend the three-cornerd parson at Westminster, &amp;c. &amp;c.—</p><p> If possible I will send the parcel by Monday’s Coach, but if later, you will
                    certainly have it, so make yourselves happy, and enjoy the Sunshine while you
                    have it.—<ref target="people.html#AnsteadMiss">Miss Ansted</ref> calld yesterday
                    and made a speech of 2 hours!! She has perhaps more sound sense than you are
                    aware of, or it would be intolerable. I shall meet <ref target="people.html#CooperRobert">Mr Cooper</ref> tomorrow week in Broad
                    Street. Thus by bits and patches I tell you my news, O how I wish I was with
                    you! When you pass the Brook could you not fancy it the <hi rend="ital">Wye</hi>, and Hilly-Close the Sugarloaf? That stream has washd my young skin
                    many a time, and there I have caught, with my bare hands, fish that would rival
                    a mackerel, and caught gudgeons with a crooked pin. What nonsense it would
                    appear to some to see me thus dwell upon such trifles. You have a better taste,
                    and will believe that the recollection of these and other such triffles have,
                    through providence, enabled <hi rend="ital">you</hi> to see the spot of my
                    nativity.—God bless you both, I am at the end before I thought of it. Yours
                    ever</p><closer><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer><postscript><p>I hope this will be recieved on Thursday night, if not you may hear of <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Mr Lofft</ref> before you are aware of
                        it.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>