<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.413</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Published in William Hone,
                            The Table Book, of Daily Recreation and Information: Concerning
                            Remarkable Men, Manners, Times, Seasons, Solemnities, Merry-Makings,
                            Antiquities and Novelties, Forming a Complete History of the
                            Year (London, 1827–28), pp. 834–35</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="413" type="letter"><head>413. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George Bloomfield</ref> to
                    William Hone, <date when="1827-12-05">5 December 1827</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Published in William Hone,
                            <title>The Table Book, of Daily Recreation and Information: Concerning
                            Remarkable Men, Manners, Times, Seasons, Solemnities, Merry-Makings,
                            Antiquities and Novelties, Forming a Complete History of the
                            Year</title> (London, 1827–28), pp. 834–35</note></head><opener><dateline><address rend="right"><placeName>2, High Baxter Street, Bury St Edmond’s, </placeName></address></dateline><dateline rend="right"><date when="1827-12-05">Dec. 5th, 1827.</date></dateline><salute>Sir,</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> A gentleman desires me to write to you, as editor of the
                        <title>Table Book</title>, it being his wish that a view which he sent of
                    the little cottage at <ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref> should
                    appear in that very curious work<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The view
                        of the cottage published in <title>The Table Book</title> is available <ref target="../images/image29.html">here</ref>.</note> The birth-place of
                    Robert Bloomfield I think may excite the interest of some of your readers; but,
                    sir, if they find out that you correspond with a superannuated <hi rend="ital">cold water poet</hi>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A nickname
                        given George after he published the poem <title><ref target="../HTML/thetford.html">Thetford Chalybeate Spa</ref></title>.</note> your work will smell of poverty.</p><p rend="indent1"> Lord Byron took pains to flog two of my brothers, as poachers on
                    the preserves of the qualified proprietors of literature.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron, <title>English Bards and Scotch
                            Reviewers</title> (London, 1809), lines 765–94.<lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3"> When some brisk youth, the tenant of a stall, </l><l rend="indent3"> Employs a pen less pointed than his awl, </l><l rend="indent3"> Leaves his snug shop, forsakes his store of shoes, </l><l rend="indent3"> St. Crispin quits, and cobbles for the muse, </l><l rend="indent3"> Heavens! how the vulgar stare! how crowds applaud! </l><l rend="indent3"> How ladies read, and literati laud!</l><l rend="indent3"> If chance some wicked wag should pass his jest, </l><l rend="indent3"> ’Tis sheer ill-nature—don’t the world know best? </l><l rend="indent3"> Genius must guide when wits admire the rhyme, </l><l rend="indent3"> And Capel Lofft declares ’tis quite sublime. </l><l rend="indent3"> Here, then, ye happy sons of needless trade!</l><l rend="indent3"> Swains! quit the plough, resign the useless
                                spade!</l><l rend="indent3"> Lo! Burns and Bloomfield, nay, a greater far, </l><l rend="indent3"> Gifford was born beneath an adverse star, </l><l rend="indent3"> Forsook the labours of a servile state, </l><l rend="indent3"> Stemm’d the rude storm, and triumph’d over fate; </l><l rend="indent3"> Then why no more? if Phoebus smiled on you, </l><l rend="indent3"> Bloomfield! why not on brother Nathan too? </l><l rend="indent3"> Him too the mania, not the muse, has seized; </l><l rend="indent3"> Not inspiration, but a mind diseased; </l><l rend="indent3"> And now no boor can seek his last abode, </l><l rend="indent3"> No common be enclosed without an ode. </l><l rend="indent3"> Oh! since increased refinement deigns to smile </l><l rend="indent3"> On Britain’s sons, and bless our genial isle, </l><l rend="indent3"> Let poesy go forth, pervade the whole, </l><l rend="indent3"> Alike the rustic, and mechanic soul!</l><l rend="indent3"> Ye tuneful cobblers! still your notes prolong, </l><l rend="indent3"> Compose at once a slipper and a song; </l><l rend="indent3"> So shall the fair your handywork peruse,</l><l rend="indent3"> Your sonnets sure shall please—perhaps your shoes.
                            </l></lg>Byron added a footnote to these lines: ‘See Nathaniel Bloomfield’s ode,
                        elegy, or whatever he or any one else chooses to call it, on the enclosure
                        of “Honington Green.”’ For the text of Nathaniel’s poem, see <ref target="../HTML/elegy.html">here</ref>.</note> It is thought, if he had
                    not been wroth with the Edinburgh Reviewers, these poor poachers might have
                    escaped; they, like me, had neither birth nor education to entitle them to a
                    qualification.</p><p rend="indent1"> If, sir, you ever saw an old wall blown down, or, as we have it
                    here in the country, if the wall ‘<hi rend="ital">fall of its own accord</hi>,’
                    you may have observed that the first thing the workmen do, is to pick out the
                    whole bricks into one heap, the bats into another, and the rubbish into a third.
                    Thus, sir, if in what falls from me to you,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Hone preceded the published text of this letter with
                        selections from manuscripts George had enclosed with it, including verse
                        written after the bankruptcy of William Austin (the younger) of Sapiston
                        entitled ‘The Unfortunate Farmer’, and lines to the ‘Psalm-singer, Parish
                        Clerk, and Sexton’ of Sapiston, Mr Wisset, entitled ‘Dear Old Brother Bard’
                            (<title>Table Book</title>, pp. 833–34). In a paragraph prefatory to the
                        letter text, Hone stated: ‘The MSS. from whence the present selections have
                        been hastily made, were accompanied by a letter from George Bloomfield,
                        written nearly a month ago. They were delayed by the person who transmitted
                        the parcel till the opportunity of noticing them in this work had almost
                        passed. All that could be done in an hour or two is before the reader; and
                        no more has been aimed at than what appears requisite to awaken sympathy and
                        crave assistance towards an aged and indigent brother of the author of the
                            <title>Farmer’s Boy</title>. George’s present feelings will be better
                        represented by his own letter than by extracting from it.’</note> you can
                    find any whole bricks, or even bats, that may be placed in your work, pick them
                    out; but I much fear all will be but rubbish unfit for your purpose.</p><p rend="indent1"> So much has been said, in the book published by my brothers, of
                    ‘the little tailor’s four little sons,’ who once resided in the old cottage,
                    that I cannot add much that is new, and perhaps the little I have to relate will
                    be uninteresting. But I think the great and truly good man, the <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">late duke of Grafton</ref>, ought
                    to have been more particularly mentioned. Surely, after near thirty years, the
                    good sense and benevolence of that real <hi rend="ital">noble</hi>man may be
                    mentioned. When in my boyhood, he held the highest office in the state that a
                    subject can fill, and like all that attain such preeminence, had his enemies;
                    yet the more Junius<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Junius: the Whig
                        pamphleteer, whose real identity has never been determined, who attacked the
                        Duke of Grafton and others in his ministry.</note> and others railed at him,
                    the more I revered him. He was our ‘Lord of the Manor,’ and as I knew well his
                    private character, I had no doubt but he was ‘all of a piece.’ I have on foot
                    joined the foxchase, and followed <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">the duke</ref> many an hour, and
                    witnessed his endearing condescension to all who could run and shout. When
                    Robert became known as the <hi rend="ital">Farmer’s Boy</hi>, <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">the duke</ref> earnestly
                    cautioned him on no account to change his habits of living, but at the same time
                    encouraged him in his habits of <hi rend="ital">reading</hi>, and kindly gave
                    him a gratuity of a shilling a day, to enable him to employ more time in reading
                    than heretofore. This gratuity was always paid while <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">the duke</ref> lived, and was
                    continued by the <ref target="people.html#GraftonGeorgeHenry4">present
                        duke</ref> till Robert’s death.</p><p rend="indent1"> Could poor Robert have kept his children in their old habits of
                        <hi rend="ital">living</hi>, he might have reserved some of the profits
                    arising from his works, but he loved his children too tenderly to be a niggard;
                    and, besides, he received his profits at a time when bread was six or seven
                    shillings per stone: no wonder that with a sickly family to sup port, he was
                    embarrassed.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">The duke</ref> likewise strongly
                    advised him not to write <hi rend="ital">too much</hi>, but keep the ground he
                    had gained, &amp;c. As hereditary sealer of the writs in the Court of King’s
                    Bench, <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">the duke</ref> gave
                    Robert the situation of under sealer, but his health grew so bad he was obliged
                    to give it up; he held it several months, however, and doubtless many a poor
                    fellow went to coop under Robert’s seal. It was peculiarly unfortunate be could
                    not keep his place, for I think <ref target="people.html#AllenWilliam">Mr
                        Allen</ref>, the master-sealer, did not live above two years, and it is more
                    than probable <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">the duke</ref>
                    would have made Robert master-sealer, and then he would have had sufficient
                    income. <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">The duke’s</ref>
                    condescension and kindness to <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my
                        mother</ref> was very great, he learned her real character, and called on
                    her at her own cottage, and freely talked of gone-by times, (her father was an
                    old tenant to <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">the duke</ref>.)
                    He delicately left a half guinea at Mr. Roper’s, a gentleman farmer, to be given
                    to her after his departure, and when he heard of her death he ordered a handsome
                    gravestone to be placed over her, at his expense, and requested the <ref target="people.html#FellowesRobert">Rev. Mr. Fellowes</ref> to write an
                    inscription. It is thus engraven:—</p><p rend="center">BENEATH THIS STONE</p><p rend="center">Are deposited the mortal remains of</p><p rend="center"><ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">ELIZABETH GLOVER</ref>
                    who died Dec. 27th, 1803.</p><p rend="indent1"> Her maiden name was MANBY, and she was twice married. By her
                    first husband, who lies buried near this spot, she was mother of six children;
                    the youngest of whom was ROBERT BLOOMFIELD, the pastoral Poet. In her household
                    affairs she was a pattern of cleanliness, industry, and good management. By her
                    kind, her meek, her inoffensive behaviour, she had conciliated the sincere good
                    will of all her neighbours and acquaintance; nor amid the busy cares of time was
                    she ever forgetful of Eternity. But her religion was no hypocritical service, no
                    vain form of words; it consisted in loving God and keeping his commandments, as
                    they have been made known to us by JESUS CHRIST.</p><p rend="center"><hi rend="ital">Reader, go thou and do likewise</hi>.</p><p rend="indent1"> If ever I was proud of any thing it was of <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my mother</ref>, nor do I think, strong
                    as is the praise in the above, it is overdone. For solid strength of intellect
                    she surpassed all her sons, and had more real practical virtues than all of them
                    put together. Kind Providence spared her to bless me till I was far on the wrong
                    side of fifty.</p><p rend="indent1"> I must say a word or two on her sons, because <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel Loftt</ref>, Esq., in his preface to
                    my brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>’s poems, has said
                        <hi rend="ital">too much</hi> about them, <hi rend="ital">viz</hi>. ‘Beyond
                    question, the brothers of this family are all <hi rend="ital">extraordinary</hi>
                    men.’ Now, sir, as I am the oldest of these brothers, I will tell first of
                    myself. I wrote a little poem, when near seventy, on the <ref target="../HTML/thetford.html">‘Thetford Spa’</ref>; but dreading those
                    snarling curs, the <hi rend="ital">critics</hi>, forebore to affix my name to
                    it. Mr. Smith, of Cambridge, printed it gratuitously; but as soon as it was
                    discovered I was the author, my acquaintance styled me the <hi rend="ital">cold
                        water poet</hi>. I think my title will do very well. Brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nathaniel</ref> wrote some poems;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathaniel Bloomfield, <title>An Essay on
                            War, in Blank Verse; Honington Green, a Ballad... and Other
                            Poems</title> (London, 1803). See <ref target="../HTML/culprit.html">‘The Culprit’</ref>, <ref target="../HTML/essayonwar.html">‘Essay on
                            War’</ref>, <ref target="../HTML/lovestriumph.html">‘Love’s
                            Triumph’</ref>, and <ref target="../HTML/elegy.html">‘Elegy on the
                            Enclosure of Honington Green’</ref>.</note> unluckily they were printed
                    and published here at <ref target="places.html#BuryStEdmunds">Bury</ref>, and
                    the pack of critics hunted down the book. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> has had thirteen children, and
                    most of them are living, and so is he. Brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> was a machinist.
                        <ref target="people.html#BoysJohn">John Boys</ref>, Esq. gave him in all
                    twenty pounds, but he died a young man, and left his self-working pumps
                    unfinished. Eight of his children are living. </p><p rend="indent1"> The old cottage sold to Robert had been in the family near
                    fourscore years. It proved a hard bargain to Robert; <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my mother</ref> and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> occupied the
                    cottage, and could not pay rent; and after the death of <ref target="people.html#GloverElizabeth">my mother</ref>, poor Robert was in
                    distress and sold it:—the lawyers would not settle the business, and Robert died
                    broken-hearted, and never received sixpence!</p><p rend="indent1"> The lawyers constantly endeavour to make work for the trade. I
                    believe it to be true, as some say, that we are now as much <hi rend="ital">law</hi>-ridden as we were <hi rend="ital">priest</hi>-ridden some ages
                    ago. I like Charlotte Smith’s definition of the Law Trade. Orlando, in the ‘Old
                    Manor House,’ says to Carr, the lawyer, ‘I am afraid you are all rogues
                    together;’ Carr replies, ‘More or less, my good friend;—some have more sense
                    than others, and some a little more conscience—but for the rest, I am afraid we
                    are all of us a little too much <hi rend="ital">professional</hi> rogues: though
                    some of us, as individuals, would not starve the orphan, or break the heart of
                    the widow, yet, in our vocation, we give all remorse of that sort to the
                        winds.’<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte Smith, <title>The
                            Old Manor House</title> (London, 1793). The quotation appears on p. 304
                        of the 1820 edition, number 37 in the series <title>The British Novelists,
                            with an Essay, and Prefaces, Biographical and Critical, by Mrs.
                            Barbauld</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), II.</note> My last account from
                    Robert’s family says, the lawyers have not yet <hi rend="ital">settled</hi> the
                    poor old cottage!</p><p rend="indent1"><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> and I only survive of the
                    little tailor’s ‘extraordinary’ children—quite past our labour, and destitute of
                    many comforts we used to enjoy in youth. We have but one step farther to fall,
                    (i.e.) into the workhouse! Yet in the nature of things it cannot be long ere
                    death will close the scene. We have had our day, and night must come. I hope we
                    shall welcome it as heartily as Sancho in Don Quixote did sleep, ‘Blessed be he
                    who first invented sleep, it covers a man all over like a cloak.’<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Miguel de Cervantes, <title>Don Quixote de la
                            Mancha</title> (1605–15), part ii, chapter 48.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> I shall indeed be agreeably disappointed if any one
                        should bestow any thing upon <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref>, or</salute><salute rend="indent1"> Sir, your humble obedient servant. </salute><signed rend="right"><ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">GEO. BLOOMFIELD</ref>.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>