<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.292</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        346–47</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="292" type="letter"><head>292. Robert Bloomfield to <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah
                        Bloomfield</ref>, <date when="1814-07-04">4 July 1814</date><note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">BL Add. MS 28268, ff.
                        346–47</note></head><opener><dateline rend="right"><address><placeName><ref target="places.html#Shefford">Shefford</ref></placeName></address><date when="1814-07-04">July 4. 1814</date></dateline><salute>Dear Hannah</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> In my letter of yesterday I left off rather abruptly, and in a
                    way which you was not likely to comprehend. I there said that the Herald was
                    follow’d by a Band, but to accommodate that Band a Boat was procured from <ref target="places.html#Chicksands">Chicksands</ref>, placed upon a carriage,
                    and surmounted by boughs of Oak and Laurel, and in the front rode Judy
                    Basterfield in White, and crown’d with a wreath, as the emblem of <hi rend="ital">Peace</hi>. In the procession rode <ref target="people.html#WilliamsonEdmund">Mr Williamson</ref> &amp;c, Mr
                    Walker, (two church parsons,) Mr Potier, the Catholick priest, and Briggs the
                    Methodest preacher, and all who could procure Horses, or wish’d to join the
                    Cavalcade, In the rear of which appeard an old black Horse decorated with an
                    enormous pair of Bullock’s horns place’d near his ears. On his back rode the
                    Devel with a monstrous Mask and horns to corispond, and drest in a black cloak.
                    Behind him rode (riding backwards both on a Horse) a lad with a pale Mask, and
                    in the utmost trembling and destress, to represent the fallen Emperor. Both
                    these perform’d their parts extreemly well, and cause’d the utmost laughter,
                        <ref target="people.html#InskipThomas">Inskip</ref> was Devil, and Jack
                    sombody was Bounaparte. It was the best Devil I ever saw, and riding thus like a
                    whipper-in after the parsons, had a strange and ridiculous appearance. A Bullock
                    drest in Ribbons, followd likewise by music, had marchd through the town two
                    days before and was now on the Spit, and in the pot, as dinner was to commence
                    at 4. A long range of Tables were placed from <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Westons</ref> door to the George, capable
                    of accommodating all the poor in the Town that is, all who labour for bread, the
                    whole was coverd with Canvass and form’d a compleat tent, border’d throughout by
                    garlands of flowers, and each table having a flag inscribe’d, ‘<ref target="people.html#AlexanderTsar">Alexander</ref>’, ‘Blucher’, ‘Platoff’
                        &amp;c.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Tsar Alexander; Marshall
                        Gebhard von Blucher, leader of the Prussian forces against Napoleon; Count
                        Matvei Ivanovich Platoff, hetman of Cossacks, and Russian commander in the
                        Napoleonic wars. Shefford was celebrating the allied victory over Napoleonic
                        France.</note> At the end stood a kind of Maypole, bearing a gilded Cock,
                    surmounted by a flag—Across the center of the street was erected a stage for the
                    band, who had there a little bower of their own, above the passing carriages.—At
                    4 about 250 people sat down to dinner in the greatest good order. [small sketch
                    at the bottom left of the page with the words ‘England’ with the drawing of a
                    cock underneath and then the words ‘of the walk’ beneath that] At the head of
                    the Table sat <ref target="people.html#WilliamsonEdmund">Mr Williamson</ref> and the other conductors of the feast took each of
                    them a Table, as president and carver, Here you might have seen two Doctors, two
                    publican’s, a parson, and a Shopkeeper &amp;c &amp;c. in White Aprons,
                    slashing up the Beef and plumb pudding, and sharing out several Baskets of
                    potatoes.—The Town was crouded with spectators, and all was joy. At 6, (after
                    grace in due order) dinner was removed, and the Gentlemen part of the company
                    had a boarded stage for their wine and refreshments, and here; while men women
                    and children were Huzzaing around, they did just what must be expected, viz, got
                    drunk by drinking Toasts. The musical performers at one time did not know ‘God
                    save the King,’ from Jack’s-alive; but this fervor subsided gradually so as to
                    produce no mischief, and to leave the evening for a still more singular
                    exhibition, which is the beautiful effect of light under boughs, which, as you
                    have now seen <ref target="places.html#Vauxhall">Vauxhall</ref>, you can fully
                    understand. I should here tell you that in the evening Tea was serve’d on the
                    platform to all the women who choose it, and dancing commenced in the real
                    country stile. Miss Weston made more tea than she ever did in one day in her
                    life. Amongsts the flags <ref target="people.html#InskipThomas">Inskip</ref> had
                    two very large, inscribed ‘The Strength of Kings is the Affections of the
                    people’ and, ‘Freedom to Slaves, and peace to the World’. Mr Walker had a real
                    fine transparency, and his house a croud of green and blossoms,—Mr Gay several
                    transparencies of his own painting, and his House shaded by Oak-limbs planted in
                    the street. Mr Radwell, Mr Betts &amp;c cut a conspicuous figure; so that
                    when I tell you that there was not a window in the town without Candles,
                    folliage, and flowers, you must try to guess at the effect. It made my eyes
                    water in spite of myself.—This first night’s frolick was not all, though the
                    Town was not quiet till two in the morning.—</p><p rend="indent1"> On Thursday—A Ball had been announced to be held at the White
                    Hart, to which were invited all the Respectable people round the neighbourhood,
                    and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> had been busily
                    employd with other scholars to write Notes of invitation. This whole day was
                    spent in mirth. Amongst the rest a large party, (in fact any who pleased) danced
                    to two fidlers on the platform, Young Girls ‘threading the Needle along’ the
                    Street, Boys kicking a Bladder; And more particularly a ridiculous scene, of a
                    Rope suspended upon poles, to which was tied by small twine two lumps of pudding
                    drip’d in treacle, under which stood on stools, two boys with their hands tied
                    behind them, whose business it was to catch the pudding in their mouths! I say
                    nothing of their faces! treacle betide us! what a mess. At Night about 40 Ladies
                    and as many Gentlemen danced at Barbers till morning, with fidlers from Bedford
                    and Nitshill &amp;c—Friday—Taylor the Sadler Chaird through the Town with
                    the Band, and the wife of our ‘Old Richard’ riding on a great thundering black
                    Horse coverd with a white sheet and flowers. This old woman litterally danced
                    all day from Wednesday morning till Friday night. On the Ball night <ref target="people.html#WestonJoseph">Mr Weston</ref> ornamented his House with
                    Hop-vines from his Garden, intersperse’d with Lamps; with several transparencies
                    of his own designing, Saturday—The Townsmen presented a Flag to <ref target="people.html#OsborneGeorge">Sir George Osborn</ref> in testimony of
                    his bounty towards this real and National holiday, which the good old man has
                    promise’d to presever and to leave to his grandchildren. &amp;c
                    &amp;c</p><p rend="indent1"> And now Father how did you get through this bustle,? what did our
                    house look like? did not you want to help?</p><p rend="indent1"> I saw on Monday that I should ‘be drag’d’ and directly began to
                    regret that <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah</ref> was not at
                    home to contrive and to help. ‘I wish <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldHannah">Hannah</ref> was here’ was repeated oftener than I ever repeated it before,
                    for <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlesSon">Charles</ref> was busy at
                    writing, and <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteShot">Charlotte</ref>
                    my only housemaid,—However I naild up lathes for the illuminatiion, sent for
                    Candles, Cockades, &amp;c—Joe Saunders procure’d a large bough of Oak, and
                    Old Squires two tall branches of Laurel;—Our three younkers went to Rowney and
                    lug’d home as much Yellow Broom and Cornflowers as they could carry, we set to
                    work, made them with form, and on Wednesday morning up at 6, I hung the outer
                    circle of the parlour window with a garland of flowers, naild a Rose-bush over
                    the door, trimd up <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldRobertHenry">Roberts</ref>
                    Hoop into a Garland and displayd it on a pole from the Landing window.—In the
                    evening lighted up about four score Candle, and remove’d your old Richard and
                        Kate<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Presumably dolls, or china
                        figurines, named after the characters in Bloomfield’s poem of that
                        name.</note> from the Mill, and with a White flag inscribed <hi rend="ital">peace</hi> mounted them on one of Barber’s Gin Kegs on a string inside the
                    parlour window, to the great amusement of the Boys. [a sketch of this below]</p><p rend="indent1"> Now my dear Girl you must absolutely come home <hi rend="ital">this week</hi>, for though <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteShot">Charlotte</ref> does all she
                    can, we are in a <hi rend="ital">muddle</hi> according to your notions, thus far
                    we have been starving upon bake’d Veal, Calve’s Liver, Shoulder of Lamb and
                    Goosbery pies. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldCharlotteShot">Charlotte</ref>
                    has a Cold and sore throat.—</p><p>NB. The only house in the Town not in the garb of joy was our neighbour
                    Fitsjohn’s. That poor sufferer died on Saturday, and was buried on Thursday
                    last, (not at Campton)</p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> Love to you and friends</salute><signed rend="right">Rob Bloomfield</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>