<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Letters of Robert Bloomfield and His Circle</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name></author><editor>Tim Fulford</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Carl Stahmer</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.25.349a</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2009-06-09">July 9, 2009</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>MS: private collection. The letter’s context and its inclusion in a small
                  collection of manuscripts all of which are associated with James Burrell Faux suggests it
                  may have been sent to, or intended for, him. Dating from internal evidence. For the context of this letter, see Letters 339a,
                  360a, 412 and 423. </p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editors wish to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>Nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25names']"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="places.xml/category[@xml:id='EE25places']"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Letters</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="#EEd.25.names"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="#EEd.25.places"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2009-07-25" n="6"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>changes from proofing a final time; new letter discovered and letters renumbered.</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-06-08" n="5"><label>Changed by</label><name>Laura Mandell</name><list><item>create image wrappers; run edition for last time through xslt.</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-04-30" n="4"><label>Changed by</label><name>Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing and TEI encoding of entire edition (further preliminary materials)</item></list></change><change who="#LM" when="2009-03-30" n="3"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name><list><item>XSLT Transforming</item></list></change><change who="#AB" when="2009-03-20" n="2"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name><list><item>Proofing, re-coding letters, and TEI encoding of preliminary materials</item></list></change><change who="#KL" when="2008-10-03" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name xml:id="KL">Kirstyn Leuner</name><list><item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all letters</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="349a" type="letter"><head>349a. <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldGeorge">George Bloomfield</ref> to Unknown Correspondent, undated [late summer/autumn
               1820?] <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: private collection. The letter’s context and its inclusion in a small
                  collection of manuscripts all of which are associated with <ref target="people.html#FauxJames">James Burrell Faux</ref> suggests it
                  may have been sent to, or intended for, him. Dating from internal evidence. For the context of this letter, see Letters 339a,
                  360a, 412 and 423. </note></head><p rend="center">Free Thoughts on the Humours of the <hi rend="ital">chase</hi> And the Park</p><p>In the year <hi rend="ital">1769</hi> our Esquire at <ref target="places.html#Honington">Honington</ref> (Mr Quince <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Quince, the local squire. </note>) had a party of <hi rend="ital">Gentlemen</hi> Boys at his
               House On a Visit to Master Quince, the Young Norfords <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Children of William Norford (1715–1793),
                  physician and surgeon of Bury St Edmunds. </note> from Bury &amp;c,—My Self and Brothers were invited as Mrs Q knew though we were
               very poor, our Mother took all possible care of our Morals,—The young Gentlemen proposed Squirrell hunting in <ref target="places.html#EustonHall">Euston park</ref>,!! — My Brothers and Me were affraid to go, But the young Gentlemen Said they knew
               Mr King the Keeper would Let us hunt, we went, and Just as my <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Brother Nat</ref> had ascended to
               the top of the Lofty Oak to dislodge the Squirrel The <ref target="people.html#GraftonAugustusHenry3">Duke and Dutches of Grafton
               </ref> in an Open Carriage and pair of poneys drove up, the Duke immediately ordered us out of the park and Desired us to hunt on our
               own premises !!</p><p rend="indent1">There higmightinesses the Critics have converted the free fields of Genious into A <hi rend="ital">park</hi> and have
               long Usurped the sole propriety thereof to themselves, But it some times happen that the unlearnd poor are sufferd to Enter this <hi rend="ital">Literary park</hi> to hunt for <hi rend="ital">fame</hi> and <hi rend="ital">profit</hi>. Bob Burns the ploughman and
               Nan Yearsley the Milk Woman were very successfull, And Jiles the Farmers Boy did wonders!! <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Labouring class poets: Robert Burns (1759–96), Ann Yearsley (1753–1806) and George’s brother Robert, who adopted the persona of
                  Giles in <title>The Farmer’s Boy</title>. </note> But poor <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldNat">Nat</ref> had the same Luck in
               the <hi rend="ital">Literary park</hi> as we had in <hi rend="ital">Euston park</hi> was orderd out by the Lords of the Soil!! Poor
                  Snip<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathaniel Bloomfield’s volume of poems, <title>An Essay on War</title>, was published in
                  1803, with a preface by Capel Lofft that revealed the author’s embarrassment about his trade of tailor (‘snip’) (pp. xxv-xxvii).
                  Critics regretted Lofft’s exposure of the author’s embarrassment but declared that Nathaniel’s poems, while exhibiting the recent
                  diffusion of knowledge among the labouring classes, were not good enough for him to give up his trade. See <title>The Annual
                     Review</title>, 2 (1803), 585–88, which remarked, ‘The poem being bad, Mr. Capel Lofft is ignorant. Q.E.D, lamentably ignorant,
                  and presumptuously obtrusive in his ignorance’ (p. 587). Cf. <title>The Monthly Review</title>, 42 (1803), 379–81. <title>The
                     British Critic</title>, 22 (1803), 81–82, declared ‘Another Bloomfield, and a poet! Are all the Bloomfields poets?’ (p. 81).
                  Byron was crueller about labourer poets, and Nathaniel in particular, in <title>English Bards and Scotch Reviewers</title> (London,
                  1809), lines 765–94. <lg><l rend="indent1">When some brisk youth, the tenant of a stall,</l><l rend="indent1">Employs a pen less pointed than his awl, </l><l rend="indent1">Leaves his snug shop, forsakes his store of shoes, </l><l rend="indent1">St. Crispin quits, and cobbles for the muse, </l><l rend="indent1">Heavens! how the vulgar stare! how crowds applaud! </l><l rend="indent1">How ladies read, and literati laud! </l><l rend="indent1">If chance some wicked wag should pass his jest, </l><l rend="indent1"> ‘Tis sheer ill-nature—don’t the world know best? </l><l rend="indent1">Genius must guide when wits admire the rhyme, </l><l rend="indent1">And Capel Lofft declares ‘tis quite sublime. </l><l rend="indent1">Here, then, ye happy sons of needless trade! </l><l rend="indent1">Swains! quit the plough, resign the useless spade! </l><l rend="indent1">Lo! Burns and Bloomfield, nay, a greater far, </l><l rend="indent1">Gifford was born beneath an adverse star, </l><l rend="indent1">Forsook the labours of a servile state, </l><l rend="indent1">Stemm’d the rude storm, and triumph’d over fate; </l><l rend="indent1">Then why no more? if Phoebus smiled on you, </l><l rend="indent1">Bloomfield! why not on brother Nathan too? </l><l rend="indent1">Him too the mania, not the muse, has seized; </l><l rend="indent1">Not inspiration, but a mind diseased; </l><l rend="indent1">And now no boor can seek his last abode, </l><l rend="indent1">No common be enclosed without an ode. </l><l rend="indent1">Oh! since increased refinement deigns to smile</l><l rend="indent1">On Britain’s sons, and bless our genial isle, </l><l rend="indent1">Let poesy go forth, pervade the whole, </l><l rend="indent1">Alike the rustic, and mechanic soul! </l><l rend="indent1">Ye tuneful cobblers! still your notes prolong, </l><l rend="indent1">Compose at once a slipper and a song; </l><l rend="indent1">So shall the fair your handywork peruse, </l><l rend="indent1">Your sonnets sure shall please—perhaps your shoes. </l></lg> Byron added a footnote: ‘See Nathaniel Bloomfield’s ode, elegy, or whatever he or any one else chooses to call it, on the
                  enclosure of “Honington Green.”‘ See text of <ref target="../HTML/elegy.html">‘Honington Green’</ref>. </note> was deemd A <hi rend="ital">poacher</hi>!! he saucily enterd the park and Mounted Aloft in <hi rend="ital">Heroics</hi> and gave the lie Direct to
               the new <hi rend="ital">scheme of philosophy</hi>!! Tis said that some 40 years ago the frightful brain of A German philosopher found
               out that by <hi rend="ital">Education </hi>&amp;c Mankind might be raised to A State of perfection little short of the perfection of
               Angells, so that War and all the great Evils of humanity would ceace for ever, !!! ——Nat opposed those Utopian notions in beautifull
               Blank Verse, <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>An Essay on War</title> took the grim line argued by Thomas Malthus in
                     <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population</title> (1798) against the philosophy of perfectibility advanced by William Godwin
                  in <title>An Enquiry Concerning Political Justice</title> (1793). Godwin had developed social views about the benefits of rising
                  population; his notion of perfectibility was built upon Enlightenment arguments made by, among others, Immanuel Kant in <title>Idee
                     zu einer allgemeinem Geschichte</title> (1784) and Johann Gottfried von Herder in <title>Ideen</title> (1784/91). Malthus, and
                  Nathaniel, argued that war was to be welcomed because it relieved poverty by keeping population in check. </note> The Critics could
               not find fault with the Poetry <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">In fact, many critics did find fault with the versification: see
                  note 4 above. </note> so they seized the <hi rend="ital">augument</hi>, Yet if ever Augument had Reason, common Sense, and
               Scripture <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">St James C4th V 1st [Bloomfield’s footnote]. George refers to James 4.1: ‘From whence
                  come wars and fightings among you? Come they not hence, even of your lusts that war in your members?’ </note> on its side it is
               Snips argument, But the Critics cried him down!! Where then said they is Mans <hi rend="ital">free Agency</hi>, where his allmost
               Angelick Mental powers, Virtues &amp;c &amp;c <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">See <title>The Monthly Review</title>, 42 (1803),
                  379–81. </note> In short they soon sent poor Snip packing out of their park, This new Scheme of <hi rend="ital">perfection</hi> was
               call’d <hi rend="ital">the new Light</hi> hence sprang The <title>Rights of Man Age of Reason</title><note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Enlightenment and revolutionary works by Thomas Paine (1737–1809), published in 1791 and
                  1793–94 respectively. These titles are double underlined. </note> &amp;c &amp;c, <ref target="people.html#LofftCapel">Capel
                  Loffts </ref><hi rend="ital"> Nest of poets</hi> were markd by the Critics <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">This derogatory term appeared in
                     <title>The Annual Review</title>, 2 (1803), 585–88, which called Lofft ‘mistaken’ in supposing he had ‘found a nest of poets’ (p.
                  587). </note> My Brother <ref target="people.html#BloomfieldIsaacBrother">Isaac</ref> was A Sinner in Rhyme, but never dared to
               Enter their park!!——poor old Crispin made his Lowest, most humble Bow, and Crawld into their park on his hands and knees,!! <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">St Crispin is the patron saint of shoemakers, so ‘Crispin’ means a shoemaker: here George refers
                  to himself and his own poems, published late in life in pamphlet form with the aid of local gentlemen who wished to relieve his
                  poverty: <ref target="../HTML/thetford.html"><title>Thetford Chalybeate Spa. A Poem by a Parishioner of St. Peters</title></ref>
                  (1820) and <ref target="../HTML/friendlyhints.html"><title>Friendly Hints Affectionately Addressed, by an Old Man to the Labouring
                        Poor of Suffolk and Norfolk</title></ref> (1822). See Letters 339a, 360a, 412 and 423. </note> And is when arrived on the
               side of the grave Haild by <hi rend="ital">Giles</hi> as <hi rend="ital">A Brother bard</hi> !!!!! ——— <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A sarcastic reference to George’s brother Robert who, offended by what he saw as George’s toadying to Lofft, as well
                  as ill and depressed, let their correspondence lapse until on 18 July 1820 he sent George a letter complimenting him on <ref target="../HTML/thetford.html"><title>Thetford Chalybeate Spa</title></ref> and hailing him as ‘brother bard’ (Letter 348).
               </note></p><p rend="indent1">I corisponded with Giles 30 Years, no language can express the pleasure I received from that Corrispondence 5 years ago
               My Letters were answerd by his Son or Daughter, <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">From 1815, Robert’s failing eyesight made
                  letter-writing very difficult. </note> my corrispondence with them soon dropd for I know no more of <hi rend="ital">Genteel
                  Life</hi> then <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Corrected from ‘then’. </note> I do of Astronomy, <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">A science pursued by George’s patron Capel Lofft. </note> After 5 years Silence I receivd the inclosd <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The enclosed letter is no longer with this letter: George probably refers either to Letter 348 or to
                  Letter 363 or 368. </note> in his own hand, I did never Expect a Line from him in his own <del>had</del> hand, though 10 years
               younger than My Self I am Sorry he is older as to health I dont want Gileses letter returnd</p></div></body></text></TEI>