<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">frank27.summary</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2009-04-01">May 1, 2009</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a">STUDY AIDS : PLOT SUMMARY</title>
						<author>
							<persName>Curran, Stuart</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<editor>Curran, Stuart</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date>2009-05-01</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g12 #g16" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="3" when="2009-05-01" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-05-01" who="#DR">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2009-05-01" who="#MQ">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>STUDY AIDS : PLOT SUMMARY</head>
				<p rend="emph">Plot Summary of the Novel (Based on the 1818 Text)</p>
				<lb/>
				<p rend="emph">Volume I</p>
				<p>The English ship's captain Robert Walton, in a series of letters to his sister Margaret Saville in England, describes the initial
					stages in his nautical journey to the North Pole (I:L1). While sailing north of Archangel in Russia, Walton's ship becomes trapped
					in arctic ice. From across the frozen sea, the sailors spot a gigantic figure on a dog-sled crossing the ice (I:L4:3), and later
					see a haggard, wild-eyed man who is pursuing him, stranded with his dogsled on an ice floe. They take him on board.</p>
				<p> This man, Victor Frankenstein, tells Walton that he is in pursuit of the figure they saw (I:L4:12). While recuperating from
					exposure, he relates his history to Walton, who makes notes on the story and includes them in a letter to his sister.</p>
				<p> Frankenstein describes his childhood in Geneva (I:1): his father, Alphonse Frankenstein, was a wealthy descendant of Genevese
					nobility; his mother, Caroline, was the daughter of Beaufort, a friend of Alphonse who was reduced to poverty and died in his
					daughter's arms. Alphonse and Catherine are married, and Victor is their first child; two other sons, Ernest and William, follow.
					When Alphonse's sister dies, the Frankensteins adopt her young daughter Elizabeth, who is brought up as a member of the family.
					Victor and Elizabeth are the closest of friends, and with their friend Henry Clerval they live an idyllic childhood.</p>
				<p> Whereas Elizabeth and Henry Clerval are fond of poetry and romance, Victor is fascinated by such mystical philosophers and
					alchemists as Cornelius Agrippa and Paracelsus, writers his father rejects as "sad trash" (I:1:15). But their pursuit of the
					elixir of eternal life continues to fascinate him, and a bolt of lightning striking a tree in the garden and reducing it to
					splinters fires Victor's imagination.</p>
				<p> Elizabeth is taken ill, and although she survives, Caroline Frankenstein contracts the fever and dies from it. Her last wish is
					that Victor and Elizabeth may someday marry (I:2:2). After mourning his mother's death, Frankenstein goes up to the University of
					Ingolstadt without his friend Clerval. There he meets a professor of science, Krempe, who berates him for wasting his time on
					Agrippa and Paracelsus and suggests a more modern course of reading. Frankenstein is little impressed with his appearance or
					manner, though, and has little interest in the mundane work of modern scientists as compared with the fantastic dreams of the
					alchemists. Upon meeting another professor, however—Waldman—his attitude toward modern chemistry changes, and he begins to study
					with ardor, rapdily progressing in his knowledge.</p>
				<p> Still filled with the grandiose dreams of the alchemists, Frankenstein devotes himself to study day and night, neglecting his
					family and friends. After two years of uninterrupted labor, he has discovered the secret which he has sought: the principle of
					life (I:3). He imagines creating a new race of beings which will hail him as their creator. On a November night, he succeeds in
					bringing life to lifeless matter (I:4). But when the eyes of his creature open, he is terrified by its appearance, and runs from
					it in horror. Fatigued from days of constant labor, he falls asleep and has a nightmare: he embraces Elizabeth, only to watch her
					turn into his dead mother, with worms crawling about her. He is suddenly awakened by the Creature standing over his bed; he then
					runs out of the room into the streets of Ingolstadt.</p>
				<p> There he encounters Clerval (I:4:7), and the two return to Frankenstein's lodging, where Frankenstein is relieved to see the
					Creature has disappeared. But he falls into a fever, with only Clerval to nurse him back to health. After months of raving he
					comes to his senses, and he and Clerval set out on a walking tour of the area to calm his mind (I:5:16).</p>
				<p> The two return to Ingolstadt to find a letter from Frankenstein's father announcing the strangling death of Victor's brother,
					William (I:6:2). They travel to Geneva, where a search for William's murderer is in progress. Outside the city, Victor spots his
					creation and is certain that the Creature is responsible for his brother's death, even though a beloved family servant, Justine
					Moritz, has been accused of the killing, having been found with the locket William wore the night of his death.</p>
				<p> Frankenstein and Elizabeth are convinced of Justine's innocence, but at her trial (I:7), Frankenstein, afraid of being thought
					mad, does not tell his story, and she is found guilty and executed. Her death and William's weigh heavily on Frankenstein, who
					blames himself as their true murderer. </p>
				<p rend="emph">Volume II</p>
				<p>Frankenstein sets out to scale Mont Blanc (II:2), and on a plain of ice he is approached by the Creature, who tells his own story.
					He begins by describing the "original æra of [his] being," his first sensory impressions, and describes his earliest
					experiences.</p>
				<p> The Creature's first encounter with humans comes as he enters a hut, causing its inhabitant to flee in terror (II:3:9)—the same
					terror he inspires in the residents of a village he enters, and after fleeing angry villagers he takes refuge in a "hovel" that
					allows him to see into an adjoining cottage. From there he silently watches the impoverished and despondent De Lacey family,
					consisting of the blind father, his son Felix, and his daughter Agatha; impressed with their "gentle manners," he secretly
					provides the family with firewood (II:4:7).</p>
				<p> There he discovers the use of language, and learns the rudiments of this "godlike science" (II:4:9) by listening to their
					conversations. His progress quickens with the arrival of the Arab Safie (II:5:4), whose language lessons he observes attentively.
					Volney's Ruins of Empire provides him with not only a grasp of the language, but "a cursory knowledge of history" as well. As his
					knowledge of language and politics improves, he is able to make sense of "the history of [his] friends" (II:6:1), which he
					recounts to Frankenstein. He supplements his linguistic knowledge with the ability to read after discovering copies of Paradise
					Lost, Plutarch's Lives, and Goethe's Sorrows of Young Werther (II:7:3).</p>
				<p> After observing the family for a year, he resolves to approach the blind De Lacey when he is alone (II:7:13). But before he is
					able to make his case, Felix rushes in and, believing his father to be threatened, beats the Creature, chasing him away. Once the
					De Laceys have fled their cottage, he burns it to the ground in a mad rage (II:8:13) and, discovering his origin in Frankenstein's
					journal, resolves to travel to Geneva to meet his creator. On the way, he tries to save a drowning girl on the way, but is shot by
					her companion. He finally reaches Geneva and encounters a young boy, whom he resolves to make his friend, but the boy, who proves
					to be William Frankenstein, calls him "Hideous monster!" and struggles to escape. The Creature kills him and frames Justine for
					the murder.</p>
				<p> The narrative breaks off, and the Creature tells Frankenstein his demand: "You must create a female for me. . . . I demand it of
					you as a right which you must not refuse" (II:9:2). Frankenstein agrees only after the Creature promises to leave Europe forever. </p>
				<p rend="emph">Volume III</p>
				<p>While Frankenstein tries to delay the fulfilment of his promise in Geneva, his father proposes that he follow his mother's dying
					wish by marrying Elizabeth (III:1:5). Although he looks forward to the wedding, Frankenstein is unwilling to marry until he has
					created the Creature's mate, he delays the event until he has finished a tour of Europe. In Strasburgh he meets Clerval, and the
					two travel across the Continent to London (III:2:1) and thence to Edinburgh. There Victor leaves Clerval and heads to the remote
					Orkney islands to fulfil his promise. But he is tortured with anxiety over the prospect of his two creations mating and
					propagating "a race of devils" (III:3:2), and he destroys the half-finished companion. Upon seeing this, the Creature, who has
					followed him across Europe, vows vengeance: "I shall be with you on your wedding-night."</p>
				<p> Frankenstein sets out in the middle of the night in a small boat (III:3:24); after being carried away from the shore, he is
					relieved to reach land, but is immediately accused of murder. He is carried before the magistrate, Mr. Kirwin (III:4:1), and
					charged with the murder of a man—whom he immediately recognizes as Clerval. He lapses into a nervous fever for two months; upon
					waking, he is cleared of the charges, and he travels with his father back toward Geneva. In Paris he receives a letter from
					Elizabeth, which makes Frankenstein resolve to marry her at once, in spite of the Creature's threat (III:5:18).</p>
				<p> Upon hearing Elizabeth's scream on their wedding night, Frankenstein realizes the true significance of this threat—he discovers
					Elizabeth's lifeless body (III:6:8), the news of which results in the death of Victor's father. Frankenstein sets out on a mission
					to destroy the Creature and embarks on "wanderings . . . which are to cease but with life" (III:7:3). He relates to Walton his
					travels across the frozen north, which take him at last to the ship where he is recovered. Here Frankenstein's narrative ends, and
					Walton continues his letters to his sister.</p>
				<p> The sailors, still ice-bound, threaten mutiny, and are calmed only when Frankenstein urges them on (III:Walton:17), but two days
					later Walton agrees to return to England. Frankenstein, refusing to abandon his quest, resolves to continue northward, but his
					health fails him, and he dies.</p>
				<p> Walton, hearing a noise in the dead man's room, enters it to find the Creature standing over his body (III:Walton:35). After
					delivering an oration over the body, the creature vows to immolate his own body at the North Pole, and springs out the window onto
					the ice: "He was soon borne away by the waves, and lost in darkness and distance" (III:Walton:48). </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
