<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Gipsy Prince</title>
				<author>
					<name>Thomas Moore</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Frederick Burwick</editor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Justin Tonra</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoding and Proofreading</resp>
					<name>Deborah K. Wright</name>
				</respStmt>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>2011-10-01</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent/>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="nines">rce890</idno>
				<idno type="edition">introduction</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2011-10-20">october 1, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts an../images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts an../images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts an../images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts an../images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
				  <analytic><title>Introduction</title>
				  <author><persName><forename>Fred</forename><surname>Burwick</surname></persName></author></analytic>
				  
					<monogr>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Thomas</forename>
								<surname>Moore</surname>
								<addName type="loc">Moore, Thomas, 1779-1852</addName>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename>Michael</forename>
								<surname>Kelly</surname>
								<addName type="loc">Kelly, Michael, 1762-1826</addName>
							</persName>
						</author>
						<title>The Gipsy Prince; or, the Loves of Don Sebastian de Nurillo, and the Fair Antonia, translated from the Spanish. By C. Moor, Esq.</title>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>London, UK</pubPlace>
							<publisher>J. Roach</publisher>
							<date when="1801">1801</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p><gi>Speaker</gi> element names have been regularised across this file and the
						Manuscript file, according to the names reproduced in the Dramatis Personae
						printed in the Historical Narrative: Don Roderic; Don Dominic; Gipsy Prince;
						Rincon; Old Jew; Alcaide; Alguazil(s); Officer(s); Messenger; Gipsies;
						Diego; Antonia; Poppee; Lachimee; Blanch; Alguazils, Peasants, Gipsies, etc.
						Note: the regularisation takes place only within <gi>speaker</gi> elements;
						it does not occur in the stage directions, text of the play or Dramatis
						Personae.</p>
				</normalization>
				<hyphenation>
					<p>All dashes have been represented with an emdash: <gi>&#x2014;</gi>, and
						surrounding whitespace has been deleted (except where dash is preceded by a
						full stop).</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for
						‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Incorrect and idiosyncratic spelling has not been regularised; instances are
						marked by a <gi>sic</gi> element.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<tagsDecl>
				<rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
				<rendition xml:id="italic" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
			</tagsDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="#LM" when="2012-03-12" n="2">
				<label>Changed by the editor</label>
				<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
				  <item>editing for TEI</item>
				  <item>add header</item>
					<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#LM" when="2011-09-05" n="1">
				<list>
					<item>IDHMC studnents do TEI encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="essay">
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <byline><docAuthor>Frederick Burwick</docAuthor></byline>
        <p>Opening mid-season at Haymarket on July 24, <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title> was the collaboration of
          Thomas Moore who composed the libretto and lyrics and Michael Kelly who provided the
          musical score and performed in the title role.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="author"
            >Thomas Moore, <title level="m">Songs, Duets, Trios, and Choruses, in the Gipsy Prince, a Musical
            Entertainment in Two Acts, first performed at the Theatre-Royal, Hay-Market, July 24,
            1801. The Overture and Musick Composed and Selected by Mr. Kelly</title> (London: Printed by T.
            Woodfall, Little Russell Street, Covent Garden, for Mssrs. Cadell and Davies in the
            Strand, 1801). <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince, A Comic Opera in Two Acts, Now Performing with
            Universal applause at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket, Compos’d &amp; Selected by Michael
            Kelly</title> (Printed for Michael Kelly, to be had at his Music Warehouse, No. 9 New Lisle
            Street, Leicester Square, &amp; at all Music Shops [1801]). In addition to these two
            published sources, I have relied on manuscript 1329, <title level="a">The Gipsy Prince,</title> in
            the collection of John Larpent, Lord Chamberlain’s Examiner of Plays (1778-1824), at the
            Huntington Library.</note> Although declared &quot;a very poor piece&quot; in Thomas
          Dutton's the <title level="j">Dramatic Censor</title>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="author"><title level="j">The Dramatic Censor;
            or, Monthly Epitome of Taste, Fashion, and Manners </title>(August 1801), by T. Dutton;
            published by J. Roach and C. Chapple; printed by J. Roach, Russel-Court, Drury-Lane;
            quoted in John Genest, <title level="m">Account of the English Stage, 1660-1830</title>, 10 vols. (Bath: Printed
            by H. E. Carrington, 1832.), 7:522.</note> <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title> was nevertheless popular
          with audiences and was performed for ten nights, the second longest run of Haymarket's
          season from June 18 to October 7. The average number of performances for a single piece
          that season was four nights, and the longest run was secured by <title level="m">The Corsair; or the
          Italian Nuptials</title>, which may have been acted as many as nineteen times.<note n="3"
            place="foot" resp="author">Closed Sundays, performances at the Haymarket for the 1801
            season were held on 96 evenings from June 18 to October 7. Not counting all afterpieces,
            25 productions were launched during that period, with the only two premier events, <title level="m">The
              Gipsy Prince</title> as Musical Entertainment and <title level="m">The Corsair</title> as Pantomime, securing the longest
            runs.</note> Dutton's opinion of the play was not shared by his publisher, the theatre
          aficionado John Roach, who was amused by the ploy of presenting the Irish disguised as
          Gipsies.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="author">John Roach, <title level="m">Authentic Memoirs of the
            Green-room; involving sketches, biographical, critical, &amp; characteristic, of the
            performers of the Theatres Royal, Drury-lane, Covent-Garden, and the Hay-Market.
            Embellished with seven portraits of eminent performers.</title> 2 vols. (London : Printed by and
            for J. Roach , 1806), 1:186.</note> Kelly claimed that he had so thoroughly lost all
          trace of brogue that he was no longer capable of playing a stage Irishman.<note n="5"
            place="foot" resp="author">Michael Kelly, <title level="m">Reminiscences of Michael Kelly, of the King's
            Theatre, and Theatre Royal Drury Lane, including a period of nearly half a century; with
            original anecdotes of many distinguished persons, political, literary, and musical.</title> 2
            vols. (London, H. Colburn, 1826), 2:76. &quot;About the middle of May, an opera was
            acted at Drury Lane, in which I had to perform an Irish character. My friend [John
            Henry] Johnstone [prominent actor of Irish character roles] took great pains to instruct
            me in the brogue, but I did not feel quite up to the mark; and, after all, it seems my
            vernacular phraseology was not the most perfect; for, when the opera was over, [Richard
            Brinsley] Sheridan came into the green-room, and said, 'Bravo! Kelly; very well, indeed
            ; upon my honour, I never before heard you speak such good English in all my life.' This
            sarcastic compliment produced much laughter from the performers who heard
            him.&quot;</note> In spite of his disclaimer, Kelly in the title role as the Gipsy
          Prince readily communicated to the audience what John Larpent in his duty as censor had
          failed to see: these Gipsies under the Spanish Inquisition were very like the Irish under
          British rule. </p>
        <p>If the disguise had become too transparent, then further disguise might not be helpful,
          but the attempt was nevertheless made, probably more out of delight in elaborating the
          hoax than with any conviction that readers might be fooled. Timed for publication at the
          end of the Haymarket summer season, the hoax might have been intended to stir up
          sufficient controversy to convince Colman, manager of the Haymarket from 1789 to
          1805,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="author">Hubert Heffner, <title level="a">The Haymarket Theater
            under Colman the Younger, 1789 to 1805,</title> <title level="m">Communication Monographs</title>, 10, no. 1
            (1943): 23-29.</note> to give place to <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title> on the performance calendar for
          1802. In September, 1801, John Roach published &quot;two genuine Historical
          Narratives&quot; which are identified on the title-page as the sources for <title level="m">The Gipsy
            Prince</title> and <title level="m">The Corsair</title>, &quot;performed at the Haymarket Theatre, with universal Applause;
          being the only New Dramas, produced at the Summer Theatre, during the present
          Season.&quot;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="author"><title level="m">The Gipsy Prince; or, The Loves of
            Don Sebastian de Nurillo, and the Fair Antonia, translated from the Spanish. By C. Moor,
            Esq. To which is added, The Corsair; or The Italian Nuptials</title>. (London: J. Roach. 1801).
            64pp. -- Front. dated Sept. 7, 1801.</note> <title level="m">The Corsair</title> was the work of Charles Farley,
          so it is no surprise that Farley himself has translated the &quot;Historical Record,&quot;
          said to be &quot;from the Italian of Geoffrey Benini.&quot;<note n="8" place="foot"
            resp="author">Probably Giovanni-Vincenzio Benini (1744?-1814).</note> The source for
          Moore's play, so this edition declares, is <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince; or, The Loves of Don
          Sebastian de Nurillo, and the Fair Antonia</title>, translated &quot;from the Spanish of Hermandez
          de Feyjoo, a Writer of considerable eminence, who flourished towards the close of the
          fifteenth century.&quot;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="author"><title level="a">Advertisement by the
            Translator</title>, <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title> p. 3.</note> &quot;The Spanish Original,&quot; according to
          the note on the title-page, &quot;may be seen in the British Museum.&quot;<note n="10"
            place="foot" resp="author"><title level="a">Advertisement by the
              Translator</title>, <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title> p. 4,
            repeats the assertion that the reader may consult the original in the Archives of the
            British Museum.</note> The translator is identified on the title-page as &quot;C. Moor,
          Esq.&quot; In the <title level="a">Supplementary Remarks</title> it is stated that &quot;Mr. Charles
          Moore, an Irish gentleman of very respectable connexions, and well know to the literary
          world, by his translation of the Odes of Anacreon, has constructed the Musical
          Entertainment, recently produced at the Haymarket Theatre, under the title of the Gipsy
            Prince.&quot;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="author"><title level="a">Supplementary Remarks</title>, <title level="m">The Gipsy
            Prince</title>, p. 50.</note></p>
        <p>Every detail of this edition has been twisted to serve the hoax. There is no
          fifteenth-century Spanish author named Hermandez de Feyjoo. Although this name is to be
          found in the catalogue of the British Library, it occurs only in reference to this
          &quot;translation.&quot;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="author"><title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title>,
            British Library shelf mark: 12330.e.37.(2.).</note> There is no Spanish original. The
          translator is &quot;C. Moor,&quot; perhaps a playful reference to Carl Moor, the hero of
          Friedrich Schiller's <title level="m">The Robbers</title>, which had been translated into English by Alexander
          Tytler in 1792.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="author">Schiller, <title level="m">The Robbers</title>, trans.
            Alexander Fraser Tytler, Lord Woodhouselee, (London: G. G. J. &amp; J. Robinsons, 1792.
            Second edition, corrected and improved, 1795. Fourth edition, 1800).</note> The stage
          adaptation, Joseph Holman's <title level="m">The Red Cross Knights</title>, was revived at the Haymarket on August
          24, 1801,<note n="14" place="foor" resp="author">When Joseph G. Holman attempted to bring
            <title level="m">The Robbers</title> to the stage, John Larpent refused a license because of the politically
            volatile themes; in Holman's tamed adaptation, <title level="m">The Red Cross Knights</title> (first performed at
            Haymarket, 21 August 1799), he changed the name of Carl Moor to Ferdinand.</note>
          exactly one month after the opening of <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title>. Holman argued that Carl Moor was
          not the radical revolutionary some critics had argued him to be, but rather a man whose
          ethical character &quot;commands admiration, when devoted to a good cause, become a
          torment to the possessor, when perverted from the proper channel.&quot; The cause of that
          change, similar to the fate of the Gipsy Prince, derives from witnessing the evil abuse of
          power perpetrated by others.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="author">Leonard W. Conolly <title level="m">The
            Censorship of English drama, 1737-1824</title> (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1976), pp.
            98-99; letter dated 29 March 1799 from Joseph Holman to John Larpent, transcribed from
            the Folger manuscript W.b. 67 (63-63v).</note> In addition to the notorious &quot;C.
          Moor&quot; as translator, this edition also names the author of the English adaptation,
          &quot;Mr. Charles Moore,&quot; another nom de plume to join company with Anacreon Moore,
          Thomas Brown the Younger, and Thomas Little. As a prose narrative it shares similarities
          with Moore's <title level="m">The Epicurean</title>,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="author">Moore, <title level="m">The Epicurean, a
            Tale</title>. (London: Printed for Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green, 1827).</note> and as a
          polemical hoax championing the cause of the exploited Irish, it can be considered
          alongside of Moore's <title level="m">Memoirs of Captain Rock</title>.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="author"
            >Moore, <title level="m">Memoirs of Captain Rock: the celebrated Irish Chieftain, with some account of
            his ancestors, written by himself</title>. (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Brown and Green,
            1824); Moore and Mortimer O'Sullivan, <title level="m">Captain Rock detected, or, The origin and
            character of the recent disturbances and the causes, both moral and political, of the
            present alarming condition of the South and West of Ireland, fully and fairly considered
            and exposed</title>. (London: Printed for T. Cadell, 1824). Attributed to O'Sullivan as a reply
            to Moore's <title level="m">Memoirs</title>.</note> Kelly most likely authored the concluding notes to the songs,
          but the narrative, with its classical allusions and its three inserted lyrical poems, was
          the work of Moore himself.</p>
        <p>The major difference between the play and prose narrative is that the latter is charged
          with salaciously explicit sexual episodes, at odds with the insistence by &quot;C.
          Moor&quot; that &quot;Hermandez de Feyjoo&quot; possesses &quot;a very devout and
          religious character, indulges in prolix moral reflexions, and interlards his narrative too
          copiously with pious comment.&quot; With reminders that moral commentary has been omitted,
          the text preserves the flowery rhetoric of erotic indulgence. In their youth Roderic (not
          the uncle but the father of Antonia) and Dominic (the father of Sebastian) were students
          at the University of Saragossa. At the convent of St. Benito they encounter two novices,
          &quot;whose uncommon beauty and elegance of figure inspired them with, the most ardent and
          ungovernable passion.&quot; Obsessed with sexual desire, they manage &quot;to gain access
          to their mistresses&quot;:<quote>In an unguarded moment; whilst prudence slept, and
            passion usurped the reins from judgment, our panting Dulcineas, yielding to Nature's
            impulse, celebrated the virgin-sacrifice of Love, in the absence of Hymen. Once
            solemnized, their Cytherean rites were found too delightful and ecstatic not to be
            frequently repeated. (p. 7)</quote> When the girls become pregnant, Roderic and Dominic
          smuggle them out of the convent and flee to Italy where Sebastian and Antonia are born and
          where their mothers die within the year. Roderic, who seeks advancement in the Church,
          must pretend that Antonia is his niece. Sebastian is put under the care of an uncle and
          experiences a series of adventures that take him to the Far East and back again, at which
          point (p. 15) the events of the prose narrative begin to coincide with those of the play.
          After hiding the Gipsy Prince overnight the garden pavilion, Antonia decides it would be
          much better to disguise him in female attire to share her bedroom as her personal maid.
          The disguise works well enough until Don Roderic becomes sexually aroused at the sight of
          Antonia's new companion: &quot;The demon of desire instantly seized upon his
          reverence&quot; (p. 25), but his amorous assault is resisted with such a degree of
          violence that the chamber-maid's masculine identity is exposed. Far more than the stage
          play, the prose narrative reveals the moral hypocrisy of the Inquisitor.</p>
        <p>The prose version concludes with <title level="a">Supplementary Remarks</title> that promise &quot;a
          brief analysis and examination of the Play&quot; (p. 31), but present only the <foreign>Dramatis
            Personae</foreign> and the lyrics to the songs with notes apparently by Kelly. In his <title level="m">Reminiscences</title>,
          Kelly recalls how the collaboration on the play came about. The two met in the King’s Road
          at the cottage of Anna Maria Crouch, Kelly’s frequent singing partner on stage and
          full-time partner off stage. Together they had performed the roles of Fatima and Selim in
          Colman’s <title level="m">Blue-Beard</title>, Katherine and Seraskier in James Cobb’s <title level="m">The Siege of Belgrade</title>, Lady
          Elinor and Lord William in Cobb’s <title level="m">The Haunted Tower</title>, Louisa and Frederick in Prince
          Hoare’s <title level="m">No Song, No Supper</title>, Lodoiska and Count Floreski in John Philip Kemble’s <title level="m">Lodoiska</title>.
          Moore arrived at the cottage in the company of Michael Kelly’s brother Joseph. It was
          Kelly who instigated the collaboration:<quote>I was much entertained with his
            conversation, and cultivated his pleasing society; and, in the course of our
            acquaintance, persuaded him to write a musical afterpiece, for the Haymarket Theatre. I
            engaged with Mr. Colman to compose music, and to perform in it. It was called <title level="a">The
            Gipsey Prince,</title> and was performed for the first time on the 24th of July, 1801;
            part of the poetry was very pretty; but the piece did not succeed, and was
            withdrawn.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="author">Kelly, <title level="m">Reminiscences</title>,
            2:162.</note>
          </quote>
          Kelly's disappointment was not in the ten-day run, but in Colman's
          reluctance to slate the musical entertainment for the following year. As a sample of
          Moore’s lyrics, Kelly cited the song that he sang in his title role as the Gipsy Prince
          upon his first appearance in the Gipsy camp, &quot;I have roam’d through many a weary
          round.&quot; The theme of restless wandering is countered in the finale with the Gipsy
          Prince's declaration of abiding love to Antonia.</p>
        <p>In addition to his successes as stage tenor, Kelly was frequently enlisted as stage
          composer. Among the sixty-two dramatic works for which he composed the songs, thirteen
          were for William Dimond, including the adaptation of Byron’s <title level="m">Bride of Abydos</title> (Drury Lane,
          2 May 1818); seven were for Matthew Gregory Lewis, and six were for George Colman. Twice
          he teamed up with Charles Dibdin, twice with James Cobb. Among the box-office attractions
          featuring his music were also Lewis's <title level="m">The Castle Spectre</title> (Drury Lane, 14 December 1797)
          and Colman's <title level="m">Bluebeard</title> (1798), in both of which Kelly sang the lead tenor role. He
          composed the music for Richard Brinsley Sheridan’s <title level="m">Pizarro</title> (1799), Joanna Baillie’s <title level="m">De
            Montfort</title> (1800), and Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s <title level="m">Remorse</title> (Drury Lane, 23 January 1813). With
          a team as talented as Kelly and Moore, one might have expected Colman to provide a more
          enduring commitment.</p>
        <p><title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title> was Moore’s first endeavor as a playwright. The scene is set in Murcia,
          the province in southeast Spain between Andalusia and Valencia on the Mediterranean coast.
          The repression of Jews, Muslims, and Gipsies under the Inquisition had brought about
          cautious alliances among the persecuted.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="author">Burwick,
            <title level="a">The Jew on the Romantic Stage,</title> <title level="m">Romanticism and the Jewish Question,</title> ed.
            Sheila Spector (Ashgate Press, 2010). The combined representation of several oppressed
            peoples such as Jews, Muslims, and Gipsies recurs frequently in the plays of the
            period.</note> The plot is thin and most of the action is reflected in the fourteen
          songs. Although the characters are provided with little depth or development, the
          performers fleshed them out effectively both in acting and in song. The two comic
          characters, the obnoxious skirt-chasing Rincon and the Gipsy girl Poppee, have original
          and well-articulated roles.</p>
        <p>Kelly’s overture, in his usual manner, opens softly and simply, then quickly transforms
          itself into a bravura piece resolutely and immovably planted in D major. The shift in
          tempo is a motif that Kelly also employed in the <title level="a">Chorus of Gipsies,</title> which opens with a
          dirge, &quot;Bleak rains may fall,&quot; but then becomes a dance, &quot;Merry we still
          fly.&quot; In the opening scene, the peasants are gathered celebrating a wedding and
          singing in chorus of their contented life: &quot;Happy the hearts that love has
          blest.&quot; Intruding upon this happy scene, Rincon exercises his accustomed lechery by
          preying on the young girls: &quot;If one of you wishes a partner, my dearies,/ Or – dam’me
          – if two of you, I am the man.&quot; His first brazen flirtation is an attempt to seduce
          the bride, Blanch, while her peasant groom is pushed aside. As an occasion to introduce
          his character, his first song, was a series of risqué quatrains, each describing a
          unconsummated affair. This song, &quot;My heart, I confess has had amorous fidgets,&quot;
          was deleted, and for the performance Moore provided him with comic lyric, &quot;I
          remember,&quot; revealing the character's incapacities, slipping memory, and inability to
          distinguish his second-childhood from his first. For this song Moore composed the music as
          well as the lyrics, and it has the unique feature of avoiding the strophic structure
          typically preferred by Moore. Rincon sings of the prophecy of a toothless old woman, who
          promised him potency as a &quot;son of a gun.&quot;<note n="20" place="foot" resp="author"
            >William Henry Smyth (1788-1865). <title level="m">The Sailor’s Word-Book: an alphabetical digest of
            nautical terms, including some more especially military and scientific, but useful to
            seamen; as well as archaisms of early voyagers, etc. By the late Admiral W.H. Smyth ...
            Revised for the press by Vice-Admiral Sir E. Belcher.</title> (London: Blackie and Son, 1867).
            Son of a gun: &quot; An epithet conveying contempt in a slight degree, and originally
            applied to boys born afloat, when women were permitted to accompany their husbands at
            sea; one admiral declared he literally was thus cradled, under the breast of a
            gun-carriage.&quot;</note> His fancy can shoot even if he cannot.</p>
        <p>The role of Rincon, played by John Fawcett, provides the comic subplot of the piece.
          During the regular season, Fawcett performed as comic actor and singer at Covent Garden,
          popular in such comic roles as Jemmy Jump in John O’Keefe’s <title level="m">Farmer</title> (1787), Placid in
          Hannah Cowley’s <title level="m">Every One has his Fault</title>, Dr. Pangloss in George Colman’s <title level="m">The Heir at Law</title>
          (1797), and Ollapod in <title level="m">The Poor Gentleman</title> (1801). He was so successful as Caleb Quotem in
          <title level="m">Throw Physic to the Dogs</title> (1798), a comic opera by Henry Lee and Samuel Arnold, that for
          subsequent revivals it was retitled as <title level="m">Caleb Quotem and his Wife! or, Paint, Poetry, and
          Putty.</title> Fawcett’s first wife, the actress Susan Moore, died in 1797 after nine years of
          marriage. He married a second time in 1806 to Anne Gaudry, who played the role of Blanch,
          object of Rincon’s advances. Fawcett heightened the comedy of his performance as Rincon
          through his ineffectual persistence, seemingly oblivious of his own impotence.</p>
        <p>Scene 2 opens with the Gipsies gathered around a fire and singing &quot;Black rains may
          fall.&quot; The Gipsy Prince arrives, dressed &quot;in a fanciful half Eastern
          Dress.&quot; When his followers depart to set up their tents, the Prince sings his
          wandering song, &quot;I've roam'd thro' many a weary round.&quot; He is about to exit when
          two Alguazils, enforcing officers of the Inquisition, drag in a frail Jew. Hearing the
          Jew's pleas for help, the Prince asks the officers to tell him the man's crime, why they
          are treating him cruelly, and where they are taking him. His only crime is that he is a
          Jew, and for that crime he shall be thrown into the dungeon to await execution. The Jew is
          played by the husband of Mrs. Atkins, née Warrell, of Covent Garden. Describing her as a
          much admired singer, <title level="m">The Thespian Dictionary</title> (1805) observes that Mr. Atkins &quot;is
          oftener seen than heard.&quot; He was most often cast, that is, in pantomimic roles. So
          too here as the pursued and persecuted Jew, his role is to quake, cower, tremble, and,
          when rescued by the Prince, to show his humble gratitude. The Prince draws his sword and
          demands the old man's release. The Alguazils respond with swords; they fight; one officer
          is wounded, and both flee leaving their prisoner to escape. The Prince's skirmish with the
          Alguazils is secretly witnessed by Rincon.</p>
        <p>In protecting the old Jew, the Gipsy Prince arouses the wrath of the Grand Inquisitor,
          Don Roderick, played by veteran comic villain Richard Suett, known for such roles as
          Yusuph in Cobb’s <title level="m">Siege of Belgrade</title> (1791), Varnel in Kemble’s <title level="m">Lodoiska</title> (1794), the Sultan
          in Prince Hoare’s <title level="m">Mahmoud, Prince of Persia</title> (1796), and Ibrahim in Colman’s <title level="m">Blue-Beard</title>
          (1798). Scene 3 is set in the garden of the Inquisitor, Don Roderick, in the company of
          the Corregidor, Don Dominick, who presides as magistrate to sentence those who oppose the
          faith and order of the Church. Their conversation introduces two essential elements to the
          plot: Don Roderick has niece for whom he is eager to arrange a marriage; Don Dominick has
          a long lost son who would have been the ideal husband. Antonia, the niece, enters with
          singing and accompanying herself on the guitar. In a comic trio, <title level="a">Sweet oh!
          sweet,</title> Don Roderick curses the music as intolerable noise and Don Dominick begs her
          to play on. A messenger arrives with the news that a stranger has interfered with the
          arrest of a Jew and has wounded one of the officers. Don Roderick vows to capture the
          stranger and have him executed for the offence.</p>
        <p>In the characters of Don Dominick and Antonia, the cast is rounded out with two more
          strong players. John Emery had performed at Covent Garden as Able Drugger in <title level="m">The
            Tobacconist,</title> as Farmer Ashfield in <title level="m">Speed the Plough,</title> as Silky in <title level="m">Road to Ruin,</title> as Zekiel
          Homespun in <title level="m">The Heir at Law,</title> and Sam in <title level="m">Raising the Wind.</title> To her role as Antonia, Rosemond
          Mountain, née Wilkinson, brought what was widely acclaimed as a truly lyrical voice. At
          Covent Garden she performed as Fidelia in Edward Moore’s <title level="m">The Foundling</title> and as Leonora in
          Isaac Bickerstaff’s <title level="m">Padlock.</title> In disagreement over salary she left Covent Garden to perform
          at Haymarket and Drury Lane, also singing in concerts at Vauxhall.</p>
        <p>After Don Roderick and Don Dominick depart, Antonia is alone in the garden, pondering her
          uncle's insistence that she find a husband. Just at this moment the Prince clambers over
          the garden wall to escape his pursuers, not realizing that he has trespassed into the
          garden of the Grand Inquisitor himself. Careful not to alarm or frighten her, the Gipsy
          Prince emerges from hiding, bowing deeply, and praising her for her song. As happens in
          plays, they quickly fall in love, and express their mutual attraction in duet, <title level="a">Good
          night! Good night, I must away.</title> Antonia conceals the Prince in the turret in her
          uncle's garden, which may be bolted from within. To signal that he may safely open the
          door, she will strum on her guitar. When Don Roderick observes her lingering by the
          turret, she attempts to lull his suspicions by claiming that she has a pet bird.</p>
        <p>Scene 4 takes place that evening in the Gipsy camp. The duet by Poppee and Lachimee,
          &quot;Where Gipsy gone,/ Night falling on,/ Fly, to de tents in der willows fly &quot; is
          sung in dialect. In the dramatis personae they are identified as Hindu Gipsies. Moore is
          responding to recent research tracing the Hindu roots of the Romany language.<note n="21"
            place="foot" resp="author">In 1763, a Hungarian, Istvan Valyi, noticed similarities, to
            the extent of mutual intelligibility, between Gipsy language and that of students from
            Malabar. Johann Christian Christoph Rüdiger (1751-1822) confirmed the similarities,
            pointing in particular to Hindustani dialects; see: Rüdiger; <title level="m">Von der Sprache und
            Herkunft der Zigeuner aus Indien</title> (Leipzig 1782) Rpt. ed. Harald Haarmann (Hamburg:
            Buske, 1990). Moore may also have consulted: Matthew Raper (trans.), <title level="m">Dissertation on the
            Gipseys: representing their manner of life, family economy, occupations &amp; trades,
            marriages &amp; education, sickness, death and burial, religion, language, sciences
            &amp; arts &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. : with an historical enquiry concerning their origin
            &amp; first appearance in Europe.</title> (London, Printed by G. Bigg, and to be had of P.
            Elmsley, and T. Cadell, 1787); Raper translated the work of Heinrich Moritz Gottlieb
            Grellmann (1756-1804), <title level="m">Die Zigeuner Historischer Versuch über die Zigeuner; betreffend
            die Lebensart und Verfassung, Sitten und Schicksale dieses Volks seit seiner Erscheinung
            in Europa, und dessen Ursprung</title> (Göttingen: bey J.C. Dieterich, 1787).</note> Although
          newly arrived in Murcia, they might be presumed to speak Romany with a mixture of
          Spanish.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="author">In the refrain to her solo, <title level="a">Oh me
            was born to wander,</title> Poppee repeats the phrase &quot;Forma notta junga.&quot;
            Although these seem to be Spanish nouns (<foreign>forma</foreign> = form, shape, order; <foreign>nota</foreign> = note, sign,
            token; <foreign>junga</foreign> = spear, lance), I hesitate to speculate on a possible a meaning. As
            printed in Kelly's edition of the musical score, the words are &quot;Fooma molta
            junga.&quot;</note> For the London stage, Moore might have given them the dialect of
          English Gipsies. Instead, he has them speak in a Pidjin dialect already made familiar in
          such slave plays as Fawcett's <title level="m">Obi, or Three-Fingered Jack,</title> with music by Samuel Arnold,
          first performed at Haymarket just the year previous (5 July 1800)<note n="23" place="foot"
            resp="author">John Fawcett. <title level="m">Songs, Duets, &amp; Choruses, in the pantomimical drama of
            Obi, or Three-Finger'd Jack: (perform'd at the Theatre Royal, Hay Market) To which are
            prefix'd Illlustrative Extracts, and a Prospectus of the Action.</title> (London: T. Woodfall,
            1800). Story by John Fawcett and music by Samuel Arnold.</note>, or Colman’s <title level="m">Inkle and
          Yarico,</title> also with music by Samuel Arnold, which premiered at Haymarket fourteen years
          earlier (4 August 1787). Both <title level="m">Obi</title> and <title level="m">Inkle and Yarico</title> were again performed at Haymarket
          during the 1801 season with same actresses, Misses Tyrer and Manage, as African
          slaves.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="author">George Colman, the Younger. <title level="m">Inkle and
            Yarico. An Opera in Three Acts</title> (London: G. G. J. and J. Robinson, 1787); Genest,
            7:522-523.</note> Moore thus added a further dimension to the covert satire on the
          subjugation of the Irish. By having the Gipsy speak in a Pidjin dialect, he hinted that
          the minorities in Spain were treated by Inquisitors much as slaves at the hands of
          plantation slaveholders.</p>
        <p>Rincon enters as Poppee and Lachimee finish their song. They tease him and snatch at his
          clothes, tossing first his hat and then his wig to their companions. Just as they are on
          the point of removing more of his dress, the Alguazils rush in to arrest the Gipsies. In
          the Finale to Act I, with a melody adapted from Giovanni Paisiello, the Alguazils claim
          their prisoners, &quot;In the name and glory of the Inquisitory stand we
          command.&quot;<note n="25" place="foot" resp="author">Giovanni Paisiello, <title level="m">Il Re Teodoro
            in Venezia,</title> heroic-comic drama in two acts; premier performance at the Burgtheater,
            Vienna, August 23, 1784. Kelly was performing in Vienna from 1783 to 1787 and may have
            brought the music with him on his return to London. Paisiello has the opening bars from
            the familiar German fanfare, <title level="a">Hoch soll er leben.</title></note> As they are marched
          off to prison, the Gipsies deny their guilt in counter-chorus, &quot;Why need we fear your
          brow severe?/ What crime is ours?&quot;</p>
        <p>Again in the garden with the turret, Act II, Scene 1 opens with Antonia strumming her
          guitar to summon the Prince. Together they sing a duet, &quot;Come from thy Cage, silly
          bird, dost thou hear,/ Thy mistress is singing to thee.&quot; No sheet music was published
          for this song, nor is it listed with the song lyrics published with the hoax translation.
          Either the melody was too well known for Kelly to publish it with his compositions, or, as
          seems more likely, it was omitted from the performance. In the ensuing dialogue, the
          Prince reveals that he knows neither his parents nor even his own name. They no sooner
          take the garden path and stroll off-stage than Don Roderick and the Alcaide enter from the
          opposite side. The Alcaide reports that the Gipsies have been imprisoned and that their
          leader has yet to be found. During the latter half of this Alcaide's report, Antonia and
          the Prince reappear on stage. Antonia is able to conceal him once again in the turret
          before she is seen by her uncle. She again averts his suspicions with her story about
          keeping a pet bird. Swearing death to the Gipsy leader, Don Roderick exits, and leaves
          Antonia alone on stage to sing of a forlorn maid who has lost her lover, <title level="a">Yes, now I
          shall think of that heart broken maid.</title></p>
        <p>Following Antonia's exit, the garden becomes a hiding place for Rincon in his attempt to
          impose himself on Poppee. The manuscript version was revised for stage performance. As
          originally drafted, Rincon pulls the Gipsy girl after him, attempts to kiss her and ply
          her with wine. Their duet, which opens with Rincon's lines, &quot;Before then I fall to
          kissing you,/ Here is a drop to baptise you.&quot; Rincon's notion of &quot;baptism&quot;
          is to convert the heathen into a properly Christian consort. In the version as performed,
          Poppee enters the garden alone and sings a song that thematically parallels Antonia's
          lament for the heartbroken maid. But Poppee's lament is expressed in terms of a more
          resilient philosophy. One must deal with hardships and get on with life, a Gipsy's life of
          thievery and song. In her solo, <title level="a">Oh me was born to wander,</title> she tells of having
          run off with a drummer boy who subsequently abandoned her. Rincon enters to hear the final
          stanza of her song, and takes the lines to argue that she is a promiscuous heathen.
          Rincon's part in their duet, <title level="a">Fye, fye, you're quite a sinner, girl,</title> taunts her
          for her dingy skin and heathen ways. He intends to shame her as a wanton pagan, and then
          offer his forgiving embrace. Not deluded by his &quot;holier than thou&quot;
          condescension, Poppee turns the shame back on him: &quot;Eh! Have you got no shame now,
          man,/ For why you talk of christen?&quot; Replying to Rincon's effort to embrace her as
          his &quot;dingy Miss,&quot; Poppee tells him to get back to his &quot;fine white
          Miss.&quot; She is not for sale. In his next strophe, Rincon, Spanish profligate though he
          is, swears a very Irish oath, &quot;By the cowl of St. Bridget,&quot; the celebrated Nun
          of Leinster.</p>
        <p>After Poppee runs off, Rincon sees Antonia's guitar. He picks it up, brushes the strings,
          and the turret door opens. The Prince thinks that he has been caught by the Alguazirs.
          Rincon momentarily worries that he has been discovered as prowler in a stranger's garden,
          but that worry passes when he recognizes the Prince as the person who rescued the Jew and
          fought with the officers. To prevent Rincon from alerting the Alguazirs, the Prince locks
          him in the turret. Without realizing that the Prince has gone in search of her, Antonia
          returns from the opposite side of the stage, strums her guitar, and hears a clamor from
          within the turret. Puzzled that door has been locked from without rather than from within,
          she opens it and shouts in alarm when Rincon steps out. Rincon vows to call a guard to
          arrest the Gipsy who has locked him in. Antonia commences a song, <title level="a">Oh! in pity hear
          me suing,</title> joined first by Rincon, who quickly deduces that Antonia is protecting the
          Gipsy, then by the Prince, who is determined to lock him up again. With Rincon back in the
          turret the lovers ponder their fate. Would she be willing to forsake her heritage and live
          with a Gipsy? Would he be willing to give up his nomadic life of wandering to stay with
          her? In their duet, Antonia affirms, &quot;Yes, for thee too charming stranger,/ I could
          smile at every danger,&quot;<note n="26" place="foot" resp="author">The lyrics for
            <title level="a">Yes, for thee too charming stranger</title> are printed as a continuation of
            <title level="a">Oh! in pity hear me suing</title> in <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince; or, The Loves of Don
              Sebastian de Nurillo, and the Fair Antonia,</title> p. 40; in the musical score, <title level="m">The Gipsy
            Prince, A Comic Opera in Two Acts, [...] Compos’d &amp; Selected by Michael Kelly,</title> the
            duet follows the trio with the musical demarcation, &quot;Largo,&quot; pp. 59-61; the
            music to <title level="a">Yes, for thee too charming stranger</title> is then printed as a separate
            song, pp. 62-63. </note> but the Prince knows that he cannot expose her to a life of
          persecuted wanderings. Antonia and the Prince depart; the Alguazirs arrive, find the
          drunken Rincon locked in the turret, and arrest him as a heretic. The scene ends with the
          discovery of Antonia and the Prince, who are taken by the officers to stand before the
          tribunal of the Inquisition.</p>
        <p>Rincon is no foe of miscegenation as long as it entails no other commitment than sexually
          exploiting a Gipsy girl. Moore's play, however, also presents the opposite example of
          interracial love, the very matter that had come to be frequently addressed in criticism of
          <title level="m">Othello</title>.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="author">Kathleen Carliner, <title level="m">The Role of Racism in
            Shakespeare's <title level="m">Othello</title></title> (Washington, DC: Georgetown University Press, 1998). Edward
            Pechter, <title level="m"><title level="m">Othello</title> and Interpretive Traditions.</title> (Iowa City: University of Iowa Press,
            1999). Arthur J. Little, <title level="a">Witnessing Whiteness,</title> <title level="m">Shakespeare Jungle Fever:
            National-Imperial Re-Visions of Race, Rape, and Sacrifice</title> (Palo Alto: Stanford
            University Press, 2000): 68-101.</note> By the end of the eighteenth century,
          miscegenation had been redefined in the context of colonial expansion and the slave trade.
          In Colman's <title level="m">Inkle and Yarico</title>, an English trader, Inkle, is shipwrecked in the West Indies
          and rescued by a slave-girl,Yarico. They fall in love, but Inkle no sooner returns to
          civilization than he plans to sell Yarico into slavery and marry a wealthy white woman,
          Narcissa. At the last moment, Inkle's sense of love and honor revive, and he returns to
          marry the faithful Yarico. Interracial, yes, but a white male makes the choice.<note
            n="28" place="foot" resp="author">Daniel O'Quinn, <title level="a">Mercantile Deformities: George
              Colman's <title level="m">Inkle and Yarico</title> and the Racialization of Class Relations.</title> <title level="j">Theatre
            Journal</title> 54.3 (2002) 389-409.</note> In Moore's play, it is a white woman, like
          Desdemona, who is about to defy the taboo. At the crucial moment, however, Moore provides
          the not altogether unanticipated turn. The Gipsy Prince is not a Gipsy at all.</p>
        <p>When he is brought before the Inquisitor, the Corrigidor, and the Alcaide to confront
          charges of opposing the Church, he is recognized by Don Dominick as his long-lost son,
          Sebastian. Although he might now take his place among the elite class of Murcia, Sebastian
          has lived too long among the Gipsies to ignore their plight. Once pardoned, he makes a
          passionate appeal for the release of his people. Moore avoids a facile and contrived
          happy-ending by making it clear that the problems of racial subjugation and class
          exploitation still persist. For the finale, the lovers are joined by the Gipsies and they
          sing in chorus a turnabout of the Gipsy Prince's first song. He has now found a bride and
          a home: &quot;The Gipsy Prince no more shall roam.&quot;</p>
        <p>Moore's libretto adheres to the conventional formula of the popular musical
          entertainment. In its romance plot it cautiously compromises the theme of interracial
          marriage, but in its comic subplot it more boldly ridicules and denounces the exploitation
          of the subjugated and marginalized lower classes. Moore's lyrics were fully integrated
          into situation and character, not simply interpolated, as was often the case in
          contemporary musical production. Kelly's musical settings were apt and varied, even the
          tunes adapted from Paisiello. The entire performance had the support of an experienced and
          capable cast. The humor depended chiefly upon Fawcett, who acted the lecherous and tipsy
          Rincon. His song, <title level="a">I remember,</title> with music as well as words by Moore, was the
          most original composition of the piece. The saucy and self-reliant Poppee was played by
          Miss Tyrer, who had joined Haymarket just the previous season, when she performed as
          Josephine in <title level="m">Children in the Wood.</title> She had been tutored in voice by Anna Maria Crouch, and
          Kelly arranged her songs especially for her voice. At the close of the season at
          Haymarket, Miss Tyrer chose the role of the slave-girl in <title level="m">Inkle and Yarico</title> for her benefit
          performance (September 28, 1801).<note n="29" place="foot" resp="author">Genest,
            7:523.</note> After leaving Haymarket, she performed on the Dublin stage.<note n="30"
              place="foot" resp="author">See entry for Miss Tyrer in <title level="m">The Thespian Dictionary</title> (London:
            J. Cundee, 1805).</note>
        </p>
        <p>The <title level="a">Notice</title> in <title level="j">The Monthly Mirror</title> (July, 1801) judged <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince</title>
          &quot;flimsy and uninteresting,&quot; but praised the good taste and &quot;scientific
          arrangement&quot; of the music. As Moore's biographer Ronan Kelly has observed, the
          dialogue was panned but the music was praised. Billed as a &quot;Musical
          Entertainment,&quot; the songs were &quot;applauded heartily&quot; and &quot;praised
          unanimously&quot; in the reviews. The critic in <title level="j">Morning Post</title> (25 July 1801) complained
          that &quot;the reputed author of the dialogue had not been very studious of
          originality.&quot;<note n="31" place="foot" resp="author">Ronan Kelly, <title level="m">Bard of Erin, The
            Life of Thomas Moore</title> (Dublin: Penguin Ireland, 2008), pp. 83-85. Ronan Kelly cites the
            reviews in the <title level="j">Morning Post,</title> and the <title level="j">Monthly Mirror.</title> From the <title level="j">London Times</title> he also
            quotes the reviewers complaint that &quot;the dialogue is as destitute of wit and humour
            as the incidents are devoid of novelty and bustle which is necessary to gratify the
            taste of the present day.&quot; </note> The dissatisfaction with the dialogue was not
          altogether unjustifiable. To be sure, the romance plot accompanied by comic sub-plot
          adhered to the conventional formula for the genre, and the amorous old man was a stock
          character. But Rincon presented a marked departure from the stock stereotype. The
          interracial theme was current but not widely risked by other playwrights. Nor had any
          recent work presented Gipsies as major characters. <title level="m">The Gipsies,</title> a comic opera by Charles
          Dibdin, was performed at the Haymarket (3 August 1778). In that work, a brother and sister
          of nobility (Clarin and Spinetta), together with the sister’s maid (Laura), disguise
          themselves as Gipsies for amusement.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="author">Charles
            Dibdin, <title level="m">The Gipsies. A comick opera, in two acts. As it is performed at the
            Theatre-Royal in the Haymarket</title> (London: printed by T. Sherlock, for T. Cadell, 1778).
            Genest, 6:35.</note> Moore and Kelly created a more original and daring piece than
          critics of the period were willing to acknowledge in print. Far more bold than bringing to
          the stage Gipsies, or would-be Gipsies, was the hint that honest Irishmen were behind the
          disguise and the Inquisitors were stand-ins for the deluded agents of the British
          government.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="citations">
        <head>Works Cited</head>
        <listBibl>
          
          <biblStruct>
            <analytic>
              <author>Burwick, Frederick</author>
              <title level="a">The Jew on the Romantic Stage</title>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="m">Romanticism and the Jewish Question</title>
              <editor role="editor">Sheila Spector</editor>
              <imprint>
                <publisher>Ashgate Press</publisher>
                <date>2010</date>
                <biblScope type="pp">23-9</biblScope>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Carliner, Kathleen</author>
              <title level="m">The Role of Racism in Shakespeare's Othello</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Georgetown University Press</publisher>
                <date>1998</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Colman, the Younger George</author>
              <title level="m">Inkle and Yarico. An Opera in Three Acts</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>G. G. J. and J. Robinson</publisher>
                <date>1787</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <!-- Letter citation needed -->
          <biblStruct>
            <analytic>
              <author>Conolly, Leonard W.</author>
              <title level="a">Letter</title>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="m">The Censorship of English drama</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>San Marino</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Huntington Library</publisher>
                <date>1976</date>
                <biblScope type="pp">98-99</biblScope>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Dibdin, Charles</author>
              <title level="m">The Gipsies. A comick opera, in two acts. As it is performed at the
                Theatre-Royal in the Haymarket</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>T. Sherlock</publisher>
                <date>1778</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Fawcett, John</author>
              <title level="m">Songs, Duets, &amp; Choruses, in the pantomimical drama of Obi, or
                Three-Finger'd Jack: (perform'd at the Theatre Royal, Hay Market) To which are
                prefix'd Illlustrative Extracts, and a Prospectus of the Action</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>T. Woodfall</publisher>
                <date>1800</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Grellmann, Heinrich Moritz Gottlieb</author>
              <title level="m">
                <foreign xml:lang="ge">Die Zigeuner Historischer Versuch über die Zigeuner;
                  betreffend die Lebensart und Verfassung, Sitten und Schicksale dieses Volks seit
                  seiner Erscheinung in Europa, und dessen Ursprung</foreign>
             </title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>
                <publisher>J.C. Dieterich</publisher>
                <date>1787</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <analytic>
              <author>Heffner, Hubert</author>
              <title level="a">The Haymarket Theater under Colman the Younger, 1789 to 1805</title>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="m">Communication Monographs</title>
              <imprint>
                <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                <biblScope type="vol">10</biblScope>
                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                <date>1943</date>
                <biblScope type="pp">23-9</biblScope>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Kelly, Michael</author>
              <title level="m">Reminiscences of Michael Kelly, of the King's Theatre, and Theatre
                Royal Drury Lane, including a period of nearly half a century; with original
                anecdotes of many distinguished persons, political, literary, and musical</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>H. Colburn</publisher>
                <date>1826</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Kelly, Ronan</author>
              <title level="m">Bard of Erin, The Life of Thomas Moore</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>Dublin</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Penguin Ireland</publisher>
                <date>2008</date>
                <biblScope type="pp">83-85</biblScope>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <!--Unsure if this was analytic or monograph-->
          <biblStruct>
            <analytic>
              <author>Little, Arthur J.</author>
              <title level="a">Witnessing Whiteness</title>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="m">Shakespeare Jungle Fever: National-Imperial Re-Visions of Race, Rape,
                and Sacrifice</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>Palo Alto</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
                <date>2000</date>
                <biblScope type="pp">68-101</biblScope>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Moore, Thomas</author>
              <title level="m">Songs, Duets, Trios, and Choruses, in the Gipsy Prince, a Musical
                Entertainment in Two Acts, first performed at the Theatre-Royal, Hay-Market, July
                24, 1801. The Overture and Musick Composed and Selected by Mr. Kelly</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>T. Woodfall for Mssrs. Cadell and Davies</publisher>
                <date>1801</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Moore, Thomas</author>
              <title level="m">The Gipsy Prince, A Comic Opera in Two Acts, Now Performing with
                Universal applause at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket, Compos’d &amp; Selected by
                Michael Kelly</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <date>1801</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Moore, Thomas</author>
              <title level="m">Memoirs of Captain Rock: the celebrated Irish Chieftain, with some
                account of his ancestors, written by himself</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Longman, Hurst, Rees, Brown and Green</publisher>
                <date>1824</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Moore, Thomas</author>
              <author>O'Sullivan, Mortimer</author>
              <title level="m">Captain Rock detected, or, The origin and character of the recent
                disturbances and the causes, both moral and political, of the present alarming
                condition of the South and West of Ireland, fully and fairly considered and
                exposed</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>T. Cadell</publisher>
                <date>1824</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Moore, Thomas</author>
              <title level="m">The Epicurean, a Tale</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green</publisher>
                <date>1827</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Pechter, Edward</author>
              <title level="m">Othello and Interpretive Traditions</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>Iowa City</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Georgetown University Press</publisher>
                <date>1999</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <analytic>
              <author>O'Quinn, Daniel</author>
              <title level="a">Mercantile Deformities: George Colman's Inkle and Yarico and the
                Racialization of Class Relations</title>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title level="m">Theatre Journal</title>
              <imprint>
                <biblScope type="vol">54</biblScope>
                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                <date>2002</date>
                <biblScope type="pp">389-409</biblScope>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <!--Person who translated the German book by Grellmann into English-->
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Raper, Matthew</author>
              <title level="m">Dissertation on the Gipseys: representing their manner of life,
                family economy, occupations &amp; trades, marriages &amp; education, sickness, death
                and burial, religion, language, sciences &amp; arts &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. : with
                an historical enquiry concerning their origin &amp; first appearance in Europe</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>G. Bigg</publisher>
                <date>1787</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Roach, John</author>
              <title level="m">Authentic Memoirs of the Green-room; involving sketches,
                biographical, critical, &amp; characteristic, of the performers of the Theatres
                Royal, Drury-lane, Covent-Garden, and the Hay-Market. Embellished with seven
                portraits of eminent performers</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Roach</publisher>
                <date>1806</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <!-- this is a translation and has several printings listed -->
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Schiller</author>
              <title level="m">The Robbers</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>G. G. J. &amp; J. Robinsons</publisher>
                <date>1795</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Smyth, William Henry</author>
              <title level="m">The Sailor’s Word-Book: an alphabetical digest of nautical terms,
                including some more especially military and scientific, but useful to seamen; as
                well as archaisms of early voyagers, etc</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>Blackie and Son</publisher>
                <date>1867</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <!--Unknown author of dictionary-->
          <biblStruct>
            <monogr>
              <author>Unknown</author>
              <title level="m">The Thespian Dictionary</title>
              <imprint>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <publisher>J. Cundee</publisher>
                <date>1805</date>
              </imprint>
            </monogr>
          </biblStruct>
          <!--The Corsair; or the Italian Nuptials. Citation?-->
          <!--The Loves of Don Sebastian de Nurillo, and the Fair Antonia. Citation?-->
          <!--Blue-Beard. Citation?-->
          <!--The Siege of Belgrade. Citation?-->
          <!--The Haunted Tower. Citation?-->
          <!--No Song, No Supper. Citation?-->
          <!--Lodoiska. Citation?-->
          <!--Bride of Abydos. Citation?-->
          <!--The Castle Spectre. Citation?-->
          <!--Bluebeard. Citation?-->
          <!--Pizarro. Citation?-->
          <!--De Montfort. Citation?-->
          <!--Remorse. Citation?-->
          <!--Farmer. Citation?-->
          <!--Every One has his Fault. Citation?-->
          <!--The Heir at Law. Citation?-->
          <!--The Poor Gentleman. Citation?-->
          <!--Throw Physic to the Dogs. Citation?-->
          <!--Caleb Quotem and his Wife! or, Paint, Poetry, and Putty. Citation?-->
          <!--Mahmoud, Prince of Persia. Citation?-->
          <!--The Tobacconist. Citation?-->
          <!--Speed the Plough. Citation?-->
          <!--Road to Ruin. Citation?-->
          <!--The Heir at Law. Citation?-->
          <!--Raising the Wind. Citation?-->
          <!--The Foundling. Citation?-->
          <!--Padlock. Citation?-->
          <!--Children in the Wood. Citation?-->
          <!--The Monthly Mirror. Citation?-->
          <!--Morning Post. Citation?-->
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
