<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Gipsy Prince</title>
				<author>
					<name>Thomas Moore</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Frederick Burwick</editor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Justin Tonra</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoding and Proofreading</resp>
					<name>Deborah K. Wright</name>
				</respStmt>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>2011-05-01</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<extent/>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">mooreGipsyNarrative</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
					Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2010-10-20">May 1, 2011</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
						or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
						purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
						use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
						are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
						with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
						permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
						requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be
						forwarded to Romantic Circles:
						<address>
							<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
							<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
							<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
							<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
							<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
							<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
						</address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
						conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
								without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
								other than their current ones.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
						them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
						have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
						Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
						continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
						a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
						use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title level="m">The Gypsy Prince</title>
						<author>Thomas Moore</author>
						<editor>Frederick Burwick</editor>
						<respStmt>
							<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
							<name>Justin Tonra</name>
						</respStmt>
						<respStmt>
							<resp>Encoding and Proofreading</resp>
							<name>Deborah K. Wright</name>
						</respStmt>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles at the University of Maryland</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park Maryland</pubPlace>
							<date when="2011-05-01">May 1, 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p><gi>Speaker</gi> element names have been regularised across this file and the
						Manuscript file, according to the names reproduced in the Dramatis Personae
						printed in the Historical Narrative: Don Roderic; Don Dominic; Gipsy Prince;
						Rincon; Old Jew; Alcaide; Alguazil(s); Officer(s); Messenger; Gipsies;
						Diego; Antonia; Poppee; Lachimee; Blanch; Alguazils, Peasants, Gipsies, etc.
						Note: the regularisation takes place only within <gi>speaker</gi> elements;
						it does not occur in the stage directions, text of the play or Dramatis
						Personae.</p>
				</normalization>
				<hyphenation>
					<p>All dashes have been represented with an emdash: <gi>&#x2014;</gi>, and
						surrounding whitespace has been deleted (except where dash is preceded by a
						full stop).</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for
						‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Incorrect and idiosyncratic spelling has not been regularised; instances are
						marked by a <gi>sic</gi> element.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="genre">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
						on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
			<variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef scheme="#genre" target="g6"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="#DKW" when="2011-02" n="1">
				<label>Changed by the editor</label>
				<name xml:id="MC">Deborah K. Wright</name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI-encoded using P5</item>
					<item>Codes and comments added by DKW, 2-23-11.</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#JT" when="2011-03-21" n="2">
				<label>Changed by the editor</label>
				<name xml:id="JT">Justin Tonra</name>
				<list>
					<item>Some minor changes and corrections. Including corrections to typographic
						errors (to line 527) in the transcription already encoded by Deborah K.
						Wright</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#JT" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
				<label>Changed by the editor</label>
				<name>Justin Tonra</name>
				<list>
					<item>Full proof correction of the encoded text against images of the original
						document.</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#JT" when="2011-07-12" n="4">
				<label>Changed by the editor</label>
				<name>Justin Tonra</name>
				<list>
					<item>Regularisation of <gi>speaker</gi> names, detailed above in
							<gi>normalization</gi>.</item>
					<item>Regularisation of dashes to em dashes. Detailed above in
							<gi>hyphenation</gi>.</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#JT" when="2011-07-13" n="5">
				<label>Changed by the editor</label>
				<name>Justin Tonra</name>
				<list>
					<item>All <gi>note</gi> elements are now encoded at their point of attachment in
						the text.</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<front>
			<div>
				<listWit>

					<witness xml:id="a">Thomas Moore, The Gipsy Prince, A Comic Opera in Two Acts,
						Now Performing with Universal applause at the Theatre Royal, Haymarket,
						Compos'd &amp; Selected by Michael Kelly (Printed for Michael Kelly, to be
						had at his Music Warehouse, No. 9 New Lisle Street, Leicester Square, &amp;
						at all Music Shops [1801]).</witness>

					<witness xml:id="c">The Gipsy Prince; or, The Loves of Don Sebastian de Nurillo,
						and the Fair Antonia, translated from the Spanish. By C. Moor, Esq. To which
						is added, The Corsair; or The Italian Nuptials. (London: J. Roach. 1801).
						64pp. -- Front. dated Sept. 7, 1801. [BL shelfmark:
						12330.e.37.(2.)].</witness>
				</listWit>
			</div>

			<pb/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativetitlepageThumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
			<titlePage>
				<docTitle>
					
					<titlePart type="main">THE<lb/> GIPSY PRINCE;</titlePart>
					<lb/>
					<titlePart type="sub">OR, THE LOVES OF<lb/> DON SEBASTIAN DE NURILLO,<lb/> AND THE<lb/>
						<emph>FAIR ANTONIA</emph>, </titlePart>
				</docTitle>
				<byline>TRANSLATED FROM THE SPANISH<!-- I've changed the note element and its attributes from <note anchored="true"> to this, simply because it works for our xslts. A different solution will be necessary. DR. --><note place="foot" resp="editors" n="1"> (<emph
							>The</emph> SPANISH ORIGINAL <emph>may be seen in the</emph>
						British Museum.)</note>.<lb/>
					<lb/> BY C. MOOR, Esq.</byline>
				<lb/>
				<docTitle>
					<titlePart type="sub">To which is added, the<lb/> CORSAIR;<lb/> OR, THE<lb/>
						<emph>ITALIAN NUPTIALS</emph>.</titlePart>
					<lb/>
				</docTitle>
				<lb/>
				<argument>
					<p>N.B. On these two genuine Historical Narratives, are founded; 1st. The New
							<emph>Musical Entertainment</emph> of the GIPSY PRINCE, and
						2nd. The <emph>Dramatic Romance</emph> of the CORSAIR; or the
						ITALIAN NUPTIALS, performed at the Haymarket Theatre, with universal
						Applause; being the ONLY NEW DRAMAS, produced at the Summer Theatre, during
						the present Season.</p>
				</argument>
				<docImprint><pubPlace><hi>LONDON:</hi></pubPlace><lb/>
					<publisher>PRINTED BY AND FOR J. ROACH,</publisher>
					<address><addName>AT THE<lb/>
					<hi>Britannia Printing-Office</hi>,</addName><lb/>
					<addrLine>RUSSEL-COURT, DRURY-LANE.</addrLine></address><lb/>
					<date when="1801">MDCCCI</date></docImprint>
				<lb/>

			</titlePage>


			<pb n="3"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep3Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
			<div>
				<head><emph>ADVERTISEMENT</emph>.<lb/> BY THE TRANSLATOR.</head>
				<p>THE following genuine Historical Narrative is translated from the Spanish of
					HERMANDEZ DE FEYJOO, a Writer of considerable eminence, who flourished towards
					the close of the fifteenth century. With the exception of a few necessary
					abridgments, where the Spanish writer, who appears to have been a very devout
					and religious character, indulges in prolix moral reflexions, and interlards his
					narrative too copiously with pious comment, the Translator has adhered, with the
					greatest fidelity, to the text of the original. He has, likewise, in verifying
					the little poetical specimens, occasionally interspersed in the work,
					endeavoured to keep, as closely as possible, not only to the <emph
						>spirit</emph>, but to the <emph>precise turn of expression</emph>
					of his author. In this view, he has likewise preserved the <emph
						>original metre</emph>, and in two or <fw type="catch">three</fw>
					<lb/>
					<pb n="4"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep4Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">ADVERTISEMENT.</fw> three instances
					sacrificed a poetical beauty, to a faithful transcript of the author's
					sentiments. This, he is well-aware, is contrary to the general custom of
					translators; who not unfrequently make the original work a mere vehicle to
					convey and usher-in their own ideas&#x2014;but this mode of conduct, the
					translator of the present work has never been able to reconcile with his fixed
					ideas of justice, consistency, and honor. Such as it is, he commits his
					performance to the Public, under the gratifying impression of having
					conscientiously discharged his duty, as far as the question involves literary
					integrity, fidelity and truth. In how far the translator is warranted in
					advancing this public boast, the learned Reader may easily convince himself, by
					referring to the <emph>Archives</emph> of the <emph
						>British Museum</emph>.</p>
				<lb/>



			</div>
		</front>
		
		<body>
			<div type="narrative">
				<pb n="5"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep5Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>


				<head>THE<lb/> GIPSY PRINCE;<lb/> OR, THE LOVES OF<lb/> DON SEBASTIAN DE
					NURILLO,<lb/> AND THE<lb/> FAIR ANTONIA, &amp;c.</head>

				<p>DON JUAN DE NURILLO, the father of Don Sebastian, and Don Francisco de Mena, the
					father of Antonia, were descended from two of the most ancient and illustrious
					families in Spain. They were first-cousins, and being nearly of the same age,
					were from their earliest infancy brought up together. After going through a
					preparatory course of school-discipline, they were placed at the University of
					Saragossa, where they made the most rapid improvement in their studies,
					combining the erudition of the scholar with the accomplishments which bespeak
					the gentleman. The fairest prospects opened to their view, when Love, that grand
					source, as well of our misfortunes as our happiness, involved them in an adven-
						<fw type="catch">t<supplied reason="character missing">u</supplied>re</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="6"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep6Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> ture, which
					entirely reversed the scene, and darkened their horizon with big and lowering
					clouds.</p>
				<p>Attending Grand Mass one day, at the convent of St. Benito, in the vicinity of
					Fraga, their attention was diverted from the duties of devotion to the
					contemplation of two novices, whose uncommon beauty and elegance of figure
					inspired them with the most ardent and ungovernable passion. The object of their
					admiration did not fail to perceive the effects wrought by their
					charms;&#x2014;a deeper blush instantly suffused their glowing cheeks at the
					discovery, which added to their attractions, and completed their triumph. During
					the remainder of the service, our amorous swains continued to feast their
					ravished eyes with the delectable prospect, imbibing large and copious draughts
					of Love's delicious poison. Service ended, they watched with circumspect heed
					the departure of the Nuns, and as the two fair novices entered the convent-gate,
					had a fortunate opportunity of exchanging a look, which spoke more than the most
					expressive language is competent to convey. 'Twas, indeed, to adopt the Poet's
					energetic phrase:
						<!-- what is the purpose of the 'indent6' attribute - how is this different from 'indent'? --><quote
						rend="indent6">"Silence, that spoke! and eloquence of eyes!"</quote></p>
				<p>Every other object was now lost and absorbed in the prosecution of this new
					pursuit. Many were the wiles and stratagems employed by our two friends, to gain
					access to their mistresses; but <fw type="catch">as</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="7"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep7Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE</fw> as a detail of
					particulars would lead us into too wide a field of digression; and as we are not
					writing The History of Don Juan and Francisco, but that of their children, we
					shall follow the example of the great Father of Epic composition, who, instead
					of commencing his narrative, <emph>ab ovo</emph>, wisely, as Horace
					remarks: <quote rend="indent6"><lg>
							<l>"Semper ad eventum festinat, et in medias res,</l>
							<l>"Non secus ac notas, auditorem rapit."</l>
						</lg></quote> Suffice it, therefore, to observe, that after a long series of
					amorous siege, the two lovers succeeded in their hopes. Persevering attention,
					backed by opportunity, proved victorious. In an unguarded moment; whilst
					prudence slept, and passion usurped the reins from judgment, our panting
					Dulcineas, yielding to Nature's impulse, celebrated the virgin-sacrifice of
					Love, in the absence of Hymen.</p>
				<p>Once solemnized, their Cytherean rites were found too delightful and ecstatic not
					to be frequently repeated; 'till at length consequences, such as might naturally
					be expected from such transactions, roused them from their delicious dream to
					scenes of perplexity and dismay. Here our Spanish author launches out into a
					wide field of pious argumentation on the virtue of chastity, and the evils which
					accrue from the heinous sin of concupiscence, in which (however edifying, his
					remarks <fw type="catch">may</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="8"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep8Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> may be) we do
					not conceive it necessary to follow him on the present occasion. Passing,
					therefore, from moral disquisition to narrative&#x2014;though the ladies were
					not professed, and consequently not liable, not having taken the veil, to the
					dreadful, punishment attendant on the violation of the monastic vow; yet had
					they and their gallants just cause of apprehension from the resentment of their
					friends, who, in the event of a discovery, would not fail to wipe out the
					dishonour brought upon their family by blood. To prevent such dire extremities
					an elopement was agreed upon, and speedily carried into execution. The necessary
					preparations being made for flight, the convent-walls were scaled, under the
					propitious auspices of the sable Goddess of Night, and the two novices,
					disguised in male attire, accompanied their lovers to Barcelona, where they
					embarked on board a vessel bound for Leghorn.</p>
				<p>On their arrival in Italy, they were married, and soon after settled in a
					delightful retreat on the banks of the Arno. Here, in due process of time, the
					ladies were both delivered&#x2014;the one of a son&#x2014;the other of a
					daughter; (the hero and heroine of our present narrative) but though they
					survived the pangs of child birth, they were not doomed long to taste the joys
					of mother-hood. <fw type="catch">They</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="9"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep9Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> They both of
					them died within a twelvemonth, leaving their husbands disconsolate for their
					loss.</p>
				<p>Deprived of their beloved companions, their Tuscan retirement now became
					insupportable. Every scene reminded them of lost happiness; every object but too
					forcibly recalled past joys, the recollection of which was now painful. Our two
					friends resolved, therefore, to leave Italy, and return to Spain, where it was
					their intention to "bid adieu to the world," and embrace a life of penitence and
					devotion. Unwilling to expose <emph>Antonia</emph>, whose delicate
					frame required the nurse's tenderest care, to the perils and inconveniences of
					the sea, arrangements were made for leaving her in Italy. They then embarked for
					Carthagena, where the young <emph>Sebastian</emph> was placed under
					the fosterage of an uncle, named Alvarez. Having thus disposed of their
					children, they repaired to the city of Murcia, where they took the vows and
					monastic habit&#x2014;Don Juan assuming the name of <emph
						>Dominic</emph>, and Don Francisco that of <emph>Roderic</emph>.</p>
				<p>Here then for the present, we take our leave of Don Francisco, and Don Juan, to
					follow the fate and adventures of <emph>Sebastian</emph>. He had not
					yet completed his seventh year, when his uncle <emph>Alvarez</emph>,
					finding him an enterprizing and spirited lad, determined, with the consent of
						<emph>Sebastian</emph>'s father to take his nephew with him on a
					voyage <fw type="catch">of</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="10"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep10Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> of discovery.
					The ship was principally fitted out for the purpose of conveying missionaries to
					China, Ava, Siam, and other remote Eastern territories; but <emph
						>Alvarez</emph> combined with this part of its destination, views of a
					different nature, involving mercantile profit. Fate, however, had differently
					decreed. <emph>Alvarez</emph> had not been landed in Ava many weeks,
					before he was seized with a malignant fever, which in a few days carried him to
					his grave, leaving our hero in the most distressing situation, an orphan, in a
					remote foreign country, the manners and language of which were alike strange and
					unknown to him. Fortunately for <emph>Sebastian</emph>, he had, by his
					frank and cheerful disposition, ingratiated himself into the affection of a
					Jesuit friar, who, on the death of his uncle, took him under his own care, and
					instructed him in the sciences, with the express design of bringing him up for a
					missionary.</p>
				<p>Under this worthy man, <emph>Sebastian</emph> improved rapidly; and in
					the course of four years made a wonderful proficiency, not merely in classical
					knowledge; but in the different languages of the East. It was not, however, the
					will of the Destinies, that the advantage he reaped from the friar's tuition
					should be permanent. <emph>Sebastian</emph> was now in his twelfth
					year, when <emph>Fereira</emph> (for that was our friar's name)
					resolved to visit the neighbouring <fw type="catch">kingdoms</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="11"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep11Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> kingdoms of
					Pegu and Siam. <emph>Sebastian</emph> accompanied him on the journey;
					but scarcely had they entered the confines of the Siamese territory, before they
					were set upon by a party of the natives, who murdered <emph
						>Fereira</emph> on the spot, and, took our hero prisoner. To his youth alone
					was it owing, that <emph>Sebastian</emph> did not experience a similar
					catastrophe with the friar.</p>
				<p>Our hero was sold as a slave to one of the principal men in the country; who at
					first employed him in a menial capacity; but soon finding him apt and
					intelligent, raised him to a post of superior trust, and generally carried him
					as his attendant, when he went to pay his court to the monarch. This Prince
					ranks among the most despotic sovereigns in the world. The mandarins themselves,
					and the highest officers of state, must always prostrate themselves, when they
					approach the royal presence. The same spirit of abject submission pervades the
					subordinate classes. Servants must always appear before their masters in a
					kneeling posture; and not only bear taunt and rebuke without reply; but even
					affect to consider stripes, kicks, and buffettings, as an honour conferred upon
					them. The monarch holds his court, and permanently resides in the city of Siam,
					from which the whole kingdom takes its name. His palace is nearly three miles in
					circumference, and is orna- <fw type="catch">mented</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="12"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep12Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> mented with
					the most costly materials. It contains among other articles of value, seven
					idols, each six feet in height, cast in gold of two inches thick, and richly
					studded with diamonds, gems, and other precious stones. The fronts of the
					different houses, of which it is composed, dazzle the eye with the brightness of
					their lustre, being gilt, painted and varnished to an indescribable refulgence.
					The honours paid to the monarch border almost on adoration. His will is law—nor
					does his authority acknowledge any controul.</p>
				<p>It was at the court of this Prince that <emph>Sebastian</emph> formed
					an acquaintance with one of those Eastern Sages, known by the name of Magi, and
					who to this day profess the doctrines of the great Zoroaster, from whom they
					claim an uninterrupted lineal descent. <emph>Kherbhorzsching</emph>
					(the name of this Sage) was a native of Cambodia, a country but little explored
					by Europeans. He was thoroughly versed and initiated in all the mysteries of
					Oriental divination, and the sacred rites of the Fire-worship. He had traversed
					not only the vast continent of Asia, but every habitable part of Africa,
					particularly Ethiopia, and the fertile plains of Egypt, where he was introduced
					to the subterranean <emph>adyta</emph> of the priests. Twelve months
					did he watch the motions of the heavenly bodies on the summit of Caucasus, and
					frequently by his potent spells, <fw type="catch">arrested</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="13"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep13Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> arrested the
					progress of the labouring moon. Nor was Europe itself unknown to his researches.
					He had peregrinated the several states of Greece, Turkey, Italy, Germany,
					Hungary and Poland; had peeped into the crater of Vesuvius, and joined a
					conclave of necromancers in the frozen climes of Lapland. In fine, he had
					attained to the very <emph>achme</emph> of magical science, and stood
					at the head of that sacred order.</p>
				<p>The more effectually to train and instruct <emph>Sebastian</emph>, for
					whom <emph>Kherbhorzsching</emph> had conceived a strong paternal
					affection, he redeemed our hero from servitude, and not only admitted him as a
					companion, but adopted him as his own son. After he had duly initiated him in
					all the arcana of magic science, and thoroughly qualified him for the grand
					design he had in contemplation, he communicated to him the project he had formed
					for the revival of the ancient race Astrologers, in the accomplishment of which
					he fixed upon <emph>Sebastian</emph> for his principal instrument and
					co-adjutor. <emph>Sebastian</emph> readily gave into his views, and
					the necessary preparations were accordingly made to carry the scheme into
					effect.</p>
				<p>For this purpose they travelled, joined by a large number of followers, to
					Ethiopia, where they still further augmented their troop, and then passed into
					Egypt. Here a solemn meeting or con- <fw type="catch">clave</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="14"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep14Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> clave was
					held, in the caverns of the largest of the Pyramids, at which <emph
						>Kherbhorzsching</emph> was unanimously and formally appointed the Head and
					Chief of the New Order, and as such, invested with the insignia of Sovereign
					Command. This done, it was next resolved to pass over into Spain, where they
					doubted not to raise a large body of adherents among the Moors. The Jews,
					likewise, formed an object of speculation; but, before this part of the business
					could be carried into execution, <emph>Kherbhorzsching</emph> died,
					appointing <emph>Sebastian</emph> to be his successor, which
					nomination was confirmed by the unanimous suffrage of the whole troop.</p>
				<p>The original intention was to land in Granada, that province being more overrun
					with Moors, as well as Jews, than any other part of Spain; but contrary winds
					drove them to the vicinity of the Cape de Palos, where they disembarked. Aware
					of the rigour of the Catholic discipline, they concealed themselves in a vast
					forest, <emph>Sebastian</emph> undertaking the perilous adventure of
					reconnoitring the disposition of the inhabitants. Several volunteered to
					accompany him; but <emph>Sebastian</emph> peremptorily insisted on
					sallying forth alone, fearful, on the one hand, of exciting alarm by carrying
					along with him too great an attendance, and reluctant, on the other, to furnish
					cause for jealousy among his fol- <fw type="catch">lowers</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="15"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep15Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> lowers, by
					giving the preference to any particular person, or number of individuals.</p>
				<p><emph>Sebastian</emph> had not proceeded many miles, on his
					reconnoittring journey, before he encountered a Jew, whom the officers of the
					Holy Inquisition were dragging to prison. The venerable aspect of the wretched
					Israelite, and the visible agony under which he laboured, excited his
					compassion. The unfortunate man appeared to be in the decline of life, and
					supplicated for his release in terms of the most piteous despondency. <emph>Sebastian</emph> strongly sympathised in his distress. Add to
					this, that the present seemed a favourable opportunity of promoting the peculiar
					and specific object of his mission. By succouring an oppressed individual, he
					hoped to conciliate the good will of the Jews at large. He therefore stepped
					forward to interrogate the officers, as to the cause of the Jew's arrest, when
					receiving, as might, indeed, be naturally expected, an unsatisfactory and even
					insolent answer, he, without further parley, drew his sword, flew on the
					alguazils, one of whom he instantly levelled with the ground—on which the other
					took to his heels, and sought safety by flight.</p>
				<p>The Jew kneeling to his deliverer, returned thanks for his rescue ; but at the
					same time warned our hero of the imminent jeopardy he had incurred. <fw
						type="catch">If</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="16"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep16Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> If
					apprehended, (and strict and immediate search would infallibly take place) his
					life, he apprized him, was forfeited beyond the hopes of redemption&#x2014;death
					being the inevitable consequence of obstructing the officers of the Inquisition.
					He therefore entreated our hero to consult his own safety by instant flight. <emph>Sebastian</emph> felt the full weight and cogency of this
					advice. Giving the Jew directions, and a passport of reception to his troop, he
					hastily took leave of him, and striking into a different path, endeavoured to
					elude pursuit.</p>
				<p>Evening was now drawing on; when <emph>Sebastian</emph> winding the
					brow of a hill, discovered a troop of horsemen at no great distance. Not
					doubting but that these were his pursuers, he quickened his pace, till he found
					himself in the vicinity of a large and populous town. To retreat, was
					impossible; to proceed, certain and inevitable destruction. In this dilemma he
					scaled the walls of a garden, which skirted the suburbs, and concealing himself
					in a pavillion, the door of which was very opportunely left open, awaited the
					approach of night.</p>
				<p>He had not remained long in this condition, before the sound of a lute struck his
					ears, and engaged his most serious attention. <emph>Sebastian</emph>
					cautiously drew near the lattice, and beheld a lady of great youth and beauty,
					who seating herself in an <fw type="catch">arbour</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="17"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep17Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> arbour near
					him, sang the following lines with a degree of sweetness that charmed his inmost
					soul, and for the moment caused him to forget the perilous situation in which he
					stood.</p>

				<lg part="I">
					<head>SONG</head>
					<l>SOFT Arno's stream&#x2014;how sweet! <emph>divino!</emph>
					</l>
					<l>As on its flow'ry banks we rove;</l>
					<l>Its cool retreats, its neat <emph>casino!</emph></l>
					<l>Its jassmine bower, and myrtle grove!</l>
					<l>There Tuscan swains, in soft <emph>soprano</emph>,</l>
					<l>Whisper the soothing, amorous tale;</l>
					<l>There Tuscan maids, in sweet <emph>piano</emph>,</l>
					<l>Coo, murmuring with the sighing gale!</l>
				</lg>

				<lg part="F">
					<l>Ah! lead me to the calm <emph>reposo</emph>,</l>
					<l> Where all the Loves and Graces dwell!</l>
					<l>Where ev'ry swain, <emph>affettuoso</emph>,</l>
					<l>Tenderly sighs his flame to tell!</l>
					<l>Where ev'ry nymph dissolves in blisses;</l>
					<l><emph>Caro!</emph> oh, <emph>Caro!</emph> waft me
						there,</l>
					<l>Where pains and sorrows die in kisses,</l>
					<l>Kisses, that charm, and heal despair!</l>
				</lg>

				<p>Having concluded her song, the lady arose, and was preparing to depart. The
					ineffable sweetness and benignity, which beamed forth in her looks, bespoke a
					soul, of Heaven's own likeness, and guaranteed the goodness of her heart. <emph>Sebastian</emph>
					<fw type="catch">felt</fw>
					<lb/>
					<pb n="18"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep18Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> felt inspired
					with confidence, and determined to avail himself of so favorable an opportunity.
					Quitting, therefore, his concealment, he threw himself at the lady's feet, and
					briefly stating his case, implored her protection. The lady, as soon as she had
					recovered from the surprize in which such unexpected interview naturally
					involved her, sympathized in the misfortunes of our hero, and promised to
					befriend him, to the utmost of her power. She counselled him, to pass the
					ensuing night in the pavillion, which was appropriated for her own use, and the
					key of which she put into his hands. She then went into the house, from which
					she soon returned with some refreshments, and a few necessaries to render <emph>Sebastian</emph>'s nocturnal abode in the pavillion more
					comfortable.</p>
				<p>Here it will be necessary for us to revert to the former part of our narrative,
					in order to account for certain circumstances, which otherwise might well excite
					the reader's astonishment. A Spanish lady, on the banks of the Segura, in the
					province of Murcia, and in the suburbs of the very capital of that province,
					chaunting a Tuscan song, descriptive of the beautiful scenery, which graces the
					flowery banks of Arno, is certainly a novel case, and demands some
					explanation.</p>
				<p>The reader will remember, that we took leave of the fathers of our hero and
					heroine, at the <fw type="catch">time</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="19"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep19Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> time of their
					embracing the monastic life. Their exemplary conduct, and strict devotion soon
					attracted the notice of the Superiors of the convent, and paved the way to their
					preferment. In due process of time they passed through all the different
					gradations of monastic rank, and on the demise of the Head Officers of the
					Inquisition established at Murcia, were appointed to fill their places, <emph>Roderic</emph> being nominated the <emph>Inquisitor
						General</emph>, and <emph>Dominic</emph> the <emph
						>Corregidor</emph> of the Holy Office.</p>
				<p>At the time this event took place, <emph>Antonia</emph>, the daughter
					of <emph>Roderic</emph>, whom we left in Tuscany, had attained her
					twentieth year. <emph>Roderic</emph> being now in circumstances, which
					admitted of her company, sent for her to Murcia, and lodged her in a pleasant
					house in the suburbs, where for the sake of obviating scandal, and to prevent
					curiosity, she pass<supplied reason="character missing">e</supplied>d for his
					niece. It was the wall of the very garden appertaining to this villa, which <emph>Sebastian</emph> scaled, as already recorded, and the lady,
					whose compassion afforded him an asylum, was no other than <emph
						>Antonia</emph> herself.</p>
				<p>Two years had intervened since <emph>Antonia</emph>'s arrival in
					Murcia, and her present rencounter with <emph>Sebastian</emph>. During
					that period many were the offers made her of marriage&#x2014;noble and
					honourable the list of suitors that solicited her hand. She was fair, as the
					dawning of day! lovely as the <fw type="catch">paradise</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="20"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep20Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> paradise of
					God! Her fine auburn locks waved gracefully over her arched and open forehead;
					or descended in wanton ringlets down her pearly neck, and sported on her
					shoulders. Her bright sparkling eyes resembled a clear expanse of water, on
					which the glorious sun casts his refulgent beam! Like Heaven's own lightning,
					they penetrated to the beholder's heart! but, like lightning, their effulgence
					was insufferable, and pained the aching sense! Her nose was aquiline, and gave a
						co<supplied reason="character missing">m</supplied>manding air to her
					appearance. The blush of her cheeks outvied the damask rose! and in their
					dimples lurked a thousand Cupids in ambush to ensnare the palpitating heart! Her
					mellifluous mouth was a garden of sweets! the honey-combs of Hybla--the perfumes
					of Arabia were there assembled and concentrated! Her coral lips swelled, as it
					were, to meet the ecstatic kiss, which their pruriency provoked! Her teeth
					surpassed in whiteness the driven snow and for regularity might be compared, in
					the language of Solomon, to a flock of sheep, that are even-shorn! Her neck, at
					once lovely and majestic, with swan-like curve, might serve as a model for the
					consort of imperial Jove! Her breasts were like the clusters of
					Engedi!&#x2014;firm and elastic to the touch! gently heaving to the motion of
					the pulse! downy pillows, on which Love would wish to lie entranced to all
					eternity! <fw type="catch">Her</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="21"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep21Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> Her figure
					corresponded in every respect with the transcendent charms of her face! She was
					alike distinguished for symmetry, and elegance! To sum up, the aggregate of her
					perfections, we may say of her, in the words of the Poet: <quote rend="indent6"><lg>
							<l>In Nature's fairest mould,</l>
							<l>Whilst Heav'n, and ev'ry genial power,</l>
							<l>Propitious smil'd, and hail'd the hour,</l>
							<l>Was blest Antonia form'd—an angel's mind</l>
							<l>Dwelt in an angel's frame enshrin'd!</l>
							<l>So flames the Orient gem, encas'd in gold!</l>
							<l>So flames in rich Golconda's mine,</l>
							<l>Where Phoebus, with meridian blaze,</l>
							<l>Darts vertical his burning rays</l>
							<l>And sublimates the precious stone,</l>
							<l>The produce of the torrid zone,</l>
							<l>To climes more temperate unknown.</l>
							<l>So flames the diamond; so sparkling rubies shine;</l>
							<l>Antonia's lustre such, and such her radiance divine.</l>
						</lg></quote> Such was <emph>Antonia</emph>&#x2014;such the person
					for whose fair hand a thousand suitors contended; but contended in vain! Was it,
					that <emph>Antonia</emph>, the fair Antonia, was insensible to love?
					Was it, that with a form calculated to kindle the flame of fierce desire in the
					bosom of every male beholder, she herself was incapable of participating in the
					passion which herself inspired? Far, from it. Her <fw type="catch">feeling</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="22"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep22Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> feelings were
					equally delicate and refined, as her person. To what cause then, continues our
					Spanish Historian&#x2014;are we to attribute this seeming indifference and
					insensibility, on the part of <emph>Antonia</emph>? Doubtless,
					marriages are decreed, and registered in Heaven! The proper hour had not yet
					struck&#x2014;the proper object not yet presented himself to her view.</p>
				<p>Leave we, however, our author to pursue his moral reflections&#x2014;and let us
					return to <emph>Sebastian</emph>. The reader will easily conceive that
					his situation was not the most enviable, and that he had sufficient cause of
					uneasiness to disturb his slumbers, and break in on his repose. Yet, amidst all
					his difficulties, he derived no small share of consolation, from the
					recollection of the lively sympathy and interest which the fair <emph>Antonia</emph> evidently took in his fate. Early habituated to a
					life of adventure and vicissitude, he had learnt to bear the reverses of fortune
					with stoic apathy; and, though not insensible of the imminent jeopardy in which
					he stood, yet was he not wholly cast down, and discomfited. Hence, after
					ruminating for some time on his forlorn condition, he resolved to bear with
					fortitude, what it was not in his power to alter, and the fatigues he had
					undergone, in the course of the day, contributing to second the calls <fw
						type="italic">of</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="23"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep23Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> of Nature, he
					fell in a few hours into profound sleep.</p>
				<p>From this state of mental abstraction, he was, aroused by the greetings of the
					fair <emph>Antonia</emph>, who rising with the lark (for her slumbers,
					likewise had been greatly broken-in upon and invaded, by busy and restless
					thought) sallied into the garden, and approaching the pavilion, gave the signal
					for <emph>Sebastian</emph> to make his appearance, by singing the
					following Lines, accompanied by her lute</p>
				<lg part="I" n="1">
					<head>1</head>
					<l>Damon! awake, unseal thine eyes,</l>
					<l>'Tis Celia calls, and bids thee rise;</l>
					<l>Celia, whose love, sincere and true,</l>
					<l>Claims some return of love from you.</l>
					<l>Damon! awake, unseal thine eyes,</l>
					<l>Thy Celia calls, and bids thee rise.</l>
				</lg>
				<lg part="M" n="2">
					<head>2</head>
					<l>The soaring lark his matin sings,</l>
					<l>And all the grove with music rings;</l>
					<l>The sun already darts his ray,</l>
					<l>And ushers in the cheerful day.</l>
					<l>Damon! awake, unseal thine eyes,</l>
					<l>Thy Celia calls, and bids thee rise!</l>
				</lg>
				<lg part="F" n="3">
					<head>3</head>
					<l>No curious prying eye is near;</l>
					<l>No list'ner on the watch, to hear;</l>
					<fw type="catch">Alone</fw>
					<lb/>
					<pb n="24"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep24Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>
					<l>Alone I come; alone I rove,</l>
					<l>With silent step, the conscious grove.</l>
					<l>Damon! awake, unseal thine eyes,</l>
					<l>Thy Celia calls, and bids thee rise!</l>
				</lg>

				<p><emph>Sebastian</emph> readily obeyed the welcome summons, and opening
					the door of the pavillion, had the pleasure of passing an hour in close <emph>tête â tête</emph> with the fair <emph>Antonia</emph>.
					Many were the plans they successively devised and rejected for securing <emph>Sebastian</emph>'s safety and escape; at length it was agreed,
					that <emph>Antonia</emph> should furnish him with female attire, and
					under that disguise, shelter him in the house, till the officers of the
					Inquisition, finding their search fruitless, should be induced to discontinue
					their pursuit, from which, it was hoped, they would the sooner desist, as the
					officer supposed to have been killed, turned out to be only wounded, and was
					pronounced by the physicians to be within the reach of recovery.</p>
				<p>This scheme was accordingly carried into immediate execution; but unfortunately
					the very means adopted to conceal our hero, proved the efficient cause of his
					detection. <emph>Don Roderic</emph>, notwithstanding the ostensible
					austerity of his manners, and his apparent sanctity, was still at heart a rake,
					and had sufficient of the old leaven in his composition, to lead him astray into
					the paths of sly and hidden licentiousness. The very day, that <fw type="catch"
							><emph>Antonia</emph></fw><lb/>
					<pb n="25"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep25Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>
					<emph>Antonia</emph> introduced <emph>Sebastian</emph> into
					the house, <emph>Don Roderic</emph> happened to indulge rather to
					freely in the good things of this world—in plain language, he had partaken of
					savoury viands, and delicious wines, till they had an effect, not altogether <emph>spiritual</emph>, on his bodily system, and excited that species
					of insurrection in the flesh, which St. Paul metaphorically designates by the
					scriptural phrase of a "<emph>war in the members</emph>." In this
					condition, his pulse beating high, and his blood running riot, he happened, to
					stumble on <emph>Sebastian</emph>, who, as we have already observed,
					was equipped in female attire, and was sitting in <emph
					>Antonia</emph>'s bedroom. The love of novelty and variety forms a leading feature
					in the character of libertines. Hence <emph>Don Roderic</emph> no
					sooner perceived a new face, than he felt his passion inflamed to a double pitch
					of violence. The demon of desire instantly seized upon his
					reverence&#x2014;place and opportunity both conspired to abet his libidinous
					inclinations&#x2014;Without further ceremony, therefore, <emph>Don
						Roderic</emph> attacked <emph>Sebastian</emph>, and was proceeding
					to extremities, when a blow from our hero felled him to the ground. This
					salutation was followed by other symptoms, which sufficiently discovered <emph>Sebastian</emph>'s actual sex, and compelled <emph
						>Don Roderic</emph> to a precipitate retreat.</p>
				<p>The alarm was now given, and the <emph>ambiguous</emph>
					<fw type="catch">chamber-</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="26"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep26Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> chamber-maid
					taken into custody. The circumstance of a man lurking in the house, under the
					disguise of a female, was of itself, sufficient to attract the notice of the
					Holy Office. <emph>Sebastian</emph> was accordingly, without further
					examination cast into a damp and frightful dungeon, where he was left to
					ruminate, at leisure, on his wretched fate.</p>
				<p>On his being brought before the Inquisition for examination, he was immediately
					recognized for the person who had attacked the officers, and rescued the Jew.
					Things seemed now to be in a bad train with him. No hopes, no chance remained of
					escaping the punishment attendant on so flagrant an outrage&#x2014;under these
					circumstances his death appeared inevitable.</p>
				<p>He was accordingly remanded back to prison, till the Head Inquisitor, and the
					Corregidor, who were better employed in feasting and regaling the inner-man,
					should be at leisure to attend the examination and enquire into the particulars
					of his case.</p>
				<p>We shall not attempt to describe the emotions of the fair <emph
						>Antonia</emph>, on receiving the intelligence of <emph
						>Sebastian</emph>'s arrest. For such a task, language is much too feeble and
					imperfect. Gravely to tell the reader, that the sentiments she entertained for
						<emph>Sebastian</emph> were not merely the effect of sympathy and
					commiseration, that they partook of a warmer <fw type="catch">passion,</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="27"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep27Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> passion,
					would be an insult to his understanding. Unconscious even to herself, <emph>Antonia</emph> harboured the lurking passion of love; the wanton
					God had taken a just aim, and shot his shaft to her very heart&#x2014;Yet still,
					so guileless and innocent was the fair nymph, she scarcely knew herself the
					nature of those feelings which agitated her bosom, till the news of <emph>Sebastian</emph>'s apprehension aroused her to a true sense of
					the actual state of her heart.</p>
				<p>The following day, <emph>Sebastian</emph> was brought up to undergo a
					formal examination. The <emph>Head Inquisitor</emph> and the <emph>Corregidor</emph>, dressed in their robes of office, presided on
					this solemn occasion. There was no occasion to consume much time in receiving
					the deposition of witnesses. Our hero's identity was soon proved, nor did he
					attempt to deny or render doubtful the fact, on which he stood arraigned.</p>
				<p>His fate, therefore, was considered as already determined. All that remained;
					previous to passing the irrevocable sentence, was to interrogate him, as to his
					past course of life. <emph>Sebastian</emph> was not one of those
					head-strong, contumacious characters, who, when they see themselves cut off from
					all hope of escaping the vengeance of the law, refuse, in sullen mood, to give
					an answer to any just question, that may be propounded by the judge. On the
					contrary, he maintained throughout the <fw type="catch">whole</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="28"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep28Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> whole of this
					trying scene, a courteous and dignified demeanour. Death he had long learnt to
					look in the face, without dismay; and he felt no spark of resentment against
					those, who in their judicial capacity, were only discharging their duty.</p>
				<p>When questioned, therefore, relative to his past life, he cheerfully replied with
					frankness and without reserve. Of his infant years, he observed, he recollected
					but little. His parents, he did not remember&#x2014;all he knew, was, that at an
					early age, he was placed under the care of an uncle, named <emph
						>Alvarez</emph>&#x2014;that he accompanied this relative and foster-parent to
					Ava, where he had the misfortune to lose him shortly after their arrival.</p>
				<p>At the name of <emph>Alvarez</emph>; but still more so, at the mention
					of Ava—both the <emph>Head Inquisitor</emph> and the <emph
						>Corregidor</emph> eyed <emph>Sebastian</emph> with a look of the
					most eager and fixed attention. The latter, in particular, appeared most
					strangely agitated. His voice faltered; his respiration hung suspended, and
					scarcely could he muster strength to ask the prisoner a few incoherent questions
					when suddenly rising from his seat, he rushed towards <emph
						>Sebastian</emph>, and fondly clasping him in his arms: "He is my
					son!&#x2014;my son!&#x2014;my long-lost son!&#x2014;my dear <emph
						>Sebastian</emph>!"&#x2014;&#x2014;he exclaimed in a paroxysm of joy and
					perturbation.</p>
				<p>Here we shall copy the example of <emph>Timanthes</emph>, <fw
						type="catch">and</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="29"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep29Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> and,
					despairing of doing justice to the feelings of parental and filial love, draw a
					veil over the affecting scene, which followed this recognition. The examination
					was, of course closed, and the prisoner conducted by his newly discovered
					father, not to the dungeons of the Inquisition; but to an apartment in his own
					house, whither <emph>Don Roderic</emph> accompanied him. The pleasing
					intelligence soon reached the ears of the agonized <emph
						>Antonia</emph>, who quickly joined them at the <emph
						>Corregidor</emph>'s.</p>
				<p>Yet, though the <emph>Corregidor</emph> , in the person of the
					prisoner, had discovered his own son, and though the <emph>Head
						Inquisitor</emph> was not only his intimate friend; but himself related to <emph>Sebastian</emph> , it was not in their power to remit the
					sentence against our hero, without a previous pardon from the Holy See. That all
					possible interest was made to obtain this necessary step, the reader will
					naturally conclude. Nor were their applications ineffectual. As no actual murder
					had been committed (the officer's wounds not proving mortal, as was first
					apprehended) the Pope, to whom a circumstantial representation of the whole case
					was made, granted a full pardon to <emph>Sebastian</emph> , on
					condition, that he should renounce his Pagan tenets, make a public and formal
					recantation of his errors, and re-enter the pale of the Mother-Church. To <fw
						type="catch">these</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="30"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep30Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE. </fw> these
					conditions, <emph>Sebastian</emph> readily acceded; only stipulating
					for a free passport for his followers, to return unmolested to Ethiopia, which
					was granted. <emph>Sebastian</emph> , thereupon made a public
					confession of the Christian faith, and was shortly after married to the fair <emph>Antonia</emph> . The rich felicity he experienced from this
					union, infinitely outweighed all the visionary schemes of happiness, which he
					had flattered himself to obtain by the accomplishment of his ambitious
					projects.</p>

			</div>
			<div>
				<head>SUPPLEMENTARY REMARKS.</head>
				<p>FROM the foregoing materials, which we have translated with great fidelity, from
					the Spanish of HERMANDEZ DE FEYJOO. <emph>Mr. Charles Moore</emph>, an
					Irish gentleman of very respectable connexions, and well known to the literary
					world, by his translation of <!-- code added 2-23-11 by DKW --> the <emph>Odes of Anacreon</emph>, has constructed the Musical
					Entertainment, recently produced at the Haymarket Theatre, under the title of
					the <emph>Gipsy Prince</emph>. As customary with dramatic, writers,
					when they dramatize an historical record, he has not adhered to the letter of
					his text, or the strict matter of fact; but introduced such new characters, as
					to him appeared necessary, to give a greater and more pleasing general effect to
					his piece. In order <fw type="catch">that</fw><lb/>
					<pb n="31"/><figure rend="rightFloat"><graphic url="../images/HistoricalNarrativep31Thumb.jpg" width="80px"/></figure>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw> that the
					reader may have the means and opportunity of appreciating, in how far Mr. MOORE
					is indebted to our Spanish author, and in how far he has indulged his own
					creative fancy, we shall enter into a brief <emph>analysis</emph> and
					examination of the Play, as performed with great and merited applause at the
					Haymarket Theatre. The Music to the Piece, partly original, and partly selected,
					is furnished by Mr. KELLY, and does honor to that gentleman's taste and
					judgment.</p>
			</div>

			<!-- From this point on, I have not been able to check the accuracy of the transcript, as
			there are no images from the document available. Consequently, there is not the same degree 
			of consistency with matters such as em dashes, white space, and dubious transcriptions. The 
			one modification I have made below is to change <hi> to <hi rend="italic> in all instances. 
			Fred Burwick has told with reference to the following text that "the textual variants [between 
			this and the ms] are minor and are already marked in my annotations. JT 2011-07-07. -->

			<div type="Dramatis_Personae">
				<head>DRAMATIS PERSONAE.</head>
				<p><castList>
						<castItem><role xml:id="dr">Don Roderic, (the <hi>Inquisitor</hi>)</role>
							<actor>Mr. Suet.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="dd">Don. Dominic, (<hi>Corregidor</hi>)</role>
							<actor>Mr. Emry</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="gp">Gipsy Prince,</role>
							<actor>Mr. Kelly.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="rin">Rincon,</role>
							<actor>Mr. Fawcett.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="oj">Old Jew,</role>
							<actor>Mr. Atkins.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="alc">Alcaide </role>
							<actor>Mr. T. Truman.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="alg">Alguazils,</role>
							<actor>Messrs. Caulfield, Klanert, Ledger.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="off">Officers,</role>
							<actor>Messrs. Stokes, Wilkins.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="mes">Messenger,</role>
							<actor>Mr. Chippendale.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="gip">Gipsies</role>
							<actor>Master Menage, Mr. Abbot</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="die">Diego,</role>
							<actor>Mr. King.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="ant">Antonia (<hi>Niece to Don Roderic</hi>)</role>
							<actor>Mrs. Mountain.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="pop">Poppee Hindu Gipsy Women </role>
							<actor>Miss Tyrer.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="lac">Lachimee,</role>
							<actor>Miss B. Menage</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="bla">Blanch,</role>
							<actor>Miss Guidry.</actor></castItem>
						<castItem><role xml:id="apg">Alguazils, Peasants, Gipsies,
							etc.</role></castItem>
					</castList>
					<stage type="setting">Scene&#x2014;Murcia.</stage></p>
			</div>

			<pb n="32"/>
			<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE. </fw>

			<div>
				<p>The Piece opens with a rich display of rural scenery. </p>

				<sp>
					<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>HAPPY the hearts that love has blest</l>
						<l>With such a tie, so sweet as this:</l>
						<l>All their nights are nights of rest,</l>
						<l>And all their days are days of bliss.</l>
						<l>Never shall time their love eclipse,</l>
						<l>Tho' it may steal some fire away;</l>
						<l>But, like the roses on their lips,</l>
						<l>Their joys shall mellow, not decay.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>Enter RINCON<note place="foot" resp="editors" n="2">The character of <emph
							>Rincon</emph>, a busy, meddling, but whimsical and good-natured fellow,
						is the author's own invention, and is, in the representation admirably
						sustained by Mr. FAWCETT<sic>,</sic>
					</note>.</stage>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<lg>
						<l>Zounds! What a merry-go-frisk-away here is.</l>
						<l>To it, my pigeons, as brisk as you can;</l>
						<l>If one of you wishes a partner, my dearies,</l>
						<l>Or&#x2014;dam'me&#x2014;if two of you, I am the Man!</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<sp>
					<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
					<l>Happy the hearts &amp;c.</l>
				</sp>

				<p>The <emph>Mock Bravura</emph>, which follows this <emph
						>Chorus</emph>, is of a very peculiar kind, and affords ample scope for the
					inimitable comic powers of Mr. FAWCETT.</p>

				<lb/>
				<pb n="33"/>
				<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

				<stage>MOCK BRAVURA <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="3">The music of this Bravura, which is highly
						characteristic, and has a truly original turn, is the composition of the
						author of the Piece, and does great credit to his
					talents.</note>&#x2014;RINCON.</stage>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<lg>
						<l>I REMEMBER</l>
						<l>'Twas last December,</l>
						<l>When the tips, Ma'am,</l>
						<l>Of old women's noses</l>
						<l>Blush like roses,</l>
						<l>Or your lips, Ma'&#x2014;</l>
						<l>'Twas then&#x2014;I remember</l>
						<l>'Twas, last November&#x2014;</l>
						<l>No, just December,</l>
						<l>When an old mumbling witch,</l>
						<l>Whose gums could scarcely nibble,</l>
						<l>Mutter'd from a ditch,</l>
						<l>And told me like a Sibyll!</l>
						<l>"Rincon, my boy, thou'lt make a row!"</l>
						<l>She said to me, as I'm saying now;</l>
						<l>And said I</l>
						<l>In reply&#x2014;</l>
						<l><app>
								<lem wit="#c">Now</lem>
								<rdg wit="#a">[No]<hi rend="sup">a</hi></rdg>
							</app> – says she</l>
						<l>To me</l>
						<l>"Thou'lt be the babe of wonder!</l>
						<l>"Be thunder!</l>
						<l>"Be lightning;</l>
						<l>"The universe frightening,</l>
						<l>"My cradle (she said) had been a large <hi>cannon</hi>!"</l>
						<l>By the bye,</l>
						<l>Thought I</l>
						<l>A very fine thing to nurse a man in!</l>

						<lb/>
						<pb n="34"/>
						<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

						<l>'Twas this they repute,</l>
						<l>Taught my fancy to shoot,</l>
						<l>And made me more flashy than others,</l>
						<l>I'm the son</l>
						<l>Of a gun,</l>
						<l>And bullets are my sisters and brothers!</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>CHORUS OF GIPSIES. (<emph>Kelly</emph>.) </stage>
				<sp who="#gip">
					<lg>
						<l>Bleak rains may fall, and winds whistle over us,</l>
						<l>Nothing but heaven and darkness to cover us.</l>
						<l>Merry we still fly,</l>
						<l>Where our fates lead us,</l>
						<l>Winter or chill sky</l>
						<l>Cannot impede us.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>SONG <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="4">There is an exquisite degree of sweetness in this
						soft and plaintive air. It ranks, indeed, among the very best pieces of
						composition in the whole <sic>drama,</sic>
						<!-- code added 2-23-11 by DKW --><!-- This should presumably be a full stop,
						but in the absence of the original document to confirm, I have let the comma 
						stand. JT, 2011-07-07. --></note>&#x2014;GIPSY
						PRINCE&#x2014;(<emph>Kelly</emph>.)</stage>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<lg part="I">
						<l>I have roam'd through many a weary round,</l>
						<l>I have wander'd East and West;</l>
						<l>Pleasure in every clime, I found,</l>
						<l>But sought in vain for rest.</l>
					</lg>

					<lg part="M">
						<l>While glory sighs for other spheres,</l>
						<l>I see; that <emph>one</emph>'s too wide,</l>
						<l>And think the home, which love endears,</l>
						<l>Were worth the world beside.</l>
					</lg>

					<lb/>
					<pb n="35"/>
					<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

					<lg part="F">
						<l>"The needle thus, too rudely mov'd,</l>
						<l>"Wanders unconscious where,</l>
						<l>"Till having found the place it lov'd,</l>
						<l>"It trembling, settles there!"</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>TRIO&#x2014;ANTONIA, DON RODERIC, DON DOMINIC&#x2014;(<emph
						>Kelly</emph>.) </stage>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="5">It is impossible for any person, who has
							not witnessed the representation, to form an adequate conception, either
							of the native sweetness of this melody, or the beautiful manner which
							Mrs. MOUNTAIN executes it.</note></speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Sweet, oh! Sweet the spring is coming,</l>
						<l>Nature's heavenly blush appears;</l>
						<l>Earth expands her breathing bosom,</l>
						<l>To be bath's in vernal tears.</l>
						<l>Sweet, oh! Sweet the spring is coming,</l>
						<l>Nature's heavenly blush appears;</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#dr">
					<speaker>Don Roderic</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Stop, oh! Stop your plaguy strumming,</l>
						<l>Or you will kill me thro' my ears,</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#dd">
					<speaker>Don Dominic</speaker>
					<l>Bravo! Delightful!</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#dr">
					<speaker>Don Roderic</speaker>
					<l>Bah! ‘tis frightful!</l>
				</sp>

				<sp>
					<l>Sweet, oh! sweet, &amp;c. </l>
				</sp>

				<stage>DUET&#x2014;ANTONIA AND GIPSY PRINCE&#x2014;(<emph
					>Kelly</emph>.)</stage>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Good night! Good night, I must away,</l>
						<l>Altho' my heart would bid me stay.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<speaker>Gipsy Prince</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Oh Lady, say "good night" once more.</l>
						<l>And I'll repeat it o'er and o'er.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<lb/>
				<pb n="36"/>
				<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

				<sp who="#ant #gp">
					<speaker>Both</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Till the first glance of dawning light,</l>
						<l>Should find us saying still "good night."</l>
						<l>Good night! good night!</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<stage>DUET and CHORUS.<lb/> POPPEE, LACHIMEE, and <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="6">It is a
						great pity, that Miss MENAGE, who personates this character, has not
						superior powers of voice. She is, likewise, much too <emph
							>affected</emph>, and dresses too <emph>finical</emph> for the
						part.</note> GIPSIES&#x2014;(<emph>Kelly</emph>.)</stage>
				<sp who="#pop">
					<speaker>Poppee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Where Gipsy gone,</l>
						<l>Night falling on,</l>
						<l>Fly, to de tents in der willows fly&#x2014;</l>
						<l>See, now dey creep</l>
						<l>From yonder steep,</l>
						<l>No fearee now de watchful eye.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<sp who="#lac">
					<speaker>Lachimee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Here we spread,</l>
						<l>In de willows our bed,</l>
						<l>Fly&#x2014;fly&#x2014;fly to de willows fly.</l>
						<l>Hush, hush, hum,</l>
						<l>De gipsies come –</l>
						<l>No fearee now de watchful eye.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<sp who="#pop">
					<speaker>Poppee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Oh! Gipsy man no care for wind,</l>
						<l>In summer's glow,</l>
						<l>Or winter snow,</l>
						<l>Gipsy man no diff'rence find,</l>
						<l>His sunshine is de happy mind.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<sp who="#gip">
					<speaker>Chorus</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Hush, hush, hum,</l>
						<l>We gipsies &#x2014;</l>
						<l>Fly, fly, fly, to de willows fly.</l>
						<l>Soft we creep</l>
						<l>To our tents of sleep,</l>
						<l>Seal'd is now the watchful eye.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<lb/>
				<pb n="37"/>
				<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

				<stage>FINALE <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="7">It were to be wished, that Mr. KELLY had
						condescended to inform the public, what part of this <emph
							>Finale</emph> is attributable to <emph>Paisiello</emph>; what
						part to himself.</note>&#x2014;(<emph>Paisiello and
					Kelly</emph>.)</stage>
				<sp who="#alg">
					<speaker>Aguazil</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>In the name and glory</l>
						<l>Of the Inquisitory</l>
						<l>Stand we command</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gip">
					<speaker>Gipsies</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>See they've surpriz'd us.</l>
						<l>What shall we do?</l>
						<l>Why need we fear</l>
						<l>Your brow severe?</l>
						<l>What crime is ours?</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#alg">
					<speaker>Aguazils</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>No fuss</l>
						<l>But come with us</l>
						<l>And yield to Murcia's powers.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gip">
					<speaker>Gipsies</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>The guilty only fear the hand </l>
						<l>Of lordly power, or law's command</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#alg">
					<speaker>Aguazils</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Thus your rude and roving band, </l>
						<l>We arrest by law's command</l>
						<l>Come, come, come, &amp;c.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gip">
					<speaker>Gipsies</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Why, why why,</l>
						<l>Why should we fear? &amp;c.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>SONG&#x2014;ANTONIA <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="8">In the performance, this plaintive
						ditty receives a considerable portion of adventitious interest, from Mrs.
						MOUNTAIN's beautiful style of singing.</note>&#x2014;(<emph
						>Kelly</emph>.)</stage>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<lg part="I">
						<l>YES, now I shall think of that heartbroken maid,</l>
						<l>Where in days of my childhood I knew.</l>
						<l>All night she would weep in the cold willow shade</l>
						<l>And her tears mingled warm with the dew.</l>

						<lb/>
						<pb n="38"/>
						<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

						<l>I've heard her exclaim, as she sadly reclin'd, [her wild bed she
							prest,]</l>
						<l>'Mid the willows [Her wild bed] all dripping and chill,</l>
						<l>I've heard her exclaim, while she shrunk in the wind, [as her wild bed
							she prest,]</l>
						<l>"In pity poor bosom lie still!"</l>
					</lg>
					<!-- The source of the bracketed phrases is not given. 2-23-11 by DKW -->

					<lg part="F">
						<l>The youth, whom she lov'd, had been torn from her arms,</l>
						<l>By a fate too severely unkind;</l>
						<l>Thus wither'd, alas! was the rose of her charms.</l>
						<l>And clouded the beams of her mind:</l>
						<l>Sweet mourner thy fortunes may haply be mine,</l>
						<l>And I fill in my heart that they will;</l>
						<l>Then sad shall I say with a sorrow like thine,</l>
						<l>"In pity fond bosom lie still!"</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>SONG.&#x2014;POPPEE <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="9">Miss TYRER, a pupil of Mr. KELLY,
						displays talents of the fairest promise, both as an <emph
							>actress</emph>, and a <emph>singer</emph>, in her performance
						of this part. </note>&#x2014;(<emph>Kelly</emph>.)</stage>
				<sp who="#pop">
					<lg part="I">
						<l>Oh me was born to wander,</l>
						<l>No money me have got&#x2014;</l>
						<l>When father stole de gander,</l>
						<l>The mother boil de pot;</l>
						<l>While me sing fal la la la la</l>
						<l>Forma notta junga.</l>
					</lg>

					<lg part="M">
						<l>Under a hedge, one summer,</l>
						<l>Me sat&#x2014;Oh, great de heat;</l>
						<l>Dere come little drummer,</l>
						<l>And gay rub dub he beat,</l>
						<l>Den me sing, &amp;c.</l>
					</lg>

					<lg part="F">
						<l>Den me leave hedge and daddy,</l>
						<l>Wid drummer lad to go,</l>
						<l>But faithless drummer laddy,</l>
						<l>Have left me full of woe.</l>
						<l>Still me sing, &amp;c.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<lb/>
				<pb n="39"/>
				<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

				<stage>DUET <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="10">Few pieces of musical composition surpass this
						Duett, in pleasing and whimsical effect. Mr. Fawcett, and Miss Tyrer are
						both alike admirable in their several parts.</note>&#x2014;RINCON and
						POPPEE&#x2014;(<emph>Paisiello</emph>)</stage>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Fye, fye, you're quite a sinner, girl.</l>
						<l>You're not the thing for me the;</l>
						<l>Without some grace, no dinner, girl,</l>
						<l>I never could kiss with a heathen!</l>
						<l>No, no, no, no.</l>
						<l>I could never kiss with a heathen.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#pop">
					<speaker>Poppee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Eh! Have you got no shame now, man,</l>
						<l>For why you talk of christen?</l>
						<l>You give poor girl good name now, man.</l>
						<l>But you'd take it away by kissin!</l>
						<l>Iss, iss, iss, iss.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>No, you rogue, I love you dearly,</l>
						<l>As well as my bottle or &#x2014;nearly.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#pop">
					<speaker>Poppee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>But bottle thrown by when you crack 'um,</l>
						<l>And lips forgot when you smack 'um.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Come along, my dingy Miss,</l>
						<l>Your face is such golden money,</l>
						<l>It must be stamp'd with a kiss,</l>
						<l>It shall, by all that's sunny.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#pop">
					<speaker>Poppee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Get along to you fine white Miss,</l>
						<l>I not de girl for you money;</l>
						<l>You may stamp and fret to kiss,</l>
						<l>You shant, by all dat's sunny.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon <note place="foot" resp="editors" n="11">The effect of Fawcett's peculiar drollery
							of manner in rehearsing these doggrels, is beyond
						conception.</note></speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>By the cowl of St. Bridget,</l>
						<l>My heart's in a fidget;</l>
						<l>Betwitter'd, befrittetter'd,</l>
						<l>Besnivell'd, bedevill'd.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<lb/>
				<pb n="40"/>
				<fw type="head" place="top" rend="centered">THE GIPSY PRINCE.</fw>

				<sp who="#pop">
					<speaker>Poppee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Eh! You come talk, you tipsy man,</l>
						<l>You not know what you about;</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>I'll touch your hand, sweet Gipsy Ma'am,</l>
						<l>But first I'll touch your mouth.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#pop">
					<speaker>Poppee</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>You must touch de hand of Gipsey, Man,</l>
						<l>Before you touch her mout.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>TRIO&#x2014;ANTONIA, RINCON, and GIPSY&#x2014;(<emph>Kelly</emph>.) </stage>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Oh! in pity hear me suing,</l>
						<l>By compassion's dearest sigh.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Oh! I see, what she'd be doing,</l>
						<l>Well, we'll talk on't by and by/</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<l>Dearest Sir&#x2014;</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<l>The deuce is in it.</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<l>Nay, but a minute&#x2014;</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<speaker>Gipsy Prince</speaker>
					<l>Stop, knave, at your peril, stir.</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<l>Curse him, here he is again.</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<speaker>Gipsy Prince</speaker>
					<l>Back, back meddler to your den.</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#rin">
					<speaker>Rincon</speaker>
					<l>Oh! dear&#x2014;</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<speaker>Gipsy Prince</speaker>
					<l>In here, in here&#x2014;</l>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<l>Hush, hush, they'll hear</l>
				</sp>

				<stage>[DUETT&#x2014;ANTONIA and GIPSY PRINCE&#x2014;(<emph
						>Kelly</emph>.)]<hi rend="sup">a</hi></stage>
				<witDetail target="#a" wit="#a"/>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Yes, for thee too charming stranger,</l>
						<l>I could smile at every danger. </l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<speaker>Gipsy Prince</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>'Tis for me, a lonely stranger,</l>
						<l>Thou dost smile at every danger.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Far, oh far, thy steps may wander</l>
						<l>Ere thou find a heart that's fonder.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<speaker>Gipsy Prince</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>Far, oh far, my steps may wander</l>
						<l>Ere I find a heart that's fonder.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#ant">
					<speaker>Antonia</speaker>
					<lg>
						<l>No, no, whatever fate is thine,</l>
						<l>Thou canst not meet a love like mine&#x2014;</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<sp who="#gp">
					<speaker>Gipsy Prince</speaker>
					<!-- In the master doc. this speaker designation is not highlighted, but the transformation
		automatically highlights it in the same manner as every other <speaker>. 2-23-11 by DKW -->
					<lg>
						<l>No, no, whatever fate is mine,</l>
						<l>I ne'er can meet a love like thine.</l>
					</lg>
				</sp>

				<stage>[FINALE-&#x2014;GIPSY PRINCE, ANTONIA, and CHORUS&#x2014;(<emph
						>Kelly</emph>.)</stage>
				<sp who="#gp #ant">
					<lg>
						<l>The Gipsy Prince no more shall roam,</l>
						<l>His sorrows all beguil'd to rest;</l>
						<l>The arms of love shall be his home,</l>
						<l>And joy his ever-smiling guest.]<hi rend="sup">a</hi></l>
					</lg>
				</sp>
				<witDetail target="#a" wit="#a"/>


				<p>END OF THE GIPSY PRINCE.</p>
				<!-- This could also be coded as <stage>. 2-23-11 by DKW -->

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
