<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Earth, Spirit, Humanity: Community and
                    the Nonhuman in Karoline von Günderrode’s “Idea of the Earth” </title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Anna Ezekiel</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-02-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.ecology.ezekiel</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">ecology</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Earth, Spirit, Humanity: Community and
                            the Nonhuman in Karoline von Günderrode’s “Idea of the Earth” 
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Anna</forename>
                                <surname>Ezekiel</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/ecology/praxis.2023.ecology.ezekiel"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Political Ecology</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-02-21">February 21, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>02.21.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
            <front>
                <div type="abstract"></div>  
            </front>
                
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Earth, Spirit, Humanity: Community and
                    the Nonhuman in Karoline von Günderrode’s “Idea of the Earth” </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Anna Ezekiel</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of York</affiliation>
                </byline>
            
            <p> Karoline von Günderrode (1780–1806) has long been recognized as a poet and
                paradigmatic figure of the tragic Romantic, but recently her writing has begun to
                receive attention for its consideration of philosophical questions. Her work is
                especially promising for its original conceptualizations of death, selfhood, gender,
                and agency, which Günderrode sites within a metaphysics developed from readings of
                F. W. J. Schelling, Johann Gottlieb Fichte, Johann Gottfried Herder, Early German
                Romanticism, and ancient Greek and Indian thought. Secondary literature has
                emerged on Günderrode’s engagement with Fichte and Schelling (Christmann; Dormann;
                Nassar), her reimagining of Early German Romantic themes
                (Heimerl; Hilger; Kuzniar), and her contributions to models of identity, especially
                female identity (Allingham; Battersby; Ezekiel “Metamorphosis”). This paper adds to
                the growing discussion of Günderrode's philosophical thought, unpacking the author's 
                metaphysics and arguing that the place she assigns human
                beings in her cosmology requires a reconceptualization of the relationship between
                human beings and the nonhuman world and the development of communities that include
                the nonhuman.</p>
            
            <p> That Günderrode’s work should be a potential source for re-imagining the
                human-nature relationship is hinted at by her connections with early German
                Romanticism and her influence on American transcendentalism. Her friend Bettina
                Brentano-von Arnim’s edited collection of their correspondence, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Die Günderode</hi>, was translated into English by Margaret Fuller, and Carol
                Strauss Sotiropoulos has argued that Fuller’s own model of friendship was informed
                by this text (81–110). Despite this, Günderrode’s work has not, so far, been much
                studied in relation to transcendentalism, environmentalism, or social or political
                theory (with the exception of work by Lucia Maria Licher [“Der Völker Schicksal”;
                “Du mußt Dich”; <hi rend="italic">Mein Leben</hi>]). In part, this may stem from
                Günderrode’s position as an intermediate figure between Early German Romanticism and
                the Heidelberg Romantics—she belongs to the broader circle of thinkers and writers
                associated with late Romanticism known as the Heidelberger Kreis. In particular, as
                Karl Heinz Bohrer has argued, there are parallels between Günderrode’s conception of
                the self and those of Clemens Brentano and Heinrich von Kleist (“Identität”;
                <hi rend="italic">Der romantische Brief </hi>75–84, 115–129).
                Brentano’s and Kleist’s focus on subjective experience is often viewed as part of
                Romanticism’s “turn inward,” that is, its move away from attempts to change
                social relationships towards a focus on the inner, emotional life and experiences of
                the individual (Bohrer “Identität”; Dallmayr 54; Sevin and Zeller 4–6). These links
                between Günderrode and later Romanticism have perhaps contributed to some
                commentators reading Günderrode as representative of this turn inward. For example,
                Ruth Christmann claims that Günderrode’s work was “in accord with developments after
                1800, which, after the failure of the Early German Romantic attempt at renewal,
                increasingly sought purchase in a retreat inwards and no longer aimed at connections
                to society” (119; see also Dormann 14, 240). <note place="foot" resp="editors">
                    Translations are the author’s, unless stated otherwise. Translations of “Idea of the Earth” and “Idea of Nature” are from Gjesdal and Nassar. 
                    Translations of “Letters of Two Friends,” “Story of a Brahmin,” “The true idea of materialism…” and “The Manes” are from Ezekiel, <hi
                                rend="italic">Philosophical Fragments</hi>. Page numbers are not yet available for the
                                English translations; references are given to the German in
                                Günderrode’s collected works.</note> 
                
                This paper argues that, rather than rejecting or neglecting social relations,
                Günderrode’s work presents an ideal of community. This ideal is embedded in the
                philosophical system that Günderrode was developing up until her death, which
                includes an account of what human beings are and how they relate to each other and
                to the nonhuman world.</p>
            
            <p> The first part of the paper provides an exposition of Günderrode’s cosmology and the
                place of human beings within it. Analysis of the unpublished essay “Idea of the
                Earth” and the closely related epistolary dialogue “Letters of Two Friends” shows
                that Günderrode presents human beings as embedded in, and the same in kind as, the
                nonhuman. Part two uses the philosophical dialogue “Story of a Brahmin” to argue
                that, consistent with this metaphysical picture, Günderrode denies that human
                beings are justified in adopting a dominating relationship to nature or the nonhuman
                (or each other). The third part of the paper explores Günderrode’s claim that human
                beings live in three ways— as animal, as human, and spiritually — and considers how
                these relate to Günderrode’s
                concept of earth. This part of the investigation reveals that, unlike many other
                philosophers of the time, who tended to strongly associate human beings and spirit,
                mind or consciousness, Günderrode disassociates these. </p>
            
            <p> The final part of the paper explores how Günderrode’s account translates into
                concrete ideas about community. I argue that Günderrode’s normative restraint, ideal
                of harmony, and view of human beings as part of and the same in kind as the rest of
                nature contribute to a vision of community in which genuine connections can flourish
                between human beings at the same time as connections to what is beyond the human.
                Rather than providing a program for ideal social relations or attitudes towards the
                natural world, Günderrode describes conditions for the emergence of small
                communities of friends in harmony with nature. On Günderrode’s model, these could
                potentially grow and eventually, perhaps, enable the emergence of the single,
                perfect organism she calls the “realized idea of the earth.”</p>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>The Idea of Earth</head>
            
          
            <p> Günderrode’s unpublished fragment “Idea of the Earth” was probably written in 1805,
                based on references to this piece in her letters (III:272). This dense essay is an
                intermediate stage between Günderrode’s notes on Schelling, especially the passages
                “Idea of Nature” (II:398–99) and “The true idea of materialism…” (II:404–6), and the
                final letter of “Letters of Two Friends” in her collection <hi rend="italic"
                    >Melete</hi>. The latter repeats passages from “Idea of the Earth,” in places
                verbatim, elsewhere with important changes, and, taken together, the pieces show
                Günderrode moving progressively further away from Schelling’s thought as she
                developed her own. <hi rend="italic">Melete</hi>, Günderrode’s third collection of
                writings, had been sent to the publishers when she died, and “Letters” is therefore
                the most authoritative of these texts in terms of representing Günderrode’s own and
                considered position. Nonetheless, the exposition below takes its starting point from
                “Idea of the Earth,” which is more detailed and more closely focused on
                metaphysics.</p>
            
            <p> In both “Idea of the Earth” and “Letters of Two Friends,” Günderrode claims that the
                world is comprised of “elements,” which join in temporary combinations to form
                individual entities. When these die or are destroyed, the elements are scattered and
                can then join together again in different combinations, creating new entities. For
                Günderrode, “life” is the combination of elements as these entities, while “death”
                is only a relative term applying to individual entities; by contrast, the elements
                out of which these are formed do not die:
                
            <quote>The most intimate mingling of different elements with the highest degree of contact
                and attraction we call life; to whatever perfection it may have developed it is
                still only the product of the synthesis of the elements that gestate life. With the
                dissolution of this synthesis the product also ends, but the life-principle in the
                elements is immortal; it requires only contact and connection again like before and
                new life blossoms with all the blooms that we call thought and sensation, and
                organism and body and soul.</quote>
                
               Thus life is immortal and surges up and down in the elements, for they are life
                itself. But determinate and individual life is only a life-form given through this
                determinate connection, attraction and contact, which can last no longer than the
                connection. (I:446–47; cf. I:359). According to Günderrode, the world we experience is thus comprised of entities that
                participate in a cycle of formation and destruction which, at all its stages,
                manifests the principle of life, just in different ways and forms. </p>
            
            <p> Günderrode applies this model of living and dying to all entities, including objects
                we usually think of as devoid of life. For Günderrode, living beings such as plants
                and animals are only higher life-forms that exist on a continuum with supposedly
                inanimate objects. The beings that we think of as alive have developed from less
                animated forms of life through the process of repeated combination, dissolution, and
                recombination, which, Günderrode claims, gradually increases the “life” of the
                elements and, through these, of the whole: 
                
            <quote>Each mortal gives back to the earth a
                raised, more developed elemental life, which it cultivates further in ascending
                forms, and the organism, by assimilating ever more developed elements, must become
                ever more perfect and universal. Thus the All [<hi rend="italic">Allheit</hi>] comes
                to life through the downfall of the particular, and the particular survives
                immortally in the All whose life it developed while alive, and even after death
                elevates and increases, and so by living and dying helps to realize the idea of the
                earth. Thus however my elements may be dispersed, when they join to what is already
                living they will elevate it; when they join to those things whose life resembles
                death, they will animate them. (I:447–48; cf. I:360)</quote>
                
                At the end of this passage, Günderrode likens this process to
                reincarnation, adding: “The idea of the Indians of the transmigration of souls
                corresponds to this opinion.” I return to this claim below. Here, I only note that
                this suggests that Günderrode sees this model as allowing some form of personal
                survival beyond the death of the individual, although in an altered state.</p>
            
            <p> Günderrode maintains that the process of increasing animation through the forming and
                re-forming of groups of elements can only stop when and if life has been fully
                actualized—that is, when all potential life has become real. This, she claims, would
                take the form of a single organism, which would constitute the realization of what
                she calls the “idea of the earth”:
                
            <quote>Each form that [the elements] produce is only a development of their
                life-principle. But the earth bears the life-material given back to it again in ever
                new appearances, until through ever new transformations everything capable of life
                in it has come to life. This would be when all mass would become organic; only then
                would the idea of the earth be realized. (I:447; cf. I:359–60)</quote>
                
            This model has clear connections to the work of Schelling, especially <hi
                    rend="italic">Bruno</hi>, which Günderrode read in 1804. Several of the concepts
                featured in Günderrode’s metaphysics appear in this text, including “the idea of the
                earth” (or “idea of earth” as Michael Vater translates <hi rend="italic">Idee der
                    Erde</hi> [Schelling 125, trans. Vater]), although Schelling aligns this concept more clearly
                with Platonic ideas than Günderrode does. Günderrode, like Schelling in <hi
                    rend="italic">Bruno</hi>, is concerned with explaining how the infinite relates
                to the finite world we experience. For Schelling, the organism is the closest
                available approximation of the way that individual things relate to the absolute,
                since the relationship between the parts of an organism is one of mutual,
                simultaneous conditioning rather than of cause and effect: “the best example we can
                find among familiar sensible things of the way the finite inheres in the infinite is
                the way individual parts of the animate body are tied into the whole organism”
                (Schelling 150). However, he adds that this is only an image or
                analogy, because “in the absolute this union of the finite and the infinite is
                infinitely more perfect than the living union of the parts of the body.”
                Similarly, Günderrode claims that the kinds of organisms we encounter in our
                ordinary lives are only approximations to the ultimate organism that would
                constitute the realized idea of the earth:
                
            <quote> The earth can therefore only attain its proper being when its organic and inorganic
                appearances dissolve in a collective organism,  [. . .]  where all body would also
                at the same time be thought, all thinking at the same time body, and a truly
                transfigured body, without lack or illness and immortal, and thus wholly different
                from what we call body or material and to which we attribute transience, inertia,
                illness and deficiency, for this kind of body is, as it were, only a failed attempt
                by nature to produce that immortal ideal body. (I:448; cf. I:360–61)</quote>
                
                Thus we should not think of the realization of Günderrode’s idea of the earth as an
                organism in the ordinary sense. Although the comparison to an organism and
                Günderrode’s emphasis on the increase of “life” through the progressive forms of its
                realization suggest that this realization would be some kind of living being, it is
                characterized most essentially by an identity of form and essence or body and
                thought. Günderrode makes this point explicitly: “This perfect unity of essence and
                form cannot be achieved in <hi rend="italic">separation</hi> and multiplicity 
                . . .  because the essence can only be one but the forms are various” (I:448).<note place="foot" resp="editors"> In “Letters of Two Friends,” the
                            passage reads: “This perfect sameness of inner essence and form cannot,
                            it seems to me, be achieved in a multiplicity of forms. The essence of
                            the earth is only one, therefore its form may also only be one”
                            (I:360).</note> </p>
                
            <p> Günderrode also explicitly claims to be uncertain about whether this ultimate
                organism, that is, the realization of the idea of the earth, can or will ever in
                fact emerge: 
                
                <quote> I do not assert whether the earth will be altogether successful in organizing itself
                immortally like this; there may be a disproportion of essence and form in its primal
                elements that always hinders it from this; and perhaps the totality of our whole
                solar system is needed to resolve the task of such an equilibrium of essence and
                form, and perhaps even this does not suffice for it and it is a task for the entire
                universe. (I:448)<note place="foot" resp="author">In “Letters of Two Friends,” the phrase “is
                                needed to resolve the task of such an equilibrium of essence and
                                form” is replaced with “is needed to bring about this equilibrium”
                                (I:361).</note></quote>
      
                This statement is significant for a number of reasons, including its suggestion that
                the earth may itself form part of a larger organism such as the solar system or the
                universe (at another point, Günderrode refers to “the realized idea of the earth (or
                of the universe)” [I:449]), and the claim that a “disproportion of form and essence”
                may exist among the elements that constitute the earth. There is not space to
                explore the latter claim here, but the question of the role and status of the
                “earth” in Günderrode’s thought is considered below.</p>
            
            <p> The picture that emerges from “Idea of the Earth” and “Letters of Two Friends” is of
                a world in which human beings are not profoundly different in kind from other
                entities, including objects we usually think of as inanimate. Instead, human beings
                are formed of the same basic building blocks (elements) as everything else in
                nature, and exist on a continuum of liveliness or animation with these other beings.
                Günderrode’s basic metaphysical picture therefore leaves space to imagine ways of
                relating to nature, or the nonhuman world, in non-oppositional terms. </p></div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>Perfection versus Exploitation</head>
            
            
            <p> Günderrode’s emphasis on increasing life or animation through the death and
                regeneration of finite beings works against the idea that the human characteristic
                of mind or consciousness is something that sets human beings apart from nature.
                Günderrode is not trying to explain how two disparate factors—essence or mind (or
                soul) and form or body—come to be joined; rather, she presents mind and
                consciousness as emerging within the material world. In other words, these occur on
                a continuum with aspects of the world that we usually think of as lacking
                consciousness. Günderrode explains this non-duality in the opening lines of “Idea of
                the Earth”:
                
            <quote>The earth is a realized idea, one that is simultaneously effective (force) and
                effected (appearance). It is thus a unity of soul and body, of which we call the
                pole of its activity that it turns outward extension, form, body; the one it turns
                inwards intension, essence, force, soul. Now, as the whole of the earth only exists
                through this unification of soul and body, so, too, the individual and smallest
                things only exist through it and cannot be conceived as split in two, for an outer
                without an inner, an essence without form, a force without some sort of effect, is
                not comprehensible. (I:446)<note place="foot" resp="author"> This passage is omitted from “Letters of Two Friends.”</note></quote>
                
                Similarly to Schelling, for Günderrode opposites are not originally separate; rather, they are
                dual aspects or poles of a single thing. This applies to the dualities we think of
                as essence and form and as mind or soul and body: at root, these are one, like the
                inside and outside of a single thing, and their full manifestation requires their
                complete commensurability. Thus, as we saw above, for Günderrode the fully realized
                idea of the earth is not one in which mind predominates over body, but a state of
                equilibrium in which these fully penetrate each other: “where all body would also at
                the same time be thought, all thinking at the same time body.”</p>
            
            <p> Günderrode does imagine a role for human beings in the development of consciousness,
                and therefore in the emergence of mind or soul in material. However, we have to
                search outside “Idea of the Earth” and “Letters” to find support for this claim and
                for the application of Günderrode’s metaphysics to her ideas on social
                relationships. Like most of Günderrode’s work, “Story of a Brahmin” is consistent
                with the metaphysical picture presented in “Idea of the Earth” and “Letters,”
                although the language is more religious and less philosophical than in these other
                pieces. This is perhaps partly because “Story of a Brahmin” was published in 1803,
                before Günderrode’s detailed engagement with <hi rend="italic">Bruno</hi>; this fact
                should also warn against reading Günderrode’s work as too derivative of Schelling,
                despite the overt similarities between their work. Günderrode seems to have adapted
                Schelling’s ideas to fit a philosophical system that she was already in the process
                of developing when she encountered his thought.</p>
            
            <p> In “Story of a Brahmin,” Günderrode claims that the development of “consciousness and
                thought” from bare matter through human beings and beyond is part of a process of
                increasing perfection and individuation that will ultimately allow the things of the
                world to be unified with what she calls, among other things, the “primal force”
                (Urkraft):
                
            <quote>[The Brahmin] taught me how in each part of the infinite spirit of nature lies the
                aptitude for eternal perfection, how the forces wander through all forms until they
                develop consciousness and thought in human beings; how from human beings on an
                infinite series of migrations that lead to ever higher perfection await souls; how
                eventually, through mysterious ways, they will all unite with the primal force from
                which they emanated and will become one with it, and still at the same time remain
                themselves, and thus unite the divinity and universality of the creator with the
                individuality of the creature. (I:312)</quote>
                
            As well as indicating that Günderrode views consciousness as developing within the
                material world, this passage helps clarify the claim in “Idea of the Earth” and
                “Letters” that “the idea of the Indians of the transmigration of souls corresponds
                to this opinion.” Günderrode views the dissolution of finite beings and their
                reconstitution in new forms as a kind of reincarnation. Human beings and their minds
                are not the unique pinnacle of existence but one form among many in a series that
                develops through and beyond human beings towards closer connection with the divine.
                According to Günderrode, human beings are not the ultimate or even penultimate form
                in this sequence but simply one stage of the development of the soul.</p>
            
            <p> The idea that human beings are part of a development of the world to consciousness
                and/or towards the divine or the absolute is, of course, not unique to Günderrode.
                In this, she draws not only on Hindu and Buddhist beliefs, but also on work by her
                contemporaries and predecessors, including Schelling, Fichte, and the Early German
                Romantics. However, unlike many European philosophers, Günderrode draws the
                implication from siting consciousness within the world and developing within it that
                the nonhuman world should not be viewed as inert or as available for human
                exploitation. </p>
            
            <p>The view of the nonhuman world as material that could or should be worked on by human
                beings, especially through the use of their reason, was widespread at the time
                Günderrode was writing (as well as before and since). For example, in
                    <hi rend="italic">The Vocation of Man</hi> Fichte states:
                
            <quote>Nature must gradually enter a condition which allows one to calculate and reckon
                safely on its regular pace, and which keeps its force steady in a definite relation
                with the power which is destined to control it — the power of man . . . 
                Cultivated lands shall animate and moderate the inert and hostile atmosphere of
                primeval forests, deserts, and swamps . . . [H]uman power, enlightened and
                armed by its discoveries, shall control [nature] without effort and peacefully
                maintain any conquest once it is
                made. (Fichte 83, trans. Preuss) </quote>
                
            In this passage, Fichte construes the natural world as “inert” and human beings as
                “destined” to “control” nature through the use of their reason. We can find similar
                claims by others, for example Herder (IV:239). Even Novalis and Schlegel, famously
                concerned with transforming Fichte’s “not-I” into a “you” (Novalis III:430), have
                been criticized for viewing the nonhuman world as something to be appropriated, or
                at least worked on and shaped, by a creative subject (Pnevmonidou 273–75; Roetzel
                370). </p>
            
            <p> For Günderrode, by contrast, although human beings have a place in the development of
                both consciousness and the earth, their role is neither to master the nonhuman nor
                to shape it. Instead, human beings are part of nature and can work on themselves as
                part of nature’s internal movement towards perfection. In “Idea of the Earth” and
                “Letters,” we saw how this occurs through the enhancement or increase of life during
                periods when the elements are organized into living beings, including human
                beings: as Günderrode writes in these pieces, “each mortal gives back to the earth a
                raised, more developed elemental life.” </p>
            
            <p> The narrator of “Story of a Brahmin” elaborates on the idea of the self-development
                of the individual within a developing whole:
                
            <quote>The philosophy that considers every individual as a means for the whole has now
                become hateful to me, [the philosophy] that always asks what use this or that is
                for the others and considers each as a fruit that has bloomed and ripened in order
                to be consumed by the whole; that plants the most various natures in one garden, and
                wants to grow the oak and the rose according to one standard. To me each individual
                is holy, it is God’s work, it is its own purpose. If it becomes what it can become
                according to its nature, then it has done enough, and what it profits the others is
                a side issue . . . Yes, a time of perfection must come, when each being will
                be harmonious with itself and with the others, when they flow into each other and
                become one in a great unison, when every melody throws itself into the eternal
                harmony. 
                
                
                Just like health, preservation, propagation are the highest for merely animal life,
                humanity [<hi rend="italic">Humanität</hi>] in the broadest sense of the word
                (according to which it also includes morality and culture) is the highest for human
                beings as human beings; as such, they have humankind [<hi rend="italic"
                    >Menschheit</hi>] as their object. Their pure relationship to it, morality,
                consists in itself, satisfies itself, and needs no other motive nor prospects than
                itself and humankind . . . Thus the human being lives in a threefold way:
                animally—this is its relation to earth; humanly [<hi rend="italic"
                >menschlich</hi>]—this is its relationship to humankind; spiritually—this is its
                relationship to the infinite, divine. Whoever does not live in these three ways has
                a gap in their existence, and something is missing in their aptitudes.
                (I:310–311) </quote>
                
            In this passage, Günderrode emphasizes the intrinsic, non-instrumental value of all
                living (and, on the basis of “Idea of the Earth” and “Letters,” also non-living)
                things. On Günderrode’s model, while human beings are part of the development and
                perfecting of nature, their role is not to master the world, nor to cultivate or
                perfect it from a position of dominance (or even stewardship), but, rather, to be
                human (and animal) and to develop a relationship to the infinite. The harmony that
                the narrator of “Story of a Brahmin” claims will (hopefully) characterize the
                end-state of the world is not imposed on or cultivated in nature by human beings
                but, if it emerges, will do so through the full self-expression of each of the parts
                within it, including human beings. </p>
            
            <p> One of the most striking characteristics of this model is its normative restraint:
                the project facing human beings is one of self-cultivation, not cultivation of
                others, whether human or nonhuman. Nonetheless, Günderrode clearly imagines this
                self-cultivation of the individual as part of a self-cultivation of the whole,
                capable of contributing to an enhanced and harmonious outcome. The last section of
                this paper explores the nature of this harmony and the means by which Günderrode
                believes certain kinds of human and nonhuman relationships can foster it. First,
                however, the next section investigates the “threefold way” of human life that
                Günderrode describes in “Story of a Brahmin” and the differences this reveals
                between Günderrode’s account and models that associate human beings uniquely with
                consciousness and spirituality.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>Being Human </head>
            
            <p> In the passage quoted above, Günderrode aligns the animal side of human nature with
                “relationship to (the) earth” (<hi rend="italic">Verhältniß zur Erde</hi>); the
                human side with “relation to humankind” (<hi rend="italic">Beziehung zur
                    Menschheit</hi>); and the spiritual side with “relation to the infinite, divine”
                    (<hi rend="italic">Beziehung zum Unendlichen, Göttlichen</hi>). Günderrode says
                the least about the animal side of human nature, and this section therefore
                considers her claims about the relationship of human beings to “humankind” and “the
                infinite” first, before returning to the animal side of human nature and its
                relationship to “earth.”</p>
            
            <p> In the above passage, Günderrode claims that the human aspect of being human
                essentially involves, or essentially <hi rend="italic">is</hi>, relationship to
                other human beings — to humanity as a whole. As humans, she states, human beings “have
                humanity as their object.” She also aligns the human aspect of being human with
                morality (<hi rend="italic">Sittlichkeit</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                >Moralität</hi>—she seems to use these terms interchangeably). To Günderrode,
                therefore, morality is specifically something that governs the relations of human
                beings to each other — in other words, morality does not apply to human
                relationships with “the earth” or with “the infinite, divine.” </p>
            
            <p> Nonetheless, both of the latter relationships are also important on Günderrode’s
                account, as she describes in “Story of a Brahmin.” After turning from a worldly life
                of trade and pleasure, the narrator of this piece first engages in moral thought
                (I:305) before realizing that participation in the moral world cannot satisfy him:
                
            <quote>The struggle . . . of the individual with society, of freedom against freedom,
                of singularity against general laws, and of morals against their impediments,
                stopped occupying and tormenting me so much. For a long time it had already been
                clear to me that justice is the basis of civil society and morality the basis of
                human society. These two relations had once satisfied me; I had sought to bring all
                the points of my mind into contact with them. Now I discovered aptitudes within me
                that these finite relations would no longer satisfy. (I:307–8)</quote>
                
            The speaker claims that whereas social relationships are based on justice (in the
                case of “civil society”) or morality (in the case of “human society”),<note place="foot" resp="author"> 
                    There is not space here to explore the relationship between Günderrode’s ideas of “civil society” and “human society,” 
                    and Günderrode does not expand on her interpretation of these concepts. Günderrode was familiar with Kant’s moral thought 
                    and these categories may map on to Kant’s distinction between juridico-civil (<hi
                                rend="italic">rechtlich-bürgerliche</hi>) society and ethico-civil (
                            <hi rend="italic">ethisch-bürgerliche</hi>) or ethical (<hi rend="italic"
                                >ethische</hi>)
                                society (Kant I.6:94). Whether or not this is the case, Günderrode
                                here marks a distinction between relationships between human beings
                                that are governed by different kinds of principles: on the one hand,
                                rules or laws, perhaps like those in the institutions of the
                                nation-state and, on the other, moral ideals of how individuals
                                should behave towards each other.</note> these matters
                do not exhaust the needs of human beings. In other words, not only is the mundane
                and materialistic business of everyday life not sufficient for a full human
                existence but neither is the moral life. </p>
            
            <p> Günderrode’s account presents morality as unrelated to the spiritual side of human
                beings, that is, their relationship to the infinite. Her narrator explains that
                the aptitudes he has discovered within himself need connection with the infinite,
                which Günderrode situates beyond the “finite relations” of morals and human society.
                Her narrator identifies this infinite with “the spirit of nature”:
                
            <quote>My . . . appetite [sought] an infinite object for its striving; and my inner
                sense intimated an invisible and mysterious connection with something that I did not
                yet know, and to which I would gladly have given a shape and name. . . . In
                this longing, in this love the spirit of nature spoke to me. . . . The more I
                listened to it, the clearer it was to me that there was a fundamental force in which
                everything, visible and invisible, was connected. I named this force primal life,
                and sought to bring my consciousness into connection with it (for a mysterious and
                unknown descent from it seemed certain to me). (I:308)</quote>
                
            Günderrode’s narrator explicitly connects this kind of spiritual relationship with
                religion (I:309). He also explicitly
                <hi rend="italic">disconnects </hi>religion from morality,
                which, he emphasizes, belongs to the human realm and not the realm of
                the spiritual: “Anyone who needs some sort of religion as a buttress to their
                morality, their morality is not pure, for according to its nature this must consist
                in itself. Thus a human being can do without religion and, considered merely as a
                human being, does not attain its prospects in religion’s territory” (I:310).</p>
            
            <p> The infinite with which Günderrode’s narrator seeks a relationship, and which he
                claims all the world’s religions attempt to disclose (I:309), does not correspond to
                what is peculiarly human in human beings, i.e. their moral and civic relations to
                other human beings. Instead, Günderrode’s narrator aligns this infinite/divine with
                the spirit of nature or “primal life” (<hi rend="italic">Urleben</hi>). This is the
                “fundamental force” (<hi rend="italic">Grundkraft</hi>) that connects everything
                that exists and from which the individual human being has emerged. This is, he
                claims, “an infinite force, an eternal life, that is everything that is, that was
                and will become, that engenders itself in mysterious ways, that remains eternal
                during all change and dying. It is at the same time the ground of all things and the
                things themselves, the condition and the conditioned, the creator and the creature”
                (I:309). </p>
            
            <p> The references to this infinite as “life” and “force,” as well as the claim that it
                underlies and runs through all things, connect the infinite “ground” of “Story of a
                Brahmin” to the “All” that Günderrode describes in “Idea of the Earth” and
                “Letters.” In “Letters,” Günderrode explicitly associates the whole, or the “All,”
                with nature, asking, “What does it mean, that from the All of nature [<hi
                    rend="italic">Allheit der Natur</hi>] a being cuts itself loose with such
                consciousness, and feels torn off from it?” (I:359). Thus, notwithstanding
                terminological differences, Günderrode articulates the same idea in all three
                pieces, i.e. that of an eternal, living whole that manifests itself in every
                aspect of the world. In “Story of a Brahmin,” Günderrode emphasizes the importance
                of cultivating a relationship to this “infinite spirit of nature” (<hi rend="italic"
                    >unendlicher Naturgeist</hi>) (I:312) or (as she calls it in “Idea of the Earth”
                and “Letters”) the “earth-spirit” (<hi rend="italic">Erdgeist</hi>) (I:360, 447,
                448).</p>
            
            <p> The above points speak in favor of interpreting the terms “life,” “spirit of
                    nature,”<note place="foot" resp="author">Günderrode treats the
                            term “nature” as roughly synonymous with “spirit of nature,” i.e.that
                            is, not (like “earth”) to describe our world of finite entities, but to
                            refer to the infinite process that underlies it (i.e., like “spirit of
                            earth” or “earth essence”). For example: , in “Letters” the author
                            writes that “infinite nature will always reveal itself anew in infinite
                            time” (I:356; see also I:350, 355); in “Idea of the Earth,” Günderrode
                            claims that ordinary bodies are “a failed attempt by nature to produce
                            that immortal ideal body” (I:448); in “Story of a Brahmin,” the Brahmin
                            says as he is dying: “I would like to . . .  […] breathe my spirit
                            silently back into silent nature” (I:313); and in “Idea of Nature,”
                            Günderrode writes: , “Nature is an eternal activity, a self producing
                            product, an ever enduring becoming” (II:398). </note> and
                “earth-spirit” (as well as several other terms including “essence of the earth,”
                “god of the earth,” and “the infinite”) as fulfilling the same function in
                Günderrode’s philosophy. All these terms refer to a single principle or force
                running through the beings and processes of our world.</p>
            
            <p> In some cases, Günderrode seems to attribute a narrower scope to the spirit or
                essence of the “earth” than to “life,” “spirit of nature,” or “the infinite.” The
                latter terms encompass the force, principle or spirit that is unfolding in the
                entire universe — in everything that exists. By contrast, at some points when
                Günderrode talks about “earth” she clearly means planet Earth, for example when she
                states that the idea of the earth may not be realizable by the Earth alone but may
                require the solar system or the entire universe (I:361, 448) or when she mentions
                “the realized idea of the earth (or of the universe)” (I:449). However, Günderrode
                also uses the terms <hi rend="italic">earth</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >earthly</hi> (<hi rend="italic">irdisch</hi>) to mean “mundane” or “worldly,”
                referring to all aspects of the world we experience in ordinary life - that is, to
                what might be called “this life” (as opposed to any idea of a “beyond” or a
                “hereafter”). For example, in “Story of a Brahmin” she refers to “everything on
                earth” (I:305) and the narrator claims “I had already been on earth a long time”
                (I:304; see also I:306, 308, 355, 356, 358). In this usage, the meaning of <hi
                    rend="italic">earth</hi> is expanded to include all aspects of ordinary
                existence, and is therefore similar to the meaning Günderrode ascribes to <hi
                    rend="italic">world</hi> and <hi rend="italic">universe</hi>. This expanded
                meaning of <hi rend="italic">earth</hi> to encompass a more general sense of the
                whole world explains why Günderrode’s use of the term “spirit of earth” generally
                corresponds to “spirit of nature,” “life,” “the infinite” and the other terms she
                uses to describe the underlying principle or force that is manifested in the beings
                of the finite world. </p>
            
            <p> This ambivalence is likely related to Günderrode’s stated uncertainty about whether
                the generative force underlying the succession of finite beings in the world is one
                that realizes itself in the Earth alone or in all the processes of the universe.
                This uncertainty causes her to shift back and forth between descriptions of a spirit
                or essence of earth and an infinite spirit or principle of life and nature in
                general. The association of the “idea of the earth” with Platonic ideas may also
                contribute to the confusion. Günderrode’s model does not include a realm of ideas,
                and she uses the notion of the “idea of the earth” as a regulative ideal rather than
                as an idea, archetype, or primal form such as we might find in the work of Goethe or
                Humboldt or in Schelling’s <hi rend="italic">Bruno</hi>. But the origins of the term
                    <hi rend="italic">Idee der Erde</hi> in Anselm’s Platonic account of the ideas
                in <hi rend="italic">Bruno</hi> may have brought with it some associations of an
                “archetypal nature” in which the ideas of finite things within the universe persist
                in a perfect form. For instance, Anselm claims that “The created earth . . . is
                not the true earth, but only an image of the earth which is uncreated, unoriginated,
                and never to pass away” (Schelling 125, trans. Vater). This is quite a different
                concept from Günderrode’s notion of “idea of the earth,” which is indeed a perfect
                and enduring entity but one that, if it ever appears, will be generated from the
                existing earth that we know and, furthermore, will emerge through the ordinary
                processes of temporal existence.</p>
            
            <p> Despite the above complication, in general, we can take the terms “life,” “spirit of
                earth,” “spirit of nature,” “the infinite” etc. as they appear in Günderrode’s work
                to all refer to the same basic concept of a single principle or force that underlies
                the beings and processes of our world (whether we focus on the planet Earth alone or
                on the entire universe). On the other hand, the “idea of the earth” or “idea of
                nature” refers to something different. As Günderrode explains, unlike the
                “earth-spirit,” which is the living, generative, original, and infinite ground of
                the world we know, the idea of the earth is the putative end-point of the process of
                generation and re-generation: it is the “collective organism” in which “all body
                would also at the same time be thought, all thinking at the same time body, and a
                truly transfigured body, without lack or illness and immortal, and thus wholly
                different from what we call body or material” (I:448).</p>
            
            <p> In the unpublished fragment “the true idea of materialism,” Günderrode uses
                different terminology that supports this point. In this piece, she explains that
                matter “is simple, unchangeable, eternal,” which “contains all things,” and she
                adds: “that through which they are all one is matter, while that through which they
                are different and separated from each other is their form” (II:404). “Matter” itself
                is yet another name for what Günderrode here calls the “principle of all forms” (<hi
                    rend="italic">Prinzip aller Formen</hi>), “worldsoul,” and the “reality of the
                absolute” (<hi rend="italic">Würklichkeit des Absoluten</hi>) (II:405). </p>
            
            <p> Günderrode contrasts this “principle of all forms” with something she calls the
                “totality of all forms” (<hi rend="italic">Totalität aller Formen</hi>). These terms
                correspond, respectively, to her later terms “spirit/essence of earth” and “idea of
                the earth,” as should be clear from the following quote, in which Günderrode again
                uses the analogy of the organism as the closest approximation to this totality that
                we can imagine. She writes that the “true essence [of finite things] eternally seeks
                the eternal and absolute form, which it would only find in the totality of all
                forms, i.e., at the end of all evolutions of the principle of form [<hi
                    rend="italic">Formprinzip</hi>] . . . The organic body, the most complete
                synthesis of form and essence, thinking and being, spirit and body, is its most
                similar copy” (II:405–6).</p>
            
            <p> The contrast between the “principle of all forms” and the “totality of all forms” (or
                the “spirit of earth” and the “idea of the earth,” or the “spirit of nature” and the
                “idea of nature,” etc.) is between the underlying driving force, principle, and
                unifying single origin of all the entities in our world (or, in other words, the
                fundamental process that is ongoing in these entities) and the end-point of this
                process in a single, perfectly balanced, and harmonious organism. </p>
            
            <p> The relationship to the infinite/divine that Günderrode describes as part of human
                existence in “Story of a Brahmin” is a relationship to the first of these factors:
                to the infinite “spirit” of earth or nature. The idea of the earth, on the other
                hand—as explained in more detail below—is a projected end-state that human beings
                can work towards and begin to realize, especially through new forms of
                community.</p>
            
            <p> There is a third term in this relationship: the “earth” itself. It is this term that
                Günderrode associates with the third and last aspect of being human described in
                “Story of a Brahmin”: the animal. While spirituality depends on a relationship to
                the infinite “life,” “nature,” or “earth-spirit” that exists in all things, the
                animal aspect of being human is the human being’s “relation to (the) earth.” In
                “Story of a Brahmin,” the narrator states that “health, preservation, propagation
                are the highest for merely animal life,” indicating that the animal aspect should be
                understood as a straightforward orientation to natural and bodily processes. This
                kind of relationship differs from the altered orientation to these processes that is
                experienced in the relationship to the infinite, self-producing force that underlies
                and inhabits them (i.e., the “earth-spirit”). In other words, the animal “relation
                to earth” is qualitatively different to the spiritual relation to the “earth-spirit”
                or the “essence of the earth”—that is, the emotional and intuitive experience of
                connectedness to the principle of life that runs through natural phenomena. </p>
            
            <p>In some respects, this model reflects ideas current in German philosophy at the time
                Günderrode was writing. For example, Novalis calls for a change in how human beings
                relate to the things of the world, including natural forms, that involves perceiving
                the single divine spirit within them (Novalis I:79; II:454 #93, 461 #112, 594 #316).
                In <hi rend="italic">Bruno</hi>, Schelling describes a similar infinitude that can
                only manifest itself in finite forms, which are therefore necessarily incommensurate
                to it but that reflect this infinity in the unfolding of the whole in infinite time
                (Schelling 151). And Fichte describes human beings as combining characteristics of
                plants, animals, and a specifically human trait of thought, spirituality, or
                consciousness (Fichte 12).</p>
            
            <p> However, as we saw above, unlike these philosophers Günderrode explicitly separates
                what is specifically human in human existence from spirituality and spirituality
                from consciousness and thought as well as from morality. Being human means,
                essentially, being moral, and this has no connection to either “earth” or the
                “earth-spirit” / “the infinite, divine.” Notably, Günderrode’s model also
                de-emphasizes the “human” aspect of human existence within the trifold structure
                described above. The development of a higher, spiritual relationship to the spirit
                of the earth does not seem to require a human element or human relationships at all
                but only a shift in how the animal relates to the earth or environment in which it
                is embedded. That is, this relationship requires a transition from relating to the
                beings and processes of the world in terms of their function for the animal’s
                survival and procreation, to a deeper connection with these beings and processes as
                reflecting an eternal life flowing through them all. Although it might be difficult
                to imagine how this would take place without a cognitive shift, at no point does
                Günderrode claim that it is through consciousness or human activity in particular
                that this shift takes place and a spiritual relationship develops. In fact, in
                places, she explicitly contrasts the revelation of an individual’s connection to the
                infinite with intellectual investigations, whether scientific or moral (I:49, 81–82,
                309; see Kastinger Riley 110). Rather, as we saw in the first section of this paper,
                Günderrode claims that all manifestations of “life” in finite entities have the
                potential to increase the liveliness of the whole, and hence contribute to its
                development. Thus for Günderrode, while human beings can certainly contribute to a
                raised, enhanced, and more animated universe by living and by developing themselves,
                they do this in essentially the same way as any other being.</p>
            
            <p> Despite this decentering of what is specifically human in human existence, Günderrode
                in fact views certain kinds of human relationships as an important part of the
                process of the development of the world towards its ideal, that is, towards the idea
                of the earth. In order to understand this, we must turn to Günderrode’s idea of
                harmony and attempt to understand the role of this idea within her cosmology and her
                social thought.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>Community</head>
           
            
            <p> Several commentators have associated Günderrode’s emphasis on relationship to the
                infinite with a turn inwards and away from social relationships (Bohrer “Identität”
                79; Christmann 119; Dormann 14, 240). In the first place, this overlooks the fact
                that the infinite, for Günderrode, is not a purely spiritual absolute, but the
                unfolding of nature or life itself, including in human beings. At worst, then, this
                would involve a turn to nature, understood in this new and deeper way, rather than a
                turn towards an ineffable absolute — in other words, it would not be a form of
                “self-annihilation” or “disintegration in infinite space” (Nees 264; Borchardt and
                Wright 254). This turn to nature might perhaps be conceived of as similar to the
                turn that Bohrer attributes to Günderrode’s friend Clemens Brentano, which he
                criticizes for its basis in a view of personal experiences as incommunicable and
                social interactions as necessarily insincere (<hi rend="italic">Der romantische
                    Brief</hi> 120). </p>
            
            <p> There is some support for this interpretation of Günderrode’s writing. On his way to
                understanding the true nature of existence, the narrator of “Story of a Brahmin”
                tells his listener that “I wrested myself away from all relations with human beings”
                (I:306), after which he enjoyed a contemplative life in the countryside. His
                interlocutor complains that this self-isolation, if adopted by many people, would
                destroy “human society” (<hi rend="italic">menschliche Gesellschaft</hi>), and the
                narrator (Almor) agrees: “I can, Lubar interrupted the storyteller, call this step
                good as little as I can suicide. Both are equally detrimental to human society, and
                what would become of [society], if everyone were allowed to kill themselves for it?
                / Young friend! responded Almor, not everyone can and will do what I did. It does
                not befit everyone” (I:307). </p>
            
            <p> However, Almor does not remain in isolation for long, and the claims that Günderrode
                advocates a turn inward overlooks the new kinds of relationships and communities
                that she indicates are fostered by an altered relationship to the infinite. In
                “Story of a Brahmin,” the narrator explains that an old Brahmin “taught me how a
                community exists between human beings in whom the inner sense has arisen and the
                worldspirit” (I:312). It would be possible to interpret this statement as claiming
                that an individual who has become aware of the inner connections between things
                enjoys a sense of communion with the infinite, without necessarily entering into any
                kind of community with other human beings. However, the context suggests that
                Günderrode means that a community exists between those who understand these inner
                connections as well as between these individuals and what the Brahmin calls the
                worldspirit. The “wrest[ing] away from all relations with human beings” is only a
                stage the narrator passes through on his way to finding a true community—one that
                not only includes a closer relationship to the nonhuman world and the spirit that
                lies behind it but also involves especially close connections with other human
                beings. </p>
            
            <p> For example, the narrator of “Story of a Brahmin” describes a community of priests
                into whose secrets he must be initiated in order to understand his intimations of
                infinitude (I:312). One of these priests has such a close connection to the Brahmin
                that he senses when the old man is dying. The narrator is, furthermore, telling his
                story to an interlocutor, Lubar, who is himself seeking initiation. And, at the end
                of the piece, the narrator has found his own community: he lives with the Brahmin’s
                daughter, accompanied by palm trees, a stream, and the immortal spirit of the
                Brahmin. </p>
            
            <p> In other pieces, too, Günderrode indicates that an ideal community is formed: (1) on
                the basis of a relation to the infinite/divine; (2) outside the institutions of
                civil society or the state (see Licher “Du mußt Dich” 30;
                <hi rend="italic">Mein Leben </hi>49); and (3) outside a
                built-up environment, in proximity to the natural world. For instance, in <hi
                    rend="italic">Muhammad, the Prophet of Mecca</hi>, Muhammad is banished from
                Mecca with his followers, during which period he appears as a wise and resourceful
                leader, guided by his faith, which he shares with his companions. After their
                conquest of Mecca and return to the city, his tyrannical impulses emerge, and some
                of the most sympathetic characters in the piece lament his domination of other
                people (I:193, 197; see Licher,
                <hi rend="italic">Mein Leben </hi>187–88). In other words, the
                ideal community created in the wilderness is lost when Muhammad founds a state with
                himself as its ruler.</p>
            
            <p> In keeping with Günderrode’s normative restraint, she presents Muhammad’s autocracy
                towards the end of the play as both wrongful and antithetical to the good community.
                As noted above, Günderrode denies that the world is improved by mastering others,
                whether human or nonhuman. The earth cannot be cultivated through the action of some
                parts on others but must develop organically through the natural self-development
                of all its individual parts. </p>
            
            <p> However, that does not mean that this self-development must occur in isolation.
                Günderrode is clear that friendship, love, and connections to others — including
                nonhuman others—are important to the emergence of a harmonious, organic whole. In
                the first place, this can involve sharing knowledge of the divine that underlies the
                everyday world we experience. In <hi rend="italic">Prophet of Mecca</hi>, Muhammad
                claims he will “inject” or “inoculate” the earth with a branch from “the tree of
                divine blessedness” (I:157), while the narrator of “Story of a Brahmin” describes
                the Brahmin as “a true priest, a mediator between God and human beings” (I:312). But
                this is not the most fundamental way that relationships between human beings can
                contribute to the development of the earth towards its organic end-point, as we can
                see if we return to Günderrode’s basic metaphysical picture. </p>
            
            <p> In the first section of this paper, we saw that, on Günderrode’s model,
                entities are formed of constellations of elements that break apart as creatures die
                (or objects break down) and are then reformed into new entities. We also saw that,
                in this process, the elements, and through them the whole, become more animated,
                more alive. In “Idea of the Earth,” Günderrode claims that this process is driven by
                the dual factors of “struggle” (<hi rend="italic">Kampf</hi>) or “exercise” (<hi
                    rend="italic">Übung</hi>) and “laws of affinity” (<hi rend="italic">Gesezen der
                    Verwantschaft</hi> [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]):
                
            <quote>When a person is dead, their mixture returns to the substance of the earth, but
                that within them that we called force, activity, or rather that of its materials in
                which the more active pole predominated, reverts to that which is related to it in
                the earth; the coarser elements likewise seek what is similar to them according to
                laws of affinity. But these elements have become different, after they have been
                forced up to life in the organism, than they were before they entered into this
                organic connection. They have become livelier, and increase the earth’s life in
                returning to the earth, like two who have hardened their strength in long struggle
                are stronger when the struggle has ended than they were before. The elements are
                like this, for they are alive, and the living force strengthens itself in every
                exercise. (I:447; cf. I:359)</quote>
                
            The first factor, struggle, explains how the elements become more animated over time
                (i.e., through their exercise, including in struggle with each other). The second
                factor, affinity—which Günderrode elsewhere refers to as “harmony” (<hi
                    rend="italic">Harmonie</hi>) and “something homogenous” (<hi rend="italic">etwas
                    Homogenes</hi>) (I:33, 34)—explains not only the law according to which elements
                combine to form new entities but also love, friendship, and other feelings of
                connection that human beings experience with each other (and, perhaps, towards other
                beings). In the philosophical dialogue “The Manes,” the teacher explains: “As surely
                as all harmonious things are connected in a certain way, whether they are visible or
                invisible, just as surely we, too, are connected with <hi rend="italic">that
                    part</hi> of the spiritual world that harmonizes with us” (I:33).</p>
            
            <p> The teacher adds that this connection is not destroyed by the death of individuals:
                “The death of a person connected with me in this way does not cancel out this
                connection. Death is a chemical process, a separation of forces, but no annihilator:
                it does not tear the bond between me and similar souls” (I:33). On this account, the
                characteristics of a dead person that harmonize with those of someone living
                continue to live on in the latter. This point underlies the deathbed scene in “Story
                of a Brahmin,” where the Brahmin anticipates continued life in Almor’s life with his
                daughter: “Live with her and tell her of me; I would like to live on in her love.
                You, Almor, farewell; I will not die for you because my spirit continues to have an
                effect in you” (I:313). This also explains why Almor’s community includes not just
                himself and the Brahmin’s daughter but also the dead Brahmin himself: the Brahmin
                has become part of them, surviving in the ways he has influenced them. Importantly,
                this model also applies to nonhuman entities, even inanimate beings, as well as
                humans. If a human being experiences a sense of affinity with nonhuman aspects of
                the world, this can be explained on the same basis as feelings of affinity between
                human beings: as an indication of harmony or homogeneity between them. For this
                reason, it is not surprising that Almor’s description of his community at the end of
                “Story of a Brahmin” includes not only the Brahmin’s daughter and the dead Brahmin
                but also a tree and a spring.</p>
            
            <p> Günderrode’s claim that the dead live on in the living is meant literally: The
                ability to experience real connections with the dead, as well as nonhuman and even
                inanimate things (“those things whose life resembles death”), is underpinned by the
                metaphysical picture outlined above. According to Günderrode, after a person’s
                death, “their mixture returns to the substance of the earth,” after which it is
                divided up and re-assembled, together with other elements, to form new entities.
                Thus, in “Letters,” the writer, saddened by the thought of being separated from
                Eusebio by death, claims that “I consoled myself that our befriended elements,
                obeying the laws of attraction, would find each other even in infinite space and
                join with each other” (I:358; see also I:68). </p>
            
            <p> A major implication of this model is that the “homogenous” elements in two people, or
                two beings of any kind, that harmonize with each other can join together after death
                according to the “laws of affinity” to create new, more harmonious forms of life
                (see, e.g., I:325). Consequently, the constitution of new entities out of the same
                elements according to laws of affinity should gradually contribute to a more
                harmonious world—and potentially to the harmonious, organic unity that Günderrode
                calls “the realized idea of the earth” (I:449). We saw above that, in “Story of a
                Brahmin,” the narrator claims that “a time of perfection must come, when each being
                will be harmonious with itself and with the others, when they flow into each other
                and become one.” The cultivation of friendships and other forms of connection to
                (human and nonhuman) others, as well as self-cultivation in order to be more capable
                of forming these connections, is the means by which the beings of the world can
                gradually come together into a harmonious whole.</p>
            
            <p> Günderrode’s ideal for community is based on connections between individuals and
                includes connections with aspects of the world beyond the human — that is, both
                nonhuman entities and the universal principle, spirit, force, or life that is
                manifested in every finite being. This form of community cannot be imposed on people
                or things, for example through laws or institutions, educational systems, or methods
                for controlling, shaping, or cultivating the natural world. This community is
                instead bound by feelings of affinity, friendship, and love, and, if it grows, can
                only do so organically, as individuals develop to have more in common with each
                other. This growth of an ideal community—or of several, for there is no reason why
                these harmonies could not develop in several places at once and then converge (see
                Licher “Du mußt Dich” 31) — creates a gradual movement towards a more harmonious
                whole. In other words, by working on oneself in this kind of community of connected
                beings — that is, in developing together a deeper, shared connection to each other
                and to the infinite, productive “spirit of nature” that runs through all things
                — individuals cultivate themselves and thereby the earth, whose elements they are
                made of. In so doing, they not only increase their own “liveliness,” “animation,” or
                “spirit,” but begin to join together into the interconnected parts of the ultimate
                organism that would constitute the final order of the earth.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>Concluding Remarks on Günderrode and Political Ecology</head>
            
            <p>Despite its strong commitments to literary and philosophical tropes of its day,
                Günderrode’s account of human nature and of communities that include both humans and
                the nonhuman is not as outlandish or outdated as it might at first appear. We accept
                the principle of the conservation of mass, as well as the idea that human beings,
                like everything else, are made up of smaller elements—chemical and mineral
                substances and, beyond these, atoms, which are themselves comprised of protons,
                neutrons, and electrons carrying an electric charge. And we know that, upon our
                death, just like with the destruction of other living and non-living entities, these
                elements will decompose and go on to participate in different forms of life. What we
                find hard to accept is the idea that mind, awareness, experience, soul, or
                life—whatever we want to call our sense of ourselves as unique living
                beings—attaches to these atoms, sub-atomic particles, forces, or, in Günderrode’s
                terminology, “elements.” </p>
            
            <p> But this is precisely where Günderrode’s account provides resources for rethinking
                our relationship, not just to the nonhuman things of the world but to each other
                and, ultimately, ourselves. In the first place, this is due to Günderrode’s denial
                that consciousness is something different to or outside the material world, or even
                a special and unique force within the material world that attaches to human beings
                alone. On Günderrode’s account, consciousness is present from the beginning in all
                parts of nature, in the elements that make up our world. As she writes in “Idea of
                the Earth,” “the life-principle in the elements is immortal; it requires only
                contact and connection again like before and new life blossoms with all the blooms
                that we call thought and sensation and organism and body and soul.” On Günderrode’s
                account, human beings are unique not because they are conscious but because of
                their specific orientation to “humanity” in their social and moral lives—and, she is
                clear, this is not sufficient for the good life. Günderrode’s account reveals the
                human overcommitment to the idea that we are special because of our consciousness,
                as well as to the idea that this gives us some kind of unique role in the world,
                even — historically in Europe and many forms of Christianity — a special relationship to
                the divine.</p>
            
            <p> However, it must be admitted that, even if we can imagine consciousness in nonhuman
                animals, and, perhaps, plants, most of us find it a stretch to imagine consciousness
                attaching to inorganic objects such as rocks and certainly to atoms or forces.
                Nonetheless, if we focus on the importance of changing how we imagine the things
                around (and within) us, rather than on the attempt to develop an ironclad
                metaphysics, Günderrode’s rethinking of the relationship between humanity and
                consciousness or spirituality, as well as of the role of humans as moral beings and
                <hi rend="italic">vis-à-vis </hi>the development of our world,
                provides resources for efforts to rethink our relationship to nature. This may be
                particularly valuable in light of the current environmental crisis. The roots of the
                ongoing human-caused devastation of our world in an attitude of human exceptionalism
                and human domination is often noted in the environmental literature (e.g., Dallmayr
                1; Pattberg 1, 6), as is the need for new ways of conceiving of ourselves in
                relation to the nonhuman (Dallmayr 2; Schulz 133). As Jane Bennett remarks in <hi
                    rend="italic">Vibrant Matter</hi>, “the image of dead or thoroughly
                instrumentalized matter feeds human hubris and our earth-destroying fantasies of
                conquest and consumption. It does so by preventing us from detecting (seeing,
                hearing, smelling, tasting, feeling) a fuller range of the nonhuman powers
                circulating around and within human bodies” (ix). In light of the serious, ongoing
                consequences of viewing non-living things as inert and unfeeling, a metaphysics that
                rejects this view is at least worth exploring. </p>
            
            <p>Bennett views the task of her book, not as proving the agentic or conscious
                properties of matter but as a partly rhetorical strategy for inducing a less
                destructive orientation to nature in human beings, a task that she describes as both
                ontological and political:
                
            <quote>(1) To paint a positive ontology of vibrant matter, which stretches received
                concepts of agency, action, and freedom sometimes to the breaking point; (2) to
                dissipate the onto-theological binaries of life/matter, human/animal,
                will/determination, and organic/inorganic using arguments and other rhetorical means
                to induce in human bodies an aesthetic-affective openness to material vitality; and
                (3) to sketch a style of political analysis that can better account for the
                contributions of nonhuman actants. (x)</quote>
                
                This is a task to which Günderrode’s ontology, and the account of human sociality
                that she situates within it, can contribute. Günderrode’s emphasis on the intrinsic
                value of all entities, including human beings, works against an instrumentalizing
                view of nature as well as against totalizing social or political discourses that
                attempt to improve the world through imposing certain ways of being on (human and
                nonhuman) others. Together with the ideal of harmony, this provides both a goal that
                we can work towards and a valuable modesty about the extent to which we can bring it
                about.</p></div>
                
                <div type="citation">
                    <head>Works Cited</head>
        
            <bibl>Allingham, Liesl. “Countermemory in Karoline von Günderrode’s ‘Darthula nach Ossian’: A Female Warrior, Her Unruly Breast, and the Construction of Her Myth.” <hi rend="italic">Goethe Yearbook</hi>, vol. 21, 2014, pp. 39–56.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Battersby, Christine. “Stages on Kant’s Way: Aesthetics, Morality, and the Gendered Sublime.” <hi rend="italic">Feminism and Tradition in Aesthetics</hi>, edited by Peggy Zeglin Brand and Carolyn Korsmeyer, Pennsylvania State UP, 1995, pp. 88–114.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Bennett, Jane. <hi rend="italic">Vibrant Matter: A Political Ecology of Things</hi>. Duke UP, 2010.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Bohrer, Karl Heinz. “Identität als Selbstverlust. Zum romantischen Subjektbegriff.” <hi rend="italic">Merkur</hi>, vol. 38, no. 4, 1984, pp. 367–79.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Der romantische Brief. Die Enstehung ästhetischer Subjektivität</hi>. Suhrkamp, 1989.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Borchardt, E., and J. Wright. “Androgyny: The Search for Wholeness in Karoline von Günderrode and Heinrich von Kleist: Christa Wolf’s Novel <hi rend="italic">Kein Ort. Nirgends</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Fantastic in the Arts</hi>, vol. 11, no. 3, 2000, pp. 245–56.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Christmann, Ruth. <hi rend="italic">Zwischen Identitätsgewinn und Bewußtseinsverlust. Das philosophisch-literarische Werk der Karoline von Günderrode (1780–1806)</hi>. Lang, 2005.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Dallmayr, Fred. <hi rend="italic">Return to Nature? An Ecological Counterhistory</hi>. UP of Kentucky, 2011.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Dormann, Helga. <hi rend="italic">Die Kunst des inneren Sinns. Mythisierung der inneren und äusseren Natur im Werk Karoline von Günderrodes</hi>. Königshausen und Neumann, 2004.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Ezekiel, Anna. “Metamorphosis, Personhood, and Power in Karoline von Günderrode.” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review</hi>, vol. 25, no. 6, 2014, pp. 773–91.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>———, editor and translator. <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Fragments</hi>. By Karoline von Günderrode, Oxford UP, forthcoming. </bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Fichte, Johann Gottlieb. <hi rend="italic">The Vocation of Man</hi>. 1800. Translated by Peter Preuss, Hackett, 1987. </bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Gjesdal, Kristin, and Dalia Nassar, editors. <hi rend="italic">Women Philosophers of
                    the Long Nineteenth Century: The German Tradition</hi>. Oxford UP,
                forthcoming.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Heimerl, Joachim. “Dem Tode verfallen: Die Ballade ‘Piedro’ im Kontext des literarischen Werks der Karoline von Günderrode.” <hi rend="italic">Wirkendes Wort</hi>, vol. 53, no. 3, 2003, pp. 401–16.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Herder, Johann Gottfried. <hi rend="italic">Ideen zur Philosophie der Geschichte der Menschheit. Erster Theil.</hi> Johann Friedrich Hartknoch, 1784.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Hilger, Stephanie Mathilde. “Staging Islam: Karoline von Günderrode's Mahomed, der Prophet von Mekka.” <hi rend="italic">Women Write Back: Strategies of Response and the Dynamics of European Literary Culture, 1790–1805</hi>, Rodopi, 2009, pp. 91–118.</bibl>
            
            <bibl>Kant, Immanuel. “Die Religion Innerhalb der Grenzen der bloßen Vernunft.” 1793. <hi rend="italic">Kants gesammelte Schriften</hi>. Edited by Königlichen Preußischen Akademie der Wissenschaften. Part I, <hi rend="italic">Werke</hi>, vol. 6, <hi rend="italic">Die Religion Innerhalb der Grenzen der bloßen Vernunft. Die Metaphysik der Sitten</hi>. Georg Reimer, 1914.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Kastinger Riley, Helene M. “Zwischen den Welten. Ambivalenz und Existentialproblematik im Werk Caroline von Günderrodes.” <hi rend="italic">Die weiblich Muse: Sechs Essays über künstlerisch schaffende Frauen der Goethezeit</hi>, Camden House, 1986, pp. 91–119.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Kuzniar, Alice. “Labor Pains: Romantic Theories of Creativity and Gender.” <hi rend="italic">“The Spirit of Poesy”: Essays on Jewish and German Literature and Thought in Honor of Géza von Molnár</hi>, edited by R. Block and P. Fenves, Northwestern UP, 2000, pp. 74–88.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Licher, Lucia Maria. <hi rend="italic">Mein Leben in einer bleibenden Form aussprechen. Umrisse einer Ästhetik im Werk Karoline von Günderrodes (1780–1806)</hi>. Winter, 1996.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>———. “Du mußt Dich in eine entferntere Empfindung versetzen.’ Strategien interkultureller Annäherung im Werk Karoline von Günderrodes (1780–1806). <hi rend="italic">“Der weibliche multikulturelle Blick.” Ergebnisse eines Symposiums</hi>, edited by Hannelore Scholz and Brita Baume, Trafo, 1995, pp. 21–36.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>———. “‘Der Völker Schicksal ruht in meinen Busen.’ Karoline von Günderrode als Dichterin der Revolution.” <hi rend="italic">“Der Menschheit Hälfte blieb noch ohne Recht”. Frauen und die französische Revolution</hi>, edited by Helge Brandes, Deutscher Universitäts Verlag, 1991, pp. 113–32.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Nassar, Dalia. “The Human Vocation and the Question of the Earth: Karoline von Günderrode’s Reading of Fichte.” <hi rend="italic">Archiv für Geschichte der Philosophie</hi>, forthcoming.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Nees, Lisette. Letter to Karoline von Günderrode, 17 April 1805. “Karoline von Günderrode in ihrer Umwelt. I,” edited by Max Preitz. <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch des Freien Deutschen Hochstifts</hi>, 1962, pp. 208–306.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Novalis. <hi rend="italic">Schriften. Zweite, nach den Handschriften ergänzte, erweiterte und verbesserte Auflage in vier Bänden</hi>. Edited by P. Kluckhohn and R. Samuel, 3 vols., W. Kohlhammer, 1960f.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Pattberg, Philipp. “Domination and Control: Europe’s Mastery of Nature in Historic Perspective. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Political Ecology</hi>, vol. 14, 2007, pp. 1–9.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Pnevmonidou, Elena. “Die Absage an das romantische Ich. Dorothea Schlegels <hi rend="italic">Florentin</hi> als Umschrift von Friedrich Schlegel’s <hi rend="italic">Lucinde</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">German Life and Letters</hi>, vol. 58, no. 3, 2005, pp. 271–92.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Roetzel, Lisa C. “Feminizing Philosophy.” <hi rend="italic">Theory as Practice: A Critical Anthology of Early German Romantic Writings</hi>, edited by Jochen Schulte-Sasse, Haynes Horne, and Andreas Michel, U of Minnesota, 1997, pp. 361–81.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Schelling, Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph. <hi rend="italic">Bruno, or On the Natural and Divine Principle of Things</hi>. 1802. Edited and translated by Michael Vater, State U of New York P, 1984.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Schulz, Karsten A. “Decolonizing Political Ecology: Ontology, Technology and‘Critical’ Enchantment.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Political Ecology</hi>, vol. 24, 2017, pp. 126–43.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Sevin, D., and C. Zeller. <hi rend="italic">Heinrich von Kleist: Perspectives of Research</hi>. De Gruyter, 2013.</bibl>
                    
            <bibl>Strauss Sotiropoulos, Carol. “Fuller, Goethe, Bettine: Cultural Transfer and Imagined German Womanhood.” <hi rend="italic">Towards a Female Genealogy of Transcendentalism</hi>, edited by Jana L. Argersinger and Phyllis Cole, U of Georgia P, 2014, 81–101.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
