<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Hölderlin: From the “Death of Nature” to “the Earth”</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Kir Kuiken</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-02-21</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2023.ecology.kuiken</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">praxis</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Hölderlin: From the “Death of Nature” to “the Earth”
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Kir</forename>
                                <surname>Kuiken</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/ecology/praxis.2023.ecology.kuiken"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romanticism and Political Ecology</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-02-21">February 21, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>02.21.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Hölderlin: From the “Death of Nature” to “the Earth”</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Kir Kuiken</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of Albany</affiliation>
                </byline>
                <div type="section">
            <p> Once various scientific societies and associations began to debate the use of the
                term “Anthropocene” as a geological time period on the same scale as the Holocene,
                what seemed to register was the paradox of a “shock of the new” that had been long
                prepared. However one dates the start of this period, it was as if an event had
                overtaken the “Anthropos” from behind, as if what was “new” in the “Anthropo”- cene
                (the “cene” deriving from the Greek “kainos” for “new”) had emerged suddenly in the
                present as a forgotten archaism, making it difficult to say exactly when the
                catastrophe began or to anticipate how it might end. This shock has launched a
                further set of reactions, from “new materialisms” to renewed attention to
                alternative cosmologies, in an attempt to have thought measure up to the seemingly
                unprecedented nature of the event we call the Anthropocene, and to mark the ways in
                which our current coordinates, concepts and concerns are no longer adequate to think
                it, much less to respond to its exigency. This in turn has proliferated a kind of
                post-mortem on a whole series of philosophemes or concepts deemed too complicit with
                the crisis. Bruno Latour’s <hi rend="italic">Politics of Nature</hi>, for
                instance, argues for a final liquidation of the main concept in its title — Nature —
                since it has authorized a whole set of power relations grounded on a constitutive
                exclusion. The notion of a “nature” separate from the “social,” for Latour,
                underpins a politics without due process for those elements of the collective
                (non-humans of various kinds, including non-human homo sapiens) whose externality to
                the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi> withdraws them from the domain of the political
                itself. </p>
            
            <p> From Timothy Morton’s notion of the “mesh”<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a full development of this term, see
                            Timothy Morton, “Thinking Big” in <hi rend="italic">The Ecological
                                Thought</hi>, Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 2010,
                        20-–58.</note> to Latour’s conception of “multi-naturalism” or the
                    “pluriverse,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Though this term is used in various places in
                            Latour, he develops it in the most detail in the first chapter of <hi
                                rend="italic">Philosophy Politics of Nature</hi>, (titled “Why
                            Political Ecology Has to Let Go of Nature”), 9-–52.</note> the concept of the Anthropocene opens up a
                world of inextricable relation and intertwinement. Just as there is no “human”
                independent of the various forms of life on which it depends (bacterial or
                otherwise), so there is no “pure nature” devoid of humanity’s intervention. A new
                political ecology comes to replace, or at least supercede, political economy.
                However, it is precisely the question of the nature of the “collectivity” that lies
                on the hither side of this “death of nature” that this paper will interrogate. The
                “common world,” of which Latour speaks in <hi rend="italic">Politics of
                Nature</hi>, (drawing on his conception of actor-network theory) has as its
                explicit focus the notion that “humans and non-humans are engaged in a history that
                should render their separation impossible” (“Promise” 39). The result, for Latour,
                is a new form of collectivity, one predicated not on the model of the “one,”
                necessarily, but certainly on the absence of the two, the absence of a unitary
                border between nature and culture, human and non-human, etc. </p>
            
            <p> What must be questioned, however, is exactly how one interprets the “death of nature”
                upon which Latour’s work is predicated. What exactly one means by it seems to
                alter the kind and nature of the intertwinements, and therefore the contours of the
                political ecology, that are grounded on it. What if the “death of nature” called
                for by Latour, Phillipe Descola, and others were an insufficient starting point for
                articulating the kind of collectivity capable of responding to the event or crisis
                of the Anthropocene? What if the “mesh,” the “pluriverse,” and all the other various
                names for this collectivity were threatened by something akin to what Jean-Luc
                Nancy, referencing Marx, calls the “equivalence of catastrophes,” where so-called
                “natural” disasters such as hurricanes and floods can no longer rigorously be
                distinguished from man-made disasters such as Fukushima. As Nancy insists, that very
                equivalence, and the totality of interdependences that constitute it, <hi
                    rend="italic">is</hi> the catastrophe itself, which acts as the limit condition
                against which any rethinking of collectivity or, to use Nancy’s term, any “communism
                of nonequivalence” (41) would have to be measured. As Frédéric Neyrat
                argues in <hi rend="italic">La Part Inconstructible de la Terre</hi> (The
                Inconstructible Part of the Earth),<note place="foot" resp="author"> Frédéric Neyrat,
                            <hi rend="italic">La Part Inconstructible de la Terre, </hi>Paris:
                            Seuil, 2016. This text was recently translated by Drew S. Burk as
                            Frédéric Neyrat, <hi rend="italic">The Unconstructible Earth</hi>
                            (trans. Drew S. Burk) New York: Fordham University Press, 2019.
                            Henceforth cited in text as (N) and, followed by French and then
                            English pagination.</note> the “death” of nature is far from a
                recent event; it has in fact occurred repeatedly in the history of the West. Neyrat
                names at least four deaths of nature (there are likely more), including the
                pre-Socratics’ transformation of nature into substance, monotheism’s conversion of
                nature into the medium through which God expresses his commandments, the
                    seventeenth century’s mechanization,
                quantification, and mathematization of nature, and our own current global
                financialization of nature into a tradeable resource (197–204; 108–12). If “Nature”
                has been dying for some time now, then its most recent entombment is perhaps more
                ambiguous than Latour admits, and correlatively, so is the new collectivity that
                emerges as a result.</p>
            
            <p> One particular form that “death of nature” takes is in the increasing interest in
                the motif of the “Earth” in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries as
                both irreducible to the natural world opened up by science, and to the world
                conceived either as the secular realm distinct from God’s kingdom, or as the arena
                of Man’s (or humanity’s) self-production. This motif emerges in several different
                contexts in the period in response to both the development of natural science and
                to the progressive reliance on natural right as the cornerstone for a reinvention of
                the political. It tends to enact a disorganization of the coordinates that define
                both the natural world “out there” as well as the politics of nature that underwrite
                social contract theory and other modern conceptions of political sovereignty. The
                Earth comes to signify something — a basic ground of the political — that remains
                irreducible to nature but also to any political theology or cosmology that would
                reduce it either to a particular place within the human “world” or to a sublunary
                natural “human habitat.” “The Earth,” rather, comes to stand in for an exteriority
                to the nature/culture divide that cannot be appropriated by any politics dependent
                on that distinction, and it begins to call into question the models of sovereignty,
                of the <hi rend="italic">polis</hi>, and of nature that depend on it. Of the many
                Romantic-era writers that explicitly treat “the Earth” as a fundamental theme, it is
                arguably Friedrich Hölderlin who most explicitly places this motif at the heart of
                his poetics and thought. The motif of “the Earth” materializes in his work at nearly
                every juncture: when he articulates the structure and aim of poetry itself, when he
                articulates the specificity of modernity in relation to classical Greece, and when
                he attempts to articulate the specificity of the “world” that modernity enacts in
                contrast to the one it purports to leave behind. In each case, as I will argue, what
                is at stake is the development of a (poetic) political ecology, one that treats the
                Earth as the in-appropriable ground of poetry and politics and thus as an <hi
                    rend="italic">event</hi> that undermines traditional forms of sovereignty,
                whether these take the form of the unified lyric voice or the form of the
                privileging of the human as the political actor par excellence. </p>
            
            <p> Focus on the question of the role of the Earth in Hölderlin has tended by and large
                to be filtered through Heidegger’s appropriation of the concept for his own
                conception of the “fourfold.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> One of the first articulations of this distinction
                            is to be found in Martin Heidegger, “The Origin of the Work of Art” in
                                <hi rend="italic">Off the Beaten Track</hi>, (ed. Julian Young and
                            Kenneth Haynes) Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002: 1-–56.
                            Henceforth cited in text as (WA) followed by the English translation).
                            This initially bipartite division is then later developed by Heidegger
                            into the notion of the “fourfold,” the play of revealing/concealing
                            between Earth, world, divinities, and mortals. For a close and detailed
                            reading of this development in Heidegger, see Andrew Mitchell’s, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Fourfold</hi>, Evanston: Northwestern University
                            Press, 2015. </note> Whereas Heidegger positions the Earth in
                terms of the interplay between revealing and concealing, Hölderlin’s own interest in
                the motif of the Earth is centered instead on its
                <hi rend="italic">irreducibility </hi>to a given world or a
                given conception of nature. Heidegger effectively dismisses the notion that
                Hölderlin’s poetry is concerned with nature. When the word does occur in Hölderlin’s
                writings, Heidegger almost always emphasizes the extent to which it must be
                understood in its “original” Greek sense as <hi rend="italic">physis</hi>: the
                appearing of what is. Lacoue-Labarthe, by contrast, interprets the motif of the
                Earth in Hölderlin according to its opposition to (political) theology, suggesting
                that its significance has to do with Hölderlin’s renunciation of the divine and
                with what Lacoue-Labarthe calls the “caesura of the speculative” (208). Yet what
                both of these interpretations never quite arrive at is the question of how
                Hölderlin’s poetry specifically addresses what it means that “poetically, man dwells on this
                Earth” (Poems, 789) since this “dwelling” is not an origin or birthplace but a series of
                different interactions with something that remains irreducible either to “nature” or
                to phenomenality itself. Heidegger gives this Hölderlinian phrase a
                specific interpretation that emphasizes the way poetry makes the Earth a “dwelling”
                and the way language is the “house of Being”; poetry, in his interpretation, is what
                makes the dwelling a “home.” Hölderlin’s emphasis, however, is on the way “dwelling
                on this Earth” impacts the relation between poetry and the Earth. In other words,
                Heidegger’s emphasis on the poetic as the site of dwelling is reversed in Hölderlin;
                it is “dwelling on the Earth”—exposure to an irreducible, unappropriable
                externality— that produces the poetics. It is precisely because man
                “dwells” on the Earth that the variety of different representations of nature and of
                the Earth itself becomes possible. Hölderlin’s poetics, in short, does not
                presume a return to a native land. Instead, his poems articulate a <hi rend="italic"
                    >dürftiger-zeit</hi> or “between time” that marks a transition between two
                different forms of dwelling in, on, or with the Earth, developing what Carl Schmitt
                might call a new “nomos” of the Earth, provided that term does not mean a
                form of law created by the appropriation of land. Hölderlin develops a poetics that
                is itself “appropriated” by the Earth, that is, exposed to its irreducibility to
                representation or its being encapsulated within a schema in which it becomes an
                object or a foundation. We move from the Earth conceived as the realm
                of “nature” to something far stranger: Hölderlin’s Earth articulates a
                quasi-Latourian “death of nature” but only by assuming this death as a <hi
                    rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> rather than as something that must be enacted.
                One can only call this a “political ecology” on the condition that the “<hi
                    rend="italic">eco</hi>” derived from “<hi rend="italic">oikos</hi>” and
                designating a “home,” “habitat,” or “dwelling” is understood in relation to what
                Frédéric Neyrat calls an “ecology of separation,” (N 237-320; 133-177), which
                designates, among other things, the <hi rend="italic">withdrawal</hi> of the Earth
                from the status of an object into something more akin to an event or a trajectory.
                That withdrawal in turn not only destabilizes any sense of “dwelling” predicated on
                a shared belonging (to Being, say) but also invokes a poetics of the Earth no
                longer grounded on the nature/culture divide.</p>
            
            <p> Hölderlin develops the motif of the Earth throughout his oeuvre, but the clearest
                tie between this motif and his conception of poetry is to be found in his difficult
                prose texts. These texts at once lay out the structures implicit in his poetics as
                well as define how the specificity of those structures relate to key thematics
                within his poetry, including the motif of the Earth. In “On the Difference of Poetic Modes,” for instance, the notion of the Earth is
                coupled with Hölderlin’s development of the idea of “alternating poetic tones,”
                which he claims characterizes not just his own but all forms of 
                poetic expression (<hi rend="italic">Essays and Letters</hi>).
                For Hölderlin, what distinguishes different genres are not their external forms but
                the relationship between what he calls their “underlying tone” (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Grundton</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Bedeutung</hi>, a work’s significance or
                meaning) and its mode of presentation or <hi rend="italic">Darstellung</hi>. This
                relation varies from work to work, but it also varies <hi rend="italic">within</hi>
                each work through an internal oscillation of tone and presentation that never
                arrives at what one might call their “alignment.” In fact, as anyone reading
                Hölderlin’s prose can attest, this alternation appears to take the form of an
                interminable oscillation between two poles of an opposition, in what Lacoue-Labarthe
                has identified as the quasi-Heideggerian logic of <hi rend="italic">Ent-Fernung</hi>
                (231), a kind of hyperbolic logic of excess that takes the form of “the more x it
                is, the more y it is,” the closer it is, the more distant, the more interior it is,
                the more exterior and so on. </p>
            
            <p> This logic comes into play, among other places, in his description of the interplay
                of tone and presentation in poetry, which oscillates between an underlying “tone”
                or mood and a form of presentation that in the end transforms that mood into its
                opposite. Regarding lyric poetry, for instance, Hölderlin writes: 
                
            <quote> In its basic mood (<hi rend="italic">Grundstimmung</hi>) the lyric poem is <hi rend="italic">more
                    sensuous</hi>, in that this
                [basic mood] contains a unity which lends itself most easily; precisely for that
                reason does it not strive in the outer appearance for reality, serenity and
                gracefulness; it evades the sensuous connection and presentation so much (because
                the pure basic tone (<hi rend="italic">Grundton</hi>) inclines precisely toward it)
                that it is rather miraculous in its formations and assembly of these. (<hi
                    rend="italic">Essays and Letters</hi> 83)<note place="foot" resp="author"> Friedrich Hölderlin,
                            <hi rend="italic">Essays and Letter on Theory </hi>(trans.
                            Thomas Pfau) Albany: State University of New York Press, 1988: 83. See
                            also Friedrich Hölderlin, <hi rend="italic">Sämtliche Werke und Briefe
                                Volume 1-2</hi>, Munich: Carl Hanser Verlag, 1970, 889. Prose texts
                            by Hölderlin will henceforth be cited in text from this edition as (PW)
                            with English pagination, followed by German volume number and
                            pagination.</note></quote>
            
            The sentence continues, and as it does so, it passes through a series of further
                oscillations between tone and presentation. Yet the basic principle remains the same
                throughout its various permutations — the work’s very tendency toward one or another
                presentation or signification is the very means by which that tendency is refracted
                or displaced. The crucial aspect of this process is that the “basic mood” or <hi
                    rend="italic">Grundton</hi> of a given poem is not refracted simply through the
                medium of its expression, as if tone and presentation were of different orders.
                Instead, the very “nature” of the “basic mood” overcomes itself, one might say, in a
                ceaseless oscillation, a continuous departure from itself.</p> </div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>The Earth, The Organic, The Aorgic</head>
            
            <p> What then, does this oscillation of poetic tones have to do with the Earth? Among
                the many forms of representation or “art character” that Hölderlin lists as
                characterizing a poem, one in particular is most pointedly associated with the
                tragic: what he calls the “idealistic image” (<hi rend="italic">idealischen Bilde</hi>) (PW 889; 1:83).
                In fact, it is not the content of a work that determines its genre but the
                oscillating interplay of a poem’s tone and presentation. “On the Difference of
                Poetic Modes” starts by providing a set of definitions: 
                
                <quote>"The lyric, in appearance idealistic poem, is naïve in its significance. It is a
                continuous metaphor of feeling. The epic, in appearance naïve poem, is heroic in its
                significance. It is the metaphor of great aspirations. The tragic, in appearance
                heroic poem, is idealistic in its significance. It is the metaphor of an
                intellectual intuition” (PW 889; 1:83). </quote>
                
                In each case, a poem’s presentation remains in a certain tension with its “basic
                mood,” yet the fact that the tragic form <hi rend="italic">appears</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Schein</hi>)
                heroic, but is in fact “idealistic” in its significance (<hi rend="italic">Bedeutung</hi>), could be said
                to characterize a fundamental tension in much of Hölderlin’s poetics. That is, what
                first appears as a lament for the old gods, for a divine that has absconded, and as
                a reinvigorated desire for the invention of new god(s),<note place="foot" resp="author"> Martin Heidegger, “Only a God Can
                            Save Us,” in <hi rend="italic">Heidegger: The Man and the Thinker</hi>
                            (ed. Thomas Sheehan) London: Routledge University Press, 2017,
                            45-–68.</note> in fact turns into something else entirely. This
                heroic representation instantiates a tragic return to an “Earth” that has begun to
                slip away from its moorings, its determination by a particular theological or
                ontological regime. In this moment, the opposition between the Earth and the divine
                ceases to operate, and a different understanding of the Earth comes to the fore, one
                predicated on its irreducibility to a given “world.” </p>
            
            <p> Something of this irreducibility is in fact legible in the central tension between
                Earth and world found in Heidegger’s “Origin of the Work of Art” yet, as we will
                see, there remains an important divergence between Heidegger and Hölderin’s
                understanding of the relation between Earth and world. If, for Heidegger, the work
                of art is the “setting up of a world” (WA 170), this setting up occurs only against
                the backdrop of an Earth “sheltered” from this formation. Since neither animal nor
                plant “have” a world and are therefore deprived of a relation to beings <hi
                    rend="italic">as such</hi>,<note place="foot" resp="author"> For a discussion of this dynamic, see Heidegger’s
                            broader discussion of the different relations to world between Dasein,
                            animal, and plant in <hi rend="italic">The Four Fundamental Concepts of
                                Metaphysics</hi> (trans. William McNeill and Nicholas Walker)
                            Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1995, 176-–200.</note>
                Heidegger is compelled to describe the specific “worldlessness” of stone, for
                example, in manifestly different terms, casting the Earth in the role of “that which
                comes forth and shelters”: “That into which the work sets itself back and which it
                causes to come forth in this setting back of itself we call the earth. Earth is that
                which comes forth and shelters . . . Upon the Earth and in it, historical man
                grounds his dwelling in the world” (WA 171-72). Heidegger here makes the Earth
                that which withdraws itself from the world. If animals are “poor in world,” the
                stone by contrast remains connected to a world only by its refusal of and by it. The
                stone’s “worldlessness” therefore pertains to its status as the “unconcealed,” as
                that which cannot be rendered by any form of measurement or calculation: “If we try
                to lay hold of the stone’s heaviness in another way, by placing the stone on a
                balance, we merely bring the heaviness into the form of a calculated weight. This
                perhaps very precise determination of the stone remains a number, but the weight’s
                burden has escaped us” (WA 172). The Earth, therefore, “shows itself only when it
                remains undisclosed and unexplained. Earth thus shatters every attempt to penetrate
                it” (WA 172). The setting forth of the Earth by the world is thus figured in
                Heidegger as a “strife” rather than an outright opposition; a strife that, moreover,
                functions as a metaphor for the movement of truth itself, the disclosure of the
                undisclosable in the movement of <hi rend="italic">aletheia</hi>, the simultaneous
                revealing and concealing that characterizes the “world” itself.</p>
            
            <p> While Hölderlin’s conception of the relation of Earth and world clearly influenced
                Heidegger, his own interpretation of this relation nevertheless entails some crucial
                differences that do not allow the tension between Earth and world to unfold as “the
                intimacy of a simple belonging to one another” (WA 174). The main aspect of this
                difference pertains to the way Hölderlin weds the motif of the Earth to the
                unfolding oscillation of poetic tones. In other words, unlike for Heidegger, for
                whom poetics is more generally the “founding” of a world in the poetic word, which
                in turn “sets forth” what remains irreducible to that world (i.e. the Earth), for
                Hölderlin poetry remains caught in the continuous and irresolvable jointure of an
                oscillation between presentation and signification. This oscillation proves
                incapable of presenting the Earth as its hidden ground, as a single signification
                that presents itself through its absence, or as that which remains undisclosed
                “within” a given world, since any underlying signification is eventually overcome by
                yet another disjunction between presentation and signification without any single,
                unified sense emerging. In other words, the Earth’s non-disclosure, in Hölderlin, is
                no longer linked to a given “world” as its constitutive abandonment. Its emergence
                occurs as a result of an excessive striving for precisely its opposite: for the
                unearthly or for the divine. And the Earth “appears” in Hölderlin only as a result
                of that excess re-emerging as the irreducibility of the Earth to the “founding word”
                of the poet in a way neither the poet nor his poetry can fully account for.</p>
            
            <p> These reflections are necessarily grounded in Hölderlin’s understanding of the
                relation between the productive capacities of poetry, and those of “nature,” since
                the latter provides the former with its most acute example of what it means to
                constitute a “world.” In one of Hölderlin’s earliest treatises, “The Ground for
                Empedocles” (in PW), he expressly takes up the question of the relation between art
                and nature in order to explain why his early play (<hi rend="italic">The Death of
                    Empedocles</hi>) is an attempt to overcome the opposition between art and nature
                as the mark of a genuinely modern form of tragedy. The opening of the treatise
                prefigures in many ways the “alternation of tones” theory that will become
                Hölderlin’s more explicit focus in “On the Difference of Poetic Modes,” since he
                describes his tragedy as proceeding through a variety of “tones” each of which is in
                tension with the “reflection” or “sensation” meant to depict it. What Hölderlin
                makes explicit, however, is that even though the “subject matter” of the tragedy is
                “foreign” to the world of the poet, the poet’s selection of this world as a “vessel”
                for his own is strictly “analogical.” That is, the poet’s world can only be
                reflected back to him and to others through the medium of the foreign (in this case,
                ancient Greek tragedy) because that world is precisely the converse of his own. A
                “modern” tragedy is possible only insofar as it engages Greek forms to articulate an
                entirely different content. In other words, something like the opposition between the Greeks and the Hesperians
                that Hölderlin describes in the December 4, 1801 letter to Böhlendorff appears to be
                operative here. To generate a form of art that is "the free use of one’s
                own" as Hölderlin insists in the letter, requires a relation to the foreign that
                refuses simple imitation (PW 150; 2:926). It must repeat the inimitable disjunction
                between tone and expression that characterizes all artforms and that leads the work
                of art to overcome its own conditions of possibility. Hölderlin insists: “We learn
                nothing with more difficulty than to freely use the national. And, I believe that it
                is precisely the clarity of the presentation that is so natural to us as is for the
                Greek the fire from heaven” (PW 149; 2:927). In other words, what is “natural”
                for the Greeks is “fire from heaven,” a sacred or ideal pathos that arises in
                connection with the divine. For us, we modern “Hesperians” it is the reverse; what
                is “inborn” for us is “clarity of presentation” (<hi rend="italic">die Klahrheit der Darstellung</hi>). And
                    <hi rend="italic">because</hi> each is “inborn,” it is precisely the opposite
                that ends up being “mastered.” The Greeks mastered sobriety or the “clarity of
                presentation” because what defined their world is “sacred pathos,” whereas for we
                Hesperians what comes most naturally is precisely that pathos, whereas what is most
                “their own” (the sobriety or the “clarity of presentation”) remains elusive for us. </p>
            
            <p> In short, to return to the problematic central to “Ground for Empedocles,” the world
                of the modern poet, though heterogeneous to the “outward presentations”
                that define ancient tragedy, must nonetheless be located and seized hold of through
                an imitation of ancient tragedy. This takes place only by reproducing the inimitable
                disjunction between presentation and tone, between the “clarity of presentation” and
                “fire from heaven” that defined the Greeks. This must be done, in other words,
                without strict imitation, without the reproduction of the precise relationship
                between the two that defined the Greeks. Hence the reason why Hölderlin must turn to
                that most ancient of questions concerning the relation of art to nature: he’s not
                simply describing the imitation of nature by art but a more complicated
                process—demonstrating the way nature and art are already intertwined to the extent
                that they are both modes of presentation and, as a result, define the contours of a
                given “world” by the specific way in which those modes of presentation interact. For
                Hölderlin, there is no nature “over there” (to paraphrase Latour) that must be
                “represented” by art in order to accomplish itself in a kind of Aristotelian
                mimesis. Rather, art and nature form a unity governed by an internal tension similar
                to the tension inherent in the opposition between representation and tone in poetry.
                What constitutes a “world” for Hölderlin is not a “decision” about beings that
                allows them to appear as beings of a certain kind. There is only an attempt to
                encounter (poetically) a set of modes of presentation in tension with each other
                that make a given world possible, even if the exacerbation of those tensions
                demonstrates that the world they have formed is in a state of collapse.</p>
            
            <p> Thus, while Hölderlin’s approach appears at first to mirror Aristotle’s conception of
                the imitation and completion of nature by art, this dialectic is in fact supplanted
                by something close to the internal oscillation described later in “On the Difference
                of Poetic Modes.” If, as Hölderlin puts in in “Ground for Empedocles”: “art is the
                blossom, the perfection of nature” (<hi rend="italic">Die Kunst ist die Blüte, die Vollendung der
                Natur</hi>) (PW 53; 2:116), this is so only because two different forms of production
                and organization come to vie with each other rather than reproduce one another.
                They form a “world” in and through their disjunction, a differentiation that both
                constitutes the relative unity of that “world” and its conditions of
                dissolution. To grasp this process poetically entails, for Hölderlin, the
                introduction of an important distinction found throughout his oeuvre: the
                distinction between “organic” (<hi rend="italic">organisch</hi>e) and “aorgic” (<hi
                    rend="italic">aorgischen</hi>) principles. This opposition has given
                commentators some difficulty, especially since “aorgic” appears to be a Hölderlinian
                neologism. Veronique Foti asserts that the organic/aorgic opposition is
                simply another name for the <hi rend="italic">physis/techne</hi> distinction, which in turn becomes translated into the
                nature/culture divide. Yet, this doesn’t always seem to be the case. Though
                Hölderlin draws on Schelling’s opposition between <hi rend="italic">organisch </hi> and <hi rend="italic">anorganisch</hi>
                    principles, <note place="foot" resp="author"> This distinction is found throughout Schelling’s works on nature. For
                            a particularly focused discussion of it, see F. W. J. Schelling,
                            “Introduction” in <hi rend="italic">Idea for a Philosophy of Nature</hi>
                            (trans. Errol E. Harris and Peter Heath) Cambridge: Cambridge
                            University Press, 1995, 9-–42.</note> his organic/aorgic
                distinction implies something more than a divergence between a purely natural and a
                purely non-natural organism or structure. </p>
            
            <p> In fact, Hölderlin’s organic represents a tendency — in works of art as much as in
                “nature” — towards a more or less stable but regulated order. The aorgic, by
                contrast, marks a tendency toward dissolution and disorganization; the coming undone
                of a particular temporary equilibrium. Hölderlin first introduces these terms in
                “Ground for Empedocles” when he is attempting to describe the specificity of the
                “world” the titular character of his play — Empedocles — inhabits, claiming that, as
                with the particular relationship between art and nature that characterizes the
                Greeks, Empedocles’s world is defined by a precise dynamic between “organic” and
                “aorgic” principles: “The more organic, artistic man is the blossom of nature, the
                more aorgic nature, when it is sensed purely, by the purely organized, purely and
                uniquely formed man, affords him the feeling of perfection” (PW 53; 2:116–17).
                The dynamic between these two tendencies characterizes Empedocles’s world but also
                signals the overcoming of that world in their mutual antagonism—Hölderlin calls it
                the “highest hostility” (<hi rend="italic">der höchsten Feindseligkeit</hi>), which
                is also their “highest reconciliation” (<hi rend="italic">die höchste
                    Versöhnung</hi>) (PW 54; 2:118) — of their relation. He conceives of his own
                play, in a sense, as nothing but the unfolding of this tension, exemplified by the
                death of Empedocles. </p>
            
            <p> As with other oppositions in Hölderlin, however, the organic/aorgic opposition that
                defines Empedocles’s world exists only to produce a form of “becoming in
                dissolution” (<hi rend="italic">Weden im Vergehen</hi>),<note place="foot" resp="author">  This is also the title of an important essay by
                            Hölderlin, “Becoming in Dissolution” (PW 96-–100;
                        1:900-–905).</note> a form of self-overcoming where each side of
                the opposition transcends into its opposite. To avoid being abstract, in order for
                the opposition to become real, or “known” according to Hölderlin,
                
                <quote>it must present itself by separating itself in the excess of inwardness where the
                opposed principles interchange so that the organic, which surrendered itself too
                much to nature, and which forgot its essence, transcends into the extreme of
                autonomous activity, whereas nature, at least in its effects on reflective man,
                transcends into the extreme of the aorgic, the incomprehensible, the non-sensuous,
                the unformed, the unlimited. (PW 53; 2:117)</quote>
                
                In other words, what initially appeared on one side—defined organization and the
                regulated order of the world known as the organic — precisely in its desire for
                organization, “interchanges” with the aorgic (Hölderlin is careful not to use terms
                such as “sublation” that might treat this exchange as a dialectic) and thereby
                undoes itself and the opposition that defines it at the same time. There is no
                reconciliation between the organic and the aorgic, only a “uniting moment that
                dissolves more and more, like a phantasm” and which “reacts against the organic in
                aorgic manner, distances itself from it” (PW 43; 2:118). This moment
                fundamentally characterizes Empedocles’s belonging to his world which is in the
                process of dissolution. As Hölderlin insists, as a character, Empedocles embodies
                the contretemps between the organic and the aorgic and so “is a son of his heaven
                and his time, of his fatherland, a son of tremendous oppositions of nature and art
                in which the world appeared before his eyes” (PW 54; 2:118–19). As a result, he
                becomes a “victim of his time” (<hi rend="italic">ein Opfer seiner Zeit</hi>) (PW
                57; 2:121). Unable to reconcile the opposition between nature and art that
                governs the totality of the world to which he belongs, he becomes a necessary
                “sacrifice” that reveals, in his death, the death of his world: “[the destiny of his
                epoch] demanded a sacrifice where man in his entirety becomes real and visible as
                that wherein the destiny of his epoch seems to dissolve, where the extremes seem to
                unite truly and visibly in one but therefore are united too closely” (PW 56;
                2:121).</p>
            
            <p> The oscillation between the organic and the aorgic functions both as that which
                defines the plot of <hi rend="italic">The Death of Empedocles</hi> and as that
                which forms Empedocles as a character by making him its archetype or figure. This
                oscillation also defines Empedocles’s “destiny.” But this form of destiny must be
                read in a thoroughly modern sense since it is not predicated on a particular
                cosmology—as it might be said to be in Sophocles, for example, in the relation
                between gods and mortals. Rather, Hölderlin imitates Greek tragedy in order to
                witness its self-overcoming, to pass through the foreign (the Greeks) and the
                collapse of “their” world, to the dissolution of our own. Perhaps this is why, once
                Hölderlin finally abandoned his play after three failed attempts to write it, the
                ending of the third and final attempt breaks off fragmentarily with the chorus
                proclaiming a “new world” that is simultaneously contrasted with the Earth:
               
               New World
            <lg type="stanza"> 
             <l>and it looms, a brazen vault</l>
            <l> the sky above us, curse lames</l>
            <l> the limbs of humankind, and the nourishing, gladdening</l>
            <l> gifts of the earth are like chaff, she</l>
            <l> mocks us with her presents, our mother</l>
            <l> and all is semblance—<note place="foot" resp="author"> Friedrich Hölderlin, <hi rend="italic">The Death of
                                Empedocles</hi> (trans. David Farell Krell) Albany, State University
                            of New York Press, 2008, 188. All citations to this work will henceforth
                            be cited in text as (DE) followed by English pagination, then German
                            volume and pagination.</note></l></lg>
                
                Neue Welt
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l> und es hängt, ein ehern Gewölbe</l>
            <l> der Himmel über uns, es lähmt Fluch</l>
            <l> die Glieder den Menschen, und die stärkenden, die</l>
            <l> erfreuenden</l>
            <l> Gaben der Erde sind wie Spreu, es</l>
            <l> spottet unser, mit ihren Geschenken, die Mutter</l>
            <l> und alles ist Schein— (DE 188; 2:152)</l></lg>
                    
            At the end of the play, in the concluding non-reconciliation between organic and
                aorgic that defines Empedocles’s “sacrifice,” we are left only with a heaven that
                has become an empty “brazen vault” and a world that has become nothing but
                “semblance” (<hi rend="italic">Schein</hi>). Far from a sacrifice that reconciles
                mortals with gods, Empedocles’s death merely gestures toward a newly reconfigured
                Earth, whose gifts “mock” those who remain, along with a world that has
                fundamentally been dissolved. In fact, Hölderlin’s notes for the continuation of the
                third version of the play describe Empedocles as “one in and through whom a world
                dissolves and in the same instant renews itself” (<hi rend="italic">in dem und durch den eine Welt
                sich zugleich auflöse und erneue </hi>) (DE 194; 2:154). In other words, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Death of Empedocles</hi> ends at the moment of the dissolution
                of a given world (and its concomitant configuration of the Earth), without
                necessarily gesturing at what follows out of it. This is perhaps why “Ground for
                Empedocles” makes of the play’s final sacrifice a figure not of the “reconciliation”
                between opposing forces but of a fundamental separation — a separation figured
                by Empedocles himself: “He is destiny itself, only with the exception that the
                contending forces inside him are tied to a consciousness, to a point of separation
                (Scheidpunkt) which keeps them facing one another in a clear and controlled manner”
                (PW 61; 2:127).</p></div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>Earth and the
                    “Original Separation”</head>
            
            <p> By the time Hölderlin had abandoned his own attempts to write a tragedy, and had
                begun the task of attempting to “translate” Sophocles’s <hi rend="italic">Oedipus
                    Rex</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Antigone</hi>, writing his enigmatic prose
                “notes” to both plays, that “separation” had a more distinctive
                significance. It is removed, first of all, from the context of individual
                “consciousness” and transformed into a question not of the “world-forming”
                capacities of poetry but of its encounter with a reality for which it has no
                coordinates, no presentational or performative capacities. This pushes the “point of
                separation” (<hi rend="italic">Scheidpunkt</hi>) attested to in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Death of Empedocles</hi> toward an entirely different conception of the
                relation between world and Earth, this time one that is no longer structured by its
                association with the divine. The “real separation” (wirkliche Trennung) (PW 86;
                1:893) that emerges as a result is still due to the irreconcilable dynamic of the
                oscillation between order and dissolution, the organic and the aorgic. Yet, when
                Hölderlin presents this oscillation again in his description of the “alternation of
                tones” in “On the Difference of Poetic Modes,” a different conception of the Earth
                begins to emerge at the juncture of the “separation” or “caesura” that Hölderlin
                makes central to his reading of Sophocles. It becomes clear that his thinking about
                classic tragedy is intertwined with his own articulation of the purpose and
                structure of poetry more generally, insofar as it repeats the hyperbolic logic of
                inversion found in the organic/ aorgic dynamic. This time, however, the overall
                problematic concerns not just the conditions for a properly modern tragedy but the
                incongruities at work in poetry itself, specifically the way tone and expression are
                repeatedly differentiated and placed into tension. The basic organic/ aorgic
                distinction is, in a sense, built in to the opposition between tone and expression
                as well. An epic poem, for example, is initially characterized by a “naïve”
                expression, whereas its underlying tone is aorgic/heroic:
                
            <quote> The epic, in its outer appearance <hi rend="italic">naïve poem</hi>, in its <hi
                    rend="italic">basic tone</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Grundton</hi>) the <hi
                    rend="italic">more pathetic</hi>, heroic, aorgic one; hence it strives in its
                art-character not for energy, movement and life, but for precision, calmness and
                pictorial quality. The opposition between its basic tone and its art-character,
                between its proper and its improper, metaphorical tone is resolved in the idealistic
                where it neither loses so much life as in its narrowly delimiting art-character nor
                as much moderation as in the immediate expression of its basic tone. (PW 83–84;
                1:890).</quote>
                
            For Hölderlin, then, every poem progresses through a series of oppositions between
                tone and expression, by which it strives to define its “unity.” Again, the
                hyperbolic logic Hölderlin articulates in “Ground for Empedocles” is at work, except
                that it is not so clear that a “resolution” of that tension is possible, as it
                appears to be in the <hi rend="italic">death</hi> of Empedocles. In fact, this
                striving after some kind of unity between tone and expression leads only to what
                Hölderlin calls a “real separation” (<hi rend="italic">wiklichen Trennung</hi>): the
                poem’s turning away from any attempt to ultimately reconcile its internal
                oppositions. </p>
            
            <p> It is precisely in this “real separation” that a second, more enigmatic, conception
                of the Earth materializes. “On the Difference of Poetic Modes” at first connects the
                “real separation” within the poem with a turning away of the gods: 
                
            <quote>And here, in the excess of spirit within unity, in its striving for materiality, in
                the striving of the divisible, more infinite aorgic which must contain all that is
                more organic . . . in this striving for separation of the divisible infinite, which
                in the state of highest unity of everything organic imparts itself to all parts
                contained by this unity, in this necessary arbitrariness of Zeus there actually lies
                the ideal beginning of the real separation. (PW 85-86; 1:892-93) </quote>
                
            As in the <hi rend="italic">Death of Empedocles</hi>, the final “reconciliation” of
                the organic with the aorgic gives way to something irreducible to either. By calling
                this the “arbitrariness of Zeus,” Hölderlin is already invoking his difficult and
                enigmatic reading of Sophocles, in particular <hi rend="italic">Oedipus Rex</hi>,
                which focuses on the way that the play stages the “caesura” or turning away from the
                gods (i.e. a particular conception of the divine) and the concomitant notion of
                tragic fate that constitutes that “world.” In the context of his meditation on
                poetry, what matters is how the “real separation” manifests itself in the poem as
                the internal tension of the opposed tendencies toward form and dissolution, until
                that very tension culminates in a return to the “real” or as Hölderlin will later
                assert, the “original” separation between the organic and the aorgic. The “new
                unity” that the internal oppositions engender in poetry is merely the “ideal”
                version of the “real separation.” Yet it prefigures what Hölderlin calls the
                “striving of the divisible,” by which he means that the initially “ideal” separation
                between organic and aorgic continues to develop in the poem “until the primordially
                separating has arrived at its total expression” (<hi rend="italic">bis das ursprünglich Trennende zu
                seiner völligen Äußerung gekommen ist </hi>) (PW 88; 1:896).</p>
            
            <p> That “total expression” of the “primordially separating” Hölderlin goes on to name,
                simply, “the Earth.” Hölderlin’s “Notes to Antigone” elaborates the emergence of
                this motif by framing the “real separation” in terms of a “reversal” that occurs
                when Kreon and Antigone both simultaneously appeal to Zeus as a principle of divine
                order lying beyond the world of the living. Beginning with a meditation on the
                “calculable law” of “Antigone,” which once again entails the “successive modes
                through which representation, sensation and reason develop according to poetic
                logic” (PW 109; 2:452), Hölderlin focuses on the moment in the play that
                “interrupts” this logic and introduces something irreducible to the succession of
                representations. This interruption happens at the moment both characters appeal to
                the same authority to justify their actions, which effectively makes it the crux of
                the play for Hölderlin. The appeals by Kreon and Antigone do not involve the same
                principle, however. In each case, Zeus represents something different to each of
                them, even if structurally the appeal takes the same form insofar as the same
                “sacred name” (Zeus) is used to designate a “highest,” an ultimate authority or <hi
                    rend="italic">arche</hi>. For Kreon, Zeus represents the traditional form of
                divine authority. In the case of Antigone, however, Zeus’s divine status is
                immediately inverted into its opposite and given an earthward turn. Zeus is
                presented as the “father of time or: father of earth, for it is his character,
                opposing the eternal tendency, to reverse the striving from this world to the other
                into a striving from another world to this one” (<hi rend="italic">“Vater der Zeit oder: Vater der
                Erde, weil sein Charakter ist, der ewigen Tendenz entgegen, das Streben aus dieser
                Welt in die andre zu kehren zu einem Streben au seiner andern Welt in diese</hi>) (PW
                112; 2:454). In other words, Antigone’s appeal is initially understood in
                classical terms as a reversal of the striving for transcendence and for a stable
                organic law (in Hölderlin’s sense) to a reversal that grounds that law in a
                strictly temporal order, the “golden stream of becoming” (<hi rend="italic">das goldenströmende
                Werden</hi>) to cite Hölderlin’s somewhat odd translation of Sophocles
                (PW 112; 2:454). Zeus, as with the fatal discordance between the organic and the
                aorgic found in “On the Difference of Poetic Modes,” constitutes here another
                example of the inversion of extremes at work in Hölderlin generally: the more divine he is,
                the more terrestrial, and this inversion organizes both the structure of the play
                and its denouement: 
                
                <quote>“Once, that which characterizes the Antitheos, where someone, in the sense of god,
                acts as if against god and recognizes the spirit of the highest as lawless. Then the
                pious fear of destiny, thus the praise of god as something preordained. This is the
                spirit of the two impartially contrasted opposites in the chorus. Antigone acting
                more in the first sense. Kreon in the second” (PW 112; 2:455). </quote>
                
                Whereas Kreon relates to Zeus as the representative of the divine and of tragic
                destiny, Antigone’s appeal to Zeus as an “Antitheos” is in opposition to his
                divinity, emphasizing instead his “lawlessness.” This presents a stark
                contrast between Kreon, for whom Zeus is the organizing principle of the world, and
                Antigone, for whom Zeus represents an aorgic disorder, a divine that has
                fundamentally absconded and which, as a result, “reverses” the desire for a
                transcendent order, turning a striving for the beyond into a return to the “Earth.”
                This “Earth,” in the context of this tragic agon of the play, emerges in opposition
                to the divine as the return to a world deprived of its center, deprived of the
                “heavenly” opposition that defines it. One could say that Hölderlin’s reading of
                Sophocles aligns itself here with Jean-Pierre Vernant and Pierre Vidal-Naquet’s
                suggestion that “the tragic universe lies between two worlds,” a past age of myth
                that was still present and the values of the new political order that emerge in and
                through the collapse of the world of myth (7). “The Earth” would thus appear to be a
                name for a political order no longer founded on theological structures. </p>
            
            <p> However, in a further development of the motif of the Earth, Hölderlin makes clear
                that this reversal is not “ours”; it is not <hi rend="italic">we</hi> who are in the
                midst of this radical reversal that undoes an entire configuration of the world. The
                reversal from the divine to the Earth belongs essentially to the Greeks — it is what
                brings about the tragic end of <hi rend="italic">their</hi> world. For us, by
                contrast, we “Hesperians” or moderns for whom a “lack of destiny” is our essential
                attribute, the earthward turn must be understood differently; according to
                Hölderlin, our “Zeus” is anything but divine, and anything but a higher principle of
                order or justice: 
                
            <quote>For us, existing under the more real Zeus who not only stays between this earth and
                the ferocious world of the dead, but who also forces the eternally anti-human course
                of nature on its way to another world <hi rend="italic">more decidedly down onto
                    earth</hi>, and since this greatly changes the essential and patriotic
                representations, and since our poetry must be patriotic so that its themes are
                selected according to our world-view and their representations, for us, then, the
                Greek representations change insofar as it is their chief tendency to comprehend
                themselves. (PW 113; 2:456) </quote>
                
            Ripped from the opposition between the terrestrial and the heavenly, “our Zeus”
                abandons any reference to transcendence, to “another world”—even one that has been
                withdrawn. </p>
            
            <p> This abandonment has a concomitant effect: the “Earth” to which it returns has become
                decidedly alien since it can no longer be defined in opposition to the divine. Our
                Zeus is a “god” in name only, who “forces the eternally anti-human course of nature
                on its way to another world <hi rend="italic">more decidedly down to Earth</hi>.”
                Here something other than the ever-present oscillating opposition between the
                organic and the aorgic comes into view. Having passed through the “foreign” that is
                ancient Greek tragedy, we arrive at something even more foreign: an Earthward turn
                that cannot be reduced either to the return to a mundane world separated from the
                divine nor to a conception of “nature” still dependent on that opposition. As
                Hölderlin makes clear, “our” Zeus forces nature toward a world even more “Earthly”
                than this other Earth whose significance still derives from the absence of the gods,
                and thus remains a withdrawal internal to that world. The “world” toward which our
                Zeus compels nature is a world no longer governed either by any relation to the
                divine or by the culture/nature division. While the translator, Thomas Pfau, uses
                the term “anti-human” here for <hi rend="italic">menschenfeindlichen</hi>, this word
                suggests something that is not just “anti-human” but also “inhuman,” a landscape
                without Man.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Jacques Derrida, in the “Ends of Man” describes this problematic as a
                            “change of terrain.” See Jacques Derrida, “The Ends of Man” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Margins of Philosophy</hi> (trans Alan Bass) Chicago:
                            University of Chicago Press, 1982, 135.</note> Whatever this
                “world” might be (if it is even still a world), its terrestrial status is certainly
                not yet a “dwelling,” since the natural world of the Greeks has been fundamentally
                overturned. </p>
            
            <p> Hölderlin’s use of the term “patriotic” (<hi rend="italic">vaterländisch</hi>) to
                characterize the representations that follow from this transformation only heightens
                the sense of a complete disorientation brought about by his second reference to the
                Earth, since the <hi rend="italic">patria</hi>, the sense of home, belonging, or
                propriety suggested both by the word “patriotic” and the phrase “the more real Zeus”
                is left fundamentally without an object. Hölderlin simply insists that the second
                earthward turn of this Zeus necessitates a radical change in “the essential and
                patriotic representations” and that “our poetry must be patriotic so that its themes
                are selected according to our world-view and their representations,”
                without detailing how this actually takes place (PW 113; 2:456). His insistence on
                the possessive “our” serves only to reinforce the fact that “Zeus” and “our
                world-view” (<hi rend="italic">unserer Weltansicht</hi>) are themselves taken hold
                of, appropriated, by this other return to an Earth that leaves us without our
                bearings, without any sense of a “world” or cosmology through which to make sense of
                it. Hölderlin’s term “patriotic,” (<hi rend="italic">vaterlandische</hi>) then, does
                not refer to a “fatherland” or “native land” in the traditional sense of a
                geographic or spiritual space in which some collective sense of belonging, an “our”
                or “we,” might materialize. Rather, it refers to what remains after the “death” of
                nature and the extinction of the “world” specific to the Greeks — that is, it is
                what characterizes “we Hesperians” only on the condition that the “we” is not
                understood according to a shared belonging to a given world.</p>
            
            <p> Hölderlin, however, goes on to claim that the “patriotic representations” that follow
                out of the forcing of “the eternally anti-human course of nature on its way to
                another world <hi rend="italic">more
                    decidedly down to Earth</hi>”
                results in a further development that, in fact, fundamentally unsettles poetry’s
                ability to “represent” or express “our world." Whereas the “nature” of the Greeks undergoes
                a “death” insofar as it is separated from the divine and therefore nature’s
                animation by otherworldy forces, “our” nature is figured as a complete reversal of
                    <hi rend="italic">all</hi> forms of representation in what Hölderlin calls a
                “patriotic reversal” (<hi rend="italic">ein vaterlandische Umkehr</hi>):
                
            <quote>For patriotic reversal is the reversal of all modes and forms of representation.
                However, an absolute reversal of these, as indeed a complete reversal altogether
                without any point of rest is forbidden for man as a knowing being. And in patriotic
                reversal where the entire form of things changes, and where nature and necessity,
                which always remain, incline toward another form—be it that they transcend into
                chaos or into a new form—in such a change everything that is necessary favors the
                change. (PW 114-1–15; 2:457)</quote>
                
            This “patriotic reversal” does not entail another “representation” of the Earth, but
                the “reversal of all modes and forms of representation” tout court. What we witness,
                according to Hölderlin, is not just a “death” of nature but its fundamental
                transformation into either “chaos” (which the translator offers for <hi
                    rend="italic">Wildnis</hi> which implies not just formlessness but rather
                something not-yet formed)—or simply “another form” (<hi rend="italic">andern
                    Gestalt</hi>). What this other Earthward turn therefore invokes is not simply a
                nature already bereft of any relation to the divine or to Man but one that begins
                to escape the space of representation altogether, of any pre-given Gestalt. The fact
                that this <hi rend="italic">other</hi> nature, which “inclines toward another form”
                even as it threatens to undo every form and representation that attempts to
                configure it, is at once inhuman and a process (it is a <hi rend="italic"
                    >course</hi> of nature—a <hi rend="italic">Naturgang</hi>), a tendency rather
                than an object or totality of objects, is not immaterial. It suggests that what characterizes “eternally
                inhuman nature” for Hölderlin are processes that outstrip each other, where
                tendencies toward order (the organic) are immediately generative of a disorder (the
                aorgic) or an entropy that is hardly in any dialectical relation to the stable
                system it disrupts. To put this in more contemporary terms, one could say that
                Nature consists of an excess to the various systems — technological, agricultural,
                scientific, moral, political, and so on — that attempt to delimit it and that by doing
                so unwittingly generate the very “aorgic” disorder found within it. Hölderlin’s
                Earth is, put simply, without any exteriority, while simultaneously an excess of
                potentialities that no system, technical or living, artificial or organic, can
                contain.</p></div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>Hölderlinian
                    “Homelessness,” World and Earth</head>
            
            <p> Examining the extent to which Hölderlin’s conceptualization of the Earth shapes his
                poetics would require a longer discussion of the way his late hymns and river poems
                    (<hi rend="italic">Der Rhine</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Germania</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Der Ister</hi> in particular) take up the organic/aorgic divide
                and the “patriotic reversal” that his prose works describe. Hölderlin’s assertion
                that a “complete reversal altogether without any point of rest is forbidden for man
                as a knowing being” suggests that, despite its complete reversal of “all modes and
                forms of representation,” poetry does in fact bear witness to the “real separation”
                between Earth and world. The question, of course, is how. Heidegger’s seminars on
                Hölderlin’s hymns<note place="foot" resp="author"> Heidegger taught several seminars on Hölderlin,
                            each one focused on a reading of a river poem. See Martin Heidegger, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hölderlin’s Hymn “Germania” and
                                “The Rhine”</hi> (trans. William McNeill and Julia Ireland)
                            Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2014; Martin Heidegger, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hölderlin’s Hymn
                                “Remembrance”</hi> (trans. William McNeill and Julia Ireland)
                            Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2019; and Martin Heidegger, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hölderlin’s Hymn “The
                                Ister.”</hi> (trans. William McNeill and Julia Davis) Bloomington:
                            Indiana University Press, 1996.</note> tend to foreground
                claims that these poems are not only about poetic production but also historicity,
                the “becoming historical” of a people and the way in which the “fatherland” comes
                to be interpreted as “Being itself,” out of which the “fundamental orientation
                towards beings as a whole arises and attains its configuration.” (Hölderlin’s <hi rend="italic"
                    > Hymn “Germania” </hi>109).
                In other words, Heidegger repeatedly insists on the extent to which Hölderlin’s
                “patriotic reversal” entails a reconfiguration of world and Earth, between the
                “orientation towards beings as a whole” that defines the world and the Earth’s
                self-concealment. While it is certainly the case that Hölderlin’s late hymns
                articulate, as Heidegger insists, a form of “poetic dwelling,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> See
                            Heidegger, “Poetically Man Dwells” in <hi rend="italic">Poetry,
                                Language, Thought</hi> 215.</note> it is not clear that anything like
                    <hi rend="italic">Dasein</hi> or its “world-forming” capacities are involved.
                The river poems treat the earthward turn described in Hölderlin’s prose works by
                following his theory of the alternation of tones, identifying that alternation with
                the movement of the river itself. The fact that his poems repeat something like the
                “real separation” Hölderlin discusses in his prose works should problematize any
                claims that his poetry concerns itself primarily with the withdrawal of the divine.
                Put another way, whereas Heidegger identifies the rivers with the poet as a
                “demi-god” situated in the time between the absence of the old gods and the arrival
                of the new, Hölderlin’s poetics actually articulates instead a fundamental break
                between the poet and the river, marking each as subject to a completely different
                temporality. Whereas Hölderlin identifies his poetry initially with a backward
                glance toward a conception of the Earth in mourning for a world that no longer
                exists, the river’s silence and forward movement in fact denote a disjunction
                between that conception and its own itinerary, which constitutes a reversal of the
                “forms and representations” that make up that world. And yet, since a “complete
                reversal” of those “modes and forms of representation” is impossible, the poem
                nonetheless bears witness to this break in and through the language of that
                    world.</p>
            
            <p> While a full analysis of the relation between Hölderlin’s longer hymns and his
                conception of the Earth is not possible here, a quick perusal of one of his early
                odes — <hi rend="italic">Der Main</hi> — provides a sense of what is stake. Like his
                later hymns, <hi rend="italic">Der Main</hi> invokes a historical and geographical
                “journeying” on the Earth. It opens in what Hölderlin calls the “naïve” mood, where
                the speaker identifies his “song” with a longing for immediacy, in this case for an
                encounter with “other lands” that remain explicitly idealized: 
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l>True, on this living earth there are many lands</l>
            <l>I long to see, and over the hills at times</l>
            <l>My heart runs off, my wishes wander </l>
            <l>Seaward, and on to those shores which more than</l>
            <l>All others that I know have been glorified</l>
                    
            <l>Wohl manches Land der lebenden Erde möcht</l>
            <l>Ich sehn, und öfters über die Berg' entheilt</l>
            <l>Das Herz mir, und die Wünsche wandern</l>
            <l>Über das Meer, zu den Ufern, die mir</l>
            <l>Vor andern, so ich kenne, gepriesen sind; (“Der Main/The River Main” 1–5)<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            See<hi rend="italic"> Poems and Fragments</hi>,
                            137; Hölderlin,
                            <hi rend="italic">Sämtliche Werke und Briefe Volume </hi>1,
                            239–40. The poem will henceforth be cited in text as (M) followed by
                            line numbers.</note></l></lg>
                
           By the third stanza, this longing has singled out a specific locale — ancient Greece — as
                its focus:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l> O once I long to land there, on Sunium’s coast,</l>
            <l> Once ask my way to your columns, Olympion, </l>
                    
            <l>Ach! Einmal dort an Suniums Küste möcht</l>
            <l>Ich landen, deine Säulen, Olympion! (M 9-10)</l></lg>
                    
            Yet the poem thereby immediately shifts into the heroic tone once it recognizes the
                bygone status of this ancient world. Desiring to “land” at Sunium, which features
                several ruined temples including the temple of Zeus (the “Olympion”), the speaker
                wishes to witness its “columns” before it too is consigned to oblivion: 
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l>And soon, before the northern gale can</l>
            <l>Bury you too in the scattered rubble</l>
            <l>Of temples Athens raised, and their imaged gods</l>
            <l>For long now desolate you have you stood, O pride</l>
            <l>Of worlds that are no more!</l>
                    
            <l>Erfragen, dort, noch eh der Nordsturm</l>
            <l>Hin in den Schutt der Athenertempel</l>
            <l>Und ihrer Götterbilder auch dich begräbt;</l>
            <l>Denn lang schon einsam stehst du, o Stolz der Welt</l>
            <l>Die nicht mer ist!— (M 11–15)</l></lg>
                    
            As the poem goes on to intimate, this very destruction of the “world” represented by
                the Greek temple is the condition for the emergence of the Earth, an even more
                radical “stranger” (<hi rend="italic">Fremden</hi>) in relation to the poet than the
                Greeks. The encounter with the “unbounded” Earth in the rubble of the divine leads
                the speaker to declare his own “homelessness”:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l>To you, perhaps, you islands, yet one day shall</l>
            <l> A homeless singer come; for he’s driven on</l>
            <l>From stranger still to stranger, and the</l>
            <l>Earth, the unbounded, alas, must serve him</l>
            <l>In place of home and nation his whole life long</l>
                    
            <l>Zu euch vieleicht, ihr Inseln! geräth noch einst</l>
            <l>Ein heimathloser Sänger; denn wander muß</l>
            <l>Von Fremden er zu Fremden, und die</l>
            <l>Erde, die freie, sie muß ja leider!</l>
            <l>Statt Vaterlands ihm dienen, so lang er lebt (M 25–29).</l></lg>
                    
            The oscillation of tones, and the abrupt shift away from the poet’s focus on the gods
                as the object and source of his song, gradually destabilizes the ground beneath the
                speaker, disrupting any clear opposition between <hi rend="italic">Heim</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Fremde</hi>, home and the strange (or foreign). Faced with the
                destruction of the temple of Zeus and the collapse of the world to which it
                belonged, the speaker is instead “driven on” from stranger to stranger toward an
                Earth freed from its determination by that
                world, prior to its constitution in relation to another.</p>
            
            <p> This “unbounded Earth,” however is in no way another world or “homeland,” since, as
                the passage makes clear, it “serves” the speaker in place of home and nation.
                Instead, the ode ends by addressing itself to the river, but only once there is
                another tonal shift after the caesura in the eighth
                stanza separating the death of the homeless singer from the river:
                
                <lg type="stanza">
            <l>And when he dies—but never, delightful Main,</l>
            <l>Shall I forget you or your banks, the</l>
            <l>Variously blessed, on my farthest travels.</l>
            <l>Hospitably, though proud, you admitted me,</l>
            <l>And, smoothly flowing, brightened the stranger’s eye</l>
            <l>And, taught me gently gliding songs, and</l>
            <l>Taught me the strength that’s alive in silence.</l></lg>
                
                <lg type="stanza">     
            <l>Und wenn er stirbt—doch nimmer vergeßt ich dich,</l>
            <l>So fern ich wandre, schöner Main! und</l>
            <l>Deine Gestade, die vielbeglükten</l>
            <l>Gastfreundlich nahmst du Stolzer! bei dir mich auf</l>
            <l>Und heitertest das Auge dem Fremdlinge,</l>
            <l>Und still hingleitende Gesänge</l>
            <l>Lehrtest du mich und geräuschlos Leben. (M 31–36)</l></lg>
                    
            The river, as intermediary between the “boundless” Earth and the poet, is both the
                condition of possibility for his song (it teaches “gently gliding songs”) and that
                which remains unspoken, unpresentable, irreducible to the song it makes possible,
                since the river also teaches “the strength that’s alive in silence.” If the
                “unbounded” Earth has overturned or eluded every “form and representation,” the
                alternation of tones, the oscillation between the death of one nature, and the
                promise or birth of another testifies in Hölderlin to an “Earth” that figures
                something other than a region of beings or an objectivity and that remains wholly
                other to human representation, as alien as another planet. What remains, in
                Hölderlin, is a relation of non-equivalence, and a collectivity predicated not simply on
                intertwinement but on differentiations that allow for no common foundation or
                starting point. Hölderlin’s poetic ecology is, to use Frédéric Neyrat’s formulation,
                “an ecology of separation” that does not attempt to revive the old gods of nature,
                who in fact died some time ago. Instead, it encounters something far
                more strange and disorienting in and through what might be called its “geopoetics”:
                the bringing-to-language of an Earth that has twisted free from any concept of
                nature, from any “world” of Man or humans. Hölderlin’s Earth: a fully
                    deterritorialized<note place="foot" resp="author"> I borrow this term from Gilles Deleuze and Felix
                            Guattari. While it is found at work throughout their corpus, a
                            particularly focused description of it can be found in the introduction
                            to <hi rend="italic">A Thousand Plateaus</hi>; see Gilles Deleuze &amp;
                            Felix Guattari, “Introduction- The Rhizome” in <hi rend="italic">A
                                Thousand Plateaus</hi> (trans. Brian Massumi) Minneapolis:
                            University of Minnesota Press, 1987, 9-–10.</note> landscape
                without Man that is at the same time the very ground we walk on.</p></div>
            
            <div type="citation">
                <head>Works Cited</head>
           
            <bibl>Deleuze, Gilles, and Felix Guattari. <hi rend="italic">A Thousand Plateaus.</hi>Translated by Brian Massumi, U of Minnesota P, 1987.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Derrida, Jacques. <hi rend="italic">Margins of Philosophy.</hi> Translated by Alan Bass, U of Chicago P, 1982.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Descola, Phillipe. <hi rend="italic">Beyond Nature and Culture.</hi> Translated by Janet Lloyd, U of Chicago P, 2013.</bibl>
            
                <bibl>Foti, Veronique. <hi rend="italic">Epochal Discordance: Hölderlin's Philosophy of Tragedy</hi>. State U of New York P, 2006.</bibl>
                
                
            <bibl>Heidegger, Martin. <hi rend="italic">The Four Fundamental Concepts of Metaphysics.</hi> Translated by William McNeill and Nicholas Walker, Indiana UP, 1995.</bibl>
                
                <bibl>———. "Origin of the Work of Art" in <hi rend="italic">Basic Writings.</hi> Ed. David Farell Krell, Harper Collins Publishing, 1971.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Hölderlin’s Hymn “Germania” and “The Rhine.”</hi> Translated by William McNeill and Julia Ireland, Indiana UP, 2014.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Hölderlin’s Hymn “Remembrance.” </hi>Translated by William McNeill and Julia Ireland, Indiana UP, 2019.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">H</hi>ö<hi rend="italic">lderlin’s Hymn “The Ister.”</hi> Translated William McNeill and Julia Davis, Indiana UP, 1996.</bibl>
                
            
                
            <bibl>———. “Only a God Can Save Us.” <hi rend="italic">Heidegger: The Man and the Thinker,</hi> edited by Thomas Sheehan, Routledge, 2017.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Poetry, Language, Thought.</hi> Translated by Albert Hofstadter, Harper and Row, 1971.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Hölderlin, Friedrich. <hi rend="italic">The Death of Empedocles.</hi> Translated by David Farrell Krell, State U of New York P, 2008.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Essays and Letter on Theory.</hi> Translated Thomas Pfau, State U of New York P, 1988.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Poems and Fragments.</hi> Translated by Michael Hamburger, Anvil Press, 2005.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Sämtliche Werke und Briefe Volume 1–2</hi>. Carl Hanser Verlag, 1970.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Lacoue-Labarthe, Phillipe. <hi rend="italic">Typography.</hi> Translated by Christopher Fynsk, Stanford UP, 1998.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Latour, Bruno. <hi rend="italic">Politics of Nature.</hi> Translated by Catherine Porter, Harvard UP, 2004.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. “The Promise of Constructivism.” <hi rend="italic">Chasing Technoscience: Matrix for Materiality.</hi> Edited by Don Ihde and Evan Selinger, Indiana UP, 2003.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Mitchell, Andrew. <hi rend="italic">The Fourfold: Reading the Late Heidegger.</hi> Northwestern UP, 2015.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Morton, Timothy. <hi rend="italic">The Ecological Thought</hi>. Harvard UP, 2010.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Nancy, Jean-Luc. <hi rend="italic">After Fukushima.</hi> Translated by Charlotte Mandell, Fordham UP, 2015.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Neyrat, Frédéric. <hi rend="italic">La Part Inconstructible de la Terre.</hi> Paris: Seuil, 2016. </bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">The Unconstructible Earth.</hi> Translated by Drew S. Burk, Fordham UP, 2019.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Schelling, F. W. J. <hi rend="italic">Idea for a Philosophy of Nature.</hi> Translated by Errol E. Harris and Peter Heath, Cambridge UP, 1995.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Schmitt, Carl. <hi rend="italic">The Nomos of the Earth.</hi> Translated by G. L. Ulmen, Telos Press, 2006.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Vernant, Jean-Pierre, and Pierre Vidal-Naquet. <hi rend="italic">Myth and Tragedy in Ancient Greece, Vol 1.</hi> Translated by Janet Lloyd, Zone Books, 1990.</bibl>
           </div>     
        </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
