<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3191</idno><idno type="nines">rce4462</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3191. Robert Southey to John
                  May, 9 September 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3191.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Houghton Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (26). ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3191" type="letter"><head>3191. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John
                  May</ref>,<date when="1818-09-09"> 9 September 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 4 Tavistock Street/ Bedford Square/ London<lb/> Stamped:
                  KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Seal: [partial; obscured]<lb/> Endorsement: N. 201 1818/ (Robert
                  Southey/ Keswick 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> September/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> T/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> W<lb/>
                  MS: Houghton Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (26). ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished.
               </note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-09-09"> 9th Sept. 1818</date></dateline><salute> My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I inclose a draft on <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> for £50. My next years account with him will probably prove a good
               one, – for the edition of Wesley may be expected to go off speedily, &amp; perhaps in
               the course of the winter I may rouse myself to go on with the Tale of Paraguay as
               something upon which I may calculate for about two hundred pounds.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise
                     and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820). <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was
                  not finished and published until 1825.</note> During this season of the year I am
               always liable to interruptions, – indeed scarcely a day passes without them, &amp;
               this will continue till the end of October. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref> {is coming to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>} with
               his wife &amp; his sons &amp; his daughters,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Wilberforce’s wife Barbara, née Spooner (1777–1847). With their children:
                  William Wilberforce (1798–1879), later a barrister and MP for Hull 1837–1838; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceRobert">Robert Wilberforce</ref>, later a clergyman and writer;
                  Samuel Wilberforce (1805–1873; <title>DNB</title>), later Bishop of Winchester
                  1870–1873; Henry Wilberforce (1807–1873; <title>DNB</title>), later a journalist;
                  Barbara Wilberforce (1799–1821) and Elizabeth Wilberforce (1801–1832).</note>
               &amp; his sons friends &amp; his daughters friends, &amp; his man servants &amp; his
               maid servants, for he travels with a tribe about him like one of the old patriarchs
               except that he does not bring with him his oxen &amp; his cattle. The most
               interesting person whom we have as yet seen this summer was a certain <ref type="m" target="people.html#EverettEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Everett</ref>, Greek Professor of
               Harvard College in New England, who has been spending three years on the continent,
               &amp; is about to extend his travels to Athens &amp; Jerusalem, as soon as he has
                  <del>xxx</del> seen which also he considers as holy ground. Old England could not
               produce a mind of a better stamp. Our most amusing visitor was a Wiltshire Clergyman
               from the neighbourhood of Longleat, Skurray by name,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Skurray (1774–1848), Perpetual Curate of Horningsham,
                  Wiltshire 1806–1823 and Lullington, Somerset 1805–1823, Rector of Winterbourne
                  Abbas 1823–1848; author of <title>Bidcombe Hill, a Rural and Descriptive
                     Poem</title> (1808), <title>Sermons on Public Subjects and Occasions</title>
                  (1817) and <title>A Metrical Version of the Book of Psalms</title> (1827),
                  dedicated to Wordsworth. Skurray was from Beckington in Somerset.</note> a person
               of no great νους,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Mind’, i.e. a comment on his intellectual capacity.</note> but a most
               entertaining companion from the exuberance of his good nature &amp; good spirits,
               &amp; his dramatic talent in telling stories, which came to me with <del>xx</del>
               peculiar zest in these uttermost parts of the North for being seasoned with the true
               Somersetshire dialect &amp; accent. But in the pulpit he is the greatest performer I
               ever remember to have heard. The word performer may properly be used, for very much
               more depended upon the delivery than the matter of his discourse: such indeed was the
               effect of his voice &amp; manner, that it was impossible to lose a word which he said
               &amp; it would have been as difficult to withdraw <del>xxx xxx</del> ones attention
               from him as <del>to fix it upon others</del> it frequently is to <del>fix it
                  upon</del> keep it in attendance upon other preachers. </p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref>
               sent me an <del>very</del> excellent specimen of Oxford, such as Oxford is now.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Arnold (1795–1842;
                  <title>DNB</title>), educational reformer and headmaster of Rugby School,
                  1828–1842. He was a Fellow of Oriel College, Oxford, 1815–1819.</note> – Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> is in the
               town, &amp; spends with us all the time that he does not pass in his bed: he is as
               mad as ever Cowper<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Cowper
                  (1731–1800; <title>DNB</title>), the poet, laboured under the obsession that he
                  was doomed to eternal punishment.</note> was, &amp; in a way more strange but
               quite as miserable; his notion being that he is the Man of Sin the Son of
                  Perdition<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">2
                     <title>Thessalonians</title> 2: 3. Phrases often interpreted as referring to
                  the Antichrist.</note> &amp; what not,– that all the rest of mankind are gone to
               Heaven, nothing but spectres remaining, <del>xx</del> that he alone is left, without
               a heart, &amp; without the possibility of dying, &amp; that the Universe will
               presently fall to pieces about his ears. His delight is to talk about this to any
               person who will listen to him (which I will not) – but at other times, &amp; always
               in the presence of strangers, his conversation is as clear, as sensible &amp; as
               discriminating as it ever was. </p><p rend="indent1"> With all these interruptions I continue to do what I can, which tho
                  <del>xxx</del> sometimes it be very little in the day is always better than
               nothing. I am just now on <del>xx</del> a very interesting part of Brazilian history,
               – the first voyage <del>up &amp;</del> down &amp; up the Madeira.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey discusses the voyage down this river in
                  his <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), III,
                  349–359.</note> Luckily I found in one of the Portugueze Journals the title of the
               Corografia Brazilica,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Manoel Aires de
                  Casal (1754–1821), <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Relação Historico-Geografica do
                     Reino do Brazil</title> (1817), no. 3252 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                  Uncle</ref> procured it from Lisbon just in time, – for by a little
               management the facts which would naturally have been stated earlier, may be
               introduced in a subsequent chapter. I shall be glad when the Patriota<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                  (London, 1810–1819), III, pp. v–vi, Southey thanked John May for procuring the
                  third volume of the Brazilian journal, <title>O Patriota</title> (1813–1814), for
                  him, ‘when it was not to be obtained at Lisbon’. It was no. 3641 in the sale
                  catalogue of his library.</note> arrives, – perhaps a <del>Tupi</del> Dictionary
               of the Tupi (or Lingua Geral) might be had at the Rio. If you could get me one it
               would probably be useful in improving my history for a second edition, which some
               time or other will be required, tho very probably not in my life time.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume only of the <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810–1819) was revised and reprinted in 1822.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Your <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">god-daughter</ref> is shooting up fast, – in good health &amp;
            spirits. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Her mother</ref>
            is neither in one nor the other, – the cause of which I <del>rather</del> believe to be
            one which – after an interval of six years, – was not expected &amp; <del>under all
               circumstances for a</del> were I to speak from my present feelings certainly not to
            have been wished.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Cuthbert Southey
               was born on 24 February 1819.</note> But we know not what is best for ourselves –
              &amp; whether he gives or takes away blessed be the name of the Lord</p><p rend="indent1">
               God bless you my dear friend. Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> 
               &amp; your daughters<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Charlotte (b.
                  1804), Susanna Louisa (1805–1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent2">&amp; believe me </salute><salute rend="indent3"> yrs most affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>