<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3128</idno><idno type="nines">rce4399</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3128. Robert Southey to Thomas
                  Southey, 28 April 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3128.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3128" type="letter"><head>3128. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas
                  Southey</ref>, <date when="1818-04-28">28 April 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey/ Warcop/ near/ Brough<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> MS:
                  British Library, Add MS 30927. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear Tom</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The ham arrived last week, &amp; ought to be the better for having
               been six or seven weeks on the road. This irregularity of the carriers is a great
               grievance, &amp; I heartily wish it were possible for Government to undertake the
               carriage of goods as well as of letters.</p><p rend="indent1"> I hope also that summer is arrived, – as for Spring, that season has
               been abolished a long while, &amp; we know as little of it in this part of England as
               they do at Petersburg. Today {Monday} we have warm rain, &amp; gleams of sunshine,
               &amp; the Birds are telling us how they like the change. And now <del>xxxxxx</del>
               that the country is likely to afford some enjoyment you had better come, &amp; bring
               with you your Opus, that we may take some serious steps concerning it; – such as
               consulting <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> &amp;
               issuing a Prospectus.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Southey,
                     <title>A Chronological History of the West Indies</title> was published by
                  Longman, Rees, Orme, Brown, &amp; Green in 1827.</note> Here will be something for
               you in this Italian book about the birth place of Columbus.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Gianfrancesco Napione (1748–1830), <title>Delia Patria di
                     Cristoforo Colombo</title> (1808), no. 730 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library. Napione argued that Columbus was of Piedmontese upbringing. </note> But
               what I look to as containing matter which is not to be found elsewhere is John de
               Laets hist: of the West India Company,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Joannes de Laet (1581–1649), <title>Historie ofte Iaerlijck Verhael van de
                     Verrichtingen der Geoctroyeerde West-Indische Compagnie</title> (1644), no.
                  1671 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – if it be not gone to the
               Goodwin Sands, – for all that I can learn as yet of that cargo is that it was sent
               from Brussels to Ostend about ten weeks ago! – it is the largest &amp; most important
               purchase that I ever made, or probably ever shall make. This book of John de Laets
               must unquestionably contain <del>xxxxxxxx</del> accounts of the first transactions of
               the Dutch in the West Indies he is a well known author, – one of those who are
               universally known, – &amp; yet tho I was led to believe that he must have written
               such a book as this, I never could meet with any proof of it, till I laid hold of
               this copy upon Vanbeasts shelf<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770–1849), famous Brussels bookseller; Southey had
                  visited his shop on his continental tour in 1817 and bought over one hundred
                  volumes.</note>, so little are books in that unlucky language known beyond their
               own country. It is by his Latin work that the author is notorious.</p><p rend="indent1"> The article upon Malthus might well surprize you. I could not take
               any notice of <del>xx Journal</del> its insertion without resenting it as a personal
               affair, &amp; throwing up the review, – this would have been throwing up the main
               part of my income &amp; was therefore out {of} the question.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly Review</title>, 17 (July 1817), 369–403
                  (published 29 November 1817), contained a review of the 5th edition of Thomas
                  Robert Malthus (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Essay on the Principle of
                     Population</title> (1817) by John Bird Sumner (1780–1862; <title>DNB</title>)
                  that was far less critical than Southey was wont to be of Malthus’s theories.
               </note> So I let the matter rest, especially as I wished to avail myself of the
               Review for bringing some views of great possible &amp; practicable benefit before the
               public in the most advantageous manner. Moreover it would have been hard upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to make him suffer for
               what was wholly <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> fault, – &amp; in him the effect of an obliging temper
               toward some body else, &amp; an active forgetfulness (not intentional indecorum) of
               me. </p><p rend="indent1"> I am going on bravely with Brazil, – far far ahead of the press.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was correcting proofs of the third
                  volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> It will be a very
               curious volume. And every day I expect the first proof of Wesley.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise
                     and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref></p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1818-04-28"> Tuesday 28 April 1818</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>