<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3166</idno><idno type="nines">rce4437</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3166. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 July 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3166.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>.  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3166" type="letter"><head>3166. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1818-07-12">12 July 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb/> Endorsements: Tea/ Nash for Frames/
                  Westall’s View/ Freight of Books/ Hyde’s Bill; 12 July 1818; 12 July 1818<lb/> MS:
                  Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Send me some money when you conveniently can, &amp; when you see <ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> (as probably you will ere
               long) pay him £ 2.18–6, for a set of Clarendon,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon (1609–1674;
                     <title>DNB</title>). Southey is possibly referring to the recent edition of
                     <title>The History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England</title> (1816).
                  If so, he did not receive a copy.</note> a book which you will be surprized to
               hear I have never read – for it never happened to be within my reach.</p><p rend="indent1"> You mistake about <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>. I am not standing on my
               defence with him, but taking advantage of his having told three lies of me in public
               to expose his public conduct, &amp; chastise him with scorpions. It is unnecessary to
               send the Times if you should find it.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had sent Southey <title>The Times</title> of 3 July 1818, which
                  reported Brougham’s campaign for the parliamentary seat of Westmorland against the
                  candidates favoured by Wordsworth’s patron, the Earl of Lonsdale. In particular it
                  reported Brougham’s speech on 29 June when he attacked Wordsworth by name for
                  supporting the Lowther cause, referring to him as ‘a man who wrote prose, and
                  other compositions which he could not call prose, but which he wished were
                  poetry’. The <title>Courier</title> and <title>The Times</title> for 4 July
                  carried Brougham’s speech at the hustings at Appleby on 30 June. In this address
                  he attacked ‘The Wordsworths and the Southeys’ for spreading false rumours about
                  Brougham and insulting the freeholders of Westmorland. It was this speech that led
                  Southey to plan a public retort to Brougham. This was not completed, though, and
                  part of it was published (without naming Brougham) as an ‘Appendix’ to the second
                  edition of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (London, 1821), pp. 45–53.</note> – I
               saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calverts</ref>, &amp;
               it was word for word as in the Courier, except that the Courier omitted the <hi rend="ital">great applauses</hi>, which the Times had carefully inserted.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Times</title>, to Southey’s
                  chagrin, leaned towards the reformers’ side and so included details of the
                  applause Brougham received. The <title>Courier</title>, a government supported
                  paper, did not in its report of the same date.</note> I suppose you know that this
               paper is in the hands of a fellow who managed the Examiner while <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref> was in prison.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Barnes (1785–1841;
                  <title>DNB</title>) had become editor of <title>The Times</title> at the start of
                  1817 and held this office until his death. He had previously contributed articles
                  to Hunt’s papers, the <title>Examiner</title> and <title>The
                  Reflector</title>.</note> And I believe you know also (what is not to be generally
               known) that I refused the management of it in April last year, when Walter<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Walter II (1776–1847; <title>DNB</title>),
                  variously manager, editor and owner of <title>The Times</title> 1803–1847. See
                  Southey to Henry Crabb Robinson, 13 March 1817 (Letter 2939) for his refusal of
                  Walter’s proposal.</note> was very desirous that I should have undertaken it,
               &amp; would have made over part of the property to me, upon such terms as would in a
               few years have made my fortune. How greatly would his Majestys ministers have been
               obliged to me, if I had made the sacrifice! They should get this paper into their
               hands, it is much more injurious to them than any other, &amp; from what I have heard
               of the proprietor he has little principle of any kind. The way would be to purchase
               the property.</p><p rend="indent1"> You had better take your six weeks here than between Boulogne &amp;
               Paris. We are enjoying good weather, sun &amp; showers, a delightful out of doors
               temperature, &amp; a fire within, in the evening. </p><p rend="indent1"> The 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> sheet of Wesley is on my desk.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of <title>The Life of Wesley; and the
                     Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> When you have any
               curiosity to go thro the sheets ask <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Artaxerxes</ref> for them, &amp; send them to me afterwards. </p><p rend="indent1"> I think the Pellitory proves useful in allaying the toothache when
               that curse occurs, which it does but too often.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith May had been suffering from toothache and Bedford had
                  sent a palliative, tincture of pellitory.</note> In all other respects <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw</ref> is as
               I could wish to see her. But <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">her
                  mother</ref> is by no means well, – &amp; I am greatly in want of
               bracing. Come &amp; set me up again by a course of boating &amp; mountaineering. The
                  Beaumonts<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady Beaumont</ref>.</note> will
               be here next month, so will <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref>; – &amp; the Islanders<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">Susannah
                     Peachy</ref>.</note> in September. If there be not inducements {enough} in all
               this worshipful society, – think of the Caviare, &amp; I promise to support you with
               all my authority in your privilege of toasting cheese in the parlour, &amp; forming a
               tripod of the poker &amp; tongs after your own fashion, in defiance of your enemy
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Coleridge</ref>. </p><p rend="indent1"> Hyde<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Hyde (d. 1820) was
                  Southey’s London tailor.</note> may send me a black coat &amp; a pair of pepper
               &amp; salt pantaloons, in such fashion as he may think proper to force upon me, – or
               black <del>x</del> worsted if it be better to be in readiness for a public
                  mourning,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The public were expected to
                  dress in mourning clothes when prominent figures, especially members of the royal
                  family, died. This was particularly true of Southey, who held a Court appointment as
                  Poet Laureate. Public mourning was instituted for Queen Charlotte (1761–1818;
                     <title>DNB</title>) after she died on 17 November 1818, and George III
                  (1738–1820; King of Great Britain 1760–1820; <title>DNB</title>) after he died on
                  27 January 1820.</note> – that <del>it</del> is to say, if it is at all necessary
               that the seat of honour should be in mourning <del>xx xxxx xx the</del> on such
               occasions.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1818-07-12"> 12 July 1818.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>