<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3145</idno><idno type="nines">rce4416</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3145. Robert Southey to Henry J.
                  Monck Mason, 2 June 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3145.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS
                  File ‘S’, Folder 14136. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3145" type="letter"><head>3145. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MasonHJMonck">Henry J.
                  Monck Mason</ref>,<date when="1818-06-02"> 2 June 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Henry J Monck Mason
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 24 Kildare Street/ Dublin<lb/> Postmark: [partial] 6
                  JU 6/ 1818<lb/> Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb/>
                  Endorsement: Robert Southey/ 14 April 1818<lb/> MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS
                  File ‘S’, Folder 14136. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Unpublished. </note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1818-06-02"> 2 June. 1818</date></dateline><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> It will not be my fault if your brothers book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Monck Mason (1775–1859; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     History and Antiquities of the Collegiate and Cathedral Church of St Patrick,
                     near Dublin, from its Foundation in 1190 to the Year 1819</title>
                  (1819).</note> should not be treated with that respect which is always due to a
               work of laborious research. And I assure you it is by no act or concurrence of mine
               that any unnecessary severity ever finds its way into the Quarterly Review. The
               principle which I have more than once declared is that whatever author comes before
               the public with the result either of his observations as a traveller, or his
               researches in history, antiquities &amp;c, is so far as he <del>communicates</del>
               {adds} any new information to the existing stock of knowledge, a public benefactor,
               to be thanked for what he had done, to be encouraged &amp; advised (if it be needful)
               for what farther he may intend to do, but in no case to be treated with severity,
               unless there be any mischievous opinions uppermost in his mind. For this is the only
               fault which can either require or justify that tone of criticism at present,
               unhappily, &amp; to the disgrace &amp; injury of literature, so prevalent. If a book
               be merely good for nothing – <hi rend="ital">mole ruit suâ</hi>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘It falls of its own weight’.</note> – neglect,
               loss of time &amp; perhaps of money, are a penalty more than sufficient for the
               writer’s mis-estimate of his own powers. In the present case I have expressed myself
               strongly to this purpose in time certainly, &amp; I hope with effect, tho I am
               perfectly ignorant into whose hands your brothers work will be consigned. – It has
               more than once happened that papers in the Quarterly have been imputed to me by the
               offended parties, when I have expressed to the publisher, in private, &amp; in the
               strongest manner, my utter disapprobation of the tone &amp; temper of the criticism,
               &amp; perhaps of the opinion pronounced upon the work.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am exceedingly glad to hear of your success in your truly patriotic
                  undertaking,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Monck Mason was a key
                  figure in the Society for Promoting the Education of the Poor People in Ireland
                  (founded 1811), usually known as the Kildare Place Society. But this letter
                  probably refers to his new venture, of which he was Secretary: the Irish Society
                  for Promoting the Scriptural Education and Religious Instruction of the
                  Irish-Speaking Population, chiefly through the Medium of their own Language
                  (1818–1914). The new Society was usually known as the Irish Society.</note> &amp;
               not a little surprized that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Troy<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Thomas Troy (1739–1823; <title>DNB</title>), Catholic
                  Archbishop of Dublin 1786–1823. At this time the Catholic hierarchy were fairly
                  neutral towards the Kildare Place Society, though they were becoming increasingly
                  suspicious. In 1818 Archbishop Troy made public his disapproval of the practice of
                  reading the Bible without Church instruction in these schools. Monck Mason’s new
                  Irish Society claimed to be inter-denominational and employed Catholic teachers,
                  as few Protestants spoke Irish. But the Catholic hierarchy were opposed to its
                  efforts from the start, seeing them (correctly) as an attempt to convert Catholic
                  children to Protestantism.</note> should sanction such a publication with his
                  name,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">This passage may refer to the
                  Irish Society’s plans for Irish–language Bibles and teaching material.</note> –
               his English brethren keep most consistently aloof from all such cooperation. At the
               Revolution in 1688 Scotland was in a more barbarous state than Ireland is at this
               day, I say more barbarous, because you could not at that time have found any where in
               Scotland men who in mind &amp; manners were entirely upon a par with the gentlemen of
               England, as you find them now every where in Ireland. Education has been the great
               instrument of the change, – a good deal also was owing to the military roads &amp;
               the good use which was made of the military after the two rebellions.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Jacobite Rebellions of 1715 and
                  1745–1746.</note> Whenever your country shall be cured of those atrocities which
               might be got rid of in one generation by a <del>xxx</del> combination of
                  <del>xxx</del> civil &amp; military law adapted to such circumstances, it will
               speedily outstrip Scotland in prosperity. Its natural advantages are far greater,
               &amp; the Irish character, deplorably as it is sometimes perverted, is compounded of
               better &amp; finer elements.</p><p rend="indent1"> I shall be much gratified by seeing some of your cheap books. Pray
               express my thanks to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> O Reilly,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Edward O’Reilly (1765–1830), another Irish scholar. He
                  compiled an Irish–English Dictionary (1817) and was Assistant Secretary to the
                  Iberno–Celtic Society, founded January 1818. O’Reilly, who owned a valuable
                  collection of Celtic manuscripts, was at this time working with Henry Monck Mason
                  on cataloguing the contents of the Library of Trinity College, Dublin. The ‘cheap
                  books’ may refer to Monck Mason’s proposal for a series of cheap editions of
                  popular books for the Kildare Place Society’s schools, including Southey’s
                     <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813). This scheme does not appear to have been
                  carried through.</note> – to whom I shall find some opportunity of acknowledging
               my obligations in kind. If it be directed to the care of Thomas Blakeney Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">This was probably <ref type="m" target="people.html#BlakeneyRobert">Robert Blakeney</ref>, Secretary and
                  Treasurer to the Whitehaven Harbour Trustees, and well-known to Wordsworth.</note>
               – who holds some office, I believe, in the Customs at Whitehaven,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The local Cumberland port for vessels coming from
                  Ireland.</note> it will reach me safely.</p><p rend="indent1"> You were unfortunate last year in your weather, &amp; I was
               unfortunate in being absent during the whole of your visit to this country. We have
               now had the finest month of May that was ever remembered, &amp; are beginning to
               complain of sunshine &amp; drought.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               Southey</ref> &amp; <del>xxx</del> her sisters<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara
                     Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> join with me in compliments to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mason<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Monck Mason’s wife,
                  the Hon. Anne Langrishe (1788–1873), whom he had married in 1816.</note> &amp;
               your family</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> with sincere esteem – </salute><salute rend="indent3"> Yrs faithfully</salute><signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>