<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2811</idno><idno type="nines">rce4082</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2811. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 19 June
                  1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2811.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 155. ALS; 3p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2811" type="letter"><head>2811. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1816-06-19">19 June
                  1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> Postmark: 10o’Clock/ JU 22/ 1816 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 155. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
                  Unpublished.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> I am just at this time finishing your French version of the Byzantine historians, – half of which I read some years
                  ago,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Corpus Scriptorum Historiae Byzantinae</title>, 24 vols (Paris, 1648–1711). See
                  Southey to John Rickman, 21 December 1807, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 1404, for his
                  earlier reading of Byzantine historians. Southey later acquired an edition of 1828–1841, no. 740 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library.</note> – &amp; now I am going thro the other half for the sake of gleaning facts there connected with the age of chivalry,
               – <del>X</del> I have long thought that as in the Levant you must trace the history of Gothic – or Church Architecture, – so also in
               these Eastern parts of Christendom the transition might be traced from the Roman to the Romantic mode of war. The Byzantine Collection
               should consist of 36 vol; – according to De Bure.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Guillaume-François Debure (1731–1782),
                     <title>Bibliographie Instructive</title> (1765), no. 805 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. </note> &amp; he mentions
               some others connected with the series, – the most important of which, Geoffroy Ville Hardouin, I picked up at Coimbra.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Geoffroy de Villehardouin (c. 1160– c. 1212), <title>L’Histoire de la Conqueste de Constantinople par
                     les Barons Français Associez aux Venitients, l’An 1204</title> (1584), no. 1135 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.
                  Southey indicates he bought this book on his visit to Coimbra in March 1801.</note> – The immediate use to which I am applying these
               things <del>xx</del> is for the preface &amp; notes to the Morte Arthur, – <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> pays me very liberally for this, &amp; I expect to execute it in a manner that will do me some credit.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title>(1817).</note> The oddest discovery which I have yet made is that chamber pots were
               not known when the Romance of Merlin was written, a remarkable incident in the history of King Arthur, or rather of Queen Guenevere his
               wife, having occurred for want of that convenient utensil.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes
                     of Kyng Arthur</title>, 2 vols (London, 1817), II, p. 462, Southey told this story in a note: ‘A plot was laid by the relations
                  of the illegitimate Guenever to pass her off upon Arthur for her half sister, and thus revenge themselves upon King Leodagan, whom
                  they hated. It was known that the true Guenever before she went to bed must go into the garden, for a purpose which the romance
                  writer states in the plainest language, and which proves that one of the commonest and most indispensable chamber utensils was not
                  in use in King Arthur’s days, nor in his own. She was to be waylaid in the garden, carried off, put into a boat, and kept somewhere
                  in durance, while the false Guenever was to be conducted to the bridal bed in her place, by a treacherous governante.’ Southey
                  derived his text from <title>Le Compte de la Vie de Merlin et des ses Faiz, et Compte de ses Prophecies</title> (n.d.).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> We are in tolerable health, &amp; in spirits much as you would anticipate.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s son Herbert had died on 17 April 1816.</note> Mine which used always to be at the high water mark, – are settled to about
               the half-tide; – enough are left for every day use, – but I have none to spare. In this point more is gone from me than would have
               evaporated in the course of twenty years. We have made up our minds to remain where we are; when other considerations made the
               determination doubtful, the pain which must needs be felt at leaving the place where the best &amp; happiest years of our life have
               been spent, was a consideration sufficient to turn the scale. So as I have yet a fourteen years lease, it is more than probable that I
               shall take up my last quarters in <del>xxxxxx</del> yonder church yard.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">St Kentigern’s Church at
                  Crosthwaite, where Southey is indeed buried.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Our fellow traveller <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> is on the way to visit us; – this I am
               glad of for in the office of showing him the country, I shall be taken out of doors myself, &amp; shall get <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> out also. He has sent me six bottles of Shiraz Wine,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Wine (mainly white) grown near Shiraz in Persia. It was imported into India by English merchants and, as Nash had
                  been based in Bombay 1801–1810, he would have had easy access to shipments.</note> – knowing that I was curious to taste it.</p><p rend="indent1"> I suppose <ref type="m" target="people.html#WalesCharlottePrincess">the Princess’s</ref> illness has delayed my
                  Poem<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Princess Charlotte, only child of the Prince Regent. She had married Prince Leopold of
                  Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld (1790–1865; King of the Belgians 1831–1865) on 2 May 1816. Southey had presented the couple with an
                  epithalamion, <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816) and was awaiting its publication. The newspapers at
                  this time (e.g. <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 7 June 1816) reported that the Princess was not carrying out public engagements
                  because of ‘a very bad cold, accompanied with some fever’. As there was a measles epidemic in London there was some concern over the
                  Princess’s health, her physicians were called and she was bled. But the publication of the poem was probably delayed because Longman
                  did not want it to interfere with sales of <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> – this is of little
               consequence, tho’ it will be a <hi rend="ital">week</hi> after the fair, – or rather a month after the honey moon.</p><p rend="indent1"> The next Quarterly has a paper of mine on the war in La Vendee, &amp; will have one upon the state of the Poor, which I
               am now finishing.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816),
                  1–69, a series of memoirs of the French Revolutionary wars, including that in La Vendée, 1793–1796; ‘On the Poor’ also appeared in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187–235.</note> – I am sorry for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa’s</ref> loss – but happening as it did, it is not likely to become a habit.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Louisa Southey had probably suffered a miscarriage.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Your copy of Brazil is going off to-night.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of the
                     <title>History Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> has printed briskly. Your huge collection of Treaties<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Portuguese manuscripts and official documents collected by Hill and used by Southey in his
                  researches.</note> has proved of use. I detect Charlevoix by its means in some falsehoods about Nova Colonia<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810–1819), II, pp. 579–580 n., Southey dealt with
                  conflicting accounts of the dispute between Portugal and Spain over Nova Colonia (in modern Uruguay) in 1680–1681, including that by
                  Pierre Francois-Xavier de Charlevoix (1682–1761), <title>Histoire de Paraguay</title>, 3 vols (Paris, 1756), II, p. 203 (no. 645 in
                  the sale catalogue of Southey’s library). Southey declared all the accounts, including Charlevoix’s, to ‘bear the grossest and most
                  ridiculous marks of partiality. Several manuscripts respecting Nova Colonia are in my possession, (for reams have been written upon
                  the question,) and from them I have collected a more credible and consistent account.’</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I shall look daily for news of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>, – love to her &amp; the
               boys –</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1816-06-19">19 June. 1816</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>