<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3210</idno><idno type="nines">rce4481</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3210. Robert Southey to John May, 16 November 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3210.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Houghton Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (27). ALS;
                  4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp.
                  318–321 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3210" type="letter"><head>3210. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1818-11-16">16 November 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 4 <del>Xx</del> Tavistock Street/ Bedford Square/
                  London<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: [partial] E/ 18 NO 18/ 18<lb/>
                  Endorsement: No 202 1818/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 16 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  1818/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                     30<hi rend="sup">th</hi><lb/> MS: Houghton Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (27). ALS;
                  4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp.
                  318–321 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-11-16"> 16 Nov 1818</date></dateline><salute> My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday as I was going to dine at the Island I took up my letters
               on the way &amp; found among them one from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> informing me
               that your son has been involved in the affair at Eton.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John May (1802–1879) had been expelled from Eton for his part
                  in an incident known as ‘Palk’s Rebellion’, that occurred on 3–4 November
                  1818.</note> The news was introduced by speaking of a heavy affliction that had
               fallen upon you, &amp; I can hardly express <del>xxxxx</del> how great a relief it
               was when I found that it was nothing worse, – nothing that affected life or limb, –
               nothing that touched you in the heart of your affections, – nothing but some
               temporary inconvenience, &amp; a vexation rather than a grief. It is no ill sign when
               a boy goes wrong in such cases from a quick sense of honour, &amp; a generous
               sympathy with his companions: – it shows that the <del>heart</del> {great principle}
               is right { – the main spring – } &amp; then we are sure that <del>xxxx</del> {every
               thing else} will come right in time. If I had learnt that John had got for himself
               the character of being what we used to call at Westminster<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s school, which he attended 1788–1792.</note><hi rend="ital">a great beast</hi>, that is one who delighted in tormenting all who
               were in his power, or that he had shown any of those dispositions which are sometimes
               so early &amp; so strongly shown that <del>they</del> it seems almost as if the
               miserable possessers were doomed to reprobation <del>xxxxxxx</del>, – then indeed I
               should have felt that you were visited with the most poignant &amp; most irremediable
               of all afflictions. But this affair will do the boy no hurt in his fortunes, &amp;
               may even prove beneficial to him by inducing a sense of error &amp; of the
               consequences of error which may possibly prevent more important aberrations. It is
               like a child’s burning his finger. </p><p rend="indent1"> I know something of rebellions, <del>Xxxx</del> &amp; generally
               suspect that there has been some fault in the master as well as in the boys, just as
               I know that a mutiny in a man of war affords a strong presumption of tyranny against
               the Captain. Without understanding the merits of this case, it is easy to perceive
               that the boys believed their privileges were invaded &amp; fancied that the Magna
               Charta of Eton was in danger.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Magna Carta
                  (1215) was perceived as a founding statement of the liberties of the subject and
                  the rule of law: the key issue in ‘Palk’s Rebellion’ seems to have been the
                  decision to bring forward curfew in the school’s boarding-houses from 6pm to
                  5pm.</note> (The <hi rend="ital">Habeus Corpus</hi> in schools is in favour of the
               Governors, – a writ issued against the subject &amp; affecting him <hi rend="ital">in
                  tail</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">An elaborate legal pun:
                  habeas corpus, the legal principle that prevented detention without trial,
                  literally means ‘you have the body’; and an estate ‘in tail’ is the inheritance
                  that legally belongs to the donee’s direct descendants. Southey uses these terms
                  to make a pun on flogging.</note>) John took the patriotic side, acting upon Whig
               principles. They are very good principles in their time &amp; place; &amp; youth is a
               good time &amp; school a good place for them. When he grows older he will see the
               necessity of subordination &amp; learn that Order should be a more sacred name than
               Liberty, – or rather that it is only by means of Order that Liberty can be secured.
               John I dare say already feels that he has done wrong, because he must see that he has
               grieved his excellent parents. But the sense of having done wrong may be use in
               softening his spirit, &amp; happy are they who purchase experience {early &amp;} at
               no dearer rate.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have a fellow feeling for your son, because I was myself expelled
               from Westminster. Not for a rebellion (tho in that too I had my share –)<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey took part in the rebellion of 1790 at
                  Westminster School.</note><del>by</del> but for an act of Authorship. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, &amp;
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">Strachey</ref> (who is now Chief Secretary at
               Madras) &amp; myself planned a periodical paper in emulation of the Microcosm.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Flagellant</title>, which ran for
                  nine issues 1 March–26 April 1792; its model was the <title>Microcosm</title>
                  (1786–1787), produced by Eton schoolboys, including George Canning.</note> It was
               not begun till the two former had left school, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &amp; I were the only persons actually engaged in it. I
               well remember my feelings when the first number appeared on Saturday, March 1. 1792.
               It was <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> writing but that
               circumstance did not prevent me from feeling that I was that day born into the world
               as an author, – &amp; if ever my head touched <del>xx</del> the stars while I walked
               upon the earth it was then. It seemed as if I had <del>xxx</del> overleapt a barrier
               which till then had kept me from the fields of immortality wherein my career was to
               be run. In all London there was not so vain, so happy, so elated a creature as I was
               that day. And in truth it was an important day in my life, far more so than I or than
               any one else could have anticipated, – for I was expelled for the fifth number. The
               subject of that number was <hi rend="ital">flogging</hi> &amp; Heaven knows I
                  <del>xxx</del> {thought} as little <del>xxxx</del> of giving offence <del>by it as
                  I xxxx if</del> by it as of causing an eclipse or an earthquake. I treated it in a
               strange whimsical ironical sort of manner, to prove that it was an unchristian
               practise because it had formed a part of the religious ceremonies of the Heathens,
               &amp; the Fathers had held that the Gods of the Heathens were our Devils, &amp; so I
               proved it to be an invention of the Devil &amp; therefore unfit to be practised {in
               schools}; &amp; tho <del>xxx</del> this was done with very little respect for the
               Devil, or the Father, or the Heathen Gods, or the Schoolmasters, yet I as little
               expected to offend one as the other.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s authorship in the fifth issue of <title>The Flagellant</title> (29
                  March 1792) of an essay which claimed flogging was an invention of the devil and
                  parodied the Athanasian creed, caused a scandal and led ultimately to his
                  expulsion from Westminster School.</note> I was full of Gibbon at the time &amp;
               had caught something of Voltaires manner.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737–1794; <title>DNB</title>), whose <title>History of the
                     Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776–1788) was critical of the
                  early history of Christianity; and François-Marie Arouet, ‘Voltaire’ (1694–1778),
                  a deist, renowned for his critique of the Catholic Church.</note> And for this I
               was privately expelled from Westminster &amp; for this I was refused admission at
               Christ Church where Randolph<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Randolph
                  (1749–1813; <title>DNB</title>), Canon of Christ Church, Oxford and Regius
                  Professor of Divinity 1783–1807, Bishop of Oxford 1799–1806, Bishop of Bangor
                  1806–1809, Bishop of London 1809–1813. He was a contemporary of Herbert Hill at
                  Christ Church, Oxford.</note> from the friendship which he then professed for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> could not else have decently
                  <del>xx</del> refused to provide for me by a studentship. And so I went to <ref type="m" target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref> instead, in a blessed hour; – for there I found a
               man of sterling virtue, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund Seward</ref>) who led me
               right, when it might have {been} easy to have led me wrong. I used to call him <hi rend="ital">Talus</hi><note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘iron man’
                  who dispenses justice with an iron flail in Edmund Spenser (1552–1599;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590–1596), Book
                  5.</note> for his unbending morals &amp; iron rectitude, – – his strength of body
               also justified the name. – His death in the year 1795 was the first severe affliction
               that I ever experienced, – &amp; sometimes even now I dream of him &amp; wake myself
               by weeping because even in my dreams I remember that he is dead. I loved him with
                  <del>all</del> my whole heart, <del>xx xxx xx</del> &amp; shall remember him with
               gratitude &amp; affection as <del>xxxxx</del> one who was my moral father to the last
               moment of my life &amp; to meet him again will at that moment be one of the Joys to
               which I shall look forward in eternity. And there you shall know him too! –</p><p rend="indent1"> My dear John May I have got into {a} strain which I neither intended
               nor foresaw – misfortunes, as the story says, are good for something. The stream of
               my life would certainly have taken a different direction if I had not been expelled,
               – &amp; I am satisfied that it could never {have} held a <del>xxxxxxx</del> {better}
               course. To your son the only difference will be that he will pass two years with a
               private tutor which would otherwise have been passed at <del>Eton</del> a public
               school. And he has already had enough of a public school, to derive from it, what
               after all is the most important acquisition to be learned there, – a knowledge of
               what it is, &amp; of the world, – that is to say of a great number of his
               contemporaries who will be auspicious in it from their rank fortune &amp; stations
               hereafter. Those years moreover which he would otherwise have spent at Eton are
               precisely those in which such a school is most dangerous. </p><p rend="indent1"> Had I not been dining out yesterday I should not have let a post pass
               without writing to you on such an occasion. <hi rend="ital">Vexatious</hi> however is
               the worst epithet that it deserves, &amp; you who have borne real &amp; great
               misfortunes with perfect equanimity will not long be disturbed by what has now
               happened. I was about to have written to you on other subjects, &amp; will not long
               delay doing so, but I will not mingle them with this. Remember me most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; to my young
               friends Mary &amp; Susan.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Charlotte
                  (b. 1804) and Susanna Louisa (1805–1885), May’s elder daughters.</note> I am not
               sure that I put the two names in their right order, or should appropriate them
               rightly if I saw the owners, – but if when their pictures are taken the likenesses be
               as vivid &amp; true to the life as the two countenances which are now in my minds
               eye, – you will be well pleased with the artist. </p><closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear friend</salute><salute rend="indent2"> believe me ever most truly &amp; affectionately yours </salute><signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>