<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3162</idno><idno type="nines">rce4433</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3162. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 10 July
                  1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3162.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 169. ALS; 4p..  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3162" type="letter"><head>3162. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1818-07-10">10 July
                  1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham <lb/> Postmark: 10 o’Clock/ 13 JY/
                  1818 NT<lb/> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 169. ALS; 4p.<title><lb/></title>Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1818-07-10"> 10 July. 1818</date></dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> A necessary regard for the ways &amp; means took me for about three weeks from my better labours, to which I set with
               fresh appetite as soon as the matter of business was done.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of <title>Memoirs,
                     Illustrative of the Life and Writings of John Evelyn</title> (1818) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 1–54,
                  had distracted him from the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> Among M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles papers are
               copious extracts from the correspondence of his predecessors as far back as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Worsley in 1721, &amp; also from
               that of our ministers at Madrid.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Walpole (1736–1810) was the British envoy to Portugal
                  1771–1800; Southey had been sent Walpole’s papers by John May, who hoped that Southey would write a memoir of Walpole. Henry Worsley
                  (1672–1740) was MP for Newport, Isle of Wight 1705–1715 and Ambassador to Portugal 1713–1722.</note> Here I have found a few
               valuable facts concerning Brazil, &amp; as you may suppose a great deal respecting Pombal<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebastião José de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Marquess of Pombal (1699–1782), Prime Minister of Portugal 1750–1777. </note> &amp; the
               mother Country. Part of my business in London will be to examine M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles own correspondence of which (very
               strangely) he has kept no copies. <del>Xxx xxx</del> {It is} in the Secretary of States Office<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The office of the Secretary of State for the Southern Department dealt with relations with Portugal in this period.</note> in
               Heaven knows how many volumes, – but such volumes are soon gone thro.</p><p rend="indent1"> While I was thus employed, the newspaper came with the speech of our friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> at Appleby,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Courier</title>
                  reported on 4 July 1818, that Brougham, campaigning for the parliamentary seat of Westmorland against the candidates favoured by
                  Wordsworth’s patron the Earl of Lonsdale, had, at the hustings at Appleby on 30 June 1818, attacked both Southey and Wordsworth.
               </note> which no doubt you have seen. It so happens that I have taken no more part in the Westmorland election than you have done, –
               &amp; had not written a single line about it nor spoken <del>out</del> of it out of my own family, – for the very sufficient reason
               that I never go beyond my own premises, except it be to take an hours walk with some or other of the children. This unprovoked
               insolence {&amp; his falsehood} therefore have made me just angry enough, – &amp; I shall trouble him with a <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">William Smithiad</ref><note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was dissuaded from
                  publishing his attack on Brougham, which he modelled on his pamphlet <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M. P.</title> (1817).
                  The sections that were completed were published (without naming Brougham) as a ‘Postscript’ to the second edition of <title>Carmen
                     Triumphale</title> (London, 1821), pp. 45–53.</note> it <del>which</del> is in good forwardness, &amp; will be pretty nearly
               finished by the time this reaches you. This will take me from home for two or three days, that I may learn a few facts concerning the
               Enemys proceedings from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth was actively (though anonymously) involved in the anti-Brougham election campaign and authored the pamphlet <title>Two
                     Addresses to the Freeholders of Westmorland</title> (1818).</note> The exercise &amp; the change of air will brace me a little –
               I live too much in the house for want of a motive for going out of it, &amp; for want of an outofdoor companion.</p><p rend="indent1"> The only strangers whom we have seen this season are a <ref type="m" target="people.html#EverettEdward">Greek Professor
                  from Cambridge in New England</ref>, – &amp; a <hi rend="ital">Latin</hi> Professor from Edinburgh.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Alexander Christison (1753–1820), Professor of Humanity at the University of Edinburgh 1806–1820.</note> The
               latter very much what you would guess him to be, – the former one of the most interesting men whom I have seen. he has been three years
               in France &amp; Germany, &amp; is now going to Rome, Athens &amp; Jerusalem. His name is <ref type="m" target="people.html#EverettEdward">Everett</ref>. From him I learnt that Humphries<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">David
                  Humphreys (1752–1818), United States Minister to Portugal 1791–1796, Minister to Spain 1796–1801. Humphreys died on 21 February 1818
                  in New Haven, Connecticut, after a wide-ranging career as soldier, politician, breeder of merino sheep and author. Southey had known
                  him in Lisbon in 1796.</note> is dead. – I had forgotten a third stranger – a very pleasant &amp; well informed Frenchman by name
                  Buchot,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given by Southey.</note> who introduced himself
               as the nephew of M. Ducis the poet.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-François Ducis (1733–1816), French poet and translator
                  of Shakespeare.</note> I know not whether we shall have any guests this year or not, – they will be welcome however if they come,
               for without some such <del>motive I shall</del> cause for locomotion I shall grow to my chair.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> is dressing up the Saints, &amp; I suppose they will very soon be out of
               his hands, &amp; on their way to Newcastle.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The massive, 53–volume collection of hagiographies
                  entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643–1794), which Southey had purchased in Brussels in 1817. The books became no. 207 in the
                  sale catalogue of his library.</note> The saving the duty upon this cargo has been a great thing, – it would have far exceeded the
               cost of the books. I am told that Holland is a fine country for a book-hunter, – &amp; this is an additional reason for making me wish
               to visit the Dutchmen.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A visit that Southey did not make until 1825.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I must now make up my dispatches, – which are somewhat voluminous this evening, – two Quarterly proofs (the Life of
                  Evelyn<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of <title>Memoirs, Illustrative of the Life and Writings of John
                     Evelyn</title> (1818) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 1–54.</note>) – &amp; one Brazilian.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The third volume of Southey’s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>. How is your rheumatism? If you are still
               tormented with it, – have we not some baths like those of the Caldas<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The Caldas da Rainha hot
                  springs in Portugal. Southey had bathed in their waters on 5 March 1801.</note> – ? I have great faith in stewing for this disorder,
               whether by <del>xxx</del> the hot bath or the steam bath. The experiment was made upon a servant at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>, at my suggestion, with great success. They boiled him &amp; he has been better
               ever since. But he was boiled frequently, &amp; in sea-water. And if <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> should complain much more of her rheumatism, I will boil her. And if should I have the complaint they
               shall boil me.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"><del>Xxxxxx xxx xx</del> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>