<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2750</idno><idno type="nines">rce4021</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2750. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 3 [April] 1816 </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2750.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 3. ALS;
                  4p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2750" type="letter"><head>2750. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>,<date when="1816-04-03"> 3 [April] 1816 </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Southey/ Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 6 AP 6/ 1816 <lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 3. ALS;
                  4p.<lb/> Unpublished.<lb/> Dating note: The letter is misdated ‘3 March’ by
                  Southey; but the content and postmark make it clear that the letter is from one
                  month later, during Herbert Southey’s final illness.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Harry</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> has been severely
               ill, &amp; tho there has been an amendment, there is still reason for alarm. The
               first affection was a slight fever accompanied with pain in the right side, – the
               pain not severe &amp; shifting. A pitch plaister seemed to relieve it, the fever
               abated, &amp; for a few days I thought him well. Then came on a sudden cough which
               for a fortnight I supposed to be the only disease – &amp; from then after it had
               lasted so long, I thought him materially better tho he complained of occasional pain
               in the chest &amp; on the back as if straight thro. One of his best days, the weather
               being too bleak to be out of doors, I thought to amuse &amp; exercise him by whipping
               a large top. In the evening he complained of great &amp; sudden pain in his breast
               when he attempted to lie down on the ground as he was used <del>xx xxxx</del> &amp;
               at night cried out with pain when he went to bed, – the pain evidently produced by
               the act of lying down, &amp; going up soon afterwards <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref> and I were inclined to think it
               was muscular proceeding from the too great exertion with the top. Symptoms however
               soon appeared of a bilious obstruction, a grain of calomel was given – observe that
               by this time he was very much weakened by the long continuance of indisposition. It
               was given at night &amp; having produced no effect by eleven the next <del>day</del>
               morning, a second grain was given with as little effect – two ingestions proved
               unavailing. Therefore at night <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref> gave two grains more combined with James powder.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The popular fever cure invented by Robert James (c.
                  1703-1776; DNB)</note> This produced towards morning a natural motion, a second
               bearing marks of medicine, – a third of the foulest nature <del>x</del> –
                  <del>xxx</del> looking like spinnage, – &amp; this was followed by tenesmus which
               an anodyne draught greatly relieved. That night he lay down without pain, – &amp; I
               then felt at rest, believing the cause had been removed. This was on Monday.
               Yesterday morning I found he had a still fouler stool in the night with small white
               specks in it, looking like a cream when it curdles in your tea. He had now a very
               great degree of fever, &amp; said that he was much worse, – it was the calomel which
               now showed itself in having affected his mouth a different purgative was given
                  <del>he grew</del> which did not operate till this morning, but he grew better
               towards evening – only he complained at times of the old pain in his chest, &amp;
               cried out when he lay down at night. This morning another bilious stool with the same
               specks – which <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref> &amp; I
               suppose to be brimstone, – an old purgative taken some fortnight ago. at least we can
               think of nothing else but upon attempting to lie down he complained – &amp; shed
               tears. There is some internal malady beyond all doubt: the fever continues &amp; is
               now freshened, – he was better in the morning very considerably, – fatigue &amp; the
               little food which he took at dinner (some fish) may easily explain this, – but how is
               the pain explicable? It is a dismal thing being so far from any good medical aid in a
               case of this kind. There is a liver affection I fear &amp; believe &amp; we cannot
               give calomel which would immediately salivate him.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is almost idle to write to you upon this subject – five days must
               elapse before your answer can arrive, – &amp; what can you tell me upon such a
               statement? There is no external soreness when he is touched; there have been no
               rigours &amp; sudden perspirations as if abscess were forming. But that something is
               very much deranged is but too certain.</p><p rend="indent1"> For many days I have been incapable of any employment, alternately
               hoping &amp; fearing – today had been hopeful, till the return of this sudden pain in
               lying down has <del>xx</del> made alarm again preponderate. And I write now rather
               that I may not have cause to reproach myself for not having written than from much
               expectation <del>xx</del> that you can throw any light upon a case so imperfectly
               represented.</p><p rend="indent1"> I cannot <hi rend="ital">ascertain</hi> that the pain is <hi rend="ital">decidedly</hi> toward the right side, but incline to think that it is.
               In the breast &amp; the back he complains sometimes one sometimes the other, &amp;
               generally lays his fingers in the middle of the sternum.</p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref>
               &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               Gonne</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has no
               recollection of having lost a veil at Champion Hill<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The home of the Gonne family.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1816-04-03">3 March.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                        misdating; the letter belongs to April 1816.</note> Wednesday.</date></p><p>I have received Haygarths drawing,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably
                     a reference to William Haygarth (1784–1825), writer who made a series of
                     sketches illustrating his travels in Greece, Italy and Switzerland. His
                        <title>Greece, a Poem</title> (1814) was no. 1176 in the sale catalogue of
                     Southey’s library. He was the son of the Bath physician, John Haygarth
                     (1740–1827; <title>DNB</title>). </note> &amp; will write to him inclosing the
                  letter he lent me, as soon as I can. His parcel lay long at <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref>.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>