<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce556</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.547</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington
                        Library, RS 9.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        122&#8211;127. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.547" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="547" type="letter">
        <head>547. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>,
                        <date when="1800-09-13">13 September 1800</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/
                            M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Rickman/ 33 Southampton
                        Buildings/ Holburn/ London/ Single<lb />Stamped:
                        LISBON<lb />Postmark: FOREIGN OFFICE/ SE/ 27/
                        1800<lb />Endorsement: Sept 13. 1800<lb />MS: Huntington
                        Library, RS 9<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter
                        (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        122&#8211;127. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1800-09-13">Saturday. Sept. 13. 1800.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Cintra"> Cintra</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The King George sails on Monday without
                        Thalaba.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        manuscript copy of the Islamic romance <title>Thalaba
                            the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> the
                        Captain<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward
                        Bayntun Yescombe (1765&#8211;1803), Captain of the Packet, <hi rend="ital">King George</hi>, which sailed between
                        Falmouth and Lisbon.</note> to whom I could have
                    entrusted it did not come this voyage, &amp; I know no
                    Passenger. The parcel therefore must remain for the first
                    opportunity that offers. I have worked at it very
                    laboriously, &amp; rewritten six hundred lines in the two
                    last books, which dissatisfied me. Your letter reached me
                    not till mine had been dispatched. for the future omit my
                    name in the direction, &amp; write only The <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> H. Hill</ref>, <hi rend="ital">Chaplain to
                        the British Forces</hi>, this will frank it thro the
                    Portugueze office. an S by the wafer may mark it as
                    mine.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are in the midst of rumours &amp; alarms.
                    Of the wise expedition to Ferrol<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The British government was increasingly
                        convinced that Spain would ally with France and declare
                        war on Britain. As a pre-emptive strike, a fleet under
                        the command of Rear-Admiral Sir John Borlase Warren
                        (1753&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>) unsuccessfully attempted
                        to capture the Spanish port of Ferrol on 25&#8211;27 August
                        1800.</note> we only know that it ended as all such
                    expeditions have ended, &amp; will end till the end of the
                    chapter. we know nothing certain of what has been done at
                    Vigo &#8211; except that their only possible motive in going there
                    must have been to make a Gazette, &amp; varnish over the
                    failure of the principal object. where they are now we do
                    not know, tho they are so near! Of our probable campaign I
                    said enough in my last. things remain in status quo, but
                    these marauding schemes of the English will probably
                    precipitate Spain into a war with this country, if only to
                    secure her own coasts by drawing our attention here. A more
                    serious danger alarms us. You must have heard of the plague
                    at Cadiz. what the disorder is we know not &#8211; it is said to
                    be the Black Vomit which some centuries since made great
                    ravages in Europe &#8211; I recollect no disease of that name in
                    history. however it is ravaging all Andalusia. they say it
                    is <hi rend="ital">epidemic</hi>, not <hi rend="ital">contagious</hi>. if so we shall escape &#8211; if not, we are
                    in hourly &amp; imminent danger. No precautions are taken. a
                    man just arrived from Cadiz who has recovered from the
                    disease, is daily on the Exchange at Lisbon, &amp; his
                    baggage underwent no fumigation: indeed no precautions could
                    be effectual. there is no natural frontier; &#8211; where the
                    birds &amp; the foxes pass &#8211; the smugglers also find their
                    way. an immense contraband trade is carried on thro
                    byepasses; &#8211; had the disease been infectious I think it must
                    ere this have arrived. The Siroc blew for nine weeks at
                    Cadiz &#8211; a place always unwholesome in summer. if this was
                    the cause &#8211; the rains will remove it; but other accounts
                    ascribe its origin to a ship from Charlestown, &amp; the
                    importation of the Yellow Fever. so little do we know of
                    what is next door to us! If it reaches Lisbon we shall
                    remove into the country &#8211; somewhere North among the
                    mountains.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So much for War &amp; Pestilence. It was a
                    saying of John 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
          <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John V (1689&#8211;1750;
                        King of Portugal 1706&#8211;1750).</note>of this country. God
                    preserve Portugal from pestilence. I will preserve it from
                    Famine &amp; War. About Buchans book<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Buchan (1729&#8211;1805;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Domestic Medicine, or
                            the Family Physician</title> (1769).</note> my
                    information may have been false. but it was positive &#8211; the
                    man had read the prohibition. That the translation of Adam
                        Smith<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam Smith
                        (1723&#8211;1790; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Wealth of
                            Nations</title> (1776).</note> is mutilated I have
                    not the slightest doubt. the principles of his work are so
                    subversive of their whole colonial system that it is not
                    possible they should pass with impunity thro a Spanish
                    Press. probably the notes mentioned by your correspondent
                    are controversial &#8211; his opinions mangled &amp; opposed. I
                    shall perhaps be able to see the book.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I told you the mines had failed. this was
                    incorrect. you know they are worked by adventurers, &amp;
                    that the King receives a fifth of the produce. they grow
                    annually less &amp; less productive, because the Brasilians
                    have found out that it is more profitable to raise sugar
                    &amp; cotton &amp;c, near the coasts or within reach of
                    exportation, than to go mine-hunting among the Savages. in
                    the one case the profit is all their own. Brasil produces
                    spices, inferior indeed to what the Dutch monopolized, but
                    still good enough, I should have thought, to have been
                    profitably used in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Portugueze merchants have advanced so
                    much as to promise something for their country: they will
                    infallibly take their trade out of the hands of the English
                    &amp; Germans who have so long enriched themselves here at
                    the expence of the indolent natives. <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxx xxx xxxxx xxxxxxxx xxxxxx
                        government</del> but this is the sole symptom of
                    improvement. when they acquire wealth they know not how to
                    employ it. they have neither arts nor sciences to encourage.
                    country-gentlemen are things unknown. the nobleman perhaps
                    visits the mansion &#8211; (house I should say) or his estate <hi rend="ital">perhaps</hi>, when the fruits are ripe. he
                    squanders his income<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> in
                    frippery &amp; dangling about the court &#8211; of course has no
                    money for improvements, &amp; distresses his tenants, who
                    cannot improve &amp; dare not &#8211; if they could. Therefore the
                    church lands are the only well-managed estates. One of these
                    wealthy men wanted some pictures. there happened to be a
                    foreign artist at Lisbon of some merit. he sent for him,
                    mentioned the size of the pictures he wanted, &amp; asked at
                    what price he would execute them. the Painter said 20
                    Moidores each. 20 Moidores! replied the Patron of the Arts &#8211;
                    I can get a Portugueze to do them for a six &amp; thirty!
                    The wealthiest of the native merchants came lately to <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> &amp; brought
                    down a whole tribe of acquaintance to enjoy this Paradise.
                    how think you they spent their time? literally at cards from
                    breakfast till supper. this lasted a fortnight &#8211; his tavern
                    bill amounted to more than 200 pounds &amp; then he returned
                    to Lisbon. Read they will not. indeed if they would they
                    have scarcely a book in their own language fit to be read. I
                    would our novel-mongers &amp; Lane<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Lane (1745&#8211;1814;
                            <title>DNB</title>), publisher of light romantic
                        novels and promoter of circulating libraries.</note> of
                    Leadenhall Street along with them, were transported here
                    &amp; condemned to manufacture trash for the Portugueze. Any
                    thing that would teach them to read! &#8211; The Academy began a
                        dictionary:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Royal Academy of Sciences published only the first
                        volume of their proposed Portuguese dictionary, covering
                        the letter A, in 1793. It was largely the work of Pedro
                        Jose da Fonseca (1737&#8211;1816).</note> a national work &#8211;
                    &amp; upon a huge scale. a large folio only contained the
                    letter A &#8211; &amp; beyond the letter A they have never got tho
                    six years have elapsed since that appeared. I shall shew you
                    in England this volume &amp; its almost unbelievable
                    absurdity. a century &amp; half ago Portugal was not behind
                    the rest of Europe &#8211; her country towns had their presses,
                    &amp; if what was done was not good, very little better was
                    performed elsewhere. There is now a man who [MS torn] a sort
                    of contraband circulating library: but his subscribers are
                    chiefly English; &#8211; I doubt whether he has a Portugueze book,
                    &amp; do not doubt that he will soon be imprisoned. The cock
                    &amp; &#8211; a &#8211; bull stories of superstition would little
                    interest you. yet there is one which you should know.
                    Portugal is infested with witches who delight in killing
                    infants &#8211; they kill them <hi rend="ital">always</hi> in the
                    night, &amp; it is known by the children being <hi rend="ital">black in the face</hi>. this is believed &#8211;
                    but this cannot be superstition on the part of the mothers
                    &amp; the nurses who overlay the infants. you cannot imagine
                        <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> how these people
                    sleep. the driver whom we always use sleeps upon his mule as
                    he drives us &#8211; we wake him &#8211; the passers-by wake him &#8211; still
                    he has more than once endangered us, &amp; was once driving
                        <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> into the river. A servant of an Englishman
                    caught his death lately <del rend="strikethrough">by
                        the</del> thus &#8211; it rained into his room &#8211; <del rend="strikethrough">profu</del> violently &#8211; without
                    waking him. he slept in a bed half full of water till his
                    usual hour, &amp; woke with a cold that killed him. I have
                    heard often of servants whom it is impossible to awaken by
                    any noise: they must be pulled &amp; shaken. does your
                    servant wait at the door when you make a morning visit? in
                    five minutes he is stretched on the stones &amp; snoring. a
                    dog does not slumber more readily. it is an act of volition
                    with them. the moment they cease from animal action, they
                    have no alternative.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a sort of general Hospital Board of
                    which on my return I shall hunt out all particulars. but you
                    can not easily conceive how ignorant the English here are of
                    the country they live in, &amp; how difficult it is to learn
                    any thing. I believe its funds are chiefly derived from
                    legacies &#8211; however that may be, they communicate with every
                    municipality, &amp; in every <hi rend="ital">town</hi> a
                    Physician, a Surgeon, &amp; a Apothecary receive either from
                    the funds of the corporation, or from this Board a certain
                    annuity: small indeed, but still enough to prevent a man
                    from starving &amp; encourage him to settle there for this
                    thus he attends the paupers. Popery is a charitable
                    religion, &amp; begging must be a good trade, where
                    alms-giving is an atonement. Every-body whom we meet in the
                    country begs &#8211; they affix no ignominy to it &#8211; the very man
                    who sells you meat or poultry takes his money &amp; then
                    begs for the love of God!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>
                    remembrances. Thalaba will come by the first
                    opportunity.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>