<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce813</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.804</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.804" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="804" type="letter">
        <head>804. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>,
                        <date when="1803-07-05">[5 July 1803]</date>
          </head><p>Address:
                        [in another hand] Lieutenant Southey/ HMS Galatea/
                        Portsmouth/ Free J May<lb />Postmark: FREE/ 1803<lb />MS:
                        British Library, Add MS
                        30927<lb />Unpublished.<lb />Dating note: The letter was
                        probably written on Tuesday 5 July 1803, at a time when
                        Southey was in London and when discussions regarding his
                        brother Edward&#8217;s joining the navy were
                    ongoing.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Tom </salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have spoken about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; he
                    has put things in a fair train so that he will doubtless
                    soon be rated. it would never do to have him on board your
                    ship &#8211; indeed the boy has sense enough himself to see &amp;
                    acknowledge that.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My time in London is grievously taken up &#8211;
                    here there &amp; everywhere &#8211; never at rest &#8211; a thousand
                    &amp; one acquaintance half of whom it is impossible to see
                    &#8211; &amp; yet they will take offence if I do not call at their
                    door. however I see land thank God! &amp; shall be at home
                    on Monday on Tuesday at the latest. Amadis<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation of
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> is
                    finished &amp; will be published this week. I shall send
                    your copy from hence as soon as I can get one. the direction
                    you gave me to the Barracks I have left at Bristol &amp;
                    cannot remember to whose care it was to be entrusted. so I
                    will send off the Books directed to you to be left till
                    called for &amp; apprize you when they go.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You talked of taking a flying leap to London.
                    I had rather you took a flying leap to Bristol, because
                    there you are sure of jumping upon me &#8211; but here I am never
                    one hour in one place &amp; if you should come up hap-hazard
                    for four &amp; twenty hours, &amp; find that I was gone East
                    West North or South to Southgate or to Stockwell or to
                        Richmond<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">It is
                        not clear whom Southey was visiting at Southgate. Thomas
                        Woodroffe Smith (c. 1747-1811), a wealthy Quaker friend
                        of Grosvenor Bedford, lived at Stockwell Lodge, and John
                        May lived in Richmond.</note> why it would vex us
                    both.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am glad to find you have so many men as you
                    have &#8211; the frigate in which Edmund Palmer<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Palmer (1782-1834),
                        naval officer who rose to be a Captain. He was the son
                        of John Palmer (1742-1818; <title>DNB</title>), theatre
                        proprietor in Bath and Bristol, postal reformer and MP
                        for Bath 1801-1807.</note> is has only 17 &#8211; &amp; this
                    war will last long enough to fill your pockets tho you stay
                    these six months at Spithead. invaded we shall be &#8211; that
                    seems beyond a doubt &#8211; but that the French should effect
                    their landing is not quite so clear. to talk of row boats is
                    nonsense. but all our measures of defence are miserably
                    feeble &amp; miserably inefficient.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> the Annual Review<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1
                        (1803).</note> will be published in about a month. it
                    seems my articles therein are in high odour &#8211; &amp; I am
                    requested to take a large part in the succeeding volume: I
                    have proposed a great work to Longman upon English
                    Literature of which you shall know more when more is settled
                    if it comes to any thing.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Bibliotheca Britannica&#8217;,
                        a plan for a chronological account of literature written
                        in Britain, which Longman and Rees abandoned in August
                        1803.</note> it will be of great labour &#8211; great
                    responsibility &amp; great importance &#8211; I must have whole
                    &amp; sole management, &amp; the free &amp; full choice of
                    all my associates. but if it be all so arranged it will be
                    of sufficient consequence in every point of view to fix me
                    near town.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. if you knew how London hurries
                    me you would not wonder at a short letter &#8211; &amp; I have the
                    less scruple in sending it as it will have a frank &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R S.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1803-07-05">Tuesday.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>