<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce535</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.526</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 74&#8211;77 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.526" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="526" type="letter">
        <head>526. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">Margaret
                        Southey</ref>, <date when="1800-05-23">23 May 1800</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Southey./ at Miss Tylers/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped: EXETER<lb />MS:
                        Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File &#8216;S&#8217;, Folder 14172<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 74&#8211;77 [in
                        part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="left">
            <date when="1800-05-23">Friday May 23. 1800.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Mother</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our trunk arrived by the last packet &#8211; a joyful arrival &#8211; for I
                    was beginning to be as bare as a plucked ostrich. the earthern-ware we do not
                    expect before the return of the King George, as it is directed to Yescombe,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Bayntun Yescombe (1765&#8211;1803),
                        Captain of the packet, <hi rend="ital">King George</hi>, which sailed
                        between Falmouth and Lisbon.</note> &amp; will (if at Falmouth) wait for
                    him, that he may bring it &amp; not charge freight. Yescombe is very friendly &#8211;
                    We go on comfortably &#8211; as clean as an English house up stairs &#8211; as dirty as a
                    Portugueze one below. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, like
                    Mr Pitt,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Pitt, the Younger
                        (1759&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806.</note>
                    is convinced of the impossibility of reform. Manuel<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel Mambrino (dates unknown), a Spanish servant from
                        Oviedo who worked for Herbert Hill. Mambrino had accompanied Southey on some
                        of his travels in Spain and Portugal in 1795&#8211;1796.</note> will clean the
                    kitchen indeed &#8211; but immediately he will scrape the fish scales all over it.
                    these people have no foresight. we however are very well off &#8211; &amp; for a
                    Portugueze our Maria Rosa is extraordinarily tidy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Little duck Stephens<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly William Stephens (dates unknown), a warehouseman, of Wine Street,
                        Bristol.</note> is here &#8211; the Wine Street man, with a Housekeeper. &amp; he
                    goes to market himself &#8211; &amp; I am going to cultivate his acquaintance &#8211; in
                    order to find out what good things may have escaped my appetite here. nothing
                    like a Bristol pointer at an eatable thing! &#8211; And we have found another Bristol
                    bird &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mitchell<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Michell, n&#233;e Shears (1765&#8211;1838).</note> &#8211; daughter of Sheeres the
                        Surgeon<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Shears (dates unknown) of Bedminster, near Bristol.</note> &#8211; &amp; niece to Patty Collins<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &#8211; a very good natured
                    woman, with a cast in her eye. her husband<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant Sampson Michell (1755&#8211;1809), was in command of the
                        Portuguese ship, <hi rend="ital">San Sebastian</hi>. He rose to be an
                        Admiral in the Portuguese Navy.</note> is a Commodore in the Portugueze
                    service &#8211; getting a great deal of money. they live in our street.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> &#8211; to my surprize &#8211;
                    liked his knives better than if the handles had been white. he has enough to do
                    with burying &amp; christening among the soldiers, tho the Priests poach among
                    his flock sadly. We profit somewhat by the war, getting most excellent pieces of
                    the sirloin from the ration <del rend="strikethrough">xx my Uncle</del>. The
                    summer we pass at <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> &#8211; whither
                    however we shall not go till July, for in June we have to see the Procession of
                    the Body of God &#8211; of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Anthony &#8211; &amp; the Royal family
                    with the Knights of the New Convent. &amp; we must also wait to see a Bull fight
                    &#8211; which being a cool summer amusement, only takes place in the hottest weather.
                    &#8211; Poor <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> is very ill &#8211;
                    &amp; must I believe once more come to Lisbon for his health. by the by he
                    desired me to say he wished <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my
                        Aunt</ref> would send to Lisbon an account of what money she had received
                    from him, that <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> might
                    see he did his duty. &#8211; I shall be very glad to have him here, as I want a
                    companion to ramble with thro the city &amp; into all the churches.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I read nothing but Spanish &amp; Portugueze. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> knows enough of the common
                    words to get all needful things done about the house. We have had an infinite
                    number of visitors &amp; our debt is not yet paid off. Young Hawker is a
                    good-humoured man &#8211; his wife disagreable enough to have the old
                    Press-gang-fellows daughter by blood instead of by law.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant Francis Hawker (dates unknown) of the 12th Light
                        Dragoons. He and his wife (n&#233;e Cripps) were friendly with Herbert Hill.
                        Southey met them again in France in 1838 (Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert
                            Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and a Visit to
                            France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 210&#8211;211). Hawker was the son of
                        Captain Thomas Hawker (dates unknown), who was head of the Impress Service
                        in Bristol from 1793 and a neighbour of Southey&#8217;s aunt Elizabeth
                        Tyler.</note> we are to dine with them one day &#8211; somewhat conveniently as
                    their barracks are nearly three miles from hence, &amp; lying near the Museum &#8211;
                    the Botanic Garden &#8211; the beasts &#8211; &amp; the beautiful &#8211; most beautiful church
                    &amp; convent at Belem &#8211; we shall be enabled to see these with little trouble
                    &amp; without the necessity of hiring a chaise for the day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has seen the Aqueduct. even
                    after having seen it I was astonished at its magnitude. Shakespere&#8217;s &#8220;lessened
                    to a crow<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of
                            <title>Cymbeline</title>, Act 1, scene 3, lines 14&#8211;16; Act 3, scene 3,
                        lines 11&#8211;13.</note> seemed hardly hyperbolical when I looked down from the
                    middle arch upon the brook of Alcantara, the women washing there would have
                    escaped my sight, if I had not seen them moving as they walked. it is a work
                    worthy of Rome in the days of her power &amp; magnificence. the Portugueze
                    delight in water. the most luscious &amp; cloying sweetmeats first &#8211; for
                    instance preserved yolk of egg &#8211; &amp; then a glass of water &#8211; &amp; this is
                    excellent which comes by the Aqueduct. The view from the top is wonderfully fine
                    &#8211; a stoney shallow brook below &#8211; a few women washing in it &#8211; bare-knee&#8217;d. the
                    sides sprinkled with linen drying in the sun. orange &amp; vine &#8211; &amp;
                    olive-yards along the narrow line of fertility that runs between the hills,
                    &amp; houses scattered in the little valley, &amp; bare dark hills &amp;
                    windmills &#8211; &amp; houses far beyond, &amp; distant mountains. &#8211; <del rend="strikethrough">&amp; looking down the str</del>. She has also seen the
                    New Convent.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Convent of the Discalced
                        Carmelite Nuns, founded in 1779 by Maria I (1734&#8211;1816; Queen of Portugal
                        1777&#8211;1816).</note> the inside of the church is of marble &#8211; &amp; the colours
                    very well disposed &#8211; you will remember that a marble room, chilling as it would
                    be in England, is here only cool &amp; comfortable. it is dedicated to the heart
                    of Jesus, which is the subject of more than one Picture in the church. in one
                    the Queen (for she built it,) is representing adoring this Heart.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and a Visit to France
                            1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), p. 9 n. 5, notes that Southey&#8217;s assertion
                        was incorrect.</note> you would not like the Roman Catholic religion quite
                    so well, if you saw it here in all its naked nonsense. could you but see the
                    mummery &amp; smell the Friars! There is no dying in peace for these fellows.
                    they kill more than even the country apothecaries. when a man is given over &#8211; in
                    they come &#8211; set up singing which they never cease till the poor wretch is dead &#8211;
                    build an altar in the room, light their candles &#8211; &amp; administer extreme
                    unction. Which has much the same effect, as if in England you measured a sick
                    man for his coffin &#8211; &amp; dressed him in his shroud. they watch after the dying
                    like Bristol Undertakers &#8211;. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> is always obliged to mount guard &#8211; &amp; yet last week they
                    smuggled off an officer &#8211; got at him when his senses were gone, &amp; stuck a
                    candle in his hand &#8211; &amp; sung O be joyful &#8211; for a convert. We have had three
                    illuminations for the new Pope!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Pius VII
                        (1742&#8211;1823; Pope 1800&#8211;1823).</note> you know the old story of lighting a
                    candle to the Devil. &#8211; <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> I remembered
                    &lt;it&gt; &amp; burnt tallow for the old Babylonian. We had another
                    illumination for the christening of a Princess.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Maria Francisca de Assis (1800&#8211;1834), fourth child of John VI
                        (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826).</note> these things are not as in
                    England at the will of the mob. an illumination is proclaimed. at a proper hour
                    the guns fire to say now light your candles &#8211; at ten they fire again to give
                    notice that you may put them out. &amp; if you do not illuminate you are fined
                    about thirty shillings &#8211; but no riots &#8211; no mobbing &#8211; no breaking windows.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall send this by a private hand. Rundell<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Rundell (first name and dates unknown) travelled
                        to Portugal with Southey. He was possibly a member of a prominent Bath
                        family of silversmiths, jewellers and surgeons.</note> I believe will return
                    by the Packet after this &#8211; &amp; by him I shall write to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>, to whom I pray you
                    remember us &amp; to his Mother. tell them the ninth book of Thalaba is not yet
                    finished &#8211; tho all but finished. the literature of this place takes up very much
                    of my time &#8211; I am never idle &#8211; &amp; I believe must set at Thalaba in good
                    earnest in order to get it out of my way.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. God bless
                        you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> your affectionate Son </salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>We look somewhat anxiously for letters by the next packet. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>