<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce543</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.534</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856).  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 112–117 [dated July 23 1801].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="534" type="letter">
<head>534. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1800-06-22">[22–]23 June 1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856)<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1856), I, pp. 112–117 [dated July 23 1801].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<address>
<placeName>Lisbon,</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1800-06-23">June 23. 1800.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Friend,</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> Your letter reached me safely. The Aveiro conspiracy<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Better known as the ‘Tavora affair’. An attempt
                        to assassinate Jose I (1714–1777; King of Portugal 1750–1777) on the night
                        of 3 September 1758 was used to destroy some of the most powerful noble
                        familes and the Jesuit Order in Portugal. Southey has named the alleged
                        conspiracy after a nobleman who was accused of being one of its leaders,
                        Jose de Mascarenhas da Silva e Lencestre, 8th Duke of Avora
                        (1708–1759).</note> will make a part of my historical researches, and the
                    hospital of my general ones; concerning both I will procure all the information
                    within my reach, and transmit to you.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> On Monday next we go to <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>. The summer is arrived, and we have had some days more
                    oppressively hot than I had ever before experienced, accompanied with the hot
                    wind, a sort of bastard siroc, which you must remember, and which it is much
                    more agreeable to remember than to feel. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> The disappointment of having a burning face fanned by a wind that
                    heats it, has been useful to me. I had described desert sufferings, and can now
                    retouch and heighten the picture. To-day we have had the fine fresh breeze
                    which, in the West Indies, they call the doctor, – a good seamanly phrase, well
                    expressing its healing comfort. The nights are miserably hot. I thirst after
                        <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>, and on Monday hope to hear
                    once more the sound of running water. We shall be fortunate in having a pleasant
                    neighbour there, in one of the birds of passage that chance sends to Portugal, a
                        <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref>, who is here with a
                    convalescent aunt,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note>
                    and remains at <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> with her aunt’s
                    infant, while she herself tries the Caldar. She is a very clever girl, all good
                    humour, and a head brimful of brains.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We were at the museum on Monday last. There are the head and
                    hands of one of our cousin ouran-outangs there, which I remember to have heard
                    of some years ago. The poor fellow who owned them was walking quietly with a
                    stick in his hand. A European saw him and shot him. He was more like the human
                    animal than any ape that had been seen before. Unless you remember the face, you
                    will hardly believe how human it is, – with black eyebrows and a woolly head
                    like a negro’s. I could and would have given a conscientious verdict of wilful
                    murder against the man who shot him – the cruelty pains me; and yet I smile at
                    the impudence of a Portuguese in presuming to kill an ouran-outang as his
                    inferior.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You imagine that we live much with the Hares.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Members of the British Factory, Lisbon. In 1797
                        John May had considered marrying Charlotte Hair, presumably their
                        daughter.</note> I had expected it, but it is not the case; their
                    acquaintance are so numerous as to leave them little leisure, and Charlotte is
                    generally with her next-door neighbour, Mrs. Warden,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the wife of the Commissary who had been very helpful
                        when Southey arrived in Lisbon earlier in 1800. The Wardens’ names and dates
                        are unknown.</note> a very pleasant and pretty woman, who, besides her own
                    society, has the attraction of an infant, – a plaything for which women have an
                    interesting and instinctive affection.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We live mostly to ourselves, seeing something of everybody, and
                    much of no one except <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle</ref>.
                    At the only two parties which I have attended, I was engrossed, much to my
                    satisfaction, by <ref target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">Koster</ref>, a
                    man more conversable than most of the English here, and whose opinions call
                    forth somewhat more freedom of conversation than I allow myself elsewhere. We
                    have dined at Mr. Walpole’s,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Hon. Robert
                        Walpole(1736–1810), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to
                        Portugal 1772–1800.</note> – seen the <hi rend="ital">Corpo de Dios</hi>
                    from Miss Stevens’s,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note>
                    and St. Anthony from Mrs. Metzener’s.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Metzeners were a long-established merchant family in Portugal, originally
                        from Germany.</note> Some alterations I find here: the sight of a generation
                    of young men and women, whom I remember in the class of children, makes me feel
                    the increase of my own age. Miss Sealy is now Mrs. Dyson.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Baldwin Sealy (c. 1780-1857) married Thomas
                        Fournice Dyson (1767-1843) in Lisbon on 15 May 1800. Anne’s sister,
                        Mary-Harriet (d. 1811), later became Henry Herbert Southey’s first
                        wife.</note> The Misses –– <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note>are diffident and accomplished young women; and Miss
                        ––,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> who wore
                    her hair tied in a Portuguese knot, and was a pretty girl four years ago, is now
                    the beauty of Lisbon, – not however in my eyes, for there is something very
                    unpleasant to me in all the family. The burying-ground was an unpleasant sight:
                    Buller, and the old Travers, and Mrs. Bulkely,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Buller: unidentified. Travers: unidentified. Mrs Bulkely was
                        possibly the wife or mother of Thomas Bulkely, son of the British merchant
                        John Bulkely, and US Consul in Lisbon 1797–1802.</note> – their names stared
                    me in the face; and the Penwarne, whom I knew, was under my feet, and poor
                    little Scott,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Penwarne: unidentified.
                        Scott: unidentified.</note>. whose foolish rhymes I now remember with a sort
                    of melancholy. The Walpoles are regretted. Their <hi rend="ital">lieutenants</hi> live too much with the emigrants, and observe too rude a
                    retirement towards the English. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> Of the books which I have met with, none has amused me so much as
                    a metrical Life of Vieyra, the painter, written by himself.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Vieira (1699–1783), <title>O Insigne
                            Pintor e Leal Esposo Vieira Lusitano</title> (1780).</note> It contains
                    a good deal of Portuguese costume. The poet is enormously vain, and abundantly
                    superstitious, – but his vanity is so open and honest, that you rather like him
                    the better for praising himself so sincerely. I have analyzed it at some length,
                    for my sketch of the poetical history, which will swell to some size and shape
                    before my return. One of the Portuguese poets, the brother of the famous Diego
                        Barnardez,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Agostinho da Cruz
                        (1540-1619), brother of Diogo Bernardes (c. 1530-c. 1600). Southey owned a
                        copy of the brothers’ poetry, no. 3178 in the sale catalogue of his
                        library.</note> passed his noviciate in the Cork convent, professed at
                    Arrabida, and died a hermit upon that magnificent mountain, – a miserably
                    useless life; but he chose his situations like a poet, and I can half forgive
                    the folly of his retirement for his taste in fixing. The “Life of Father
                        Anchieta”<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Simão de Vasconcelos
                        (1596-1671), <title>Vida Do Veneravel Padre Jose de Anchieta do
                            Brasil</title> (1672), no. 3799 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library. Jose de Anchieta (1534-1597) was a Jesuit missionary to Brazil and
                        one of the first Brazilian writers. He was beatified in 1980, but still
                        awaits canonisation.</note> very much tickled my fancy. As a Latin poet, I
                    biographise him; but Anchieta was a candidate for canonisation, and worked more
                    miracles than all the Apostles. Strip him of his miracles, and the truth is,
                    that he was an honest Jesuit, who wrote vile verses in alphabetical praise of
                    the Virgin Mary. He was among the savages in Brazil, and his practice was to
                    write his verses upon the sea-sands, and then commit them to memory; and so,
                    says his Life-writer, he brought home in his head about 5000 lines. You may
                    believe the Jesuit, if you please; but he is so abominable a liar that I do not.
                    Anchieta was in <hi rend="ital">the habit</hi> of turning water into wine – “he
                    did not do it once only, like Christ at Cana,” says the Jesuit; “and when the
                    sun was too hot he called the birds to fly over his head and screen him, which
                    was a much more elegant (<hi rend="ital">gracioso</hi>) miracle than the cloud
                    that shadowed the children of Israel!”<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Simão de Vasconcelos, <title>Vida do Veneravel Padre Jose de Anchieta do
                            Brasil</title> (Lisbon, 1672), pp. 204-205. Anchieta’s bird parasol was
                        used in the note to <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 4,
                        line 285.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> At <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> I design to read
                    the <hi rend="ital">Ordinançoês de Affonso V.</hi>,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The Afonsine Ordinances (1446) of Afonso V (1432–1481; King
                        of Portugal 1438–1481).</note> and extract from them a summary of the laws
                    as he left them. This legal part of the history will be the most laborious and
                    uninteresting. The East Indian affairs must be separated; they are totally
                    unconnected, and to carry on two distinct stories in one chronological series is
                    perplexing beyond all patience. The Portuguese story is uncommonly splendid, but
                    I find their exploits in the Indies sullied by a detestable barbarity, which
                    their own old writers had not moral courage enough to condemn.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> To-morrow is the first bull-fight, and <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle</ref>’s man<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel Mambrino (dates unknown), Herbert Hill’s
                        servant, from Oviedo in Spain. He had accompanied Southey on some of his
                        travels in 1795–1796.</note> is gone to take a box for us. This happens
                    fortunately, as it will save us the trouble of returning from <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> to see one, which we certainly
                    should else have done. I expect only to be pained and disgusted.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<date when="1800-06-23">
<hi rend="ital">Monday, June 23rd</hi>.</date> – The
                    bull-fight excited nothing but pain and anger at the cruelty and the cowardice
                    of the amusement. These spectacles must have a bad effect upon the public
                    morals. Mr. Wyndham and Mr. Canning defended bull-baiting upon the ground that
                    these sports preserved the national courage.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">William Windham (1750–1810; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of
                        State for War, 1794–1801, and George Canning (1770–1827;
                        <title>DNB</title>), Under-Secretary at the Foreign Office, 1795–1799,
                        Commissioner at the Board of Control 1799–1800 and Paymaster of the Forces
                        1800–1801, had been the most eloquent opponents of the unsuccessful Bill to
                        outlaw bull-baiting in 1800.</note> The opinion was absurd enough and
                    unfeeling enough to come with propriety from Mr. Wyndham and Mr. Canning. If it
                    were true, the courage of a nation would be in proportion to the cruelty of its
                    sports or to the danger, the same would be the case with individuals; the
                    Spaniards therefore who fight the bulls with untipped horns must be the most
                    courageous people in Europe, and the butchers the bravest class of the
                    community. Our laws only recognise them as men necessarily hardened by the
                    habitual sight of blood, and therefore exclude them from the office of jurymen.
                    I cannot understand the pleasure excited by a bull-fight. It is honourable to
                    the English character that none of our nation frequent these spectacles. <hi rend="ital">I am not quite sure that my curiosity in once going was
                        perfectly justifiable; but the pain inflicted by the sight was expiation
                        enough.</hi>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have not applied to Mr. Coppendale<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Coppendale (d. 1833), John May’s uncle and business
                        partner.</note> for money, – <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        uncle</ref> has supplied me. Our departure for <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> is delayed till Thursday. We have
                    two baggage-carts from the army; and if the war did no more mischief elsewhere
                    than in Portugal, I might reconcile myself to its continuance. I shall look out
                    for the Tagus.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Mr. Worthington<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">John
                        Worthington (dates unknown), business partner of John May’s and later a
                        merchant in Brazil.</note> tells me the books are directed to him. The
                    advantage of sending by Yescombe<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward
                        Bayntun Yescombe (1765–1803), Captain of the packet, <hi rend="ital">King
                            George</hi>, which sailed between Falmouth and Lisbon.</note> is that
                    they are landed without difficulty or examination. Warden goes on board as soon
                    as the packet arrives, and takes on shore unexamined all army parcels. I am
                    certainly better: my heart continues its irregularities, but I am less disturbed
                    at night, and less alarmed, and my spirits suit the climate, which is more than
                    half the battle. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to
                    be remembered. God bless you.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
