<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce622</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.613</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849-1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.)
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 164-167.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="613" type="letter">
        <head>613. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith
                        Southey</ref> [fragment], <date when="1801-10-14">14 October
                        1801</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849-1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.)
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 164-167.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>,
                            <date when="1801-10-14">Wednesday, Oct. 14. 1801.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p>. &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; . On Sunday, after delaying till the latest possible moment for the
                    chance of passengers, we dropped down the river Dee. The wind almost immediately
                    failed us; I never saw so dead a calm; there was not a heaving, a ripple, a
                    wrinkle on the water; the ship, though she made some way with the tide, was as
                    still as a house, to our feelings. Had the wind continued as when we embarked,
                    eighteen hours would have blown us to <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>. I saw the sun set behind Anglesea; and the mountains of
                    Carnarvonshire rose so beautifully before us that, though at sea, it was
                    delightful. The sun-rise on Monday was magnificent. Holyhead was then in sight,
                    and in sight on the wrong side it continued all day, while we tacked and
                    retacked with a hard-hearted wind. We got into Beaumaris Bay, and waited there
                    for the midnight tide: it was very quiet; even my stomach had not provocation
                    enough, as yet, to be sick. In the night we proceeded: about two o&#8217;clock a
                    very heavy gale arose; it blew great guns, as you would say; the vessel shipped
                    water very fast, it came pouring down into the cabin, and both pumps were at
                    work, &#8211; the dismallest thump, thump, I ever heard: this lasted about three
                    hours. As soon as we were clear of the Race of Holyhead the sea grew smoother,
                    though the gale continued. On Tuesday the morning was hazy, we could not see
                    land, though it was not far distant; and when at last we saw it, the wind had
                    drifted us so far south that no possibility existed of our reaching <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> that night. The captain, a good man
                    and a good sailor, who never leaves his deck during the night, and drinks
                    nothing but butter-milk, therefore readily agreed to land us at Balbriggen; and
                    there we got ashore at two o&#8217;clock. Balbriggen is a fishing and bathing
                    town, fifteen miles from <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>, &#8211; but
                    miles and money differ in Ireland from the English standard, eleven miles Irish
                    being as long as fourteen English. &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    . </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To my great satisfaction, we had in our company one of the most
                    celebrated characters existing at this day; a man whose name is as widely known
                    as that of any human being, except, perhaps, Bonaparte!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769-1821; First Consul 1799-1804,
                        Emperor of the French 1804-1814).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He is not above five feet, but, notwithstanding his figure, soon
                    became the most important personage of the party. &#8216;Sir,&#8217; said he, as
                    soon as he set foot in the vessel, &#8216;I am a unique; I go anywhere, just as
                    the whim takes me: this morning, sir, I had no idea whatever of going to <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>; I did not think of it when I left
                    home; my wife and family know nothing of the trip. I have only one shirt with me
                    besides what I have on; my nephew<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> here, sir, has not another shirt to his back: but
                    money, sir, money, &#8211; anything may be had at <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>. &#8216;Who the devil is this fellow? thought I. We talked of
                    rum, &#8211; he had just bought 100 puncheons, the weakest drop 15 above proof: of the
                    west of England, &#8211; out he pulls an Exeter newspaper from his pocket: of bank
                    paper, &#8211; his pocket-book was stuffed with notes, Scotch, Irish, and English; and
                    I really am obliged to him for some clues to discover forged paper. Talk, talk,
                    everlasting; &#8211; he could draw for money on any town in the United Kingdoms; ay,
                    or in America. At last he was made known for Dr. Solomon.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Solomon (1768/9-1819;
                        <title>DNB</title>), manufacturer and promoter of the best-selling quack
                        medicine &#8216;Cordial Balm of Gilead&#8217;. His MD, from Marischal College, Aberdeen,
                        was probably obtained fraudulently.</note> At night I set upon the doctor,
                    and turned the discourse upon disease in general, beginning with the Liverpool
                    flux &#8211; which remedy had proved most effectual &#8211; nothing like the Cordial Balm of
                    Gilead; at last I ventured to touch upon a tender subject &#8211; did he conceive Dr.
                        Brodum&#8217;s<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Brodum (fl.
                        1795-1814), quack medicine seller. He had been the mentor of Samuel
                        Solomon.</note> medicine to be at all analogous to his own? &#8216;Not in
                    the least, sir; colour, smell, all totally different: as for Dr. Brodum, sir, &#8211;
                    all the world knows it &#8211; it is manifest to everybody &#8211; that his advertisements
                    are all stolen, <hi rend="ital">verbatim et literatim</hi>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;word by word and letter
                        by letter&#8217;.</note> from mine. Sir, I don&#8217;t think it worth while to
                    notice such a fellow.&#8217; But enough of Solomon, and his nephew and successor
                    that is to be &#8211; the Rehoboam<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Rehoboam
                        succeeded his father Solomon (King of Israel 971-931 BC) as King of Judah
                        (931-915 BC).</note> of Gilead &#8211; cub in training.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Mr. Corry</ref> is out of town for two
                    days, so I have not seen him. The probability is, <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> tells me, that I shall return
                    in about ten days: you shall have the first intelligence; at present I know no
                    more of my future plans than that I am to dine to-day with the secretary of the
                    Lord Lieutenant,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip Yorke, 3rd Earl
                        of Hardwicke (1757-1834; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Lieutenant of Ireland
                        1801-1805. His private secretary was Charles Lindsay (1760-1846), later
                        Bishop of Kildare 1804-1846.</note> and to look me out a lodging first.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But you must hear all I have seen of Ireland. The fifteen miles
                    that we crossed are so destitute of trees, that I could only account for it by a
                    sort of instinctive dread of the gallows in the natives. I find they have been
                    cut down to make pikes. Cars, instead of carts or waggons; women without hats,
                    shoes, or stockings. One little town we passed, once famous, &#8211; its name Swords;
                    it has the ruins of a castle and a church, with a round tower adjoining the
                    steeple, making an odd group; it was notoriously a pot-walloping borough:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Swords returned two MPs to the Irish House
                        of Commons until its abolition in 1800. It was one of only ten Irish
                        boroughs that had a potwalloper franchise, i.e. any householder with a
                        hearth big enough to boil a pot could vote. Despite (or because of) this
                        relatively wide franchise, the borough had a reputation for
                        corruption.</note> and for breeding early ducks for the London market, the
                    manufactory of ducks appeared to be in a flourishing state. Post-chaises very
                    ugly, the doors fastening with a staple and chain; three persons going in one,
                    paying more than two. The hotel here abominably filthy. I see mountains near
                        <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> most beautifully shaped, but
                    the day is too hazy. You shall hear all I can tell you by my next. I am quite
                    well, and, what is extraordinary, was never once sick the whole way.
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; Edith, God bless
                    you! I do not expect to be absent from you above a fortnight longer.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>