<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2010-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.669b</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2010-08-15">August 15, 2010</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
						47891.  Previously  published John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
						(London, 1856), I, pp. 189-192 [dated April 1802]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.669b" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="669b" type="letter">
        <head>669b. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">John King</ref>, <date when="1802-04-15">15-16 April 1802</date>
						[translation]</head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> King/ Dowry Square/ Hot
						Wells/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Postmark: BRISTOL/ APR 19 1802<lb />Seal: [illegible]<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS
						47891<lb />Previously published John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
						(London, 1856), I, pp. 189-192 [dated April 1802]. </p>
        <opener>
          <date when="1802-04-15">April 15. 1802.</date>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yesterday my friend I was at the home of M. V_____<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">He could be connected to
						the J.A. Voullaire (first name and dates unknown), whose French translation of <title>The Vicar of Wakefield</title> was
						published in 1811.</note> I have forgotten his name. He was not at home, I left him your letter saying that in a few days I
					will return. at present it would not be possible for me to learn French &#8211; I have so much to do every hour that it would not be
					difficult to find many more things to do that would be enough work for two [people]. &#8211; Ah &#8211; the particles<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In grammar these are function words, such as pronouns, articles and conjunctions.</note> &#8211; the &#8216;<hi rend="ital">ens</hi>&#8217;. &amp; the &#8216;<hi rend="ital">ons</hi>&#8217;, &amp; the &#8216;<hi rend="ital">nes</hi>&#8217; &amp; the &#8216;<hi rend="ital">ys</hi>&#8217; &#8211;
					there are the little Devils who torment me &#8211; Oh well &#8211; hereafter with the assistance of your friend I will defeat the Devils &#8211;
					grammar is worth as much as a Breviary in this war &#8211; or even the perfect Exorcist. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am going to learn <hi rend="ital">Welch</hi>. I have thought a lot about whether the knowledge is worth the
					trouble, as the language is not easy. here are the treasures that it contains &#8211; several chronicles, several centuries of very
					curious Triads<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Rhetorical forms in Welsh poetry that group objects together in
						threes.</note> in which are perhaps the most ancient traditions of all the histories of the world. a very large collection of
					Poems &#8211; of which several are from the same century as that of my hero Madoc, &amp; were hymns of victory at his father&#8217;s
						court.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The legendary Madoc was said to be the son of Owen Gwynedd (c. 1100-1170;
							<title>DNB</title>), Prince of Gwynedd 1137-1170.</note> There is another motive for me to learn this language. I believe
					it is the most ancient of all the European languages &#8211; I have a great desire to travel to Biscay, &amp; perhaps knowledge of Welsh
					will add to my understanding of Basque, which is the foundation, the root, the source of Spanish and Portuguese.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was incorrect: Basque is unrelated to Spanish or Portuguese.</note> up till the present
					all the works of the Bards, &amp; all the Triads [have] existed only in MS.S. But they are being printed [thanks to] a private
					individual, a patriotic man to whom all the savants should erect a monument.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The
							Myvyrian Archaiology of Wales</title> (1801-1807), edited by William Owen Pughe, printed many Welsh medieval manuscripts
						for the first time. It was funded by Owen Jones (1741-1814), a wealthy, Welsh-born, London furrier. The three volumes cost
						Jones over &#163;1,000.</note> Two very large volumes have already appeared. he is going to print three or four more. the expense
					will be very great &#8211; he is a pretty rich merchant. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You ask me what I think of M. [MS obscured] <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is referring to William
						Rough (1772/3-1838; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer and poet. He had been a schoolboy at Westminster with Southey 1786-1792 and
						was the author of the tragedies <title>Lorenzino de Medici</title> (1797) and <title>The Conspiracy of Gowrie</title> (1800)
						and <title>Lines on the Death of Sir Ralph Abercromby</title> (1801). The latter referred to Sir Ralph Abercromby (1734-1801;
							<title>DNB</title>), who was killed commanding the invasion of Egypt in March 1801.</note> I knew him at school. I thought
					him a boy of genius &#8211; but today he has not a single friend of his youth, &amp; I do not believe he has a heart worthy of esteem.
					He is a man of words &#8211; professions &#8211; smiles, I hate &#8211; I distrust that politeness he shows in every word, in every look. I have
					read his Tragedies &#8211; his poem on General Abercromby. they are worth nothing. they are exactly like himself &#8211; words &#8211; &amp; nothing
					else. he writes as he spoke, without feeling. this portrait is not very pleasant. too bad! I feel it is true.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The review<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor&#8217;s review of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801)
						had appeared in <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 12 (Supplement, 1801), 581-583.</note> by my friend <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>. &#8211; it is an extraordinarily good piece of work. I do not know a man
					with a more brilliant genius or a more amiable heart. In all his work we see the same spark &#8211; the same scintillation &#8211; what is the
					word that is needed? &#8211; the same play of imagination &#8211; the same depth of knowledge &#8211; the same intellectual jewellery. but he has no
					taste in his work [of poetry]. &lt;although,&gt; I think (he has always praised me strongly &amp; set me right nicely) for the
					works of others his judgement is almost Papal. Everything is flowers, and gold &amp; precious stones &#8211; for me it&#8217;s a banquet &#8211; but
					for ordinary people, the puppies of critics, they cannot pass in the same sentence with him from England to China &#8211; from this
					world to the other &#8211; from clouds with the&lt;<del rend="strikethrough">a</del>&gt;Hippogrif or the Simorg to &lt;the&gt; caves of
					Dom Daniel.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The hippogryph was a legendary flying creature, the offspring of a griffin and
						a mare; the simorg was a bird in Persian mythology and guided the hero in <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book
						11. In Book 12 Thalaba destroyed the caverns of the Dom Daniel.</note> his associations are too lively, too rapid for most
					readers, &amp; often there is something bizarre mixed in with [his] noble thoughts. You have described his review well. but why
					have you asked pardon for your praise of Wieland?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Christoph Martin Wieland (1733-1813),
						German poet and author of the epic <title>Oberon</title> (1780).</note> I have never said nor imagined that the author is not
					a man of genius. I only say that his Oberon is not a poem to my taste. I see there a man of intellect, of imagination, and,
					believe that judgement to be general. the perfect master of poetical language. but he does not have that nobility that power of
					soul with which it is absolutely necessary to sympathize &#8211; softness &#8211; sensual pleasure &#8211; that is what he loves. His genius is
					Greek I swear &#8211; but he could not have been born in the beautiful age of Greece, neither Athens nor Lacedamenon could have been the
					place of his birth, nor Minerva nor Diana<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Greek goddesses of wisdom and hunting,
						respectively.</note> the Goddess of his vows. He <del rend="strikethrough">must be</del> &lt;would be&gt; Cypriot, the priest
					of the most beautiful, but not the best of the Goddesses.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Aphrodite, goddess of love, who
						was particularly associated with Cyprus.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The fate of Thalaba is very similar to that of his author, his reputation is made &#8211; but for his fortune &#8211; alas! &#8211;
					no matter! one does not feel, the other does not care, &amp; both will live.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This morning, for the first time, an invitation from M. Edgeworth<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard
						Lovell Edgeworth (1744-1817; <title>DNB</title>), educational writer and engineer, who lived on his family estate at
						Edgeworthstown, County Longford.</note> to his ch&#226;teau has reached me, that is verbally, by a young Irishman<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> a man of wit &amp; what is better, a good democrat. I beg you to give my
					thanks to Madame Beddoes<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Anna Beddoes (1773-1824), daughter of Richard Lovell Edgeworth
						and wife of Thomas Beddoes.</note> for her father. I feel myself truly obliged, &amp; I hope to benefit from his courtesy in
					the future. perhaps my friend we will travel together in Ireland &#8211; the mountains, the rocks, the wild people &#8211; could there be more
					to make it A Picturesque Journey &#8211; better than that of your friend M. Bourrit<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Marc
						Theodore Bourrit (1739-1819), Swiss travel writer, especially about the Alps.</note> who has written about your country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> is not returning to Ireland. Here he does not have so good a salary, but
					it is worth more than a few 100 &#163; to live among civilised people. His house<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">As Secretary
						to The Speaker, Rickman had an official residence in the corner of Palace Yard, Westminster, and adjoining The Speaker&#8217;s own
						house.</note> is charming &#8211; the garden is on the banks of the Thames &#8211; there is not a more pleasant dwelling-place in that
					great city. <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> was at my house last night. he is very well &#8211; this evening James
						Tobin<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">James Webbe Tobin (1767-1814; <title>DNB</title>), poet and abolitionist.</note>
					is coming to supper here, he wishes to see the great Pagan Thomas Taylor,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Taylor
						(1758-1835; <title>DNB</title>), philosopher and translator. He published the first English translation of the complete works
						of Plato in 1804.</note> &amp; I think we will have a very edifying <hi rend="ital">discussion</hi> between a man who believes
					in a thousand gods &amp; a man who does not believe in one. the great Pagan has translated all the works of Plato &#8211; the Duke of
						Norfolk<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Howard, 11th Duke of Norfolk (1746-1815; <title>DNB</title>), Whig
						politician.</note> is paying for the printing &#8211; the Duke, says his protege, &#8216;puts me in mind of a fine saying of Plato &#8211; in
					men of vice there is a respect for virtue by which they sometimes do virtuous things &#8211; that is an honest Pagan.&#8217;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have begun preliminary Dealings with my Booksellers<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Longman and Rees.
						They wished Southey to put his name to his proposed translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> the
						Maecen&#232;s<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Cilnius Maecenas (70-8 BC), a famous patron of the arts.</note> of
					English literature. I do not know if we will agree on the Terms. If they want me to sign my Name I will let you know, &amp;
					perhaps beg &#8211; for your assistance. The disagreement is over &lt;my&gt; name that I do not want to give, because it may harm me
					like a statesman. But for the first &lt;time&gt; I have learnt that Robert Southey is worth 40 &#163;.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot make my compliments in this language &#8211; but I beg you to say for me English words of the greatest and
					truest affection &amp; esteem to your friend <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> and <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">his good mother</ref> &#8211; he &amp; she [are] the best &amp; the most dear of all my friends.
					&amp; believe me, notwithstanding your terrible name. M. the King I am truly in bad grammar your friend</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> R Southey.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1802-04-16">April 16. 1802 </date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>