<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce310</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.301</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>MS has not
                        survived.  Previously  published: Monthly Magazine, 5 (April
                        1798), 275–276 [from where the text is taken] under the pseudonym ‘T. Y.’
                        For attribution to Southey, see Kenneth Curry, ‘Southey’s contributions to
                            The Monthly Magazine and The Athenaeum’,
                            The Wordsworth Circle, 11 (1980), 216.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="301" type="letter">
<head>301. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>
</ref>, <date when="1798-04">[April
                        1798]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has not
                        survived<lb/>Previously published: <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 5 (April
                        1798), 275–276 [from where the text is taken] under the pseudonym ‘T. Y.’
                        For attribution to Southey, see Kenneth Curry, ‘Southey’s contributions to
                            <title>The Monthly Magazine</title> and <title>The Athenaeum</title>’,
                            <title>The Wordsworth Circle</title>, 11 (1980), 216.</note>
</head>
<p>The second volume contains the “<hi rend="ital">Selva Military
                        Politica,</hi>”<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A mis-spelling of
                        ‘Selva Militar y Politica’ (1652), in <title>Obras Poéticas del Conde Don
                            Bernardino Rebolledo</title>, 4 vols (Madrid, 1778).</note> “a work
                    (says Don Juan de Sedano) truly masterly and unique in its kind; it is our most
                    celebrated and most useful didactic poem.”<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan José Lopez de Sedano (1729-1801), <title>El Parnaso
                            Español</title>, 9 vols (Madrid, 1768-1778), V, p. xlv.</note> It should be
                    remembered, that when this panegyric was published, Yriarte<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tomas de Iriarte y Orpesa (1750–1791) Spanish
                        poet whose works included <title>La Musica</title> (1779).</note> had not
                    written his admirable poem upon music: “with incomparable skill, and singular
                    genius to lay down the rules and precepts of military duty, and of the most
                    sound policy.”<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan José Lopez de Sedano,
                            <title>El Parnaso Español</title>, 9 vols (Madrid, 1768-1778), V, p. xlv.</note>
                    The “<hi rend="ital">Art of War</hi>” of Rebolledo will not bear comparison with
                    Mr. Fawcett’s excellent poem,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Fawcett (c. 1758–1804; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Art of War. A
                            Poem</title> (1795).</note> a work which it would be unjust to mention
                    without the highest approbation: yet is it respectable both for poetry and
                    morality, when we recollect, that it has been written nearly a century and a
                    half, and that its author was a count and an ambassador.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> This poem begins with the existence of God, an explanation of the
                    trinity, the history of the devil, an account of chaos, of the creation and
                    fall; the progress of society is then described, and Rebolledo asserts, that
                    distinctions were first made by nature, who gave active and enterprising minds
                    to the rulers, and fitted the others for subjection, by making them stupid,
                    indolent, and contented. If indolent and contented stupidity should characterise
                    the governed, and active and enterprising minds were designed by nature to rule,
                    this system has been strangely inverted.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The author next examines the various forms of government, and
                    points out the inconveniences of all. He allows the dangers of monarchy, but
                    observes that, in a christian state, these dangers are not to be feared. The
                    right divine is asserted, and as the consummation of this policy, we have
                    immediately the art of war.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> To this poem sixteen little pieces are added, each containing
                    some example from history. One of these is upon the death of Uriah, and it
                    concludes thus: “if good kings can act thus wickedly, what ought we not to fear
                    from tyrants?” <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">2 <title>Samuel</title>
                        11–12; King David desired Bathsheba, the wife of one of his captains, Uriah
                        the Hittite, so he ordered Uriah to be put in the most dangerous position in
                        a forthcoming battle. Southey’s translation is from <title>Obras Poéticas
                            del Conde Don Bernardino Rebolledo</title>, 4 vols (Madrid, 1778), II,
                        p. 376.</note> Perhaps Rebolledo had seen Algernon Sidney<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Algernon Sidney (1623–1683; <title>DNB</title>),
                        English republican politician. He served as a commissioner to negotiate a
                        peace between Denmark and Sweden in 1659. Bernardino de Rebolledo
                        (1597–1676) had been an envoy to the Danish court in 1649–1652.</note> at
                    Copenhagen; for this and the following poem seem more like the sentiments of an
                    Englishman at that period, than of a Spaniard.</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3"> Not long this fearful conflict shall endure,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> That arms the earth with light’ning, that
                        o’erspreads</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Earth with its horrors, making the firm globe</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Tremble. Not long these terrors shall endure,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> That seem as they appall’d the fires of
                        heav’n,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> For night approaches now, preserving night,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And war will sleep in darkness. But the chief</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Stretch’d forth his hand, and bade the sun stand
                        still</l>
<l rend="indent3"> On Gibeon; “and thou, moon, o’er the vale</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Of Ajalon, till vengeance be complete!”</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And wherefore did the harmonies of heav’n</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Cease at the voice of Joshua? The Most High,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> He who is just, suspended nature’s laws,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> That kings might meet the meed they merited.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Obras Poéticas del Conde Don
                                Bernardino Rebolledo</title>, 4 vols (Madrid, 1778), II, pp.
                            377–378. The translation is probably Southey’s own, see
                                <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                            (London, 1849–1850), IV, p. 272, where it is dated 30 January
                            1798.</note>
</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent1"> The third volume is composed of religious poems, chiefly
                    paraphrased from the bible; among these are versions of the psalms, of the book
                    of Job, and of the Lamentations of Jeremiah. These he dedicated to Christina,
                    queen of Sweden;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Christina (1626–1689;
                        Queen of Sweden 1632–1654), abdicated and became a Catholic.</note> and the
                    Spanish editor says, they may greatly have contributed to the conversion of that
                    princess to the Catholic faith. His version of the Lamentations concludes with
                    the doxology, and with a declaration that he lays it at the feet of the church
                    with all catholic obedience.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Obras Poéticas del Conde Don Bernardino Rebolledo</title>, 4
                        vols (Madrid, 1778), III, p. 388.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> In this volume the history of the “<hi rend="ital">New
                        Testament</hi>” is thrown into a sacred Idylium. He commences it by saying,
                    that the mysteries of our redemption are properly concealed in the sacred books,
                    lest they should get into the profane hands of the vulgar: and the introduction
                    concludes thus; “ye who heard the profane thoughts of my first follies, hear now
                    my last accents, though not so poetical, much more pious.”<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Obras Poéticas del Conde Don Bernardino
                            Rebolledo</title>, 4 vols (Madrid, 1778), III, pp. 415-416.</note> He
                    then explains how the word was united to the flesh hypostatically; and this is a
                    fine instance of the <hi rend="ital">sesquipedalia verba</hi>,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A foot and a half long word.</note> as it has a
                    whole line to itself, “hipostaticamente.”<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Obras Poéticas del Conde Don Bernardino
                            Rebolledo</title>, 4 vols (Madrid, 1778), III, p. 416.</note> The
                    Franciscan dogma is elucidated by the usual comparison of the sun-beams passing
                    through glass; and by another, which I do not recollect elsewhere; “as the dew
                    falls upon the earth, without disturbing the air.”<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Obras Poéticas del Conde Don Bernardino
                            Rebolledo</title>, 4 vols (Madrid, 1778), III, p. 416.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The “<hi rend="ital">Selvas Danicas</hi>” fill the last volume, a
                    genealogical poem upon the succession of the kings of Denmark.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Obras Poéticas del Conde Don Bernardino
                            Rebolledo</title>, 4 vols (Madrid, 1778), IV.</note> This work I have
                    never seen.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Such are the works of Rebolledo, who “to the manners of a
                    Christian <hi rend="ital">and of a cavalier</hi>, united the virtues and
                    endowments that constitute a hero; such as <hi rend="ital">nobility of blood,
                        and good fortune in his undertakings:</hi> and here (says Sedano)<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan José Lopez de Sedano, <title>El
                            Parnaso Español</title>, 9 vols (Madrid, 1768-1778), V, xl.</note> I will no
                    longer delay a reflection, that has often occurred to me in collecting the
                    memoirs of our illustrious Spanish poets; and that is, that the epithet <hi rend="ital">illustrious</hi> is perfectly applicable with regard to their
                    blood; not that this is any recommendation of the intrinsic merit of the
                    sciences; but because it confirms the opinion of those, who think that good
                    blood and an illustrious education contribute to a love of, and progress in
                    letters. He then shows, that it is not absolutely necessary that a good poet
                    should be poor.</p>
<closer>
<signed rend="right">T.Y.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
