<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce568</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.559</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Previously  published: Adolfo Cabral
                        (ed.), Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800–1801
                            and a Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                    140–143.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="559" type="letter">
<head>559. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1800-12-08">8 December 1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: [deletions and
                        readdress in another hand] To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        M.P./ <del rend="strikethrough">5. Stone Buildings/ Lincolns Inn/
                            London</del> Wynnstay / Wrexham/ Wales <lb/>Stamped:
                        LISBON<lb/>Postmarks: FOREIGN OFFICE/ DE/ 25/ 1800; DE/ 25/
                        1800<lb/>Endorsements: Dec. 8 1800; 25 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
<lb/>MS:
                        National Library of Wales, MS 4811D<lb/>Previously published: Adolfo Cabral
                        (ed.), <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800–1801
                            and a Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                    140–143.</note>
</head>
<p> Lisbon. <date when="1800-12-08">December 8. 1800.
                    Monday</date>
</p>
<p>My dear Wynn</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your letter reached me yesterday, only 13 days after its date. it
                    may be worth while to tell you that the Lisbon mail leaves London every Tuesday.
                    a days delay in writing therefore loses that mail &amp; probably that
                    packet.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am troubled in spirit about a Xmas ballad. I have conned &amp;
                    reconned all my stock-stories, &amp; cannot catch fire. there are plenty of
                    seeds but the soil is not prepared for them. my head is full of history &amp; my
                    very dreams made up of chronicles &amp; records. poetry written out of season is
                    as vapid as forced fruits. my best pieces have ever been written most rapidly,
                    three or four during the same heat. If I had stiled the books of Thalaba Fits
                    this old word would have been strictly applicable. – however I am straining a
                    costive brain – to what purport I know not. There was a Bishop of Bremen <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> &lt;seen&gt; once in a ship full sail <hi rend="ital">against</hi> the wind – going to old Beelzebub in Mount
                        Hecla.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">‘How the Bishop of Bremen went
                        to Hell by water’, <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4
                        series (London, 1849–1850), IV, p. 274.</note> but whether you will have
                    him. – or the Monk that dipt down a volcano with a brass bucket for gold<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Dominican dipping for gold in a
                        volcano’, <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849–1850), IV, p. 274.</note> – or a corpse-candle story<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed.
                        John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, p. 212.</note> – may be
                    perhaps written upon the great adamantine table by the self-moving pearl
                        pen<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 11, line 363 and Note, from Lodovico
                        Maracci (1612–1700), <title>Alcorani Textus Universus</title>, 2 vols
                        (Padua, 1698), I, part 2, p. 94.</note> – but ink &amp; grey goosequill have
                    yet done nothing. most probably I shall send you some headless &amp; tail-less
                    story, which <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> &lt;has&gt; the polypus power of
                    growing at both ends. Old Nick is grown too familiar – a mealy-faced Mumbo Jumbo
                    would excite more wonder in a ballad or a masquerade.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> is gone to <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx</del> England. a small living has become vacant
                    in his own gift &amp; he went to present himself.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill was Chancellor of Hereford Cathedral. This gave
                        him the right to appoint the incumbent of the joint living of Little
                        Hereford and Ashford Carbonell. The post became vacant in 1800 and Herbert
                        Hill appointed himself to the living on 5 December 1800.</note> its clear
                    value does not exceed 60 £ after paying a curate – but it was worth the voyage.
                    We therefore removed into his house for the convenience of having the Library
                    &amp; Cellar at hand. moreover there was a fire-place to tempt us.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am delighted with historical labour.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished ‘History of Portugal’.</note> the
                    materials are ample &amp; excellent. beginning with Count Henrique<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Henrique (1066–1112; Count of Portugal
                        1093–1112), re-established Portugal’s separate identity.</note> there is
                    much preliminary matter needful. I think the fabulous history ought summarily to
                    be given. Milton<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Milton (1608–1674;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of Britain, that Part Especially
                            Called England; From the Beginning, Continued to the Norman
                            Conquest</title> (1670).</note> thought so – &amp; I love old Geoffrey
                    of Monmouth<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Geoffrey of Monmouth (c.
                        1100– c. 1155), <title>Historia Regum Britanniae</title>.</note> and he
                    ought to be kept in countenance by showing that these as great liars as the
                    Welsh. What can be gleaned from the classical writers respecting the old
                    Lusitanians ought to have its place. the Gothic period is all a barbarous
                    confusion – &amp; had better be made into a sort of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                    Pelaye chapter<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptiste de la Curne
                        de Sainte-Pelaye (1697–1781), compiler of the 40-volume manuscript,
                        ‘Dictionnaire des Antiquites Francaises’.</note> – an historical sketch of
                    manners. afterwards it will be best to insert as far as can well be done all
                    traits of costume in the main story. I do not strip off all the embroidery of
                    miracles. Popery has acted a higher part than Paganism – &amp; the monks have as
                    much right to have their rogueries related as the Priest of Delphi<del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> much however of all this descend to the
                    bottom of the page, – <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxx</del> – blessed be the
                    man who invented notewriting! –</p>
<p rend="indent1"> The scarcity: – you will doubtless foreknow my opinion as to the
                    main cause, a failing harvest &amp;c are only aiding &amp; abetting
                    circumstances. the enormous war expences pressing upon all parts of the
                    community must inevitably occasion a rise in the price of provisions
                    proportionate to that of every thing else. not that peace can immediately
                    alleviate the evil. tis a gloomy prospect. the funding system seems to have
                    nearly reached its utmost extent – the burden is so heavy upon the poor that
                    their distresses are made the subject of parliamentary discussion. I should hope
                    for a radical remedy if I saw the possibility of one. but relief can hardly be
                    expected – &amp; nothing can be more likely to render a populace turbulent than
                    assistance with whose manner they will always be dissatisfied – &amp; which –
                    instead of to humanity – they will always attribute to fear. I never here see
                    the papers – nor have I any wish. conversation informs me of any important
                    event. I long for peace because the evil of continued war is certain &amp; the
                    good very doubtful. I should also rejoice to hear of a change in ministry, but
                    this is not probable. no middle standard is hoisted.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Lately my health has been comfortable. indeed I like the climate
                    so well that if there were any possible situation <del rend="strikethrough">here
                        xx</del> &lt;in&gt; which I could settle, there would be very little
                    hesitation about giving up England. except climate <del rend=" xx">xx</del>
                    Portugal has little to recommend it – &amp; the only person in whose intimate
                    society I could take pleasure<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Identity
                        unclear, but possibly <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert
                            Hill</ref>.</note> looks on to a speedy removal. but I feel an ease here
                    which ether &amp; laudanum will hardly give me at home – &amp; in the literature
                    – it were more proper to say in the – books of the country materials might be
                    found for long amusement &amp; useful labour. to this there are some slight
                    obstacles &amp; objections. imprimis<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Translates as ‘in the first place’.</note> the plague is likely to arrive
                    next year. 2<hi rend="sup">ds</hi> there must most inevitably be a Boderation
                        here.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A banking crisis.</note> &amp;
                    lastly it is impossible.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> But the suicide tale – I had almost forgotten. a Serjeant in our
                    cavalry here was jealous of his wifes attachment to one who held the same rank
                    in the same regiment. this man was in his manners &amp; conduct remarkably good
                    for his situation – the woman a modest &amp; interesting woman. That she was
                    improperly attached is evident from the sequel – but it is not believed that she
                    was otherwise guilty than in admitting this feeling of preference. Her husband
                    however beat her. the other man was so wretched at being the cause of this
                    quarrel that he said he would shoot himself. one night accordingly, after the
                    hour when he ought to have been in the barracks – he went into a little
                    wine-house – a taberna – shot himself &amp; died instantly. At the tidings She
                    came in – in a state of frenzy. she gathered up the blood with both her hands –
                    mingled with the dust – &amp; devoured it greedily, by handfuls. her husband
                    attempted to force her away. she called the Centinel – commanded him to take him
                    into custody for being out at that hour, &amp; threatened to report him to the
                    Colonel unless he did his duty. the fool was afraid – &amp; did so. immediately
                    she ran to a large deep well &amp; threw herself in. a weeks confinement &amp;
                    bread &amp; water were necessary to tame the husband &amp; prevent him from
                    compleating the catastrophe. They did not bring them to Lisbon for Xtian burial
                    – neither did they practise the old brutality of our custom. at low water they
                    dug a grave in the sands – one grave – &amp; the Tagus flows over it.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> If you send Lewis’s book<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Matthew Gregory Lewis (1775–1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Tales of
                            Wonder</title> (1801), which reprinted several poems by Southey.</note>
                    to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Danvers</ref>. 9 S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> James Place. <ref target="places.html#KingsdownParade">Kingsdown</ref>. Bristol – he will send
                    it in a parcel. I dread having it by post. the letter your brother<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Watkin Williams Wynn (1772–1840).</note> was
                    to send from the Secretary of States Office came as usual thro the Post office.
                    your last I know not how – but General Fraser<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Simon Fraser (1738–1813), major-general in command of British
                        forces in Portugal 1797–1800.</note> sent it me. To my great joy I have at
                    last got the Guerras Civiles do Granada<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Gines Perez de Hita (1544? –1619?), <title>Historia de los Vandos, de los
                            Cegries, y Abencerrages, cavalleros moros de Granada, y les civiles
                            guerras que huvo en ella, hasta que el Rey Don Fernando el Quinto la
                            gano</title> (1595–1619), no. 3403 in the sale catalogue of Southey's
                        library.</note> – with a second volume by the same author bringing it down
                    to their expulsion. God bless you. I shall send something by the next packet –
                    &amp; the parts of Thalaba – which will at least prevent you from going empty
                    handed.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
