<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce753</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.744</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Houghton
                        Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (6).  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="744" type="letter">
        <head>744. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1802-12-21">21 December
                        1802</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ G
                        C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster/ Single
                        <lb />Postmarks: [partial] 122/ DEC; B/ DEC 22/ 1802<lb />MS: Houghton
                        Library, bMS Eng 265.1 (6)<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="center"> Kehamiana 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="center"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Invent me a name instead of Book<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">This letter is a response to Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s criticism of
                        the final part of Book 1 of an early version of the <title>Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810), which Southey had sent to him on [c. 30 November
                        1802], Letter 738. Bedford&#8217;s critique has not survived.</note> &#8211; or Canto.
                    instead of 10 &#8211; or 12 books I shall find it convenient to divide the poem into
                    shorter portions. Scene will not do, because progression from one scene to
                    another is often part of the poem. Chapter &amp; Section are ugly words. &amp;
                    Song &#8211; which else were the best of all &#8211; is abused for what was never intended
                    to be sung. Fit &amp; Rhapsody are affected &amp; loathsome. Part. is good
                    English but I likes it not. Canticle would be better than Canto &#8211; but then you
                    know the Song of Songs<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Book of the
                        Old Testament usually known as the <title>Song of Songs</title>. It is
                        sometimes called the Canticle, a shortened version of the Latin Canticum
                        Canticorum. The alleged author is Solomon (c. 1011-c. 932 BC, King of Israel
                        971-932 BC).</note> has but that modest title, &amp; it would not be modest
                    to imitate Solomon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> However I object to Fit &#8211; by fits the poem will be written &#8211;
                    &amp; I am glad to feel a fit coming on. weak eyes will force me to poetry, yet
                    in truth a certain dissatisfaction at what I have done has been the main cause
                    why Kehama has lain so long on hand. there is a piece-meal-ness of plot &#8211; it is
                    federal plot instead of being one &amp; indivisible &#8211; &amp; unity is my creed in
                    all things. I have planned how to make the Curse operate <del rend="strikethrough">in each &amp; every part</del> to Kalyals preservation
                        <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> as it relates to Water &#8211; Fire &amp;
                    Death. that with respect to food &amp; sleep it should not quadrate is no fault.
                    it need not fit like your </p>
        <p rend="center">[Southey draws a mock, scrawled signature]</p>
        <lb />
        <p>upon a bankers check or a Consuls testimonial.</p>
        <p rend="center"> ___</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your first objection &#8211; to &#8216;obedient to the call&#8217; &#8211; is not valid &#8211;
                    have the goodness to all my is&#8217;s &amp; is nots &#8211; to affix an I think or an in my
                    opinion subintellecto modesti&#230; gratia?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;unintelligently for the sake of modesty&#8217;.</note> a
                    man goes to the gallows obediently, for &lt;then&gt; as the learned Prelate<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Richard Watson (1737&#8211;1816;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Llandaff.</note> who is about as orthodox
                    in his politics as his religion observes &#8211; he has nothing to do with the law
                        <del rend="strikethrough">than</del> but to obey it. Shrieking &#8211; I cannot
                    judge of that for blockhead like I forgot to correct my own copy by yours &amp;
                    that passage was altered &#8211;but I see you would drive my poor metre mad by putting
                    shrieking at the end of a line &amp; make it no metre at all. sprung &#8211; clung &#8211;
                    hung &#8211; the rhymes have a merit, &amp; one might fancy in them a sameness of
                    feeling &amp; action. Of the passage you have written you will see lines &amp;
                    phrases whenever I recopy the book. but its too apostrophical. that note of
                    interrogation must be sparingly handled, it is playing with an edge tool to use
                    it too often. I reverse the as if despair &amp; &#8211;. scratch out &#8216;the crime is
                    his&#8217; &amp; Laderlad speaks to your feeling &amp; quite enough for mine. Kehamas
                    eye must not fascinate &#8211; you will see why at the end of the second book. the
                    Kehama reigns below is but rhyme &amp; shall go out &#8211; I want however a rhyme or
                    two in his place &#8211; they ought to ding-dong in a curse till the ears ring
                    again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You do not make out At fits to short convulsive starts was stung
                    &#8211; it is the pain &amp; shooting thrill of recovery in a dead limb. the pain of
                    drowning is nothing, except when wilful and accompanied with strong mental
                    agitation: recovery on the contrary is very painful, I knew a man who had
                    experience &amp; told me this. Laderlad could not bear a hand on his head
                    because it was throbbing in a high fever. &#8211; did you ever come near your fathers
                    hand when it was gouty?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now for the rest of the poem you may have it in what shape
                    you will &#8211; but in truth I think letters better &#8211; because if you think proper to
                    bind the whole the letters may come in as interludes between the acts, being all
                    of one size &#8211; &amp; so you will have the hints &amp; the poem &amp; the
                    criticism &#8211; the meat &amp; the sauce, the egg &amp; the chicken all together.
                    But this is as you please &#8211; &amp; the sooner you let me know the sooner you will
                    have the second book for I am now half way thro the third.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know the Vedas are the Brahminical bibles. now one of these
                    Vedas has been translated into French,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Guillaume de Clermont-Lodeve, Baron Sante-Croix (1746-1809),
                            <title>Ezour-Vedam</title> (1778), though this was not in fact an
                        authentic translation of a Sanskrit work.</note> &amp; if you could get it
                    for me you would be my magnus Apollo.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Latin translates as &#8216;great Apollo&#8217;, Publius Vergilius Maro (70-19 BC),
                            <title>Eclogue 3</title>, line 104.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> will perhaps have
                    the goodness to enquire at the foreign bookseller when he goes there. The only
                    writer of late years who has at all methodised the system is Sonnerat<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre Sonnerat (1748-1814), <title>Voyage aux
                            Indes Orientales et a la Chine</title> (1782).</note> &#8211; from Sir W
                        Jones<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir William Jones (1746-1794;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Britain&#8217;s foremost orientalist.</note> you learn
                    little unless you previously have read much. his information is scattered &amp;
                    execrably arranged. Some of the old Dutchmen give a far clearer account. I have
                    sent to Italy for the fullest &amp; last work the Systema Bramanicum of Fra.
                    Paolo de San Bartolomeo.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Paulinus a
                        Sancto Bartholomaeo (1748-1806), <title>Systema Brahmani, et Liturgicum
                            Mythologicum</title> (1791), no. 2143 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> with these helps I shall do something &#8211; &amp; am killing two
                    birds with one stone, for all the knowledge I acquire for Kehama will be
                    necessary for the Oriental part of my history.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you seen the Scotch Review of Thalaba?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 1 (October
                        1802), 63-83, carried <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis
                            Jeffrey&#8217;s</ref> hostile review of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801).</note> of which <del rend="strikethrough">is good</del> what is good
                    is not about Thalaba, &amp; what is about Thalaba is not good. <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">the Critic</ref> says there is no
                    invention in Thalaba. now Grosvenor I will tell you what I think of the Critic &#8211;
                    to speak mildly of him &#8211; as one always should in these cases he is a damnd lying
                    Scotch son of a bitch.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Eyes better. but I cannot have the Welsh house &amp; that is a
                    sore disappointment for I made sure of it. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> well. oh I had
                    almost forgot a poem</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent2"> Grosvenor has a dog &amp; his dogs name is Snivel</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> I have a daughter &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">my daughters</ref> name is
                    Drivel.</p>
        <lb />
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Vale vale me sodali &#8211;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as &#8216;farewell, farewell, my
                            friend&#8217;.</note>
          </salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1802-12-21">Tuesday 21. Dec. 1802.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>