<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce385</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.376</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS has
                        not survived.  Previously  published: Monthly
                            Magazine, 7 (Feb 1799), 125&#8211;126 [from where
                        the text is taken] under the pseudonym &#8216;S.R.&#8217;. New
                        attribution to Southey.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.376" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="376" type="letter">
        <head>376. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>
          </ref>, <date when="1799-02-04">4 February 1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has
                        not survived<lb />Previously published: <title>Monthly
                            Magazine</title>, 7 (Feb 1799), 125&#8211;126 [from where
                        the text is taken] under the pseudonym &#8216;S.R.&#8217;. New
                        attribution to Southey.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>MR. EDITOR,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the 13th volume of the works of Louis de
                        Saint-Simon,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis de Rouvroy, Duc de Saint-Simon (1675&#8211;1755),
                            <title>Oeuvres Complettes</title> (1791).</note>
                    printed at Strasburg in 1791, I find some curious remarks on
                    the ecclesiastical discipline of Spain, and on the authority
                    of the Inquisition, which I flatter myself will not be
                    unacceptable to your readers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;One day,&#8221; says the duke, &#8220;the Archbishop of
                    Toledo took me aside, and with the most lively emotions,
                    said to me: for Heaven&#8217;s sake, Sir, let your bishops in
                    France beware of the following the example of their brethren
                    here in Spain. For, by little and little, Rome has brought
                    us under her yoke, and reduced us to mere cyphers in our own
                    dioceses. Mere priests of the inquisition are become our
                    teachers and our masters, and are in possession of our
                    authority; and we are daily indebted to our very servants
                    for the information, that a decree on doctrinal points is
                    affixed to the doors of our cathedrals, of which we had no
                    previous knowledge, but to which we must submit without
                    reply. The correction of vice and the regulation of the
                    manners of the people belongs also to the inquisition. In
                    the concerns of the bishop&#8217;s court, whoever pleases may
                    disregard the proper officers and go to the tribunal of the
                    nuncio, where, if dissatisfied with his officers too, he has
                    only to appeal from their decision to that of the nuncio. So
                    that, deprived as we are of all authority, we have only the
                    powers of ordination and of confirmation left us: in truth,
                    we are no longer the bishops of our own dioceses. The pope
                    is the immediate bishop of every diocese here, and we are no
                    more than his vicars, consecrated indeed, and mitred, but
                    for the sole purpose ordaining priests, and of performing a
                    few other manual operations, without daring to intermeddle
                    with, otherwise than by blindly submitting to, the
                    inquisition, the nunciature, and whatever is sent us from
                    Rome: and should a bishop happen to displease them in the
                    smallest tittle, he is instantly punished, without being
                    allowed to offer any thing in his own defence; because
                    nothing less than the submission of deaf and dumb animals is
                    expected from him. It seldom indeed happens now, that any
                    one is sent to the prison of the inquisition, or to Rome,
                    bound and gagged, because these instances, in past times,
                    have been too frequent, and because they wish to run no
                    risk; yet we are not entirely without such punishments, and
                    these very recent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Judge then, Sir, what weight and authority
                    the constitution can derive from the acceptance of bishops
                    thus enslaved, as we in Italy, Portugal, and Spain are; and
                    from the universities, the doctors, and the secular,
                    regular, and monastic bodies of the clergy in the same
                    countries. But this is not all. Do you imagine that a single
                    individual among us would have accepted the bull, if the
                    pope had not, by his nuncio, commanded it? Our very
                    acceptance of it would itself have been a crime, which would
                    not long have remained unpunished. It would have been deemed
                    an encroachment on the infallibility of the holy father; for
                    to dare to accept what he decides, is to judge that he has
                    decided aright. Now who are we to add our judgment to that
                    of the Pope? When he has spoken, silence and blind obedience
                    are our portion: we must bow down in perfect adoration to
                    what he has said, and surrender, as I may say, into his
                    hands, our will, memory, and understanding. So that far from
                    daring to contradict, move any amendment, or ask for any
                    explication, we are not allowed to approve, accept, or do
                    any thing, that bespeaks an active part in what he
                    decrees.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Such, Sir, is the nature of the acceptance
                    given by Spain, by Portugal, and by Italy, and which I find,
                    is so much extolled in France, and held out as the free
                    judgment and approbation of all the churches and schools!
                    But, in truth, they are no better than slaves, whose matter
                    has condescended to open his lips, and has prescribed the
                    form of words that they are to pronounce, and which, without
                    the change of a letter, or an iota, they have servilely
                    pronounced. This is the pretended judgment, that is so much
                    talked of in France, and which we have given indeed
                    unanimously, because the same form was prescribed to us
                    all!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;At this view of the calamitous situation of
                    the church, the archbishop could no longer contain himself,
                    but melted into tears. He intreated me, for obvious reasons,
                    not to mention to any one what he had said. Accordingly I
                    kept the secret inviolably as long as he lived, but as he is
                    now no more, I think myself equally bound to reveal it to
                    the world.&#8221;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis de
                        Rouvroy, Duc de Saint-Simon, <title>Oeuvres
                            Complettes</title>, 13 vols (Strasburg, 1791), XIII,
                        pp. 245&#8211;248.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The inquisition, Mr. Editor, which generally
                    narrows and debases the mind of those who live within the
                    sphere of its activity, had little or no effect, it seems,
                    on this sensible primate of Spain, whoever he was &#8211; for I am
                    not sufficiently conversant in the history of Roman
                    Catholics to know his name, nor of what constitution and
                    bull he speaks, unless of that which is called
                        <title>Unigenitus</title>, which, as history tells us,
                    convulsed all France and Flanders in the beginning of the
                    present century<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Papal Bull Unigenitus, issued in 1713, condemned as
                        heretical the 101 Propositions of the Jansenist Pasquier
                        Quesnel (1643&#8211;1719).</note> &#8211; yet, as his language
                    appears to be so very unusual in the mouths of bishops of
                    the Romish communion, I shall be glad to learn, from some of
                    your correspondents, what degree of credit is due to Louis
                    de Saint-Simon, and to the archbishop. Permit me also to
                    ask, whether the inquisition ever found its way into England
                    before the Reformation; or whether any such tribunal now
                    exists among the Roman Catholics of this kingdom. I hope,
                    for the credit of Englishmen, they are under no such baneful
                    influence. Yet as they acknowledge the Bishop of Rome to be
                    the head of their church, they cannot but be influenced, in
                    some degree, by him. What then has hitherto been the nature
                    of this influence? and, what change is it likely to undergo
                    from the present state of affairs at Rome?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Rome had been occupied by
                        French troops in February 1798 and a client Roman
                        Republic inaugurated. However, the Inquisition had never
                        operated in England.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="right">S. R. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1799-02-04">February 4th, 1799.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>