<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce493</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.484</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bristol Reference Library,
                        B20862.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols
                        (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    220&#8211;223.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.484" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="484" type="letter">
        <head>484. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>,
                        <date when="1800-02-02">2&#8211;3 February 1800</date>
          </head><p>Address:
                        To/ Lieutenant Thomas Southey/ Bellona/ Torbay/
                        Single<lb />MS: Bristol Reference Library,
                        B20862<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols
                        (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    220&#8211;223.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My letter must have reached you while yours
                    was on the road. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mothers</ref> desk arrived safely &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> has
                    rigged himself with the money you sent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My life is almost as uniform as yours, &amp;
                    as barren of all occurrencies wherewith to fill a letter. we
                    are both perpetually busy in unvarying employments. the
                    knowledge of this makes me an unfrequent correspondent &#8211; to
                    write is only to spin out into a sheetfull information not
                    more than the answer to a How d&#8217;ye do <del rend="strikethrough">?</del> &#8211; question. You ask me my
                    opinion of peace. nothing but a series of defeats or a
                    change of ministers can give it to us. the answer to
                    Bonapartes offers is the most clumsy piece of insolence
                    &amp; inconceivable stupidity that ever disgraced an
                    obstinate minister.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">As soon as Napoleon took power in the Brumaire coup of
                        November 1799 he instituted a number of peace feelers
                        towards members of the Second Coalition. William Wyndham
                        Grenville, Baron Grenville (1759&#8211;1834; Foreign Secretary
                        1791&#8211;1801; <title>DNB</title>), gave a lengthy speech to
                        the House of Lords on 27 January 1800 outlining the
                        history of the French approaches and explaining why the
                        British government had declined to negotiate.</note>
                    they cannot treat with France because she does not
                    acknowledge herself the aggressor &#8211; France had made no such
                    acknowledgement when they treated last. They cannot treat
                    because the French government has not existed long enough.
                    the then French government had existed <hi rend="ital">not
                        so long</hi> when they treated last. they would treat if
                    France restored her old monarchy &#8211; yet they disclaim <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> the idea of forcing a
                    government of their chusing upon France &#8211; &amp; yet they
                    continue the war because France chuses one herself. &amp;
                    this is all <hi rend="ital">except</hi> personal insults to
                    Bonaparte! &amp; all these absurdities &amp; contradictions
                    are in the note &#8211; &amp; for these reasons we are to have
                    another campaign &amp; another expedition! Amen &#8211; so be
                    it!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the mean time what have our ministers done
                    &#8211; they have intercepted some Letters from Egypt &#8211; they have
                    forged others &#8211; they have put these papers into the hands of
                        <ref target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffard</ref>
                    the satirist &#8211; who has interlarded them with the rankest
                    &amp; most virulent abuse of Bonaparte &#8211; they have published
                    all this by Authority &#8211; &amp; thus contrived to <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx</del> throw another obstacle
                    in the way of peace &#8211; by rendering themselves the personal
                    enemies of the Chief Consul.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably <title>Copies of Original
                            Letters from the Army of General Bonaparte in
                            Egypt</title> (1798), which had gone into numerous
                        expanded editions since its first publication by the
                        loyalist bookseller and propagandist John Wright
                        (1770/71&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Good God
                    admitting that he was the worst of all rascals &#8211; what is
                    that to us? &#8211; they have as much right to force a wise
                    governor upon us, as we have to force an honest one upon
                    them. &amp; when this man whom they so vilify &#8211; is Napoleone
                    Bonaparte! &#8211; I do not justify his assumption of power &#8211; let
                    the use he makes of it, do that. but in reviewing his past
                    conduct &#8211; what I privately know of his youth &#8211; what all the
                    world know of his actions &#8211; the rank he holds as a general &#8211;
                    the views he entertains as a philosopher &#8211; the feelings
                    which made him in the career of victory the advocate of
                    peace &#8211; I do not hesitate in pronouncing him the greatest
                    man that events have called into action since Alexander of
                        Macedon.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander III, the Great (356&#8211;323 BC; King of Macedonia
                        336&#8211;323 BC).</note> &#8211; And for what is the valour of
                    Englishmen to be exerted, is the treasure &amp; the blood of
                    the country to be drained? to aggrandize Austria &#8211; &amp; to
                    restore the worthless Bourbons<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The ruling dynasty of France since
                        1589.</note> to that throne, from which for so many
                    years they harrassed &amp; distressed this country!! as if
                    this were possible! &#8211; if Bonaparte could land a million of
                    Frenchmen in England do you believe that he could compel the
                    English to submit to a government of French fashion? &amp;
                    have not Frenchmen the same feeling of indignation? have
                    they not the spirit of men &#8211; &amp; numbers enough to trample
                    under foot all the savages of Tartary<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Russia was a member of the
                        Second Coalition formed in 1798.</note> that can be
                    pourd among them?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a dawn of hope but a feeble one in
                    the sentiments expressed by some of the House of Lords<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wyndham
                        Grenville had given a speech to the House of Lords on 27
                        January 1800 on the government&#8217;s refusal to negotiate
                        with Napoleon; it had been heavily criticised by Whig
                        Peers like Francis Russell, 5th Duke of Bedford
                        (1765&#8211;1802; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; they continue
                    to vote with the Minister but blame him for not negotiating.
                    &#8211; &amp; the debates in the Commons have been twice delayed
                    because some of the Members have qualms of conscience to be
                    settled. Could we but shake off these accursed ministers &#8211;
                    could we but once see the activity &amp; the courage &amp;
                    the wealth of England well employed &#8211; what might we not hope
                    for! </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Enough of politics &#8211; in what has been said my
                    own peculiar notions have not intruded &#8211; they are the
                    arguments which must occur to every man whose interest has
                    not hoodwinkd his common sense. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref>
                    direction is simply Cambridge. what you say about <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> could only be answered by entering into
                    particulars, which, as they do not <del rend="strikethrough">neither</del> interest you, &amp; would not amuse you,
                    may as well be omitted. With <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> I have no
                    quarrel. he remains an acquaintance, whose faults cannot
                    injure <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del>, &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">therefore</del> shall not irritate
                    me. I had long understood his character, &amp; what I learnt
                    at <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref> in
                    confirmation of it was not from <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Poole had written to Southey on 8 August 1799
                        about Lloyd&#8217;s conduct (E.L. Griggs (ed.), <title>The
                            Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor
                        Coleridge</title>, 6 vols (Oxford, 1956&#8211;1971), I, p.
                        286).</note> I had long known that no dependance could
                    be placed upon his <hi rend="ital">conduct</hi> &#8211; &amp; is
                    it strange that his <hi rend="ital">word</hi> should be as
                    little to be relied on? yet I do not impute this to
                    conscious falshood &#8211; but to an instability of mind &#8211; perhaps
                    a derangement. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will I suppose be more at leisure, &amp;
                    may possibly come home during the summer. if I do not go
                    abroad before the Autumn I shall pass the spring &amp;
                    summer at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As you are so fond of Taunton I wish you were
                    settled there. the country in that neighbourhood which you
                    have never seen is so beautiful, that I should much like to
                    be in reach of it sometimes. beyond all comparison the North
                    of Somersetshire is the most beautiful part of England that
                    I have ever seen. &amp; if only beauty of landscape were to
                    influence me in choice of a residence &#8211; I should at once fix
                    on Porlock.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To Bristol I grow more attached. my intimacy
                    with <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> makes
                    it more agreable than it ever was before to me. if the <ref target="places.html#CollegeGreenBristol">College
                        Green</ref> were but transplanted among the Hottentots
                    then might <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                        Mother</ref> live here in peace.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp;
                            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> remembrance.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#KingsdownParade">Kingsdown.</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1800-02-02">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 2.
                            1800.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> The second Anthology<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Annual
                                Anthology</title> (1800).</note> will soon be
                        published. you have never had the first yet. where shall
                        they be directed?</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> NB. I drink Port Wine plentifully &amp;
                        &#8220;suck air out of a bag.&#8221;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had participated in
                            experiments with nitrous oxide at the Pnuematic
                            Medical Institution, Bristol. These involved
                            inhaling the gas from a green bag. Its effects on
                            Southey were described in Thomas Beddoes,
                                <title>Notice of Some Observations Made at the
                                Medical Pneumatic Institution</title> (Bristol,
                            1799), p. 11; and Humphry Davy, <title>Researches,
                                Chemical and Philosophical, Chiefly Concerning
                                Nitrous Oxide, or Dephlogisticated Nitrous Air,
                                and Its Respiration</title> (London, 1800), pp.
                            507&#8211;509. They were also parodied in &#8216;The Pneumatic
                            Revellers, An Eclogue&#8217;, <title>Anti-Jacobin
                                Review</title>, 6 (May 1800) 109&#8211;118 (esp.
                            115&#8211;116).</note>
          </p>
          <lb />
          <p>
            <date when="1800-02-03">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>
                            3.</date> Yours has just reached me. I am glad you
                        have got S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pierres book.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques-Henri
                            Bernardin de Saint Pierre (1737&#8211;1814), <title>Paul
                                et Virginie</title> (1787).</note> it is full of
                        genius, &amp; of hints which ought to be pursued. the
                            bottle-experiment<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey took up his brother&#8217;s
                            suggestion and in 1802 threw a number of bottles
                            containing messages overboard in mid-Atlantic. One
                            was washed up in the Bahamas and the message was
                            posted to Tom&#8217;s brother in England; see Robert
                            Southey to Thomas Southey, 22 April 1803, Letter
                            775.</note> I have often wished to have generally
                        tried. &#8211; <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>
                        is by no means an unwholesome place. I <hi rend="ital">took</hi> my complaint with me from <ref target="places.html#Westbury">Westbury</ref> &amp;
                            <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                            mother</ref> was never better anywhere.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 3 ... anywhere&#8217;: inserted upside down at
                            top of fol. 1 r.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>