<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce626</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.617</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Pforzheimer Collection,
                        New York Public Library, G&#8217;ANA 0032.  Previously 
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 167-171.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.617" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="617" type="letter">
        <head>617. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>,
                        <date when="1801-10-16">16 October 1801</date>
          </head><p>Watermark:
                        crown with fleur de lys<lb /> MS: Pforzheimer Collection,
                        New York Public Library, G&#8217;ANA 0032<lb />Previously
                        published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                            and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 167-171.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1801-10-16">Friday. Oct. 16 1801.</date>
          <placeName>
            <ref target="places.html#Dublin"> Dublin</ref>
          </placeName>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>Dear Edith, in my last no direction was given. you will write
                    under cover, &amp; direct exactly in this form</p>
        <p rend="indent3">
          <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> Right Honble </p>
        <p rend="indent4">
          <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Isaac Corry</ref>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent5"> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</p>
        <p rend="indent6">
          <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>.</p>
        <p>this said personage I have not yet seen, whereby I was kept
                    in a state of purportless idleness. he is gone to his own
                    country, playing truant from business among his friends.
                    tomorrow his return is probable. I like his character he
                    does business well &amp; with method, but loves his
                    amusement better than business &amp; prefers books to
                    official papers. It does not appear that my work will be
                    anyways difficult copying &amp; letter writing which any
                    body could do, if any body could be confidentially trusted.
                        <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>
                    is a great man in <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> &amp; in the eyes of the world, but not
                    one jot altered from the <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> of
                    Christ Church, save only that in compliance with an extorted
                    promise he has deprived himself of the pleasure of [MS
                    illegible] his head by putting powder on it. he has
                    astonished the people about him &#8211; the government stationer
                    hinted to him when he was giving an order, that if he wanted
                    any thing in the pocket book way &#8211; he might as well put it
                    down in the order. But he pulled his own &#8211; look Sir &#8211; I have
                    bought one for two shillings. his predecessor admonished him
                    not to let himself down by speaking to any of the clerks &#8211;
                    why Sir &#8211; said <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                        Rickman</ref> &#8211; I should not let myself down if I spoke
                    to every man between this &amp; the bridge &#8211; &amp; so he
                    goes on in his own right way. he has been obliged to mount
                    up to the third story, before he could find a room small
                    enough to sleep in &#8211; &amp; there he led me to show me his
                    government bed, which because it is a government bed
                    contains stuff enough to make a dozen &#8211; the curtains being
                    compleatly double &amp; mattress piled upon mattress, so
                    that tumbling out would be a dangerous fall. &#8211; About our
                    quarters here when we remove hither in June, he will look
                    out. the filth of the houses is intolerable &#8211; floors &amp;
                    furniture offending you with Portugueze nastiness. but it is
                    a very fine city &#8211; a magnificent city &#8211; such public
                    buildings &amp; the streets so wide. for these advantages
                        <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> is
                    indebted to the prodigal corruption of its own government.
                    every member who asked money to make improvements got it &#8211;
                    &amp; if he got 20,000 pounds &#8211; in decency spent 5 for the
                    public, &amp; pocketed the rest. these gentlemen are now
                    being hauled a little over the coals, &amp; they have grace
                    enough to thank God the Union did not take place sooner.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Peace<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Britain and France had signed
                        &#8216;Preliminary Articles of Peace&#8217; on 1 October 1801. This
                        was effectively a ceasefire to allow negotiations for a
                        full treaty.</note> was not welcome to the
                        Patricians<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Irish, as followers of St Patrick, 5th-century patron
                        saint of Ireland; but also a play on the word for Roman
                        aristocrats.</note> &#8211; it took away all their hopes of
                    &#8220;any fun&#8221; by the help of France. the government acting well
                    &amp; wisely, controul both parties, the Orange men &amp;
                    the United Irish men,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Orange Order, founded in 1795, was supported by
                        Irish Protestants, especially in Ulster. The United
                        Irishmen, founded in 1791, was the revolutionary
                        organisation behind the 1798 uprising for an
                        independent, democratic Ireland.</note> &amp; command
                    respect from both. the old fatteners upon the corruption are
                    silent in shame. the military who must be kept up will be
                    well employed in making roads, this measure is not yet
                    announced to the public. It will be difficult to civilize
                    this people. an Irishman builds him a turf stye &#8211; gets his
                    fuel from the bog, digs his patch of potatoes &amp; then
                    lives upon them in idleness. like a true savage he does not
                    think it worth while to work that he may better himself.
                    potatoes &amp; buttermilk &#8211; on this they are begotten &amp;
                    born &amp; bred, &amp; whiskey sends them to the third
                    heaven at once. If <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> had one of them in his laboratory, he could
                    analize his flesh blood &amp; bones into nothing but
                    potatoes &amp; buttermilk &amp; whiskey. they are the
                    primary elements of an Irishman. their love of &#8220;fun&#8221;
                    eternally engages them in mischievous combinations, which
                    are eternally baffled by their own blessed instinct of
                    blundering. the United Irishmen must have obtained
                    possession of <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>
                    but for a bull.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        United Irishmen&#8217;s rising was planned for the night of 23
                        May 1798. It was largely prevented by information from
                        informants, which allowed the army to occupy the rebels&#8217;
                        assembly points.</note> on the night appointed, the mail
                    coach was to be stopt &amp; burnt about a mile from town
                    &amp; that was the signal. the lamplighters were in the plot
                    &#8211; &amp; oh to be sure! the honeys would not light a lamp in
                        <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> that
                    evening, for fear the people should see what was going on. &#8211;
                    Of course alarm was taken &amp; all the mischief prevented.
                    &#8211; Modesty characterises them as much here as on the other
                    side of the water. a man stopt <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> yesterday
                    &#8211; I&#8217;ll be obl<hi rend="ital">a</hi>ged to you Sir &#8211; if youll
                    plaise to ask M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Abbot<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Abbot, Lord
                        Colchester (1757-1829; <title>DNB</title>), Chief
                        Secretary for Ireland 1801-1802, The Speaker 1802-1817.
                        Rickman was his secretary.</note> to give me a place of
                    sixty or seventy pounds a year &#8211; . favours indeed are asked
                    here with as unblushing &amp; obstinate a perseverance as in
                    Portugal. &#8211; This is the striking side of the picture. the
                    dark colours that first strike a stranger. their good
                    qualities you cannot so soon discover. genius indeed
                    immediately appears to characterise them. A love of saying
                    good things &#8211; which 999 Englishmen in a thousand never dream
                    of attempting in the course of their lives. When Lord
                        Hardwicke<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip
                        Yorke, 3rd Earl of Hardwicke (1757-1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Lord Lieutenant of Ireland
                        1801-1805.</note> came over there fell a fine rain <del rend="strikethrough">after</del> the first after a long
                    series of dry weather. a servant of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Lindsays<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles
                        Lindsay (1760-1846), private secretary to the Lord
                        Lieutenant and later Bishop of Kildare 1804-1846.</note>
                    heard an Irishman call to his comrade in the street &#8211; Ho
                    Patt &#8211; &amp; we shall have a riot &#8211; of course a phrase to
                    quicken an Englishmans hearing. this rain will breed a riot
                    &#8211; the little potatoes will be pushing out the big ones.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I send in my last the noble bull that
                        <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>
                    heard? he was late in company when a gentleman looked at his
                    watch &amp; cried <hi rend="ital">it is tomorrow
                        morning</hi>! &#8211; I must wish you good <hi rend="ital">night</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has
                    received a sane letter from <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>, who
                    only plays off the desperato where it will produce an
                    effect. <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref>
                    writes that the person with whom he cohabits is a young
                    surgeon &amp; nephew to a great wine merchant,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Both the merchant and his
                        nephew are unidentified.</note> who gives him long
                    credit. so they drink two sorts of wine &amp; live happy.
                        <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwin</ref> is
                    courting a widow who has one child; <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">On 21 December 1801 Godwin married his
                        second wife, Mary Jane Clairmont (1768-1841;
                            <title>DNB</title>). She had two children, but was
                        probably not a widow.</note> she is a very disgusting
                    woman says <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref>,
                    &amp; wears green spectacles.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall send you no money, because I shall
                    bring it. dear <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> I wish I knew when &#8211; but certainly very
                    soon. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Abbot goes in a few days &amp;
                    I should not think, nor is it thought that <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Corry</ref> will long remain after him. perhaps ten days
                    &#8211; or a week may be the utmost of my stay. the shorter the
                    better. it is hateful to be alone. about my shirts. cloth is
                    but sixpence a yard less than in England, &amp; to that
                    amount at last I am sure to be cheated. is it not better
                    wait till you can buy them for me? the people love a little
                    cheatery dealings. in the first shop which <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> entered,
                    he was asked 8 shillings &amp; sixpence for what the man
                    directly sold him at four shillings. I have bought no books
                    yet &#8211; for lack of money. today <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is
                    engaged to dinner &#8211; &amp; I am to seek for myself some
                    ordinary or chop house. this morning will clear off my
                    letters, &amp; I will make business a plea hereafter for
                    writing fewer. tis a hideous waste of time. &#8211; my love to
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp;c. <del rend="strikethrough">I
                        will</del> if indeed I do not write to him also.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> God
                        bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yr</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>