<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce846</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.837</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Previously  published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 226-229 [in
                    part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="837" type="letter">
<head>837. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>,
                        <date when="1803-09-08">8 September [1803]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address:
                        [deletion and readdress in another hand] To/ Lieutenant
                        Southey/ H. M. S. Galatea/ <del rend="strikethrough">Cork</del> &lt;Cove&gt; / Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        KESWICK/ 298; CORK<lb/>Postmark: SE/ 27/ 1803<lb/>MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 30927<lb/>Previously published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 226-229 [in
                    part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<address>
<placeName>
<ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greeta Hall</ref>. Keswick.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1803-09-08">Thursday night. Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 8. &lt;1803&gt;</date>
<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> &lt;1803&gt;:
                            Inserted in another hand.</note>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Tom</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> We arrived yesterday. yours reached me today.
                    I was glad to hear from you – a first letter after such a
                    loss is always expected with some sort of fear – tis pulling
                    off the bandage that has been put on a green wound. your
                    letter <del rend="strikethrough">was</del> is a very good
                    one – I have laid it with those which I preserve.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> was very
                    ill at Bristol. on the way we staid five days with <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> in
                    Staffordshire – one of the people in the world whom I love
                    best. To escape from Bristol was a relief. the place was
                    haunted, &amp; it is my wish never to see it again. here my
                    spirits suffer from the sight of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">little
                        Sara</ref>
<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge was
                        born 23 December 1802 and so was three months younger
                        than Margaret Southey.</note> who is about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">her</ref>
                    size – but not such a child – Oh Christ I shall not see such
                    another! However God knows that I do not repine, &amp; that
                    in my very soul I feel that his will is best. these things
                    do one good. they loosen one by one the roots that rivet us
                    to earth – they fix &amp; confirm our faith till the thought
                    of death becomes so inseperably connected with the hope of
                    meeting those whom we have lost, that death itself <del rend="strikethrough">exer</del> is no longer considered
                    as an evil.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Did I not tell you in the universal panic
                    &amp; palsy <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has requested me to delay the
                        Bibliotheca?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        ‘Bibliotheca Britannica’ was a planned – but
                        unexecuted – chronological history of all literature
                        produced in Britain. Southey was to have been its
                        editor.</note> this is a relief to me. I feel freer
                    &amp; easier. in consequence I do not go to Richmond, but
                    remain here where I can live for half the expence. my design
                    is to finish &amp; print Madoc,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had completed a version of
                            <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799 and was revising
                        it for publication. It did not appear until 1805.</note>
                    that by the profits I may be enabled to go to Portugal. but
                    my plans have been so often blasted that I look upon every
                    thing as quite vague &amp; uncertain. this only you may know
                    that while I am well I am actively employed – &amp; that
                    now, not being happy enough for the quiet half hours of
                    idleness, I must work with double dispatch.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I hope you will see the Annual Review.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual Review
                            for 1802</title>, 1 (1803).</note> there are some
                    admirable things by <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> in it. my own
                    part is very respectable – &amp; one article I hear is by
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        review of Jean-Louis Giraud-Soulavie (1751-1813),
                            <title>Historical and Political Memoirs of Louis
                            XVI</title> (1802) in <title>Annual Review for
                            1802</title>, 1 (1803), 308-311.</note> I shall
                    probably do more in the next volume. you could have helped
                    me in the maritime books. Do you know <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is
                    an Ensign in the Norwich Volunteers?</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> has
                    written to me. he was to go on board the following day. <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his damnable
                        Aunt</ref> was at Plymouth – spending her money – or
                    rather <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> there, &amp; all the while insisting that
                    she cannot supply him with linen for want of cash! I could
                    not at that time see to his fitting out as I should have
                    done. but when once fairly quit of her the boy shall not
                    want as far as my means will go. it is you &amp; I who have
                    fared the worst. the other two will have fewer difficulties
                    to cope with – yet perhaps they will not go on so well. Men
                    are the better for having suffered. of that every years
                    experience more &amp; more convinces me.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Poor Bella<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Southeys’ servant, she died in
                        1804.</note> is going very fast. it was a great shock to
                    me to see her. – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> suffers deeply &amp; silently. she is kept
                    awake at night by recollection – &amp; I am harrassed by
                    dreams of the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">poor
                        childs</ref> illness &amp; recovery. but this will wear
                    away. Would that you could see these Lakes &amp; Mountains!
                    how wonderful they are – how aweful in their beauty – all
                    the poet-part of me will be fed &amp; fostered here. I feel
                    already in tune, &amp; shall proceed to my work with such a
                    feeling of power as old Sampson had when he laid hold of the
                    pillars of the temple of Dagon.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Judges</title> 16: 30. After
                        Samson was captured and blinded by the Philistines he
                        was taken to the Temple of Dagon. There he prayed to
                        God, felt his strength return and pulled down the
                        pillars of the temple.</note> the Morning Post will
                    somewhat interrupt me. <ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> has paid
                    me so well for doing little – that in honesty I must work
                    hard for him. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> will copy you some of my rhymes.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Amadis<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>
                        (1803). The printer was <ref target="people.html#BiggsNathaniel">Nathaniel
                            Biggs</ref>.</note> is most abominably printed:
                    never book had more printers blunders. how it sells is not
                    in my power to say. in all likelihood badly, for all trade
                    is suspended, to a degree scarcely credible. I heard some
                    authenticated instances at Bristol. Hall the Grocer<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Hall (dates
                        unknown), grocer and tea-dealer in Maryport St,
                        Bristol.</note> used to have tea &amp; sugar weighd out
                    in pounds &amp; half pounds &amp;c on a Saturday night for
                    his country customers. thirty years established business
                    enabled him to proportion the quantity to this regular
                    demand almost to a nicety. he has had as much as twenty <hi rend="ital">pounds-worth</hi> uncalled for. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Morgan<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Sarah Morgan (dates unknown),
                        milliner of 23 High St, Bristol.</note> on a Saturday
                    used to take upon the average 30£ in her shop. she now does
                    not take five. but this will wear away. I am quite provoked
                    at the folly of any man who can feel a moments fear for this
                    country at this time.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We look to the Morning Post with daily
                    disappointment for news of the Galatea.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey’s ship, a 32-gun
                        Royal Navy frigate.</note>
<ref target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> has sold
                    the paper having thus realized 25,000 pounds – while his
                    advice &amp; influence upholds it little difference will be
                    perceived, but whenever that be withdrawn I prophecy a slow
                    decline &amp; downfall.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> How comes on the Spanish? you will find it
                    useful before the war is over I fear, – <hi rend="ital">fear</hi> because the Spaniards are a good &amp;
                    honourable people &amp; in spite of the plunder which will
                    fall to the share of the sailor I cannot but wish they may
                    be spared from suffering in a war to which they assuredly
                    are averse.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> God bless you <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>! you must
                    inquire of <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> for Joe.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey’s dog.</note> he will look
                    after him &amp; drop a card occasionally at his door. poor
                    fellow I was sorry to leave him. – <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> twas a heart-breaking day that of our
                    departure. Can’t you contrive to chase some French frigate
                    thro the Race of Holy head up to the Isle of Man, engage her
                    there &amp; bring her into Whitehaven? – Ediths love –</p>
<closer>
<signed rend="indent1"> RS.</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
