<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce623</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.614</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                        30928.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        250-253.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.614" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="614" type="letter">
        <head>614. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1801-10-15">15 October 1801</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30928<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                        250-253.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1801-10-15">Thursday 15 October. 1801. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Dublin"> Dublin</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was not altogether wrong in supposing that no inconvenience
                    would have arisen to any other person if I had been spared the fatigue of a
                    voyage to <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>. the unexpected
                    conclusion of peace<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Britain and France
                        had signed &#8216;Preliminary Articles of Peace&#8217; on 1 October 1801. This was
                        effectively a ceasefire to allow negotiations for a full treaty.</note> will
                    take the Irish members to London sooner than they would otherwise have removed.
                        M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey leaves a gap, but he means <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Isaac Corry</ref>.</note> is at present
                    in the country &#8211; so that we have not met, &#8211; but <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> tells me that in all
                    probability I shall not remain here a fortnight. so much the better. it is not
                    good for man to be alone. &#8211; I have taken lodgings here &#8211; two good rooms &#8211; at a
                    guinea a week. dear &#8211; but for so short a stay it was not worth while to trouble
                    myself in a long search. my living will be little expensive &#8211; I expect enough
                    invitations. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know it was my intention to embark from Whitehaven &#8211; or
                    Workington in a collier. the way of the wind, &amp; the uncertainty of the
                    passage made me change my intention &amp; I got to Parkgate.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Port on the River Dee.</note> &#8211; whence after a
                    wearisome delay because the Captain waited for more passengers &#8211; I sailed on
                    Sunday last at noon. the wind was favourable &#8211; it failed before we were out of
                    the river &#8211; we fell down only with the tide, &amp; so dead a calm prevailed all
                    night, that the ship was perfectly still as a house. there was not one heaving
                    on the waters &#8211; I never saw the sea so smooth &#8211; not a curl &#8211; a ripple &#8211; a
                    wrinkle. the shores in view, Flint &#8211; &amp; Caernarvonshire, &amp; the mountains
                    among which I had so lately been journeying. I quite enjoyed the sunset. All day
                    Monday we tacked &amp; retacked with light &amp; unkind winds to weather
                    Holyhead, but in vain. at evening we stood for Beaumarais Bay, &amp; there lay
                    to, waiting the midnight tide. the wind rose about one in the morning. we were
                    then in the Race of Holyhead, a rough sea, of infamous character. it blew a
                    heavy gale &#8211; the vessel shipped much water &#8211; it came pouring into the cabin,
                    &amp; our pumps were both at work, thump &#8211; thump &#8211; a melancholy sound at all
                    times! &amp; with the working of the ship, &amp; the cries of young children,
                    &amp; the roar of the wind &amp; the waves &#8211; faith it was an ugly concert. at
                    dawn the wind abated, &amp; we had arrived beyond the race into smoother water.
                    the Sun rose hazily, we were near land, yet could see nothing, &amp; the
                    steersman could only go by guess. in consequence when we were near enough to see
                    the shore, it was found that we were too far North of Dublin bay, &amp; could
                    not possibly reach it that night. the Captain a civil careful man, willingly
                    consented to land at Balbriggen. I never sailed with a better man. he never left
                    the deck during night, &amp; his only drink &#8211; on shore or at sea, was buttermilk
                    &#8211; or milk. At Balbriggen then we landed &#8211; a little fishing &amp; bathing town,
                    fifteen &amp; a half miles from <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> &#8211;
                    Irish miles &#8211; for all things all topsy turvy here, of which eleven here equal to
                    fourteen in England. no means of conveyance to the capital &#8211; we sent two miles
                    &amp; a half to a single Inn &#8211; for five chaises, while we dined. the messenger
                    returned with one coach. in that we shipped the women &amp; children, loaded a
                    car with the luggage, &amp; proceeded with it on foot to the Inn &#8211; so after
                    leaving the packet, we slept in the Man of War, so the Inn is called &#8211; because
                    its sign is a Saracens head, with a pipe in his mouth. &#8211; In my company I was
                    more than usually fortunate. the Wife of the L Lieutenants Aid du camp<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &#8211; with her infant &#8211; a
                    genteel woman. a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ottley<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">George Brook Taylor Ottley (b. 1774) of Delaford, County
                        Dublin. Commissioner of military accounts and public works in Ireland. In
                        1799 he married Isabella Maria Brown, daughter of John Brown of
                        Belfast.</note> of University, who nosing out my name upon the trunk civilly
                    requested my acquaintance. his wife is very young, has been in Portugal, &amp;
                    is a very favourable specimen of Irish women. An old Irish gentleman of kindly
                    manners, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Knox,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> who fell to my share in a post chaise, whom also I am
                    bound to call upon. &amp; tho last not least &#8211; to my infinite amusement D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Solomon<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel
                        Solomon (1768/9-1819; <title>DNB</title>), manufacturer and promoter of the
                        best-selling quack medicine &#8216;Cordial Balm of Gilead&#8217;. His MD, from Marischal
                        College, Aberdeen, was probably obtained fraudulently.</note> himself. &amp;
                    his nephew,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> a young
                    &amp; stupid cub, in training to become Prime Quack of the World whenever his
                    Uncle shall resign. Oh I set off Solomon in all his glory! I got him upon physic
                    &#8211; upon The Cordial Balm of Gilead, &amp; the Anti-Impetig&#299;nes<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Anti-impetigines or &#8216;Solomon&#8217;s Drops&#8217;, another
                        of Samuel Solomon&#8217;s remedies.</note> as in defiance of all prosody he called
                    it &#8211; &amp; upon D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brodum.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Brodum (fl. 1795-1814), quack medicine seller. He had
                        been the mentor of Samuel Solomon.</note> yes &#8211; I touched upon the tender
                    subject &#8211; &amp; he said there were Quacks in the world. I asked him what was the
                    cause of the Bilious Flux at Liverpool. Sir said he &#8211; I can attribute it to
                    nothing but the prodigious quantity of flies this summer. never were so many
                    flies! all the meat was fly-blown. &amp; what was the best remedy? &#8211; nothing had
                    been found so effectual as &#8211; the Balm of Gilead. I asked him what he thought of
                    the Acids in syphilitic cases<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                        Beddoes, <title>A Collection of Testimonies Respecting the Treatment of the
                            Venereal Disease by Nitrous Acid</title> (1799).</note> &#8211; he replied
                    that Pneumatic medicine had not succeeded. literally this was his answer. When
                        <del rend="strikethrough">he</del> I had left the room he asked if I was not
                    a medical gentleman. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Wednesday morning I reached <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> &amp; found <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, who is no little personage in Ireland. he was engaged to
                    dine with a D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lindsay,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Lindsay (1760-1846), private secretary to the Lord
                        Lieutenant and later Bishop of Kildare 1804-1846.</note> brother to the Lady
                        Lieutenant<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Elizabeth Lindsay
                        (1763-1858), wife of Philip Yorke, 3rd Earl of Hardwicke (1757-1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Lord Lieutenant of Ireland 1801-1805.</note> as she
                    is called, &amp; private Secretary to her husband. he invited me also, &amp; I
                    found out he was a <ref target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref> man &#8211;
                    &amp; thus <del rend="strikethrough">now</del> got a hook &amp; eye of
                    acquaintance with him. to day after breakfasting with <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> I am returned to write my
                    letters &#8211; to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> I had of course
                    dispatched a bulletin of my arrival before. &#8211; I know nothing of my own situation
                    farther, but that my labour will be easy work, be it much or little, &amp; that
                    I suppose myself to be, according to the language of the world, in a good way.
                    my time will be spent from Xmas till June in London, the rest of the year, in
                        <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>. Of the government I am led to
                    believe every thing that is good &#8211; at least they have every temptation to do
                    good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The country that I passed is destitute of trees as if there
                    existed an instinctive dread of the gallows in the people. indeed most of the
                    &lt;young&gt; trees in the kingdom had been cut down to make pikes. I am
                    disgusted by seeing barefooted women, in their caps, trolloping thro the
                    streets. cars drawn by one horse are the only carriages of burden, &amp; over
                    this the posteriors of the horse so project as if they were designed to catch
                    all chance manure by the way. one little town I past, of ancient importance,
                    Swords, its castle &amp; church which had a bell round tower by its square one,
                    formed an uncommon picture. it was famous of late years as a <hi rend="ital">potwalloping</hi> borough,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Swords
                        returned two MPs to the Irish House of Commons until its abolition in 1800.
                        It was one of only ten Irish boroughs that had a potwalloper franchise, i.e.
                        any householder with a hearth big enough to boil a pot could vote. Despite
                        (or because of) this relatively wide franchise, the borough had a reputation
                        for corruption.</note> &amp; for rearing early ducks for the <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> mark[MS obscured] the Union has
                    prevented its corruption from breeding vermin any longer &#8211; but the
                    duck-manufactory is in a flourishing state. &#8211; the post chaises are clumsy &amp;
                    bad. they charge more for three passengers than for two, &amp; always
                    expensively. &#8211; <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref> is rapidly
                    improving &amp; will be a most magnificent city. it is already a very fine one.
                    as yet I have only seen the outline of the Wicklow mountains thro a haze. their
                    shape is beautiful. the people very filthy &#8211; beastlily filthy. I cannot like
                    them &#8211; &amp; yet they are a people of genius. a fellow builds a turf hovel &#8211;
                    plants his patch of potatoes &amp; will do nothing else. he will be idle &amp;
                    live upon potatoes &amp; butter milk. they have an innate love of combination.
                    if you have three workmen about your house &#8211; they combine against you for more
                    wages. this is <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> account.
                    They are always saying odd things. Pat! said a fellow in the streets when the
                    dry season was at an end &#8211; this rain will breed a Riot &#8211; for the little potatoes
                    will be pushing out the big ones! &#8211; I have room for a Bull which <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> heard &#8211; they were late in
                    company, when one of the party looked at his watch &#8211; faith &#8211; said he &#8211; it <hi rend="ital">is tomorrow morning</hi>! &#8211; I must wish you good <hi rend="ital">night</hi>! </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am anxious to hear of <ref target="people.html#HillMargaret">Peggy</ref>. How is <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Danvers</ref>? &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>? she shall have my next
                    letter to Bristol. this contains all my present stock of information.</p>
        <p>write to me under cover thus</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Right Honble</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Isaac</ref>
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    this is the form.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>
          <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">write to me ... Dublin: added on the
                        left hand margin of the final paragraph.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>