<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce511</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.502</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>.  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.),
                            A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 339–343; Adolfo Cabral
                        (ed.), Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800–1801
                            and a Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp. 68–69 [in
                        part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="502" type="letter">
<head>502. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref>, <date when="1800-03-26">[started ‘some weeks’ before and
                        continued on] 26 March [1800]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry
                        Street/ Norwich./ Single<lb/>Postmarks: BRISTOL/ MAR 26 1800; B/ MAR
                        27/1800<lb/> Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1 April<lb/>MS:
                        Huntington Library, HM 4828 <lb/>Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.),
                            <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 339–343; Adolfo Cabral
                        (ed.), <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800–1801
                            and a Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 68–69 [in
                        part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> Your Wortigerne reached me,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Taylor’s unfinished play ‘Wortigerne’, in the style
                        of Thomas Chatterton’s (1752–1770; <title>DNB</title>) pseudo-medieval
                        writings, which he attributed to the 15th-century Bristol priest, Thomas
                        Rowley.</note> &amp; it has given me much pleasure. the Anthology<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Annual Anthology</title> (1800).</note> I
                    find has not room for it. are you willing to annex it, with all due doubtfulness
                    of prefatory scepticism, to the Rowleys of Chatterton in the new edition?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Cottle’s edition of the
                            <title>Works of Thomas Chatterton</title> (1803).</note> I should
                    &lt;think&gt; nothing misplaced that gave additional value to the volumes, &amp;
                    this your fragment assuredly would do. As for the proof it contains of the
                    possibility of writing such poems now, there needs no new evidence. But the
                    poetry is very – very fine –, &amp; its masquerade-spelling will become familiar
                    to the reader who has previously decyphered Chattertons. If you think this a fit
                    mode of publication, I will save you the trouble of making a glossary. – A few
                    evenings since my friend <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>
                    amused himself in examining the fac-simile in Rowley, &amp; copying out all the
                        <hi rend="ital">e</hi>s in the twelve lines. he found no less than 27 <hi rend="ital">genera</hi>, each totally different from the other &amp; many of
                    them impossible to have ever been used in writing (except with a design of
                    producing a strange unsightliness) from the various manners in which it was
                    necessary to hold the pen in tracing them. These <hi rend="ital">e</hi>s I shall
                    place at the bottom of the fac-simile.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Sir Herberts</ref> letter I saw in the
                    Gentlemans Magazine<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Gentleman’s
                            Magazine</title>, 70 (February–April 1800), 99–104, 222–226,
                        322–325.</note> just before your information respecting him arrived. in my
                        reply<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">See Robert Southey to the
                        Editor of the <title>Gentleman’s Magazine</title>, 20 March [1800], Letter
                        497.</note> I have <del rend="strikethrough">not noticed xxxxxxxxxx xxxxxxx
                        xxx xxxx xxxxxxxxxxx</del> admitted no personality, his own letter
                    sufficiently proves the truth of my statement. do you know that he is distantly
                    related to me?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s mother’s
                        grandmother (Margaret) was a member of the Croft family (Robert Southey to
                        John May, 1 August 1820). The name ‘Herbert’ was traditional in the Croft
                        family in honour of the first baronet, Sir Herbert Croft (1651–1720).
                        Southey named his eldest son Herbert (1806–1816), presumably in honour of
                        his maternal ancestors.</note>
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> bears also the name
                    Herbert from the same <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxx</del> &lt;origin&gt;, a
                    name which has continued in <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                        mothers</ref> family since they branched from the <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Croft</ref> stock.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your epigrams<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Taylor’s epigrams on all the poems in <title>Annual Anthology</title>
                        (1799); see Taylor to Southey, 16 February 1800, J.W. Robberds (ed.),
                            <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 332–334.</note>
                    frightened <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>. he deprecated
                    their insertion lest they should intimidate all correspondents. I laughed &amp;
                    argued – but not effectually – &amp; as the risque of the Anthology is <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottles</ref>, did not feel justified in
                    using my voice potential. Wherever you print them, do not suppress the chilly
                        River.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor’s epigram on Southey’s
                        ‘Inscription I, For the Banks of the Hampshire Avon’, <title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1799), pp. 67–68.</note> the Inscription is
                    a bad one &amp; deserves no mercy. &amp; were it better, you know not the little
                    value I set upon these trifles. I expect soon to send you the Anthology &amp;
                    with it the Noah;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Jakob Bodmer
                        (1698–1783), <title>Noachide</title> (1752), which Southey had borrowed from
                        Taylor. Southey probably did not finish it until 26 March 1800, and then
                        dismissed it as a ‘bad poem’ (<title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John
                        Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, p. 2).</note> which has been
                    detained too long &amp; used too little.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I wait with unpleasant anxiety the letters from Lisbon which will
                    decide my destination. Lisbon I hope will be the place, old recollections
                    attract me there, &amp; the prospect of employment in the History of the
                        Kingdom,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished
                        ‘History of Portugal’.</note> important enough to excite ardour, &amp;
                    sufficiently interesting to prevent lassitude. – <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is at M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Donalds. 5. Nicholsons Street.</p>
<p rend="center">–––––</p>
<p>
<date when="1800-03-26">March. 26.</date> – This unfinished sheet has remained
                    like an evil conscience, for some weeks in my desk. <del rend="strikethrough">I
                        hav</del> my destination is now settled. we are in all the bustle of
                    preparing for a twelvemonths absence from England, &amp; purpose leaving this
                    place in a fortnight on our way to Falmouth, &amp; Lisbon. If I were not
                    villainously sick at sea – the whole anticipation would be pleasant – but the
                    certainty of intestine commotions excites qualms already – </p>
<p rend="indent1"> Between the setting foot on board a ship and leaving it in port
                    the interim is like a phantasma or a hideous dream! – My intention is seriously
                    to undertake the History of Portugal, &amp; to qualify myself for the task by
                    travelling over the whole of the little Kingdom, &amp; well understanding the
                    site of every place whereof it may be my office to write. no country possesses a
                    better series of chronicles. I shall visit the various Convent Libraries &amp;
                    hunt out all scarcer documents. twelvemonths well employed will suffice for the
                    collection of materials – &amp; if otherwise – I am not limited to time. One
                    thing I shall especially attempt in writing history. to weave the manners of the
                    times, as far as can properly be done into the narrative – instead of crowding
                    the volumes with appendix chapters. rather in this point to resemble the old
                    chroniclers than the modern historians.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You will direct to me with the <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Reverend Herbert Hill</ref>. Lisbon.
                    your gossamery paper, which I have sometimes growled &lt;at&gt; for letting the
                    ink thro, will suit well the post office of a country where an extravagant price
                    is charged by weight. remember that as for society – such as suits my habits –
                    Lisbon is always in a state of famine – &amp; that the receipt of a letter in a
                    foreign country is a joy which lasts for a week. My intention is, if peace
                    permits, to return thro the South of Spain &amp; over the Pyrenees to Calais.
                    surely there will not be another years war – &amp; I would wait some months for
                    peace beyond <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> the proposed limits of my stay.
                    Much however depends upon the effects which the climate may produce upon me.
                    experiments upon health [MS torn] important in their result not to excite some
                    anxiety. my complaint is probably not organic, but it remains to be proved
                    removable, &amp; only from climate can I expect this.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> In the course of ten days you will receive the Anthology. I will
                    send it to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> in his
                    parcel, &amp; he can forward it thro <ref target="places.html#Yarmouth">Yarmouth</ref>. for the third volume I shall delegate my authority. I am
                    sorry my name was given in the Reviews &amp; Monthly Magazine,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been named as the editor of the
                            <title>Annual Anthology</title> in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>,
                        8 (December 1799), 1052; and in numerous other periodicals, including the
                            <title>Critical Review</title>, 28 (January 1800), 82–89.</note> In
                    reviewing anonymous works myself, when I have known the authors, I have never
                    mentioned them, taking it for granted they had sufficient motives for avoiding
                    this publicity.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Let me hear from you before my departure.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<address>
<placeName>
<hi rend="ital">10. <ref target="places.html#StokesCroft">Stokes Croft</ref>
</hi>. Bristol.</placeName>
</address>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
