<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce664</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.655</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 268-270 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.655" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="655" type="letter">
        <head>655. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>,
                        <date when="1802-02-06">[started before and continued
                        on] 6 February [1802]</date>
          </head><p>Address:
                        John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsements: R.S./ Feb 6th/ 1802; R.S.<lb />MS:
                        Huntington Library, RS 20<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 268-270 [in part].</p>
        <p>I copy for you the most authentic account of the <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del> &#931;&#964;&#951;&#955;&#945;&#953;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek translates as
                        &#8216;pillars&#8217;.</note> &#8211; as part of your office is to settle
                    the disputes about the Round Towers.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Ireland has about 120 stone towers. Their
                        age and origin has been much debated and Rickman seems
                        to have been collecting evidence that they were built
                        for early Christian ascetics.</note> Raderus is the
                    authority quoted in the Acta Sanctorum . T. 1. p. 262.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Acta
                            Sanctorum</title> (1643-1940) is a 68-volume
                        critical hagiography of Catholic saints, organised by
                        calendar date of the saints&#8217; feast-days. Southey had
                        borrowed the first three volumes from Dr Williams&#8217;s
                        Library; see Southey to John Rickman, [c. 17 January
                        1802], Letter 651. Matthaus Rader (1561-1634) was a
                        German Jesuit and hagiographer.</note>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>Columnarum (quas ego omnibus Aegypti prodigiosis pyramidibus
                    elaboratis, &amp; pictis obeliscis, colossis, columnisq
                    Trajani, propter ipsa quae supra illas fulgebant sidera,
                    antepono) formae fere fuit, ut arbitror, rotunda, altitudo
                    varia &#8211; Auctor enim Stylitarum Simeon primum columellam
                    ascendit non nisi sen&#251;m cubitorum (sive novempedum) mox
                    duoden&#251;m, postea vicen&#251;m du&#251;m, postremo tricen&#251;m sen&#251;m, sive
                    ut Nicephorus &amp; alii tradunt, quadregen&#251;m. Modius, seu
                    cella, sive domicilium columnis impositum, in quo
                    consistebant, in omnem partem binos cubitos seu tres pedes
                    patebat, tecto nullo, ut libere caelum omne contemplarentur,
                    &amp; omnibus injuriis caeli expositi majorem haberent
                    tolerantiae segetem &amp; messem. Januas habebant nonnulli,
                    nullas alii, quod tempestatis violentia parietis partem
                    disjecisset Scalae admovebantur, cum vel alii ad illos
                    enitebantur, vel illi, ad alios se demitterent, quod quidem
                    vel nunquam, vel ad summa Reipublicae pericula devocati
                    factitabant. Statione porro aetern&#226; se cruciabant; nec enim
                    jacendi vel decumbendi spatium erat: poterant tamen sedere;
                    sedisse ver&#224; nusquam lego, numquam puto. Nam primis
                    quidraginta diebus Simeon ad trabem se alligari<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey inserts a footnote:
                        &#8216;N.B. This settles the question whether the Crocodiles
                        of the old &amp; new world are of the same species. for
                        it plainly implies the existence of an Alligator in
                        Egypt.&#8217; This is a rather painful pun on the Latin word
                        &#8216;alligari&#8217;.</note> curavit, alterisq quadraginta mox
                    liber absque adminiculo consistebat, medio corpore superne
                    velut Ecclesiastes in ambone extabat.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Latin translates as: &#8216;I
                        count the Pillars before all Egypt&#8217;s prodigious,
                        elaborate pyramids and its painted obelisks, colossi and
                        Trajan&#8217;s columns, because of the stars which shone over
                        them: their cross-section was pretty well round, I
                        think, and their heights various. The founder of the
                        Stylite sect Simeon first ascended a little pillar of
                        six cubits at the least (or nine feet); then twelve,
                        then twenty-two and finally thirty-six, or, as
                        Nicephorus and others say, forty cubits&#8217; height. The
                        barrel or cell or room perched on the pillars in which
                        they used to live extended two cubits (or three feet) in
                        all directions and was roofless, so that they could gaze
                        at the whole of heaven in freedom and by exposure to all
                        the perils of the sky have a greater crop and harvest of
                        endurance. Some had doors, some not, because the
                        violence of a storm had dislodged part of a wall.
                        Ladders were put in place when either people tried to
                        reach them or they went to see others, something they
                        used to do either not at all or when invoked at times of
                        great political anxiety. They tortured themselves by
                        staying perpetually on their feet, since there was no
                        space to lie or stretch out; that they sat I read
                        nowhere, and I think they never did. For his first forty
                        days Simeon took care to be tied to a plank; for the
                        next forty he kept position on his own without aid,
                        visible from the waist up like a preacher in a pulpit.&#8217;
                        The source is <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, (1643), I,
                        p. 262.</note>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1802-02-06">Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 6. </date>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Strand"> 35. Strand</ref>.</placeName>
          </address>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The otherside extract hath been written many
                    days. meantime the removal of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Abbot<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman&#8217;s
                        employer, the politician Charles Abbot (1757&#8211;1829;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Abbot was in London and was
                        soon to leave his post as chief secretary to the Lord
                        Lieutenant of Ireland. On 10 February 1802 he began a
                        new role as The Speaker, 1802-1817.</note> to England
                    left me ignorant of your due direction. &amp; I am now half
                    suspicious that <ref target="people.html#LambMaryAnne">Mary
                        Lamb</ref> has given me one which wants some of its
                    formalities. The Letter you sent vi&#226; <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Caroli Agni</ref> &#8211;
                    after crossing the Channel &amp; travelling from Holyhead to
                    London, has lost its way between Westminster Bridge &amp;
                        <ref target="places.html#Strand">the Strand</ref>.
                    matter for some vexation &#8211; &amp; a legitimate cause for
                    breaking the third commandment.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Exodus</title> 20: 7, &#8216;You shall
                        not make wrongful use of the name of the Lord your
                        god&#8217;.</note> Yesterday yours to <ref target="people.html#LambCharles">Lamb</ref> was brought
                    me with the commission for an Epitaph.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman had asked both Lamb
                        and Southey to write an epitaph for Mary Druitt (c.
                        1782-1801), who is buried at Wimborne, Dorset. It does
                        not appear that Southey undertook the task.</note> I
                    will write one if I can. but what medicine will move a
                    costive brain? you did not know that in my judgement it is
                    more difficult to write an Epitaph than an Epic Poem or a
                    voluminous History. with the full feeling &amp;
                    consciousness of incapacity nothing can be done well. I
                    cannot &#8211; I never could succeed in these short compositions.
                    carving beef never teaches a man to dissect butterflies.
                    Oaks will grow on my ground &#8211; but I cannot raise cucumbers
                    there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Corry</ref> &amp; I
                    have not seen the light of each others countenance for this
                    last fortnight. tho (except one day when prevented by
                    serious illness) I have daily &amp; generally twice a day,
                    done the duty of my Secretaryship by knocking at his door.
                    he is now unwell, but mending. I also have been &amp; am in
                    that sort of health that makes me think with regret of
                    Lisbon. As soon as the form of announcing my wishes to the
                        <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Chancellor</ref> is
                    past, I purpose migrating for a week or ten days to Norwich.
                    change will benefit me. I shall be glad to see <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my
                        brother</ref> &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>.
                    this London poisons my body &#8211; &amp; God knows is not the
                    most favourable atmosphere for my brain. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnetts</ref>
                    pupils have eloped.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Burnett had been employed as tutor to Charles Stanhope
                        (1785-1809) and James Stanhope (1788-1825), the younger
                        sons of the controversial politician and inventor
                        Charles (&#8216;Citizen&#8217;) Stanhope, 3rd Earl Stanhope
                        (1753-1816; <title>DNB</title>). The boys&#8217; flight from
                        their father&#8217;s house was described in a letter from
                        Charles Lamb to John Rickman, [?1 February 1802], E.W.
                        Marrs Jr (ed.), <title>The Letters of Charles and Mary
                            Anne Lamb, 1796-1817</title>, 3 vols (Ithaca, NY and
                        London, 1975-1978), II, pp. 49-50.</note> Lord Stanhope
                    seems attached to him &amp; will be his friend. That right
                    republican Lord<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Earl
                        Stanhope was notoriously democratic and pro-French in
                        his political opinions.</note> is an excellent man &amp;
                    of less eccentric habits than there was reason to suspect. &#8211;
                        <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> of
                    course is well &amp; successfully employed. a new discovery
                    of his will enrich somebody &#8211; that the Terra Japanica is
                    pure tannine.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Davy
                        had conducted experiments to confirm the view of Sir
                        Joseph Banks (1743-1820; <title>DNB</title>) that Terra
                        Japonica, or Catechu, an extract obtained from mimosa
                        wood, was rich in tannin and could therefore be used in
                        the process of tanning leather. As Terra Japonica was
                        cheaper than oak bark, the substance usually employed,
                        its widespread use might reduce the price of leather
                        goods. Davy publicised his discovery in &#8216;An Account of
                        some Experiments and Observations on the Constituent
                        Parts of Certain Astringent Vegetables; and On Their
                        Operation in Tanning&#8217;, <title>Philosophical Transactions
                            of the Royal Society of London</title>, 93 (1803),
                        233-273.</note> I wish it would lower the price of
                    shoe-leather. Carriages driven by Steam are the most
                    important novelties. Two Cornish men are in London for the
                        patent.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard
                        Trevithick (1771-1833; <title>DNB</title>) and Andrew
                        Vivian (1759-1842) secured a patent for their steam
                        locomotive on 24 March 1802. The locomotive had been
                        trialled in Camborne, Cornwall, in December 1801. Their
                        initiative was backed by two fellow Cornishmen, Davies
                        Giddy (1767-1739; <title>DNB</title>) and <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Humphry
                        Davy</ref>.</note> they succeed on the hills of
                    Cornwall, &amp; the next army that shall cross the Alps will
                    be saved some fatigue.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have unpleasant tidings from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. he is sent to
                    the West Indies after Ganteaume!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Honor&#233; Joseph Antoine Ganteaume
                        (1755-1818), commander of the French fleet which left
                        Toulon on 14 February 1802 to support the French
                        re-conquest of Haiti.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is very
                    unwell &#8211; &amp; I fear will not be better while she remains
                    in town. You will be glad to hear that my History is
                        progressive.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s projected &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> the
                    head progress outruns the hand. I confess a silk-worm
                    propensity to feeding rather than spinning. howbeit there is
                    a visible progress, &amp; the Moths do not digest so many
                    folios as I do. Meantime I am increasing my knowledge of the
                    Living Remarkables, &amp; added to my list &#8211; Charlotte
                        Smith<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The poet
                        and novelist Charlotte Smith (1749-1806;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; a woman of genius,
                    good sense, &amp; pleasant manners &#8211; Mrs Inchbald<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The writer and
                        actress Elizabeth Inchbald (1753&#8211;1821;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; very odd &#8211; very clever
                    &#8211; very beautiful. D&#8217;Israeli<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The writer Isaac D&#8217;Israeli (1766&#8211;1848;
                            <title>DNB</title>). He was of Italian-Jewish
                        descent.</note> &#8211; he looks &lt;like&gt; a Portugueze who
                    being apprehended for an assassin is convicted of being
                    circumcised. I don&#8217;t like him. &#8211; <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, the
                    Historian of the Anglo Saxons.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Sharon Turner's four-volume
                            <title>History of the Anglo-Saxons</title> was
                        published between 1799 and 1805.</note> read his book,
                    it is the very worst in style that ever can be written &#8211; but
                    in research &amp; novelty of information the best historical
                    work, beyond comparison that I have ever seen. I like the
                    man &amp; only wish there was one spark of genius in that
                    dark warehouse of his. the Misses Berrys<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary (1763&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Agnes (1764&#8211;1852;
                            <title>DNB</title>) Berry, cousins of Southey&#8217;s
                        friend Barbara Seton.</note> &#8211; to whom Ld Orford left so
                        much.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace
                        Walpole, 4th Earl of Orford (1717&#8211;1797;
                            <title>DNB</title>). On his death, Walpole left the
                        Berry sisters &#163;4000 each, the house Little Strawberry
                        Hill and his literary manuscripts.</note> very
                    delightful women. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Damer<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The sculptor and writer Anne
                        Seymour Damer (1749&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>). As
                        executor and residuary legatee of Walpole&#8217;s estate, she
                        inherited his property at Strawberry Hill,
                        Twickenham.</note> &#8211; Lawrence the painter.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Lawrence (1769&#8211;1830;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> somewhat oily of tongue.
                    to day I am to meet Hopner.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The painter John Hoppner (1758&#8211;1810;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> I am about to call on
                        Sotheby.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        poet and translator William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> this by the blessing of
                    God being my last long spell in London, tis well to make the
                    most of it. Farewell. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p>Should you ascertain that these Round Towers were the
                        Fool pillars that you suspect, it will rather favour the
                        claims of the Patricians<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">The Irish, as followers of their
                            5th-century patron saint St Patrick; but also a play
                            on the Roman word for aristocrats.</note> to earlier
                        civilization than Giraldus &amp; the English allow
                            them.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Giraldus Cambrensis (c. 1146- c. 1223;
                                <title>DNB</title>) had given a very
                            unsympathetic portrait of Irish civilization in his
                                <title>Topographia Hibernica</title>
                            (1188).</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>