<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce749</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.740</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of
                        Wales, MS 4811D.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 296-297.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.740" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="740" type="letter">
        <head>740. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>,<date when="1802-12-05"> 5 December 1802</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M.P./ Lincolns Inn/ London<lb />Postmark:
                        [partial] DEC 5 <lb />Endorsement: Dec. 5/ 1802<lb />MS: National Library of
                        Wales, MS 4811D<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 296-297.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not dissatisfied with the Monthly Review<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The appraisal of <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801), <title>Monthly Review</title>, 39 (November
                        1802), 240-251.</note> as to its quantum of praise but very much so as to
                    its quality. it is done with sufficient civility &amp; fairness but it is not
                    well done. the extracts are abundant but rarely adduced to justify either
                    censure or commendation, &amp; of the passages which I feel to be the most
                    striking in the poem not one has been selected &#8211; no part of the life of Thalaba
                    in book 3 &#8211; nor of the meeting with Maimuna<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 8, lines
                        287-374.</note> &#8211; nor of the incantation of Khawla. book 9<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801),
                        Book 9, lines 49-81.</note> &#8211; which is the most irregular in its metre &amp;
                    the most appropriate in the volumes. Such as it is, it is likely to help the
                    lame dog over the stile for like a certain description of Xtians poor
                    &lt;Thalaba&gt; stands in need of a hearty shove.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A favourite saying of Southey&#8217;s, derived from <title>An
                            Effectual Shove to the Heavy-Arse Christian</title> (1768), wrongly
                        attributed to Richard Baxter (1615-1691; <title>DNB</title>). The pamphlet&#8217;s
                        author was the Welsh minister William Bunyan (fl. 1760s).</note> yet I trust
                    it is not a fundamental fault.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Catalogue. I possess all the Portugueze books
                    in it &amp; the Chronicle of the Cid<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had transcribed for Wynn material relating to Rodrigo Diaz de Bivar
                        (c. 1040-1099), a Castilian aristocrat and military commander, whose
                        exploits were the subject of numerous poems and tales. Southey&#8217;s English
                        translation and compilation of three of these was published in 1808 as
                            <title>The Chronicle of the Cid</title>.</note> which is to me the most
                    important of the Spanish. the two Books of Amadis (the 8. &amp; 9) I should like
                    to see because I have <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> &lt;an&gt; eighth book
                    in D&#8217;Herberays<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicolas de Herberay des
                        Essarts (d. c. 1557), author of an 8-volume French translation of
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1540-1548).</note> French wherein this in
                    the Catalogue is alluded to as apocryphal, &amp; a ninth in Spanish which is
                    certainly in sequence to the one translated by D Herberay, &amp; which treats of
                    Florisel of Niquea, instead of his father Amadis of Greece.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Feliciano de Silva (1491-1554), Spanish author
                        of four &#8216;sequels&#8217; (i.e. entirely new Books) to <title>Amadis of
                        Gaul</title>. His Book 9 (1530) dealt with Amadis of Greece, and Book 10
                        (1532) with Florisel of Niquea.</note> But this will be a dear book &#8211; &amp;
                    I must not pretend to make out a history of the Amadis story from imperfect
                    materials. my dissertation must confine itself to the first four books &#8211; the
                    work of the Portugueze author Vasco de Lobera<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Vasco de Lobeira (d. 1403) was believed, on the evidence of a
                        15th-century chronicle, to be the originator of <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title>. However, the poem is now generally thought to have an
                        earlier origin in 14th-century Spain.</note> &#8211; compared with which all that
                    follow are trash. Did I tell you that Spensers Mask of Cupid<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Spenser (1552-1599; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590-1596), Book 3, Canto 12, stanzas
                        3-27; and the eighth volume of Nicolas de Herberay des Essarts,
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, published in 1548.</note> is to be found
                    in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> book of Amadis? The Amadigi of Bernardo
                        Tasso<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Bernardo Tasso (1493-1569),
                            <title>L&#8217;Amadigi</title> (1755), no. 2773 in the sale catalogue of
                        Southey&#8217;s library. An epic poem inspired by <title>Amadis of
                        Gaul</title>.</note> has been lately brought me from Italy &#8211; there is
                    however one book in the Catalogue which I could wish to have &#8211; N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 304. the works of Bartholome de las Casas,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Bartolome de las Casas (1484-1566), Spanish priest and critic
                        of Spanish treatment of native Americans.</note> the friend of the Indians.
                    this will be worth from five shillings to three half crowns.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should a copy of Giraldus Cambrensis<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Giraldus Cambrensis (c. 1146- c. 1223), Norman-Welsh
                        chronicler. Southey probably wanted a copy of his <title>Itinerarium
                            Cambriae</title> (1191).</note> fall in your way pray buy it for me &#8211;
                    &amp; if the old Welshman should be in company, as I have seen him, with some
                    half dozen of our monkish annalists so much the better. I must read the English
                    as well as the Welsh histories.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> this weakness of sight drives me to poetry again. so much of that
                    may be done by candlelight with closed eyes &#8211; &amp; the lines then scrawled no
                    matter how roughly. I move slowly on with Madoc<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had finished a version of <title>Madoc</title> in
                        1797-1799. He was revising it for publication, though it did not appear
                        until 1805.</note> &#8211; your second book will soon be ready. If you do not see
                    how Kehama<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810). Southey had sent an early draft of Book 1 to
                        Charles Grosvenor Bedford on 7 October (Letter 726) and [c. 30 November
                        1802] (Letter 738).</note> proceeds it is <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Dapples</ref> fault.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> still in
                    Scotland? should you see the Ubiquitarian <ref target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> tell him I am carefully using his Amadis<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, a Spanish
                        romance, first published in four books by Rodriguez de Montalvo (d. 1504).
                        Southey had borrowed an edition from Heber earlier in 1802; see
                        Southey to Heber, 7 May [1802], Letter 674.</note> &amp; shall return it
                    safe &amp; uninjured with the English version<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Anthony Munday (1560-1633; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Ancient, Famous and Honourable History of Amadis of Gaul</title>
                        (1589-1619).</note> as soon as that be completed &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R S.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1802-12-05">December 5. 1802.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>