<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce290</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.281</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS has not
                        survived.  Previously  published: Monthly Magazine, 5
                        (January 1798), 11&#8211;12 [from where the text is taken] under the pseudonym &#8216;T.
                        Y.&#8217; For attribution to Southey, see Kenneth Curry, &#8216;Southey&#8217;s contributions
                        to The Monthly Magazine and The Athenaeum&#8217;,
                            The Wordsworth Circle, 11 (1980), 216.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="281" type="letter">
        <head>281. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>
          </ref>, <date when="1798-01">[January
                        1798]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has not
                        survived<lb />Previously published: <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 5
                        (January 1798), 11&#8211;12 [from where the text is taken] under the pseudonym &#8216;T.
                        Y.&#8217; For attribution to Southey, see Kenneth Curry, &#8216;Southey&#8217;s contributions
                        to <title>The Monthly Magazine</title> and <title>The Athenaeum</title>&#8217;,
                            <title>The Wordsworth Circle</title>, 11 (1980), 216.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>SIR,</opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Permit me to correct some errors in my account of Lupercio and
                    Bartolome Leonardo.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish poets
                        Lupercio Leonardo de Argensola (1559&#8211;1613) and Bartolom&#232; Leonardo de
                        Argensola (1561&#8211;1631).</note> I asserted, from the Parnaso Espanol, that no
                    edition of their works had been printed since that of Zaragosa, 1634:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Jos&#233; Lopez de Sedano (1729&#8211;1801), <title>El
                            Parnaso Espa&#241;ol</title>, 9 vols (Madrid, 1768&#8211;1778), III, p.
                        xvii.</note> I have now procured one published since the Parnaso. Don Ramon
                    Fernandez, the editor, has prefixed a sensible preface: &#8220;One of the principal
                    causes,&#8221; he says, &#8220;of the bad taste observable in the greater part of the poetry
                    of the present day, is the scarceness of good authors, who might serve as models
                    to our youth; while the multiplied editions of the corruptors of our poetry are
                    in the hands of all, maintaining and perpetuating a bad taste.&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Ramon Fernandez [pseud. Pedro Mariano de los
                        &#193;ngeles Estala Ribera] (1757&#8211;1815), <title>Rimas del Doctor Bartolome
                            Leonardo de Argensola</title>, 3 vols (Madrid, 1786), I, p. [4]. The
                        translation is probably Southey&#8217;s own.</note> He remarks the vague eulogies
                    lavished upon the Spanish poets by their editors, applying to them
                    indiscriminately the phrases of purity, elegance, enthusiasm, beauty, &amp;c.
                    and proceeds to point out the characteristic and peculiar merit of the two
                    Argensolas. In this preface there is a very curious trait of the national
                    vanity. After mentioning the rich and harmonious versification of these authors,
                    he adds, this has at all times been an endowment peculiar to the Spanish poets,
                    for if we consider well, we shall find that they gave a harmony and ease to the
                    Latin metres which is not to be met with in the poets anterior to Lucan and
                        Seneca.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcus Annaeus Lucanus (AD
                        39&#8211;65) and Lucius Annaeus Seneca (4 BC&#8211;AD 65).</note> The chorusses of the
                    three genuine tragedies of this great tragedian,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lupercio Leonardo de Argensola wrote three tragedies,
                            <title>Filis</title>, <title>Isabela</title> and
                            <title>Alejandra</title>. The first was lost, the latter two were
                        modelled on Seneca and remained unpublished until 1772.</note> incomparably
                    exceed those of Horace in their flowingness and harmony; and the excellent
                    hexameters of Lucan, have, in these points, a great advantage over those of
                    Virgil. And even what Cicero<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey adds
                        footnote: &#8216;Cordubae natis poetis pingue quiddam cantibus atque peregrinum.
                        Cicer. pro Archia.&#8217; [Editorial note: The Latin translates as &#8216;to poets born
                        at Cordova who sound a bit coarse and foreign&#8217;, Marcus Tullius Cicero
                        (106&#8211;43 BC), <title>Pro Archia Poeta</title>, 26.]</note> says of the
                    Cordovan poets confirms this, though some, from wrongly understanding the
                    passage, interpret it as a reproach: for Tully, in this place, speaks only of
                    their pronunciation and accent, which to Roman ears, accustomed only to
                    sweetness, might appear strange and harsh; this by no means proves that their
                    verses were bad or deficient in harmony; instead of this I presume, that the too
                    great swell and fullness of the Spanish poets, that <hi rend="ital">loquiore
                        rotundo</hi>,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace (65&#8211;8 BC),
                            <title>Ars Poetica</title>, line 323. The Latin translates as &#8216;with
                        full-voice&#8217;.</note> that <hi rend="ital">os magna sonaturum</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace, <title>Satires</title>, Book 1, no. 4,
                        lines 43&#8211;44. The Latin translates as &#8216;a grand and lofty style&#8217;.</note> which
                    Horace so much recommends, and which since the Greeks none have executed better
                    than the Spaniards; this I conceive to be what appeared unpleasant to Cicero,
                    whose ears were accustomed to verse little more harmonious than those of
                        Ennius.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Quintus Ennius (239&#8211;c. 169
                        BC), Roman poet. The previous paragraph derives from Ramon Fernandez,
                            <title>Rimas del Doctor Bartolome Leonardo de Argensola</title>, 3 vols
                        (Madrid, 1786), I, pp. 17&#8211;18. The translation is probably Southey&#8217;s
                        own.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The epistle from which an extract was printed in your Magazine,
                    is given by the present editor to Francisco de Rioje.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Epistola&#8217; (&#8216;Fabio, las esperanzas cortesanas&#8217;) had been
                        attributed to Bartolom&#232; Leonardo de Argensola by Juan Jos&#233; Lopez de Sedano,
                            <title>El Parnaso Espa&#241;ol</title>, 9 vols (Madrid, 1768&#8211;1778), I, pp.
                        226&#8211;233. Southey had included a translated extract from the poem in a letter
                        published in the <title>Monthly Magazine</title> in July 1797 (see
                            <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 1</title>, Letter
                        230). The poem was reattributed to Francisco de Rioja (1583&#8211;1659) by Ramon
                        Fernandez, <title>Rimas del Doctor Bartolome Leonardo de Argensola</title>,
                        3 vols (Madrid, 1786), III, p. 10.</note> I know not whether the reasons he
                    assigns are sufficient to ascertain the author, but they certainly prove that it
                    could not have been written by Bartolome Leonardo:</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have selected three sonnets as characteristic of these authors,
                    the two first are by Lupercio:</p>
        <lg>
          <l rend="indent4"> Thou art determined to be beautiful,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Lyris! and, Lyris, either thou art mad,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Or hast no looking-glass; dost thou not know</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Thy paint-beplaster&#8217;d forehead, broad and bare,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> With not a grey lock left, thy mouth so black,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And that invincible breath? We rightly deem </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> That with a random hand blind Fortune deals</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The lots of life, to thee she gave a boon</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> That crowds so anxiously and vainly wish,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Old age, and left in thee no trace of youth</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Save all its folly and its ignorance.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Lupercio Leonardo de Argensola, &#8216;Por fuerza
                            quieres, Lice, ser hermosa&#8217;, in Ramon Fernandez, <title>Rimas del Doctor
                                Bartolome Leonardo de Argensola</title>, 3 vols (Madrid, 1786), I,
                            p. 73. The translation is probably Southey&#8217;s own, and a copy in
                                his<title> Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                            (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 272, dated 2 January 1798, suggests it was a
                            very recent one.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent6"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent4"> Content with what I am; the foundling names</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Of glory tempt not me; nor is there ought</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In glittering grandeur that provokes one wish</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Beyond my peaceful state. What tho&#8217; I boast</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> No trapping that the multitude adores</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> In common with the great; enough for me</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> That naked, like the mighty of the earth,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> I came into the world, and that like them</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> I must descend into the grave, the house</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> For all appointed; for the space between,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> What more of happiness have I to seek</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Than that dear woman&#8217;s love, whose truth I know,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And whose fond heart is satisfied with me?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Lupercio Leonardo de Argensola, &#8216;Dentro
                            quiero vivir de mi fortuna&#8217;, in Ramon Fernandez, <title>Rimas del Doctor
                                Bartolome Leonardo de Argensola</title>, 3 vols (Madrid, 1786), I,
                            p. 18. The translation is probably Southey&#8217;s own, and a copy in his
                                <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                            (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 272, dated 1 January 1798, suggests it was a
                            very recent one.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent6"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent5">
          <title>From Bartolome Leonardo</title>
        </p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent4"> Fabius, to think that God hath in the lines</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Of the right hand disclosed the things to come,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> And in the wrinkles of the skin pourtrayed,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> As in a map, the way of human life,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> This is to follow with the multitude</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Error or ignorance, their common guides;</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Yet surely I allow that God has placed </l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Our fate in our own hands, or evil or good</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Even as we make it: tell me, Fabius,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Ar&#8217;t not a king thyself? &#8212; when envying not</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> The lot of kings, no idle wish disturbs</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Thy quiet life; when, a self-govern&#8217;d man,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> No laws exist to thee; and when no change</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> With which the will of Heaven may visit thee,</l>
          <l rend="indent3"> Can break the even calmness of thy soul?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Bartolom&#232; Leonardo de Argensola (1561&#8211;1631),
                            &#8216;Fabio, pensar que el Padre soberano&#8217;, in Ramon Fernandez, <title>Rimas
                                del Doctor Bartolome Leonardo de Argensola</title>, 3 vols (Madrid,
                            1786), II, p. 187. The translation is probably Southey&#8217;s own, and a copy
                            in his <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                            (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 272&#8211;273, dated 31 December 1797, suggests
                            it was a very recent one.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent9">T.Y.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>