<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce458</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.449</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4824 .  Previously 
                        published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp.
                        299&#8211;301 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.449" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="449" type="letter">
        <head>449. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>,
                        <date when="1799-10-22">22 October 1799</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/
                            M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor
                            Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/ Norwich./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: CHRIST/ CHURCH<lb />Postmark: E/ OCT
                        24/ 99 <lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1
                        Nov<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4824 <lb />Previously
                        published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp.
                        299&#8211;301 [in part].</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is one among the many disadvantages of
                    being without a local habitation, to be without a direction.
                    a rambler is half forgotten by his friends because they know
                    not where to remember him. We are now revolutionizing two
                    adjoining hovels, into a dwelling house one &amp;
                    indivisible, &amp; in the course of another ten days I shall
                    be settled with my books about me. my direction is <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> near Ringwood.
                    Hampshire. our situation two miles from the verge of the New
                    Forest &amp; one &amp; a half from the sea. the Needles
                    &amp; the Southern &amp; Western rocks of the Isle of Wight
                    rise opposite our shore at the distance of nine miles. I
                    should like to show you the country, &#8722; &amp; if Summer &amp;
                    Autumn are not dead, <del rend="strikethrough">but</del>
                    only missing like half the poor soldiers in Holland,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">An Anglo-Russian
                        invasion of Holland on 27 August 1799 had led to a
                        serious defeat at the Battle of Castricum on 6 October
                        1799. In the ensuing retreat, two field hospitals of
                        wounded, 400 women and children and an unknown number of
                        soldiers were left behind.</note> there is perhaps
                    enough to repay you, in a better season, for the journey. we
                    are just an hundred miles from London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am finishing the fourth book of my
                        Dom-Daniel-romance<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">An early name for <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> &#8211; the plan of the
                    remainder is matured, my head full of eastern scenery &amp;
                    I look to speedily conclude it. have you seen a poem called
                        Gebir?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter
                        Savage Landor, <title>Gebir</title> (1798), although the
                        poem was published anonymously.</note> It appears to me
                    the miraculous work of a madman &#8211; <del rend="strikethrough">it</del> its intelligible passages are flashes of
                    lightning at midnight &#8211; like a picture in whose obscure
                    colouring no plan is discoverable, but in every distinct
                    touch you see the Masters hand.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is a
                        prisoner.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">It was
                        widely reported in the British Press in early October
                        1799, e.g. <title>St James&#8217;s Chronicle</title>, 5
                        October 1799, that the brig, <hi rend="ital">Sylph</hi>,
                        on which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom
                            Southey</ref> was serving, had been captured and was
                        at the Spanish port of Ferrol.</note> at least we hope
                    so. it is eight or ten weeks since we have heard from him.
                    on our arrival here we saw in the newspaper that a large
                    Kings brig had been seen lying in Ferrol, &amp; that she was
                    supposed to be the Sylph. here our intelligence ends &#8211; but
                    this is almost a certainty, &amp; our chief uneasiness
                    arises from not knowing whether there had been an action
                    previous to the capture. I conclude not &#8211; because a Spanish
                    brig would not attack &amp; could not take an English one,
                    &amp; because a brig could not resist a ship of superiour
                    force. It is most probable that the Sylph was picked up by
                    the line of battle ships that have been dodging from Ferrol
                    to Rochefort, from Rochefort to L&#8217;Orient &amp; from L&#8217;Orient
                    to Ferrol again. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">My mother</ref> is of course very uneasy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We shall see <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> at
                    Christmas. in six or twelve months more he will be able to
                    begin anatomical or chemical studies. I think of placing him
                    at a German University to graduate &#8211; because it is less
                    expensive &amp; because he will at least acquire a knowledge
                    of the language.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a paper in one of the late Monthly
                        Magazines<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 8 (September
                        1799), 597&#8211;601. The article was by Taylor.</note> which
                    I half belief to be yours &amp; half disbelieve its
                    contradictory evidence &#8211; upon modern Jesuitism. I miss you
                    in the Review. the Critical is so miserably bad, that
                    indolently as I write myself I am almost ashamed to be in
                    such company. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am arranging my materials for the second
                        Anthology.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1800).</note> the
                    first has crept into the world silently &#8211; perfectly still
                    born. the home-sale at Bristol has been extensive &amp; the
                    book where it is known sufficiently popular. the Reviews may
                    perhaps do something for it, &amp; the second volume will do
                    more. As yet I have no stranger-communication, but in the
                    little world of poetry my acquaintance is by no means
                    confined. I have one or two pieces of greater length than
                    any in the first volume, &#8722; but nothing to equal your
                    topographical ode.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Annual Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1799),
                        pp. 1&#8211;9.</note> that stands &amp; must stand alone. Did
                    you receive the first volume?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have &lt;just&gt; got the Zend-Avesta &#8211; but
                    have not yet advanced thro the preliminaries. the merits of
                    Anquetil du Perron<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Abraham-Hyacinthe Anquetil Du Perron (1731&#8211;1805),
                            <title>Zend-Avesta</title> (1771), a French
                        translation of the sacred writings of Zoroastrianism.
                        The book was no. 3135 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                        library.</note> I am told, have been underrated by
                    Richardson &amp; Sir William Jones.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Richardson (1740/1&#8211;1795;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Sir William Jones
                        (1746&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), Britain&#8217;s two foremost
                        orientalists of the late eighteenth century.</note> he
                    is not answerable for the nonsense of the book. I procured
                    the book with the remote view of making Mango Capac<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Legendary founder of
                        the Inca Empire in the 12th or 13th centuries.</note>
                    the hero of a poem, &amp; bringing him from among the <del rend="strikethrough">persecuted</del> followers of
                    Zoroaster flying from Mohammedan persecution. a more
                    immediate motive was to gratify an old curiosity. some
                    assistance I may perhaps derive for Thalaba &#8211; my
                    Dom-Daniel-Destroyer. &amp; among the many little pieces
                    that I needs must write it is my intention to write <del rend="strikethrough">skex</del> sketches characteristic
                    of the manners &amp; mythologies of different nations. some
                    of these relative to the American Indians you may possibly
                    have seen in the Morning Post.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Song of the Araucans&#8217;, <title>Morning
                            Post</title>, 10 August 1799; &#8216;The Dirge of the
                        American Widow&#8217;, <title>Morning Post</title>, 11
                        September 1799; &#8216;The Old Chikkasah to his Grandson&#8217;,
                            <title>Morning Post</title>, 21 September
                        1799.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Brownes Travels<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William George Browne (1768&#8211;1813;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in Africa,
                            Egypt, and Syria, from the Years 1792 to
                            1798</title> (1799).</note> disappointed me. that a
                    man should go so far &amp; see so little! &amp; in the
                        Critical<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Critical Review</title>, 26 (August 1799),
                        [361]&#8211;379.</note> there is the puff superlative upon his
                    meagre narrative. Park<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Mungo Park (1771&#8211;1806;
                        <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Interior of
                            Africa</title> (1799).</note> interested me far
                    more. these African adventurers seem to go foolishly to
                    work. circumcision would save them half their dangers.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Both Browne and Park
                        endured periods of captivity at the hands of Muslim
                        rulers. Southey is implying their journeys would have
                        been more trouble-free if they had converted to
                        Islam.</note> after all the probability is that Africa
                    will be chiefly explored from [MS torn] English Cape of Hope
                    &#8211; &amp; from French Egypt. Buonaparte!!<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                        (1769&#8211;1821, First Consul 1799&#8211;1804, Emperor of the
                        French 1804&#8211;1814).</note> [MS torn] </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I directed a fortnight ago from Exeter a
                    letter for <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> to you [MS torn]ceiving that he would be
                    with you when it arrived. it encloses the half [MS torn] ten
                    pound bill &amp; as he has not acknowledged it I fear it
                    must have been lost.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A little practice has enabled me to
                    hexametrize with facility. in my next I will send you a
                    specimen. the people at Christ Church have been disappointed
                    of an illumination. they were going to light up their houses
                    for the capture of Alkmaar<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Alkmaar in the Netherlands had been
                        captured by Anglo-Russian allied forces on 2 October
                        1799. However, the French successfully halted the
                        allies&#8217; advance at the Battle of Castricum, 6 October
                        1799.</note> &#8211; but consented to wait till the allies had
                    got to Amsterdam!</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1799-10-22">Tuesday Oct. 22. 99.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>