<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce783</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.774</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols
                        (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    311-312.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="774" type="letter">
<head>774. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1803-04-19">19 April
                        1803</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. M.P./ Chester<lb/>Postmark:
                        [partial] BRISTOL/ APR 1803<lb/>Endorsement: April 19
                        1803<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                            <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols
                        (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    311-312.</note>
</head>
<p>I have just received yours. your grandmothers death<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Wynn, née
                        Shakerley (1717-1803), second wife of Sir Watkin
                        Williams-Wynn (1692-1749; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
                    the papers had told me – but I was not aware that she had
                    outlived all the enjoyment of life. this cursed
                        Influenza<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        influenza epidemic of 1803.</note> has <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del> cut off my best friend
                    here – the mother of <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>. an
                        <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">old Lady</ref> of
                    whom you must have heard me speak. whom I regarded with
                    something like a family affection. I got thro the Influenza,
                    &amp; then <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>
                    had it – next it passed to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> &amp; lastly the servant<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> was
                    attacked so we had our share.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> is
                    appointed to the Galatea – not the Mercury.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, a 32-gun Royal Navy frigate, bound
                        for the West Indies; HMS <hi rend="ital">Mercury</hi>, a
                        28-gun Royal Navy frigate, serving in the Eastern
                        Atlantic.</note> but the papers were well informed, for
                    his commission had the word Mercury erased. he of course
                    joined immediately. he tells me our present naval force is
                    mere show. the ships all want men. One of the 74s at
                    Spithead which lies there as if ready for service has only
                    40 hands besides the marines. the Galatea has not a single
                    man. Surely if war was actually apprehended higher bounties
                    would be offered &amp; the press be hotter.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Yesterday the last of Amadis<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s translation of
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> went
                    off to London. I have now to review a collection of the
                    living Italian poets<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly G.B. Cassano (fl. 1802), <title>Il Fiore della
                            Poesia Italiana</title> (1802), which Southey
                        reviewed in <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2
                        (1804), 562-563.</note> &amp; then shall feel myself
                    free again. in writing the preface to Amadis I formed an
                    opinion concerning the origin of romantic machinery
                    different from either Wartons<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Warton (1728-1790;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Observations on The
                            Fairy Queen of Spenser</title>, 2 vols (London,
                        1762), II, p. 84, claimed ‘the romances of the dark
                        ages’ were ‘founded on Saracen superstitions’.</note> or
                        Percy.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                        Percy (1729-1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliques
                            of Ancient English Poetry</title>, 3 vols (London,
                        1767), I, pp. xix-lxxvi, ‘An Essay on the Ancient
                        English Minstrels’ claimed an Anglo-Saxon and Nordic
                        origin for romance.</note> it appears to me to be
                    derived neither from Arabia nor Scandinavia, but to be of
                    classical derivation, modified by the circumstances of
                    society. Enchanted arms, magical rings – dragons – are all
                    to be found in classical fiction. The Fairies (the
                    legitimate fairies – such as Morgana le Fay are Nymphs –
                    &amp; the Ladies of the Lake a great improvement upon the
                    Naiads.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I do not think it impossible that the
                    original Amadis may still exist. before the present Spanish
                        book<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The earliest
                        printed edition of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> was
                        produced in 1508. Southey may not have seen this
                        version. Though he borrowed a Spanish version of the
                        story from Reginald Heber for his translation of
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803), the earliest
                        Spanish edition in Heber’s library is from 1551,
                            <title>Biblioteca Heberiana; Catalogue of the
                            Library of the Late Richard Heber, Part One</title>
                        (London, 1834), no. 92. This may explain Southey’s
                        puzzlement about the popularity of the story during the
                        invasion of Mexico in 1519-1521.</note> was printed the
                    story was popular. the Spaniards when they came in sight of
                    Mexico said it was like the enchanted palaces in Amadis–
                    &amp; they called a braggart another <hi rend="ital">Agrajes
                        sin obras</hi>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish translates literally as ‘Agrajes without
                        deeds’, a description from <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>
                        of the knight Agrajes of Scotland, which later migrated
                        into popular usage. Southey’s introductory essay to his
                        translation, <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>, 4 vols
                        (London, 1803), I, pp. xxxii-xxxiii, repeats much of the
                        information in this paragraph.</note>
<del rend="strikethrough">which xxx</del> the character of
                    Agrayes has been modified by the Spanish editor – but one
                    sees that it may have been originally of that stamp. Now
                    manuscript copies must have been common in some shape or
                    other, or the book never could have been the bye-word of an
                    army. Tressan<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis-Elisabeth de La Vergne, Comte de Tressan
                        (1705-1783), <title>Traduction Libre d’Amadis de
                            Gaule</title>, 2 vols (Amsterdam, 1780), I, p. xxv,
                        no. 41 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                        library.</note>
<hi rend="ital">thinks</hi> he saw the <hi rend="ital">Picard</hi> original as he will have it, in the
                    Vatican. if he saw it at all he might have mistaken old
                    Portugueze for Romance. I should not be very greatly
                    surprized were I one day to find the original rotting in
                    some Convent Library.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You will now hear of Madocs <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had completed a
                        version of <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799 and was
                        revising it for publication. It did not appear until
                        1805.</note> rapid progress. I wish I could find such
                    mines of Welsh anecdote as my Spanish books open of Indian
                    costume. there I am very rich. &amp; on the other hand my
                    head is full of Welsh scenery – not American. I did not see
                    enough of Wales – but not a single thing of what I did see
                    is lost. I can call up the whole succession of <del rend="strikethrough">hills &amp;</del> rocks &amp;
                    streams &amp; lakes &amp; mountains with life-vividness.
                    Last Autumn I went to Dinevor – full of expectation &amp;
                    determined to make my description upon my spot. It was so
                    little &amp; insignificant compared to the Northern scenery
                    that I did not write a line; it is a mighty pretty noblemans
                    seat – but for the castle of a Welsh Prince! Dolbadan is the
                    place.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you –</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> R S.</signed>
<lb/>
<date when="1803-04-19">Tuesday 19. April. 1803.</date>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
