<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce859</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.850</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 81-83. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.850" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="850" type="letter">
        <head>850. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1803-11-10">10 November 1803</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond/
                        Surry/ Single<lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />Postmarks: E/ NOV 14/ 1803;
                        10o&#8217;Clock/ NO 14/ 1803 F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Watermark: JM &amp; Co/
                        1800<lb />Endorsement: 86 1803/ Robert Southey/ No place 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Nov/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi>
                            d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title>
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 81-83. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter as you may well suppose has given me very great
                    uneasiness. Among all his faults <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> disingenuousness appears to me the worst. I could more readily
                    have admitted or devised palliations for the rest. It grieves me that he has
                    been thus turned to Edinburgh, tho after M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Martineau<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip Meadows Martineau (1752-1829),
                        surgeon at the Norfolk and Norwich Hospital and a member of the Martineau
                        family, prominent Unitarians in Norwich. Henry Herbert Southey entered the
                        University of Edinburgh in November 1803.</note> refused to keep him I know
                    not what else could have been done. But to the point of the money matters &#8211; add
                    the sum you speak of to my debt &#8211; the burden belongs to me more fitly than to
                        <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, &#8211; &amp; in fact
                    it is the same thing for if I should want he would be ready did he know it to
                    assist me. I am labouring assiduously to make Madoc<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey completed a version of <title>Madoc</title> in
                        1797-1799 and was revising it for publication. It did not appear until
                        1805.</note> fit for the press. my intention is to publish it by
                    subscription that I may make as much by it as I can, &amp; my object with those
                    profits to discharge my debt to you, that is what of it is dischargeable, for
                    the bond of deep &amp; lasting obligation will remain, a thankful recollection
                    of good offices, &#8211; unalterable esteem &amp; affection. this intention I have
                    just begun to make known to my friends. not meaning to announce it publicly till
                    I have seen what private success I may meet with. It was at the age of fourteen
                    that the design of this poem was conceived &#8211; at that &lt;time&gt; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> was made acquainted with it
                    &amp; from that time it has never been out of my mind. There is to me a sort of
                    awefulness in compleating it &#8211; I feel as tho discharging one of the purposes of
                    my existence, &amp; have a sort of presage that I shall live to set forth that
                    &amp; my History<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s uncompleted
                        &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> &amp; that then my work will be done. I would
                    fain leave those fair testimonies behind me, proofs of what I could have done
                    under more favourable circumstances, for my chief labours will have been obscure
                    task work, things written without choice, without pleasure, without hope &#8211; from
                    the mere motive of the from-hand-to-mouth profits which poor as they are are
                    more than could be obtained by the best &amp; voluntary efforts of a healthy
                    intellect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What you say of your own affairs grieves me deeply.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John May&#8217;s business was in serious financial
                        difficulties because of unpaid debts.</note> I have no consolation to offer.
                    perhaps the evil may be averted &#8211; God grant it! yet at the worst you are a man
                    prepared for the change, &amp; a mind of Xtian fortitude extracts not only
                    consolation but even a kind of joy from endurance. Your relatives too have the
                    means &amp; the will to set your fortunes once more afloat should they now be
                    wrecked. To me however it appears very improbable that even if Portugal be
                    forced into a war with England<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Portugal
                        and Britain did not go to war and Portugal retained a precarious neutrality
                        until 1807.</note> she would commit an act of such villainy so to terminate
                        <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> an alliance so faithfully preserved for
                    so many generations. Our Government too must be very remiss if they suffer such
                    a confiscation to take place. Lisbon is not the defenceable city it was in
                        1384,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1384 Lisbon was
                        unsuccessfully besieged by a Castilian army.</note> nor are its batteries
                    such as would now intimidate an English fleet. If the property of the English
                    merchants be not regularly embarked, a few ships of the line would prove
                    excellent negociators.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I continue in tolerable health. my eyes have been a sore
                    grievance to me &amp; a very serious evil. from the expence of time they have
                    occasioned. at present they are better &#8211; yet they still prevent me from that
                    continual employment to which I have been accustomed. my mornings are still at
                    Reviewing, the least interesting of all employments but the most profitable.
                    when this is cleared off I must look out for some fresh job. my evenings are at
                    history or Madoc. as I feel the wind blow &amp; both advance well. but I shall
                    soon be distressed for the Castenheda.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Fernao Lopes de Castanheda (c. 1500-1559), <title>Historia do
                            Descobrimento, e Conquista da India pelos Portuguezas</title> (1554).
                        Southey owned two volumes of a 1797 eight-volume edition, no. 3187 in the
                        sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> having only the first book like
                    yourself. the enormous price of the old copy put it quite of my reach. indeed
                    this unhappy broil with Portugal will sadly affect my history. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> was perpetually on the
                    look out for materials &#8211; &amp; now I shall have no other resource than to beg
                    favours of great men, &amp; examine books uncomfortably in their libraries which
                    would have made me quite happy by my own fire side.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> is in a
                    miserable state of health. he has a sort of anomalous gout which damp weather
                    never fails to put in action, &amp; which flies all over him, sometimes puffing
                    up his hand or feet or knee &#8211; then back into the stomach or head. it does not
                    emaciate him, yet the attacks are so sudden, &amp; so often accompanied by
                    violent diarrh&#230;a that they are very alarming. he himself is convinced that a
                    warm climate would be his only cure &amp; all the medical friends whom he has
                    consulted are of the same opinion. indeed he is as much affected by weather as a
                    barometer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is in feeble health. our low
                    spirits we both keep to ourselves, perhaps thinking the more because we never
                    mention the subject. we beg our remembrances to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        May.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Susanna Frances Livius
                        (1767-1830).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1803-11-10">Thursday. Nov. 10. 1803.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>