<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce529</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.520</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Huntington Library, RS 7.  Previously  published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 223–227.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="520" type="letter">
<head>520. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                        Rickman</ref>, <date when="1800-05-02">2 May 1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John
                        Rickman/ 33 Southampton Buildings/ Holburn/ London/ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        LISBON<lb/>Postmark: FOREIGN OFFICE/ MA/ 17/ 1800<lb/>Endorsement: May 2.
                        1800<lb/>MS: Huntington Library, RS 7<lb/>Previously published: Kenneth
                        Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London
                        and New York, 1965), I, pp. 223–227.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<address>
<placeName>Lisbon.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1800-05-02">Friday May 2. 1800</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> The voyage is over. we had fair weather, light winds, &amp; a
                    fine passage of only five days &amp; a half. soon said – but what a world of
                    misery was comprized in those five days &amp; half! I neither could eat or
                    sleep, &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> suffered more
                    than me. all my former sea nausea was trifling to this – &amp; yet our weather
                    was so singularly favourable. I saw porpusses – &amp; a grampus. a shark was
                    seen but not by me. one only adventure diversified our voyage. a cutter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Fortunately, the ‘cutter’ turned out to be
                        the British frigate HMS <hi rend="ital">Endymion</hi>.</note> bore down upon
                    us, we supposed her to be French &amp; prepared for action – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> – half dead with fear – was
                    stowed in the cockpit – &amp; I stationed myself on the quarter deck with a
                    musquet – which I replaced in the musquet chest with no small joy when the
                    cutter spoke us – or rather answered us in English. it cured me for six hours,
                    the joy of keeping my legs &amp; arms made my stomach in good humour.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We arrived yesterday morning, &amp; are now half settled in our
                    house. My old friend Manuel<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel
                        Mambrino (dates unknown), a Spanish servant from Oviedo who worked for
                        Herbert Hill. Mambrino had accompanied Southey on some of his travels in
                        Spain and Portugal in 1795–1796.</note> is consigned over to me, much to my
                    satisfaction as well as his own. he has I believe a regard for me &amp; talks of
                    our journey with a minuteness of recollection which only pleasure could have
                    preserved. his voice &amp; tones are familiar, &amp; assist me in the language –
                    besides he has brains, &amp; if he cannot take me the straight road to his
                    meaning, will drive roundabout till I get there at last. We are without a female
                    servant. the one who was engaged for us disappointed <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>. his old woman at
                    present visits us. today I have sate at the receipt of visits – these I must
                    return in due form, – then plead my health, drop the intercourse &amp; go to
                    work.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Four years have passed away since I left Lisbon. so long a time
                    had blunted memory, &amp; every thing seems half new to me – new enough to
                    interest – not to depress by a total strangeness. I see much which would else
                    have escaped me thro <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> eyes.
                    she is as much amused at seeing the Portugueze women walking in thick heavy
                    large woollen cloaks in their May, as they would be at her muslin in an English
                    December. Every thing, while it amuses her, makes her like England – but you
                    know how any foreign country makes an Englishman proud – &amp; will easily
                    conceive that I am all Anglicanized already. An Englishman in the streets of
                    Lisbon – is like the Heathen Gods of poetry when they descend you know them by
                    their gait – their figure – not by their odours indeed – for the difference
                    between them &amp; the natives is that they do not smell, &amp; the perfumes of
                    ambrosia could have been nothing to the delight of having no stink at all here.
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has discovered that there
                    are no middle-aged women to be seen – this is a well known effect of hot
                    climate. like the primrose that <del rend="strikethrough">blossom</del> flowers
                    the Portugueze women burst into full bloom at once – &amp; then wither away. I
                    have discovered something too – that married persons use seperate beds – this is
                    the necessity of the climate, which I might have guessed. the natives are a
                    libidinous people &amp; perhaps this custom may be one of the disposing
                    causes.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I learnt from a fellow passenger, who has been two years ago in
                    Spain, that their abridged translation of Adam Smiths book<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam Smith (1723–1790; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>The Wealth of Nations</title> (1776).</note> has been suppressed.
                    they have also suppressed a translation of Buchans domestic physician<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Buchan (1729–1805; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Domestic Medicine, or the Family Physician</title> (1769).</note>
                    because he says the passing bell is a ridiculous custom, which sometimes kills
                    the sick by terrifying them. the chief novelty here is paper money – of how long
                    date I know not yet – but the government themselves discounted it at six per
                    cent the first week – &amp; it is now at 20 per cent – <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxxx</del> discount! this occasioned an odd symptom here some fortnight
                    ago only. they paid their sailors chiefly in this paper – the men went to pay it
                    away as they received it, at par – &amp; their disappointment produced a sort of
                    riot – they shouted out Liberty – &amp; Bonaparte. it was quelled &amp; some of
                    the ring leaders are in custody, but no punishment has been inflicted.</p>
<p rend="indent1">I must not forget one great innovation – a mail coach runs to
                    Coimbra – on the way to Porto &amp; is to go all the way when the road is
                    compleated. it travels eight miles an hour. true <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> – <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> has taken the journey
                    in it. tis a Royal business, &amp; it answers for the road is frequented. one
                    might prophecy good from this, the establishment of decent inns &amp; the growth
                    of civilization.</p>
<p rend="center">___</p>
<p rend="indent1">Half a days delay has already given me something to correct. the
                    Mail Coach is not well managed &amp; not expected to last. tis a government
                    business &amp; priced so high as to exclude the great body of travellers – the
                    little dealers who mount their mules. now a single persons expences amount to as
                    much as if he was in a chaise singly. the Paper money has produced its usual
                    consequence – Forgery. you must note however that Portugueze eyes can see these
                    slippery places for roguery. a German of talents &amp; once of respectability is
                    in custody for it in England.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Some inconvenience <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> has been
                    produced to Strangers by the wish of England to send her wild Irishmen here.
                    they are detained at a little fort to give in their names &amp; be vouched for
                    by some settler, &amp; the nephew of a settler was <del rend="strikethrough">not</del> sent back by the ship in which he came only because he was born
                    in Ireland! – Counsellor Sampson<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Sampson (1764–1836; <title>DNB</title>), United Irishman and lawyer, exiled
                        after the 1798 rising. Arrested at Oporto, 12 March 1799 and imprisoned in
                        Lisbon. He eventually settled in the United States.</note> – one of the
                    Directors there who fell – magnis tamen ausis<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of Publius Ovidius Naso (43 BC–AD 17),
                            <title>Metamorphoses</title>, Book 2, line 323: ‘magnis tamen excidit
                        ausis’; ‘he fell, however, in a noble attempt’.</note> – landed at Porto
                    &amp; after a months quiet residence was arrested – brought here &amp;
                    imprisoned at Belem. some of his countrymen asked permission to see him. it was
                        <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> answered – o yes – as many as please may
                    see him – but then you shall stay with him – &amp; they actually did shut <del rend="strikethrough">one</del> up one person for his visit. Sampson has
                    since been sent to Hambro.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> An imposition of some consequence takes place upon passengers at
                    Falmouth. four guineas are taken – by no authority whatever, at the passport
                    off[MS torn] say it is a Post Office charge. &amp; that the money goes to some
                    charity. When <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; I
                    crossed in the Spanish captain the same charge was made. why how is this? said
                    he to the Spanish Captain. the Post Office cannot put this on. No. said
                        Aruspini<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Don Raimundo Aruspini (dates
                        unknown), Captain of the Spanish packet on which Southey crossed from
                        Falmouth to Coruna in 1795.</note> – but I do.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We landed without difficulty &amp; our trunks were not examined.
                    for this we were obliged to the Commissary here who came on board with <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> to serve us in this
                    business. – I have been paying my form visits to the Envoy<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Walpole (1736–1810), Envoy Extraordinary
                        and Minister Plenipotentiary to Portugal 1772–1800.</note> – the Consul<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Arbuthnot (1767–1850;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Consul and Charge d’Affaires in Portugal 1800–1801.
                        Educated at Westminster School 1779–1784; a career diplomat, later a
                        government Minister and confidante of the Duke of Wellington.</note> – the
                    Commander in Chief<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Simon Fraser
                        (1738–1813; <title>DNB</title>), Major-General in command of British forces
                        in Portugal 1797–1800.</note> – &amp; this round is not yet over, but after
                    the ceremonials are over an invalids privilege will secure me enough privacy. we
                    shall summerize at <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>. I <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> have begun immediately my plan of early
                    rising &amp; it has helped me thro my letter writing, which on arrival in a
                    foreign country is a serious job. this once done – &amp; the next packet will
                    finish it, for I cannot write all by this. I turn to serious employment. in my
                    next I will tell you my intended plan of proceeding in my historical
                    undertaking.</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<del rend="strikethrough">If the Magazine plan xxxxxxx xxx xxxx like xxxxxx
                        rhyme xxxx xxxxxxx xxxxxxxx be of any xxxx – but my xx xxxxxxx xxxxxxxx of
                        the scheme xxxx xxxxx xxxxxx these xx xxxxxxxx xxxx of xxxxxxx xxxxxx &amp;
                        xxxx &amp; xxxxxxxx for you &amp; xx xxxxxx I wrote to xxxxxx xxxxxxxx xxxx
                        xx xxxx xx my plan xxxxx up to xxxx xxxxxx xxxx xxxxx xxx</del> – I had almost forgotten <title>Thalaba.</title> at Falmouth I wrote half a book
                    – &amp; digested my plan for the remainder in bed on shipboard. – I am not a
                    little proud to find that I speak the language &amp; understand it better than
                    when I left Lisbon. Reading has done this for me.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref target="people.html#DyerGeorge">George
                        Dyer</ref>, my very good friend, who is the friend of every body &amp; to
                        <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#Cottlefamily">Robert Cottle</ref> – I have brought a
                    pair of the clogs over – but dare not show them before the wet weather – for now
                    they are preposterous as a parasol would be in Greenland. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> begs to be remembered. we felt
                    your loss at Bristol – &amp; I often wish <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> could annihilate space as well as matter &amp; enable me to
                    perceive the percipient Perception which conveys to me the <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> impression called <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>. </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> Farewell – yrs truly</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey</signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
