<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce581</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.572</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849-1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.)
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 136-140 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and
                            a Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp. 152-153 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.572" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="572" type="letter">
        <head>572. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel
                        Taylor Coleridge</ref> [fragment], <date when="1801-03-28">28 March
                        1801</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849-1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.)
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 136-140 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and
                            a Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 152-153 [in
                        part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>Lisbon,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1801-03-28">March 28. 1801.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The sight of your hand-writing did not give me much pleasure;
                    &#8217;twas the leg of a lark to a hungry man &#8211; yet it was your hand-writing.
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been more than once tottering on the brink of a letter to
                    you, and more than once the glimpse at some old Spaniard, or the whim of a walk,
                    or an orange, or a bunch of grapes, has tempted me either to industry or
                    idleness. I return rich in materials: a twelvemonth&#8217;s work in England will
                    produce a first volume of my History, and also of the Literary History.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s uncompleted &#8216;History of
                        Portugal&#8217; and his proposal to write a history of the literature of Portugal
                        (and possibly Spain as well).</note> Of success I am not sanguine, though
                    sufficiently so of desert; yet I shall leave a monument to my own memory, and
                    perhaps, which is of more consequence, procure a few life-enjoyments.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My poetising has been exclusively confined to the completion of
                    Thalaba. I have planned a Hindoo romance of original extravagance, and have
                    christened it &#8216;The Curse of Keradon;&#8217;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s plan for what became <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810),
                            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 12-15.</note> but it were unwise to do anything
                    here which were as well done in England; and indeed the easy business of hunting
                    out everything to be seen has taken up no small portion of my time. I have ample
                    materials for a volume of miscellaneous information; my work in England will be
                    chiefly to arrange and tack together; here, I have been glutting, and go home to
                    digest. In May we return; and, on my part, with much reluctance. I have formed
                    local attachments and not personal ones: this glorious river, with its mountain
                    boundaries, this blessed winter sun, and the summer paradise of <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>. I would gladly live and die here.
                    My health is amended materially, but I have seizures enough to assure me that
                    our own unkindly climate will blight me, as it does the myrtle and oranges of
                    this better land; howbeit, business must lead me here once more for the
                    after-volumes of the History. If your ill health should also proceed from
                    English skies, we may perhaps emigrate together at last. One head full of
                    brains, and I should ask England nothing else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Meantime my nearer dreams lay their scenes about the Lakes.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge had moved to the Lake District
                        in 1800.</note> Madoc<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
                        written a version of <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799, but it was
                        extensively revised before publication in 1805.</note> compels me to visit
                    Wales; perhaps we can meet you in the autumn: but for the unreasonable distance
                    from Bristol and London, we might take up our abiding near you. I wish you were
                    at Allfoxen,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Alfoxden House,
                        Somersetshire, rented by William and Dorothy Wordsworth in 1797-1798.</note>
                    &#8211; there was a house big enough: you would talk me into a healthy indolence, and
                    I should spur you to profitable industry.</p>
        <p>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .</p>
        <p>We are threatened with speedy invasion, and the critical hour of Portugal is
                    probably arrived.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Spain had declared war
                        on Portugal on 27 February 1801 and a Spanish invasion was widely
                        expected.</note> No alarm has been so general; they have sent for transports
                    to secure us a speedy retreat; nor is it impossible that all idlers may be
                    requested to remove before the hurry and crowd of a general departure. Yet I
                    doubt the reality of the danger. Portugal <hi rend="ital">buys respite</hi>;
                    will they kill the goose that lays golden eggs? Will Spain consent to admit an
                    army through that will shake her rotten throne? Will Bonaparte<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769-1821, First Consul
                        1799-1804, Emperor of the French 1804-1814).</note> venture an army where
                    there is danger of the yellow fever? to a part whence all plunder will be
                    removed, where that army will find nothing to eat after a march of 1000 miles,
                    through a starved country? On the other hand, this country may turn round, may
                    join the coalition, seize on English property, and bid us all decamp; this was
                    apprehended; and what dependence can be placed upon utter imbecility? Were it
                    not for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, I would fairly see
                    it out, and witness the whole boderation. There is a worse than the Bastile
                    here, over whose dungeons I often walk
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; But this is not
                    what is to be wished for Portugal, &#8211; this conquest which would excite good
                    feelings against innovation; if there was peace, the business would probably be
                    done at home. England is now the bedarkening power; she is in politics, what
                    Spain was to religion at the Reformation. Change here involves the loss of their
                    colonies; and an English fleet would cut off the supplies of Lisbon.
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160; The monastic
                    orders will accelerate revolution, because the begging friars, mostly young, are
                    mostly discontented, and the rich friars everywhere objects of envy. I have
                    heard the people complain of monastic oppression, and distinguish between the
                    friars and the religion they profess. I even fear, so generally is that
                    distinction made, that popery may exist when monkery is abolished. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In May I hope to be in Bristol; and if it can be so arranged, in
                    September at the Lakes. I should like to winter there; then I might labour at my
                        History;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s projected &#8216;History
                        of Portugal&#8217;.</note> and we might perhaps amuse ourselves with some joint
                    journeyman work, which might keep up winter fires and Christmas tables. Of all
                    this we will write on my return. I now long to be in England; as it is
                    impossible to remain and root here at present. We shall soon and inevitably be
                    expelled, unless a general peace redeem the merchants here from ruin. England
                    has brought Portugal into the scrape, and with rather more than usual prudence,
                    left her in it; it is understood that this country may make her own terms, and
                    submit to France without incurring the resentment of England. When the
                    Portuguese first entered this happy war, the phrase of their ministers was, that
                    they were going to be pallbearers at the funeral of France. Fools! they were
                    digging a grave, and have fallen into it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of all English doings I am quite ignorant. Thomas Dermody,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Dermody (1775&#8211;1802;
                            <title>DNB</title>), poet whose career was interrupted by military
                        service and alcoholism. His <title>Poems, Moral, and Descriptive</title>
                        appeared in 1800, eight years after his previous collection.</note> I see,
                    has risen again; and the Farmer&#8217;s Boy is most miraculously overrated.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s opinion was not shared by
                        others. Robert Bloomfield (1766-1823; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                            Farmer&#8217;s Boy: A Rural Poem</title> went into 10 editions between 1800
                        and 1808.</note> The Monthly Magazine speaks with shallow-pated pertness of
                    your Wallenstein;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Death of
                            Wallenstein. A Tragedy in Five Acts. Translated from the German of
                            Frederick Schiller by S. T. Coleridge</title> (1800), reviewed in the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (December 1800), 611, as &#8216;very
                        affectedly and unequally translated&#8217;.</note> it interests me much; and what
                    is better praise, invited me to a frequent reperusal of its parts: will you
                    think me wrong in preferring it to Schiller&#8217;s other plays?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Christoph Friedrich von Schiller
                        (1759-1805), German playwright.</note> it appears to me more dramatically
                    true. Max may, perhaps, be overstrained, and the woman is like all German
                    heroines; but in Wallenstein is that greatness and littleness united, which
                    stamp the portrait. <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                    Taylor</ref>, you see, is making quaint theories of the Old Testament
                        writers;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter of 1 February
                        1801, Taylor had told Southey that he was working on a &#8216;dissertation&#8217; to
                        prove that &#8216;the apocryphal book, commonly called the Wisdom of Solomon, was
                        written by Jesus Christ himself after the crucifixion&#8217; (J.W. Robberds (ed.),
                            <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, p. 367).</note> how are you
                    employed? Must Lessing wait for the Resurrection before he receives a new
                        life?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge&#8217;s projected life of
                        the German poet, Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (1729-1781).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So you dipped your young <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Pagan</ref> in the Derwent, and
                    baptized him in the name of the river! Should he be drowned there, he will get
                    into the next edition of Wanley&#8217;s Wonders, under the head of God&#8217;s
                        Judgments.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathaniel Wanley
                        (1632/3&#8211;1680; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Wonders of the Little World,
                            or, a General History of Man</title> (1678), a compendium of human
                        prodigies.</note> And how comes on <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref>, and will he remember
                    me? God bless you!</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>