<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce542</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.533</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.) Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.)
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 89&#8211;94 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and
                            a Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp. 101&#8211;102 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="533" type="letter">
        <head>533. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas
                        Southey</ref> [fragment], <date when="1800-06-22">22 June 1800</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: H. M. S.
                        Bellona.<lb />MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.) <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.)
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 89&#8211;94 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and
                            a Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 101&#8211;102 [in
                        part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1800-06-22">June 22. 1800.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Tom,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are just returned from a bull-feast, and I write to you while
                    the feelings occasioned by this spectacle are fresh. I had never before seen
                    one. The buffoonery of teazing bullocks at Madrid was rather foolish than cruel,
                    and its extreme folly excited laughter, as much at the spectators as the thing
                    itself. This is widely different. The handbill was pompous: &#8211; &#8216;Antonio de
                    Cordeiro, who had so distinguished himself last year, was again to perform. The
                    entertainment would deserve the approbation of a generous public. Ten bulls were
                    to be killed, four to be tormented; they were picked bulls, of the Marquis de
                    &#8211;&#8211;&#8217;s breed (I forget his name), and chosen out for their courage and ferocity.&#8217;
                    Yesterday the bull-fighters paraded the streets, as you may have seen
                    rope-dancers and the &#8216;equestrian troop&#8217; at Bristol fair; they were strangely
                    disfigured with masques; one fellow had a paunch and a Punch-hump-back, and all
                    were dressed in true tawdry style. Hot weather is always the season, and Sunday
                    always the day, the amusement being cool and devout! At half after four it
                    began: the hero was on horseback, and half a dozen men on foot to assist him;
                    about ten more sat with pitchforks to defend themselves, ready when wanted: the
                    bulls were all in the area till the amusement opened; they were not large, and
                    not the same breed as in England; they had more the face of the cow than the
                    short sulky look of gentlemen, &#8211; quiet, harmless animals, whom a child might
                    safely have played with, and a woman would have been ashamed to fear. So much
                    for their <hi rend="ital">ferocity!</hi> Courage, indeed, they possessed; they
                    attacked only in self-defence, and you would, like me, have been angry to see a
                    fellow with a spear, provoking a bull whose horns were tipt with large balls,
                    the brave beast, all bleeding with wounds, still facing him with reluctant
                    resistance: once I saw crackers stuck into his neck to irritate him, and heard
                    them burst in his wounds; you will not wonder that I gave the Portuguese a
                    hearty and honest English curse. It is not an affair of courage; the horse is
                    trained, the bull&#8217;s horns muffled, and half a dozen fellows, each ready to
                    assist the other, and each with a cloak, on which the poor animal wastes his
                    anger: they have the rails to leap over, also, and they know that when they drop
                    the cloak he aims always at that; there is, therefore, little danger of a
                    bruise, and none of anything else. The amusement is, therefore, as cowardly as
                    cruel. I saw nine killed; the first wound sickened <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, and my own eyes were not
                    always fixed upon the area. My curiosity was not, perhaps, strictly excusable,
                    but the pain which I endured was assuredly penalty enough. The fiercest of the
                    whole was one of the four who were only tormented; two fellows on asses attacked
                    him with goads, and he knocked them over and over with much spirit; two more
                    came on, standing each in the middle of a painted horse, ridiculously enough &#8211;
                    and I fancy those fellows will remember him for the next fortnight whenever they
                    turn in bed &#8211; and their sham horses were broken to pieces. Three dogs were
                    loosed at another bull, and effectually sickened. I hate bull-dogs; they are a
                    surly, vicious breed, ever ready to attack, mischievous and malicious enough to
                    deserve parliamentary praise from Mr. Wyndham and Mr. Canning.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Windham (1750&#8211;1810; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Secretary of State for War, 1794&#8211;1801, and George Canning (1770&#8211;1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Under-Secretary at the Foreign Office, 1795&#8211;1799,
                        Commissioner at the Board of Control 1799&#8211;1800 and Paymaster of the Forces
                        1800&#8211;1801, had been the most eloquent opponents of the unsuccessful Bill to
                        outlaw bull-baiting in 1800.</note> A large theatre was completely full;
                    men, women, and children were clapping their hands at every wound, and watching
                    with delight the struggles of the dying beasts. It is a damnable sport! and much
                    to the honour of the English here they all dislike it &#8211; very rarely does an
                    Englishman or Englishwoman witness it a second time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will find in Thalaba one accurate image which I observed this
                    evening: a death-sweat <hi rend="ital">darkening the dun hide</hi> of the
                        animal.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 9, line 273.</note> This amusement must
                    have mischievous effects; it makes cruelty familiar: and as for the assertion,
                    that bull-baiting, or bull-butchering, keeps up the courage of the nation, only
                    Wyndham and Canning could have been absurd enough and unfeeling enough to
                    believe it; &#8211; if it were true, the Spaniards ought to be the bravest nation in
                    the world, because their amusement is the most cruel; and a butcher ought to
                    make the best soldier.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On Thursday we go to <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>; this, therefore, will be my last letter of Lisbon anecdote.
                    In Africa a Portuguese saw an ouran-outang, the most human beast that has yet
                    been discovered, walking quietly with a stick in his hand; he had the wickedness
                    to shoot him, and was not, as he ought to have been, hung for wilful murder. The
                    head and hands were sent here; I have seen them in the Museum, in spirits. I
                    have seen many an uglier fellow pass for a man, in spite of the definition that
                    makes him a reasoning animal: he has eyebrows, and a woolly head, almost like a
                    negro&#8217;s, but the face not black.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Fielding<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Fielding
                        (1707&#8211;1754; <title>DNB</title>), novelist, who died in Lisbon where he had
                        gone for his health.</note> died and was buried here. By a singular
                    fatality, four attempts have been made to erect a monument, and all have
                    miscarried. A Frenchman set on foot a subscription for this purpose, and many of
                    the factory engaged for one, two, or three moidores; circumstances took him from
                    Lisbon, and this dropped. Another Frenchman had a monument made at his own
                    expense, and paid for it; there was a fine French inscription, that, as his own
                    countrymen had never given the great Fielding a monument, it was reserved for a
                    Frenchman to honour his country by paying that respect to genius: he also went
                    away, and is now following the French Pretender;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis &#8216;XVIII&#8217;, Comte de Provence (1755&#8211;1824; King of France
                        1814&#8211;1824), heir to the French throne.</note> and his monument lies among
                    masonry and rubbish, where I have sought for it in vain. Then De Visme<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Gerard De Visme (1726&#8211;1797), wealthy
                        British merchant long resident in Portugal.</note> undertook the affair; and
                    the bust of Fielding, designed for this purpose, is still in the house which
                    belonged to him here. I know not what made this scheme abortive. Last, the
                    Prince of Brazil<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King
                        of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826), Prince Regent 1799&#8211;1816.</note> went to work, and
                    the monument was made. The Lady Abbess of the New Convent<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Convent of the Discalced Carmelite Nuns, founded
                        1779.</note> wished to see it; it was sent to her; she took a fancy to it,
                    and there it has remained ever since: and Fielding is still without a
                    monument.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> De Visme introduced the present fashion of painting rooms in
                    stucco, with landscapes on the walls, and borders of flowers or arabesque; the
                    fashion is, I believe, Italian. The workmen whom he employed had taste enough to
                    be pleased with it, and it is general in all new houses. The ceilings are now
                    painted; thus, instead of the huge layer of boards which was usual, nothing can
                    look more cool, or be more convenient, for a cloth and soap cleans it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the larger old houses, here and in Spain, in the country,
                    there is usually a room with no windows, but, instead, arches quite open to the
                    air; the appearance is strange and picturesque, and I should esteem it one of
                    the inconveniences of Lisbon, that the intolerable dust prevents the enjoyment
                    of these open rooms there &#8211; the dust is a huge evil. &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .</p>
        <p rend="indent1">. &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;We had the hot wind for three
                    days this week; a detestable burning blast, a bastard sort of siroc, tamed by
                    crossing the sea and the land, but which parches the lips, and torments you with
                    the Tantalus plague of fanning your cheek and heating it at the same time. The
                    sea breeze is, on the other hand, as delightful: we feel it immediately; it
                    cools the air, and freshens up all our languid feelings. In the West Indies they
                    call this wind the doctor &#8211; a good seamanly phrase for its healing and
                    comfortable effect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At the time the aqueduct was built, a large reservoir was made
                    for its waste water. In winter, much water runs to waste; in summer, more is
                    wanted, and the watermen wait a long time round the fountain before they can in
                    turn fill their barrels: but these people, in building the reservoir, never
                    calculated the weight of the water till the building was finished, &#8211; so it
                    stands still uncovered, a useless pile, and a rare monument of the national
                    science. I saw a funeral from the country pass the window at night, the
                    attendants holding torches, and the body in the trunk coffin carried upon a
                    litter (that is, like a sedan chair carried by mules instead of men).</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The servants here, in marketing, think it a part of their fair
                    profits to cheat you as much as they can, and have no idea that this is
                    dishonesty; it is a sort of commission they think they are entitled to. This is
                    so much the case, that one of these fellows, when he was stipulating about
                    wages, thought them too little, and inquired if he was to go to market; he was
                    told yes, and then he said he would come. &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Queen&#8217;s stables serve as an asylum. Rogues and murderers go
                    there and do the work for nothing; they are safe by this means, and the people,
                    whose business it is to hire and pay the servants, pocket the money, so that
                    they infest the neighbourhood: they quarrelled with our dragoons, who broke into
                    the stables and thrashed them heartily, to the great satisfaction of the people
                    near. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you! <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>&#8217;s love.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R. S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>