<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce299</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.290</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery,
                        KESMG 1996.5.180.  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="290" type="letter">
<head>290. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas
                        Southey</ref>,<date when="1798-03-03"> 3 March 1798</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To / M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/
                        H.M.S. Mars/ Spithead./ or elsewhere./ Single <lb/>Stamped:
                        BRISTOL<lb/>Seal: [trace] Red wax<lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery,
                        KESMG 1996.5.180<lb/>Unpublished.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline rend="right">
<address>
<placeName>Bristol.</placeName>
</address>
<date when="1798-03-03"> March 3. 98</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Tom</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I have this day received <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> letter respecting <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Lord Proby</ref>, &amp; will give you his
                    own words. “My motive for writing is to desire you would consult with <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas</ref> whether it would not be more
                    advantageous for him to get on the Lisbon station, where perhaps I might be of
                    use to him by means of <ref target="people.html#JervisAdmiral">Lord S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincent</ref>. If he should wish it, <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Lord Proby</ref> who expects to have a
                    Frigate given him &amp; to return to that station has promised me to bring him
                    out – that is to give him a birth, or an appointment on board his ship. You will
                    write to <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Ld P.</ref> to inform him that
                    Thomas will accept of his offer, &amp; to give him Thomas’s direction that he
                    might inform him whence &amp; when he sails. There need not be any explanation
                    with <ref target="people.html#HoodAlexanderCaptain">Capt. Hood</ref> till <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Lord P.</ref> writes to him, as you see,
                    it depends on two contingencies. <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Lord
                        P.</ref> may not get a ship, &amp; if he does may not go to Lisbon. tho of
                    this last he tells me he is certain”</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Now Tom you must use your own judgement. if you see no
                    impropriety in leaving <ref target="people.html#HoodAlexanderCaptain">Capt.
                        Hood</ref> – &amp; as the change would be so much to your advantage I should
                    think he cannot but wish you to accept it, I can see no other objection. let me
                    know immediately, that I may inform <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Ld.
                        P.</ref>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You tell me you have left off sugar &amp; rum. I do not know my
                    dear Tom that this, or any circumstance could now raise you in my opinion – but
                    I know well what in your situation the sacrifice must be. Be not surprized if I
                    say that I do not wish you to persevere in it. When I first did the same, it was
                    at a time, when, from the general agitation of the subject, &amp; the number of
                    abolitionists, there was a hope &amp; prospect of mortally wounding the traffic
                    by the disuse of West Indian commodities. that prospect is gone. it is now
                    evident that the very few who persevere can do nothing. &amp; my reason for
                    still persisting as I ever shall, is from a respect to my own feelings, for the
                    satisfaction I feel in being conscious that in no ways do I contribute to so
                    accursed an evil as the Slave Trade, that if all else had acted as I act, that
                    Trade must have been destroyed. for you Tom – your possible comforts God knows
                    are few enough, nor do I think that you ought to abridge yourself of one, by
                    indulging in which no actual evil is <del rend="strikethrough">done</del>
                    &lt;committed.&gt; <hi rend="ital">now</hi> it is true that the efforts of an
                    individual can do nothing.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> My last it seems (inclosing a 2 pound bill from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref>) had not reached you
                    when you wrote. it was directed to Torbay. I shall not send you a parcel till my
                        Joan<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Joan of Arc</title>
                        (1798).</note> be finished, which will be now in about a month. In the
                    Autumn I have some thoughts, &amp; serious ones, of publishing another volume.
                    to this my chief inducement is the hope of getting a house to call my own; <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del> I think, if my literary plans do not sadly
                    fail, to accomplish this by the next Christmas – &amp; then Tom you shall come
                    &amp; chuse a cot &amp; fit up a room in your own taste.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We came here on Wednesday last, &amp; to night enter our
                    lodgings, in the very house on <ref target="places.html#KingsdownParade">Kingsdown Parade</ref> where my <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt
                        Mary</ref> once lodged. I shall have a barrel of cider there Tom – &amp; if
                    you can come to us we will work it merrily. I expect to hear from <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> daily respecting her
                    house. if she gets rid of that, &amp; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> reaches Lisbon well – why our family affairs will look
                    better than they have long done. &amp; God knows it is time we had a little sun
                    shine. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is well – &amp; I hope
                    air &amp; exercise will clothe her bones. for me I am the healthiest of all
                    skeletons. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> I mean to write a ballad soon. in the course of next week if
                    nothing prevents me, &amp; you shall see it as soon as done. the Magazines shall
                    come with the parcel – but tell me what was the last number you had.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I hope you may go to Lisbon – far as the distance will be, &amp;
                    long as it would seperate us. your time would pass comfortably – &amp; it is
                    snug lying in the Tagus. I must prepare my Letters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and
                            Portugal</title> (1799).</note> for a new edition with prints. &amp; you
                    shall have a noble set of impressions – </p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yr<del rend="strikethrough">s</del> affectionate
                        brother</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey. </signed>
</closer>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
