<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce303</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.294</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>Brotherton Library, University of Leeds .  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry, New Letters of Robert Southey, 2
                        vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 163–165.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="294" type="letter">
<head>294. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1798-03-10">10 March [1798]</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 4. Bedford
                        Square/ London<lb/>Stamped: BRISTOL<lb/>Postmark: B/ MR/ 12/
                        98<lb/>Endorsement: 1798 N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 14[obscured by seal trace]/
                        Robert Southey/ 10 March [obscured by seal trace]/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>:
                        12 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 19 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
<lb/>MS: Brotherton Library, University of Leeds <lb/>Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry, <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2
                        vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 163–165.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear friend</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> This voyage of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> makes me somewhat uneasy, it could not be a slight indisposition
                    that induced him to go to sea. &amp; yet I think if his illness had been any
                    ways alarming he would have asked leave of absence from the Factory. I pray you
                    let me have the earliest intelligence you get from Lisbon respecting him. the
                    Letter you sent me related entirely to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my
                        brother Tom</ref>, whom he wishes to get on the Lisbon station, where he can
                    assist him probably by means of <ref target="people.html#JervisAdmiral">Ld. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Vincents</ref>, &amp; whither <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Ld Proby</ref> will carry him, who is now
                    expecting a frigate to return there. <ref target="people.html#ProbyWilliam">Ld
                        Proby</ref> is <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref>
                        cousin.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
<ref target="people.html#ProbyJohn">John Joshua Proby</ref>, 1st Earl of
                        Carysfort’s second wife was Elizabeth Grenville (1756–1842), the sister of
                        Charles Watkin Williams Wynn’s mother, Charlotte Grenville (1754–1832). But
                        Lord Proby was not Wynn’s cousin, because he was the son of Carysfort’s
                        first wife, Elizabeth Osbourne (d. 1783).</note> this is well. &amp; were I
                    assured of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> health, I
                    should hope that our family affairs were assuming a better appearance than they
                    have worn for the last seven years. I cannot but be uneasy respecting him.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> This evening I traced with a pen the pencil notes of poor
                    Ostervald in my copy of Les Trois Siecles.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Ostervald’s identity is uncertain. One possibility is that he
                        was Jean Frederic Ostervald (1773–1850), later a surveyor, cartographer and
                        publisher in Paris. The book annotated by Ostervald and in Southey’s
                        possession was Antoine Sabatier de Castres (1742–1817), <title>Les Trois
                            Siècles de Littérature Française</title> (1772). Southey possessed a
                        1779 edition of this work. It was no. 554 in the sale catologue of his
                        library.</note> I never think of that man without feeling a great degree of
                    interest – &amp; something like regret that I should not have seen him at
                    Lisbon. It is possible that this Revolution in Switzerland<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">There were revolts in Switzerland in 1797–1798
                        against the domination of politics by local elite families and the lack of
                        political rights in rural areas. This process culminated in the declaration
                        of the democratic, centralised and pro-French Helvetic Republic on 12 April
                        1798.</note> may open a return for him to his own country, &amp; with fair
                    prospects. It would give me much pleasure if I could convey to him a set of my
                    books. but this the distance forbids. I never look at his drawings without
                    recollecting that perhaps his present situation is sadly altered from what it
                    was when he read these books. – these are painful thoughts. but what retrospect
                    is not painful? I fear life is like a journey – we are never satisfied till we
                    arrive at the end of it. we must always be looking on. &amp; surely this proves
                    a hereafter, or we might sleep away existence like a beast.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have received a letter from <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref>, in which I am sorry
                    to say, he complains of a relapse. should he be obliged once more to visit
                    Lisbon he must give up his present situation, &amp; the certain prospect it
                    affords of soon realizing a comfortable independance.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Your account of E. Grigg<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a ‘fallen woman’ whom John May was attempting to help.</note>
                    concerns me, tho I well know that repeated disappointments will not discourage
                    you from doing good. I fear little good can be done among the lower rank of
                    those miserable women the victims themselves &amp; the agents of evil. Among
                    those who have been better educated, whose feelings have been cultivated, those
                    lingering feelings that make their severest torture, afford something to work
                    upon. they linger after principle is gone.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> If you do not soon hear from Thornton<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Thornton (1760–1815; <title>DNB</title>): banker and
                        political economist; cousin of William Wilberforce (1759–1833;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and leading member of the Clapham Sect. In 1791
                        Thornton became chairman of the court of directors of the newly constituted
                        Sierra Leone Company, dedicated to establishing a colony of freed slaves in
                        Africa. The company aimed to confer on Africa the blessings of European
                        religion and civilization through a trading operation that would be both
                        profitable and free from the taint of slavery. John May and Southey were
                        trying to recruit Thornton to help with their scheme for a convalescent
                        hospital.</note> it will be necessary to look elsewhere for assistance. It
                    would be well for you to call on <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; consult with him; he is much interested in the scheme,
                    &amp; will be very glad to see you. I want to carry the begging box about while
                    I am here, &amp; hope to succeed where the Church Wardens have failed.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> A Magazine Man<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                        likeness was wanted by the <title>Monthly Visitor</title> ; see his letter
                        to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 8 March 1798, Letter 292. The magazine did
                        not publish his portrait.</note> has been requesting permission to publish
                    my likeness – &amp; I escaped an interview with him upon this subject by leaving
                    London, just as he had enquired out my direction for that purpose. this was
                    fortunate, as a refusal can always be better given on paper than verbatim.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> My book<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Joan of Arc</title> (1798).</note> is advancing; they give me three
                    sheets a week &amp; at that rate will compleat it soon. – <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is much better than when she
                    left London, tho still far from that state of health in which I wish again to
                    see her. we are well situated on <ref target="places.html#KingsdownParade">Kingsdown</ref>, the Buenos Ayres of Bristol<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Kingsdown is an area of Bristol that is on top of a hill,
                        like Buenos Ayres, a district of Lisbon (now known as Lapa).</note> exactly;
                    &amp; a walk of fifty yards leads us into the country. Can you not find time to
                    visit us here? I should very much like to show you the country, &amp; its many
                    glorious prospects. they affect me strongly. I am a different being at London,
                    &amp; on these rocks. &amp; you cannot have a better guide than me, who know
                    every crag &amp; every winding of the woods.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
<salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p rend="indent1"> Nothing is settled about <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mothers</ref> house – but I
                        believe the Landlord<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A Mr Chilton
                            (first name and dates unknown) was the owner of the boarding-house at
                                <ref target="places.html#WestgateBuildings">8 Westgate
                                Buildings</ref>, Bath, and therefore Margaret Southey’s landlord;
                            see <title>The New Bath Directory</title> (Bath, [1792]), p. 29.</note>
                        will take it. in that case, if no unforeseen disappointment &lt;occur&gt; I
                        hope to get into a house in the winter.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You will receive a copy of Musæus<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Grosvenor Charles Bedford’s translation of Musaeus (fl.
                            c. early 6th century), <title>The Loves of Hero and Leander</title>
                            (1797).</note> soon.</p>
<p rend="right">Saturday 10 March.</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
