<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce772</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.763</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public
                        Library.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="763" type="letter">
        <head>763. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Charles
                        Biddlecombe</ref>, <date when="1803-03-06">6 March
                        1803</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address:
                        To/ Charles Biddlecombe Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/
                        Burton/ near/ Ringwood/ Single<lb />Postmark: [partial]
                        BRISTOL/ MAR 7<lb />MS: Berg Collection, New York Public
                        Library<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1803-03-06">Sunday evening. March 6.
                            1803.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> By some accident, which is a very unusual one
                    with me, your last letter was mislaid, &amp; this vexed me
                    when I wished to answer it. I remember however a very
                    friendly invitation, for which we thank you now, &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">by</del> of which we hope one day
                    to avail ourselves when <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> shall be grown big enough to be a play
                    fellow for your little girl.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Biddlecombe&#8217;s daughter was born in 1799.
                        Her name is not recorded.</note> little indeed is an
                    epithet which better suits what I remember her than what she
                    must be now.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When last I wrote we were in treaty for a
                    house in Wales<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="places.html#MaesGywn">Maes Gwyn</ref>, near
                        Neath.</note> &amp; I considered that treaty as
                    concluded, for we had agreed upon terms. but an unlucky
                    dispute between the landlord &amp; his tenant about certain
                    premises necessary for my accommodation has deprived me of
                    one of the prettiest places I have seen or expect to see in
                    this Island. <del rend="strikethrough">never</del> since
                    then I have been on the look out &amp; hitherto without
                    success. we have now a house in view about three miles from
                    Bristol, a spot with some inconveniences, but some
                    advantages also, &amp; great beauty of situation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you received the copy of Chatterton<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Joseph
                        Cottle&#8217;s edition of <title>The Works of Thomas
                            Chatterton</title> (1803). Biddlecombe was listed as
                        a subscriber.</note> for which you subscribed? if
                    neither yours. nor those of your friends whose &lt;names&gt;
                    you were good enough to procure have been sent down, you had
                    better apply for them to your London bookseller when you
                    write him. but with a caution that he apply to the
                    publishers for them as <hi rend="ital">subscribers
                        copies</hi>, else the benefit will not be M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Newtons.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Newton (1749-1804), Chatterton&#8217;s
                        sister.</note> we expect to clear above &#163;400 for her. I
                    have succeeded better for her than I was ever able to do for
                    myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The books &amp;c that you may still be
                    troubled with of mine have the goodness to direct here,
                    &amp; they will then travel with the rest of my lumber in
                    one embarkation to my place of rest &#8211; wherever that may be.
                    In about three months time, calculating by my printers speed
                    I also shall have some books to send you &#8211; a version of
                    Amadis of Gaul;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>
                        (1803).</note> a work which being obliged to do
                    something for the lucre of gain, I preferred for its own
                    intrinsic merit. I have work in hand for this Annual
                        Review<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1
                        (1803).</note> which will contain some good articles,
                    &amp; in average merit probably, &amp; in impartiality
                    certainly exceed the monthly ones. Madoc<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had completed a
                        version of <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799. He was
                        revising it for publication, but it did not appear until
                        1805.</note> comes slowly but surely on:. &amp; will I
                    fear &#8211; rather than hope &#8211; be published at no very distant
                    period. but not while my ways &amp; means can be supplied
                    without it. History<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s uncompleted &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note>
                    continues my favourite pursuit. I should be very glad of an
                    opportunity to show <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> you
                    some specimens, with which I feel confident you would be
                    pleased.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Colonel Despards<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Despard (1751-1803;
                            <title>DNB</title>) was tried and executed on 21
                        February 1803 on a charge of treason. It was alleged
                        that he had tried to organise a revolution in 1802. He
                        had previously served in the Royal Navy and been
                        Superintendant of British Honduras 1787-1790. He was
                        imprisoned without trial in 1798-1801 under particularly
                        harsh conditions on the charge of involvement in the
                        Irish rising of 1798.</note> business is to me still
                    mysterious. I could have found him guilty of high folly &#8211;
                    but not of high treason. it rather seems as if he <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> had been talking treason
                    than conspiring, prating about what might or could be, not
                    plotting what <hi rend="ital">should</hi> be, playing with a
                    halter till he was caught in the noose. I wish he had been
                    spared, because tho his former <del rend="strikethrough">offerings</del> services were no fair plea for pardon
                    upon such an occasion, his former sufferings were:
                    oppression maketh a wise man mad, &amp; it should have been
                    remembered that Colonel Despard had been the most oppressed
                    man in his Majestys dominions. his pardon would have given
                    administration a character for clemency which is always
                    advantageous. however to their credit they saw none of that
                    wanton cruelty in the whole proceedings which the old
                    ministry eternally exercised. Portland &amp; Grenville &amp;
                        Pitt<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William
                        Cavendish-Bentinck, 3rd Duke of Portland (1738-1809;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1783, 1807-1809,
                        Home Secretary 1794-1801; William Grenville, Lord
                        Grenville (1759-1834; <title>DNB</title>), Foreign
                        Secretary 1791-1801, Prime Minister 1806-1807; William
                        Pitt (1759-1806; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister
                        1783-1801, 1804-1806.</note> made imprisonment an engine
                    for personal punishment, in this instance the law was
                    enforced, but with every indulgence to alleviate.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In spite of Sebastianis<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace Fran&#231;ois Bastien
                        Sebastiani de La Porte (1771-1851), French diplomat and
                        soldier. His report, published in <title>Le Moniteur
                            Universal</title>, 30 January 1803, suggested that
                        France could still re-conquer Egypt and was a major
                        factor in worsening Anglo-French relations.</note>
                    rascally report from Egypt, &amp; Bonapartes<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                        (1769-1821, First Consul 1799-1804, Emperor of the
                        French 1804-1814).</note> threats, &amp; the growling of
                    the Grenvillian<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Followers of William Grenville, Lord Grenville. They
                        had left office in 1801 and were moving closer to the
                        Whigs.</note> faction, who blessed be God cannot bite
                    now! I expect the continuance of peace. they who are weary
                    must rest &#8211; &amp; a sound drubbing will tire any body. &#8211; My
                    eyes have been very weak &amp; have cost me <del rend="strikethrough">almost all</del> the sacrifice of
                    almost all my candle light hours this winter. I am
                    trespassing now &amp; sparing them by this straggling hand &#8211;
                    yet still they smart &amp; itch &amp; warn me of my
                    imprudence. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> desire to be remembered. remember me also to
                    your mother &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleman<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; presumably an
                        acquaintance of Southey from his residence at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>.</note> to
                    whom I am very much obliged &#8211; Your Curates book<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Clapham (1757-1830;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Sermons: Selected and
                            Abridged, Chiefly from Minor Authors</title> (1803).
                        He had become Vicar (rather than curate) of Christchurch
                        in 1802.</note> is a useful compilation. It wants
                    prints. I read it with pleasure &amp; profit &amp; thought
                    at the time I could have furnished him with some anecdotes
                    which have not fallen in his way.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yr affectionate friend</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#StJamesPlace">12. St Jamess Place</ref>. Kingsdown.</placeName>
          </address>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>