<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce579</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.570</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d.
                        3.  Previously  published: Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in
                            Portugal 1800-1801 and a Visit to France
                            1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                    150-152.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="570" type="letter">
        <head>570. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert
                        Southey</ref>, <date when="1801-02-22">22 February
                        1801</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> H H.
                        Southey./ with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> P. Martineau/
                        Norwich<lb />Stamped: LISBON<lb />Postmark: FOREIGN
                        OFFICE/ MR 14/ 1801<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d.
                        3<lb />Previously published: Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in
                            Portugal 1800-1801 and a Visit to France
                            1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                    150-152.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> As this letter will in all probability reach
                    you before the expiration of your trial-term with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Martineau<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip Meadows Martineau (1752-1829),
                        surgeon at the Norfolk and Norwich Hospital and a member
                        of the Martineau family, prominent Unitarians in
                        Norwich.</note> &#8211; it will not be improper before your
                    final decision is made to set you right upon one or two
                    points on which you appear to judge erroneously.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your entering the church could not prejudice
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>.
                    because the immediate object is to secure a part of my <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncles</ref>
                        preferment,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill was Chancellor of Hereford Cathedral. This
                        gave him the right to appoint the incumbent of the
                        living of Little Hereford and Ashton Carbonell; in
                        December 1800 Hill had appointed himself to this
                        position, with the intention of resigning later in
                        favour of a member of his family.</note> which he could
                    transfer to a better life than his own, &amp; with it a
                    church-estate on a lease of 21 years, renewable annually at
                    one fifth of its value which is from 4 to 500 pounds. Of
                    this, now in a strangers hand, seven years are expired. at
                    the end of four more my <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncle</ref> can
                    grant a lease for ten years to commence at the end of the
                    existing one, &amp; year by year fill it up to the term of
                    twenty one &#8211; thus securing it to his family. if his health
                    declined the Chancellorship &amp; leasing-power might be
                    transferred to you as soon as in orders &#8211; to wait for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> is
                    expecting a longer term than a man of his age can calculate
                    upon. besides <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> is too young to form any plan for &#8211; &amp;
                    bright as his talents are there is in my opinion every
                    symptom that they will be most miserably misapplied. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Again. you deem yourself unqualified for
                    university studies. of these I can only say <del rend="strikethrough">that</del> they are so trifling
                    that you will be ashamed of your task. the trick of writing
                    Latin verse is the only one in which you are deficient. that
                    worthless habit is little necessary &amp; may soon be
                    acquired to the needful extent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All this I have said that you may make your
                    judgement knowing all the circumstances. the most important
                    is upon what principles you could enter the establishment.
                    Whatever your opinions be, right or wrong, they must as yet
                    be the prejudices of friendship, &amp; personal attachments.
                    it is not possible that you should yet have knowledge
                    whereon to found belief or disbelief. My conduct ought not
                    to influence yours. the cases are wholly different. Nor
                    would I advise you or any one to be as inattentive to
                    worldly advancement as I have been.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should you continue in your present choice,
                    you know your expectations. application may raise you to
                    eminence &amp; affluence &#8211; you will have a profession most
                    useful &amp; most honourable, &amp; if the surgical studies
                    are at first loathsome there is pleasure enough in chemistry
                    amply to counterbalance what is unpleasant in anatomy. your
                    alternative presents nothing terrifying. it is to accept a
                    competence &#8211; or acquire it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the case of your fixing with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Martineau, you ought to know with what
                    money you can be supplied for cloaths washing &amp;c. at
                    present more than 20&#163; a year cannot be afforded or procured.
                    My expences are increased here, &amp; my resources for the
                    time cut off. there is the heavy charge of returning to look
                    on to. a years hard labour in England will hardly make me
                    again equal to the world. from my employments here I expect
                    emolument but it will be distant &amp; is doubtful. to
                    recommend decent oeconomy is needless. You would I think do
                    well by keeping for your own satisfaction an account of your
                    expences.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our return may probably be hastened. May is
                    the month fixed, but the state of Portugal is become
                    uncertain &amp; dangerous. if France be resolved to shut
                    this port also against England, there is nothing but Famine
                    to prevent her. Spain is <del rend="strikethrough">weak</del> willing but weak. the force of the country
                    absolutely nothing, no preparation whatever of magazines or
                    even ammunition. yet a French army must bring their own food
                    &#8211; for they cannot find it here. &amp; a weeks blockade would
                    starve Lisbon, for here we are dependant upon almost daily
                    supplies by sea. We cannot protect Portugal by land &#8211; France
                    cannot support it by water &#8211; the country cannot please both
                    powers, &amp; may be ruined by either. this is exactly our
                    state &#8211; &amp; France &amp; England are equally imperious in
                    injustice. the merchants are preparing to secure their
                    property, those who can. to the many whose trade is selling
                    to the natives it will be utter ruin. That the danger may
                    again be bought off is merely possible. the Spanish
                        Ambassador<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Ambassador&#8217;s name is not recorded in contemporary
                        reports; he left because Spain was about to declare war
                        on Portugal.</note> left Lisbon on Thursday last, &amp;
                    invited all Spaniards to follow him. the port is of
                    importance, &amp; in my own opinion the only hope is of a
                    general peace, which may perhaps follow the change<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The resignation of
                        William Pitt (1759-1806, Prime Minister 1783-1801,
                        1804-1806; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My stay when prolonged to the utmost will be
                    so inadequate to my wants &amp; wishes that I can ill afford
                    to have it shortened by the accidents of politics. A rupture
                    with Spain will seriously inconvenience me. I have sent for
                    books there of indispensable importance. they are indeed
                    accessible in England but in an unpleasant manner &#8211; I could
                    quarter myself upon Lord Bute<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Stuart, 1st Marquess of Bute
                        (1744-1814; <title>DNB</title>), Ambassador to Spain
                        1795-1796.</note> for the sake of his most magnificent
                    Library, but tho he would gladly receive me I should rather
                    avoid the visit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncle</ref> returned very unwell &amp; pale &amp; thin.
                    but this climate &amp; good food after his voyage-fast are
                    recovering him. he is anxious to remove his books as
                    speedily as possible from danger. I also only wait an
                    opportunity to ship off mine &#8211; for already I have bought
                    more than would have been justifiable were <del rend="strikethrough">not</del> they not my stock in
                    trade &amp; responsible debtors. I must return to Lisbon &#8211;
                    even if my health (which there is little reason to expect)
                    should endure the blighting-blasts of England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are now in Lent, suffering for the follies
                    of our neighbours. it is difficult to procure meat. indeed
                    were there not beef killed for the few troops that remain
                    here we must more than once already have done penance upon
                    fish. in about another week the people will fall sick &amp;
                    eat flesh with a safe conscience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Write to me soon. inform <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> that I have received his
                    letters &#8211; &amp; thank him for his arrangement.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor had been instrumental
                        in placing Henry Herbert Southey with Martineau; see
                        Taylor&#8217;s letter to Southey, 1 February 1801, J.W.
                        Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings
                            of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2
                        vols (London, 1843), I, p. 365.</note> I am interrupted
                    &#8211; so God bless you &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1801-02-22">22. Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.
                        1801.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>