<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce782</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.773</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 73-75.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="773" type="letter">
        <head>773. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1803-04-19">19 April 1803</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond
                        Green/ Surry/ Single<lb />Stamped: [partial] TO<lb />Postmarks: B/ APR 20/
                        1803; 10 o&#8217;Clock/AP 20/ 1803 [illegible]<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 77 1803/ Robert Southey/ No place 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        April/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title>
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 73-75.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I need not say that your last letter gave me great pain, but it
                    was less than what I apprehended from your long silence &amp; your mourning
                        wafer.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John May&#8217;s second son,
                        Richard, had died on 21 February 1803, aged ten days. His wife, Susanna
                        Frances Livius (1767-1830), recovered from the birth. In addition, May was
                        suffering financial troubles due to unpaid debts.</note> the black wafer had
                    made me so fully believe the worst, that the intelligence of your other losses,
                    heavy as they are, came like a light evil. I hope however you will yet recover
                    more than you seemed to expect.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You say you shall think as badly of mankind as I do. I am
                    heartily grieved that the opinion should be purchased so heavily. I would rather
                    you thought as well of men in their <hi rend="ital">posse</hi> than as badly in
                    their <hi rend="ital">esse</hi>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. &#8216;In
                        their potential rather than as badly as in their actuality&#8217;.</note> in their
                    actual state. a system of emulation, of struggling &amp; scrambling necessarily
                    makes them bad. Some years &amp; some observation have modified many of my
                    opinions, but every thing that I have observed in the history of man &amp; in
                    the nature of the mind of man, has tended to confirm &amp; establish the belief
                    that the inequalities of property are <hi rend="ital">now</hi> the cause of
                    moral evil &amp; human misery. I say <hi rend="ital">now</hi>, for they were
                    necessary parts of the process. I conceive this to be the doctrine of Christ,
                    when he so explicitly forbids the existence of power or riches among his
                    disciples. at present, the institutions of society are perpetually counteracting
                    the precepts of religion, for selfishness &amp; acquisition make the basis of
                    the commercial system. the Mosaic dispensation approaches Xtianity in this
                    political system, as it does in every thing else, by its year of jubilee, &amp;
                    agrarian division.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Leviticus</title> 25. The Year of Jubilee occurred every 49 or
                        50 years. In that year all property was to be returned to its original
                        owners and indentured servants manumitted. <title>Numbers</title> 26: 53-56
                        and 33: 54 told how the land of Israel was divided by lot among the twelve
                        tribes, depending on the number of families in each tribe.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To teach such a system which would best secure the happiness
                    &amp; virtue of man appears to me a worthy part of revelation. &amp; without
                    such a system revelation can do comparatively little. the quantum of wickedness
                    in London is probably not less than that of Rome under Augustus,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus (63 BC-AD 14;
                        Emperor of Rome 30 BC-AD 14).</note> &amp; the quantum of misery is
                    certainly greater, for poverty in the true sense of the word, actual physical
                    want, is an evil of modern growth, unknown under the ancient <del rend="strikethrough">for</del> regime of domestic slavery, unknown in the
                    feudal times, the effect of the commercial system, beginning with that system
                    &amp; increasing with it. The first Xtians understood the gospel as I understand
                    it, &amp; half a score sects have grown out of parts of it. but any system will
                    be spoiled if parts only be taken. the loss of one wheel deranges a watch.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I heard lately from Lisbon, but <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> mentioned nothing of
                    his legacy nor of his increased salary &#8211; the letter was too full of his English
                    business. perhaps that increase, if it be any thing considerable, may fix him at
                    Lisbon, a circumstance which would give me great pleasure, for my heart is fixed
                    upon Portugal, &amp; I look forward with something of the same hope towards my
                    next voyage &#8211; as I used to the holydays when a school boy. By the winter of next
                    year my history<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s uncompleted
                        &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> will be, I trust, so forward as to give me a
                    fair cause for crossing the Bay. I shall work the harder with that hope. the
                    occupations which keep me from history are quite irksome &amp; laborious.
                    Yesterday I sent off the conclusion of Amadis.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>
                        (1803).</note> I have done a world of reviewing, &amp; have now a Collection
                    of all the Living Italian Poets<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly
                        G.B. Cassano (fl. 1802), <title>Il Fiore della Poesia Italiana</title>
                        (1802), which Southey reviewed in <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2
                        (1804), 562-563.</note> to go thro for the same purpose. but then I shall
                    take breath &amp; go on like old Christian when his bundle fell from his
                        back.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bunyan (1628-1688;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Pilgrim&#8217;s Progress</title> (1678-1684).
                        Christian&#8217;s burden is sin and when he reaches the &#8216;place of deliverance&#8217;
                        (Calvary), it rolls away into the tomb left empty by Jesus&#8217;
                        resurrection.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you have forty pounds of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> will you have the
                    goodness to send it to me, payable to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Charles Danvers</ref>. it is due to him for
                    freight &amp; duties from Lisbon, &amp; for money which <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> obtained thro <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my poor Mother</ref>. <del rend="strikethrough">x</del>
          <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> thought there was
                    100&#163; in poor <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas&#8217;s</ref> hands,
                    as <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> told me when last
                    I saw him. he desired me to pay Danvers with it &amp; keep the remainder. but on
                    enquiry it seems <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> had
                    advanced money to <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>,
                    &amp; some she has had from the Executors since &#8211; so that only &#163;14. remains of
                    the whole hundred. with all this I have acquainted <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; likewise told him
                    that if you have 40&#163; I should apply for it to pay <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">old Lady</ref> whom I
                    mentioned in my last was the mother of <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>, &amp; died as we expected. She was a most excellent woman,
                    &amp; her death is a serious loss to us. we were near neighbours &#8211; only three
                    doors asunder &#8211; I saw her daily, &amp; had for many years regarded her &amp;
                    been by her regarded with something like family affection.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had nearly forgotten to thank you &amp; Burn<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Burn (dates unknown), a member of the
                        English Factory, Lisbon.</note> &amp; Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Markham<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Markham (1761-1827;
                            <title>DNB</title>), naval officer; served on the Board of Admiralty
                        1801-1804 and 1806-1807; MP for Portsmouth 1801-1818 and 1820-1826.</note>
                    for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> appointment to the
                    Galatea Frigate.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">HMS <hi rend="ital">Galatea</hi>, a 32-gun Royal Navy frigate, bound for the West
                        Indies.</note> if it be war he is in a fair way of making money &#8211; but God
                    grant it may be Peace!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> is growing a
                    very fine little girl. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">her mother</ref>
                    still suckles her. we are all well. your next I hope will bring me as good an
                    account of your family [MS torn] I hope &#8211; a fairer prospect of retrieving the
                    very heavy losses which you have sustained from the dishonesty of others.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1803-04-19">Tuesday. Apr. 19. 1803</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>