<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce408</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.399</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Special Collections, The Johns Hopkins
                        University, Raymond Dexter Havens Papers, MS. 24
                        .  Previously  published: Andy P. Antippas, &#8216;Four New
                        Southey Letters&#8217;, The Wordsworth Circle,
                        5 (1974), 94&#8211;95.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="399" type="letter">
        <head>399. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1799-04-18">18 April
                        1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 4. Bedford Square/ London/
                        Single<lb />Postmark: AP/ 18/ 99<lb />Endorsement: 1799
                            N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 35./ Robert Southey/ No
                        place 18 April/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 19/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 20} d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Special Collections, The Johns Hopkins
                        University, Raymond Dexter Havens Papers, MS. 24
                        <lb />Previously published: Andy P. Antippas, &#8216;Four New
                        Southey Letters&#8217;, <title>The Wordsworth Circle</title>,
                        5 (1974), 94&#8211;95.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have another letter from Lisbon. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>
                    says he has sent fifty pounds for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref>. be
                    good enough to receive twenty of these towards the payment
                    of the forty which I received of you for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> at
                    Xmas 1797. <del rend="strikethrough">x</del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> he likewise says he would endeavour to lodge
                    money with Burn<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Burn (dates unknown), a member of the English
                        Factory, Lisbon.</note> for the expence of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> passing. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has been
                    little burthensome to him &amp; a Lieutenancy, which I think
                    there can be no doubt of his speedily obtaining, will render
                    him compleatly independant. he passes on May day. will you
                    have the kindness to call for him at the Navy Office where
                    you took out his time ticket &amp; enquire whether a
                    Midshipman whose time is out on the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    of April, passing day being the next, should lodge his
                    journals &amp; other certificates there before that day, he
                    having all his certificates except that for the last month,
                    for which time he is lent to another ship for the purpose of
                    having an opportunity to pass, whilst his own is at sea.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I look forward with little pleasure to the
                    month of May as I must pass the whole of it from home. as
                    one term is to be kept at the beginning &amp; the other at
                    the end the intermediate fortnight is too short a time to
                    return for &amp; I shall have it to pass how I can. if I can
                    find any friend disengaged enough to stroll somewhere with
                    me during that time it would be infinitely more agreable
                    than remaining in London. I should like to walk to the Peak
                    &amp; see the wonders of Derbyshire, or to ramble round
                    Kent, much of which country I have never seen, &amp; what
                    would not be new it would be pleasant to revisit. I should
                    have gone to Cambridge to visit <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> but <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> is
                    detained at Birmingham by concerns of more importance than
                    term-keeping. there is a probability of his speedy
                        marriage.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles
                        Lloyd married Sophia Pemberton on 24 April
                    1799.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I continue enfeebled &amp; indisposed &amp;
                    look on very unwillingly to the exertion of a journey. here
                    I have good advice &amp; take all due care of myself. in
                    London I shall talk with <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>
                    &amp; see if he can mend me. The Pneumatic &amp;
                    Physiological Institution<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Pneumatic Institute, Dowry Square,
                        Bristol, had opened earlier in 1799.</note> is opened at
                    last, I occasionally go down &amp; take much interest in its
                    success. it bids fair to ascertain medical facts of the
                    greatest importance.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Its early findings were publicised in Thomas Beddoes,
                            <title>Notice of Some Observations Made at the
                            Medical Pneumatic Institution</title> (1799).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> I know
                    something of, &amp; am more intimate with <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> the
                    immediate director of the Institution, a young man of the
                    most miraculous talents I ever met with. I am chemist enough
                    to understand him upon chemical subjects. in scrofulous
                    &amp; consumptive cases they are meeting with great success.
                    I have put my cousin <ref target="people.html#HillMargaret">Margaret</ref> under their care, she has but just begun
                    to follow their prescriptions, but her case is a very
                    extraordinary one, &amp; <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> is not
                    a man to give any hope where there is the least probability
                    of disappointment. I am busily employed in doing the work
                    which is necessary for the next month, that I may be at my
                    own free disposal. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>
                    sent me a copy of the American advertisement of Joan of Arc.
                    it was edited by one Joseph Nancrede of Boston, &amp; he was
                    by no means parsimonious in praise.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">An American edition of Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Joan of Arc, An Epic Poem</title> had been
                        published by Joseph Nancrede (1761&#8211;1841) in Boston,
                        Massachusetts, in 1798. The text followed that of the
                        1796 British edition of the poem.</note> I certainly
                    should not have subscribed to a work so panegyrized.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref>, our friendly neighbour at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> has lost his
                    wife in childbed. for ten years had they looked on to their
                    marriage &#8211; &amp; she survived the marriage but ten
                        months.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles
                        Biddlecombe&#8217;s wife, Catherine (n&#233;e Lacy), had died on 24
                        March 1799 (see <title>The Oracle</title>, 2 April 1799)
                        from complications in childbirth. The Biddlecombes had
                        married on 4 June 1798.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is very
                    unwell. her indisposition is regularly every morning &#8211; mine
                    very night. this however is better than permanent illness,
                    &amp; change of air will probably benefit us both. she
                    desires to [MS torn]bered.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1799-04-18">April. 18. 99.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>