<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce786</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.777</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos,
                            The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 75-77.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.777" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="777" type="letter">
        <head>777. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1803-05-01">1 May 1803</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond
                        Green/ Surry/ Single<lb />Postmarks: [partial] STOL/ MAY 1 1803; B/ MAY 2/
                        1803, 10 o&#8217;Clock/ MY 1/ 1803F. N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 78. 1803/ Robert Southey/ No place 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> May/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                            d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                        University of Texas, Austin<lb />Previously published: Charles Ramos,
                            <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title>
                        (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 75-77.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your with the bank-post bill of &#163;40 for <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> arrived safely &amp; the
                    money has been paid. the first part of your letter gave me great pleasure. what
                    relates to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> is every
                    way unpleasant, &#8211; what <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref> palliates as only an imprudence I feel to be a very serious
                    &amp; a very dangerous fault. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry&#8217;s</ref> allowance is surely a sufficient one. my dress, including
                    every article, costs me upon the average not more than &#163;15 a year, set down 5
                    more for the indulgence of a pardonable pride of appearance &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> ought to be contented.
                    he must after his washing &amp; other little necessary expences be paid have a
                    clear ten pounds for his yearly pleasures. <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del>
                    his journey to Paris did not break in upon his allowance. <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> you
                    know bore his expences there, conditioning that he should pay for his own
                    journey, <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> said he had his
                    unencumbered quarterly sum for that &#8211; but I gave him ten guineas for the
                    occasion. The mischief is that prodigality is in his nature &amp; in the nature
                    of all my brothers. he must write to Lisbon now &#8211; the act of writing will give
                    him some pain, &amp; the very gentle reproof which he will receive <del rend="strikethrough">from</del> &lt;in&gt; <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> answer ought to give
                        <del rend="strikethrough">more</del> &lt;him&gt; more &#8211; for he knows how
                        <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, who would else be
                    an opulent <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> man, has been &amp; is still kept
                    needy by spendthrift connections. I will write to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref>. I do
                    not like that substitution of honour for steady principle, which he is disposed
                    to make. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> prospects
                    are as good as he could wish if he did not mar them by his own folly. let him
                    keep out of debt &amp; about four years hence, he is almost secure of <del rend="strikethrough">xxx xxxxx</del> a good practise in Norwich &amp; he
                    will probably marry well &#8211; ambition will make him prudent <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> in that instance. he will do well in the
                    world &#8211; but I have no expectation of his doing good in the world. he has great
                    talents, but no genius. <hi rend="ital">videri</hi> might be his motto. I should
                    chuse <hi rend="ital">esse</hi> to be mine.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;To seem might be his motto. I should chuse to be to be
                        mine.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall perhaps see you in the course of the summer. it was my
                    design to go to London for the purpose of getting materials in the Museum<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The British Museum, London, opened in
                        1759.</note> for the first Chapter upon Monastic institutions &#8211; &amp; the
                    last upon the mixed Moorish period<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">For
                        Southey&#8217;s uncompleted &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> &#8211; this I had determined
                    to delay, but an unpleasant complaint has been stealing upon me unawares, for
                    which exercise is one of the main remedies, &amp; I know no place
                        <del>where</del> that so compels me to great exercise as London. the
                    complaint is diabetes with a disposition in the kidneys to manufacture <del rend="strikethrough">lime</del> calculus matter, which I hope has been
                    discovered in time to prevent the bladder from becoming a lime-kiln. soda is the
                    peculiar medicine needful &#8211; aided by the red sulphat of iron, which is certainly
                    the most powerful general tonic that has yet been discovered. I know &lt;not&gt;
                    how I can take so much exercise with so little expence &amp; so <del rend="strikethrough">much</del> little loss of time as by passing a
                    fortnight with <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> in London,
                    &amp; <del>on</del> resting myself for two hours at midday in the Museum.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must have expressed my<del rend="strikethrough">self</del>
                    &lt;meaning&gt; improperly in my last if you understood that I considered the
                    present period, upon the general average of good &amp; evil, as worse than older
                    times. On the contrary it appears to me very far the best, as being the most
                    enlightened. it is the best for the best men, virtues &amp; talents which would
                    have been blasted formerly can grow up &amp; flourish now. what I meant to
                    express was that the condition of the greater part of society &#8211; of the poor, is
                    more uniformly miserable now than it ever has been in any former period, &amp;
                    that, in consequence <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del> of the inevitable
                    effects of our commercial system. they were exposed to sudden calamities
                    formerly from which we are now tolerably secure &#8211; war we have not at home &#8211; nor
                    pestilence, nor actual famine. but when neither of these <del rend="strikethrough">ravages</del> &lt;visitations&gt; happened to be let
                    loose the peasantry &amp; labourers of England in old times enjoyed a degree of
                    comfort &amp; plenty which they now never can attain. their morals &amp; their
                    health were not poisoned by the soul-&amp;-body-murdering plan of herding
                    together in large &amp; unwholesome manufactories. the aggregate of human wisdom
                    &amp; human virtue is greater now. but the aggregate of human misery is
                    increased also. Upon my view of the moral government of the world, these
                    progressive steps have all been needful &#8211; a state of <hi rend="ital">innocence</hi> is necessarily insecure. the Tree of Knowledge<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Genesis</title> 2-3. Adam and Eve were
                        forbidden to eat the fruit from the tree of knowledge. When they did so they
                        were banished from the Garden of Eden.</note> must be tasted, &amp; good
                    &amp; evil must be experienced before mankind can attain a state of <hi rend="ital">wisdom</hi>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the gospel &#8211; in the express words of Christ I find the
                    distinctions of rank &amp; riches expressly forbidden to his disciples.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">For instance, <title>Mark</title> 10:
                        21-25.</note> &amp; it is well known that the first Xtians understanding
                    this as I understand it had among themselves a community of goods. Without this
                    indeed Xtianity is but a palliative for human evils &#8211; not a remedy. indeed
                    unless morals be grafted upon civil polity they can never generally flourish.
                        <del rend="strikethrough">this rule xxx the xxxxxxx xxxxx xxx xxxxxxx
                        xxxx</del>. now the institutions of society directly counteract the main
                    precepts of Christ. he forbids rank &amp; riches &amp; worldly ambition &#8211; to
                    renounce them is not merely difficult now &#8211; it is actually impossible &#8211; but
                    either the way of the world or the way of the gospel must be wrong.</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is not the time past when they nominate the boys for Christ
                        Hospital?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Famous public school,
                        founded in 1552, which admitted some pupils free, or on much-reduced fees.
                        Those entitled to nominate pupils included certain livery companies and the
                        Guild of Freemen of the City of London.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter could not be answered by return of post because
                    letters are not delivered here till after the post returns. our respects to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Susanna
                        Frances Livius (1767-1830).</note> &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1803-05-01">Sunday. May 1. 1803. </date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>