<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce549</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.540</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Royal
                        Institution, London, Davy MSS.  Previously  published:
                        John Davy (ed.), Fragmentary Remains, Literary
                            and Scientific, of Sir Humphry Davy, Bart.
                        (London, 1858), pp. 43&#8211;47 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.540" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="540" type="letter">
        <head>540. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Humphry Davy</ref>,
                        <date when="1800-07-26">26 July 1800</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/
                            M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davy./ Pneumatic
                        Institution./ Hot Wells./ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped:
                        LISBON<lb />Endorsement: July 1800<lb />MS: Royal
                        Institution, London, Davy MSS<lb />Previously published:
                        John Davy (ed.), <title>Fragmentary Remains, Literary
                            and Scientific, of Sir Humphry Davy, Bart.</title>
                        (London, 1858), pp. 43&#8211;47 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <date when="1800-07-26">July 26. 1800.</date>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had the good luck as a poet, &amp; the
                    misfortune as a man to feel the night mare last night. the
                    night was very hot, I had been extremely restless for many
                    hours, the intelligence that my <ref target="people.html#HillMargaret">Cousin Margarett</ref>
                    was in a decline had reached me in the morning &amp;
                    prevented me from sleeping. a sort of delirious activity at
                    last seemed to possess my imagination &amp; I remember
                    combining in words that the mind heard the most incongruous
                    associations of monstrous thought, involuntarily. I was in a
                    seperate bed, lying on my back, my arms &amp; legs stretched
                    out asunder, the right hand fearing to touch the left on
                    account of the heat. I recollect my last definite feeling
                    was as tho I had been stretched on a wheel that raised up my
                    breast &amp; strained my extremities. after that, I had
                    forgotten myself &amp; the seizure came on. it was a weight
                    on the breast &#8211; I thought some evil being was trying to
                    destroy me. I attempted to move but I saw other legs than my
                    own coming from the bed as if mocking me &#8211; I thought I was
                    awake &#8211; this was the most singular circumstance &#8211; I knew
                    where I was &#8211; I knew it was the night mare, I knew one word
                    one motion would relieve me yet it appeared that my eyes
                    were open &#8211; that I saw a red fire suspended in the middle of
                    the room, that some evil being had caught me. there was a
                    lamp burning on the table. <del rend="strikethrough">at
                        length with great effort I made a feeble noise which
                        awakened Edith. she called to me &#8211; the charm was
                        broken</del>. the oppression brought on the same head
                    seizure to which I was subject in England, &amp; then with
                    very great difficulty I at last made a feeble noise, but
                    enough to awaken <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>. she called to me &#8211; the charm was broken. I
                    do not wonder at the old superstition, for nothing can so
                    strongly impress the belief of an evil agency. you have an
                    accurate account of what my feelings were, &amp; given while
                    the recollection is still vivid.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You request a particular account of the
                    effect the change of climate &amp;c has produced upon me. I
                    slept so well on my arrival that I made no use of the
                    Laudanum which Pitcairns<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The London-based physician David Pitcairn
                        (1749&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), who discovered the
                        connection between rheumatic fever and valvular disease
                        of the heart. Ill health drove him to Portugal in 1798.
                        He spent eighteen months there, his visit overlapping
                        with Southey&#8217;s.</note> prescribed. as to diet I have
                    drank more wine, &amp; it is likewise probable that eating
                    much fruit by assisting digestion may have had some
                    beneficial effects. but assuredly the total change of
                    external objects &amp; the climate must have &lt;been&gt;
                    the great causes. my spirits have been uniformly high, &amp;
                    the bodily anxiety which threatened very badly in England,
                    gone. last week <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> was seized with a sick head ache. I did
                    not know he was subject to this, &amp; it alarmed me as the
                    probable fore runner of a fever. I lay in fear at night
                    listening to hear him breathe or move. that night I was
                    attacked as when in England. anxiety had renewed the
                    complaint. the news of <ref target="people.html#HillMargaret">my Cousins</ref> state
                    of health produced the same effect. Pitcairns was right when
                    he told me I should not soon be thoroughly recovered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It must be Climate that has been most
                    beneficial. I have no society in which I take pleasure, or
                    feel any interest whatever. thus am I without the greatest
                    inducement to chearfulness, &amp; in a state of mental
                    solitude which might be thought likely to depress the mind.
                    it is true I look on to England &#8211; I write, read &#8211; gather
                    information &amp; hear good news &#8211; but it is told me with a
                    long face, &amp; there is only one Englishman,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Southey&#8217;s uncle,
                            <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert
                            Hill</ref>.</note> whom I can see but seldom, who
                    looks at the world with eyes like my own.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Voltas<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Alessandro Volta (1745&#8211;1827) had invented the &#8216;voltaic
                        pile&#8217;, an early form of electric battery, in 1800. <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Humphry Davy</ref>
                        built on this work, making several crucial contributions
                        in the new field of electrolysis.</note> experiment is
                    important. it should appear as the galvanic fluid stimulates
                    to motion, that it is the same as the nervous fluid; &amp;
                    your system will prove true at last. has it yet been tried
                    whether the electrical shock will produce the same motion in
                    frogs as the galvanic fluid? &#8211; I have seen D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Constantia<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> he has tried the
                    fox-glove unsuccessfully. I thought possibly from having a
                    tincture not well made, &amp; gave him the bottles from your
                    manufactory. since then I have not seen him. <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> consumption is certainly
                    a disease not uncommon among the natives. if with the
                        Alfred<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph
                        Cottle, <title>Alfred, an Epic Poem in Twenty-Four
                            Books</title> (1800).</note> you could send some of
                    the new acid<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably
                        nitrous acid; see Thomas Beddoes, <title>A Collection of
                            Testimonies Respecting the Treatment of the Venereal
                            Disease by Nitrous Acid</title> (1799).</note>
                    securely packed &#8211; I would give it him to try in venereal
                    cases. what you sent was so insecurely stopped that I could
                    not venture to bring it. &#8211; I tremble for Alfred. those long
                    speeches! &amp; if reviewed by a hostile or even an
                    indifferent hand &#8211; had he listened to me, cut out his
                    dialogues &amp; introduced machinery he would have done.
                    angel &amp; devil nature he could have known as much about
                    as his neighbour, but of human feelings he knows nothing,
                    &amp; might as well write an account of the moon &amp; a
                    history of the Man in it. I shall &lt;expect&gt; it with
                    your book the next voyage that Yescombe<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Bayntun Yescombe
                        (1765&#8211;1803), Captain of the packet, <hi rend="ital">King
                            George</hi>, which sailed between Falmouth and
                        Lisbon.</note> makes, that is in about a month from this
                    time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thalaba<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801).</note> is finished, &amp; my employment is now
                    correcting &amp; copying it for the press. my resolution
                    being to send it over for publication. I have new plans of
                    poetry, but it is impossible to build without materials,
                    &amp; the books needful are in England. I design a romance
                    founded upon the creed of Zoroaster,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Zoroaster (11/10th centuries BC), Prophet
                        and founder of Zoroastrianism, the state religion in
                        Persia until the 7th century; see Robert Southey to
                        Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 23 July 1800, Letter
                        538.</note> the scene of course in Persia. the leading
                    character one of the Sons of the Great King: persecuted by
                    the Evil Powers, but every evil that they inflict developes
                    &#8211; <del rend="strikethrough">he</del> in him some virtue
                    which his situation had smothered. a Greek slave is a
                    prominent character, &amp; the conclusion is that the
                    Persian Prince is exalted into a Citizen of Athens. here is
                    an opportunity for seasoning the dish to my taste. no
                    farther has the story got. &#8211; for another &amp; more serious
                    poem I design the Establishment of the Inquisition to serve
                    as subject. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Dominic<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">St Dominic (c. 1170&#8211;1221),
                        born Domingo Guzman, in Castile. Founder of the
                        Dominican friars, he preached extensively against the
                        Albigensian heresy in southern France; the Dominicans
                        were later closely associated with the Inquisition; see
                            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood
                        Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 11.</note>
                    (more properly Domingos) the hero. a man indulging the
                    blackest feelings of malignity &amp; cruelty &amp; believing
                    them religious virtues. you may perhaps smile but by writing
                    two Poems <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del> at once I
                    expect to save time. because I may write a book of one,
                    while the story for a book of the other matures, &amp; thus
                    not pause so long between the books of each as would be
                    necessary to let the seeds ripen. these however are to be
                    written in England. what I bring home will be labours of
                    another cast.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For the History of Portugal<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished
                        &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> I shall be likely to have
                    a compleat &amp; finished subject. the country is in a
                    decline &amp; cannot recover, beyond this it is not easy to
                    speculate. Spain is <del rend="strikethrough">so</del> weak
                    &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> tottering &amp;
                    nearer the edge of the precipice, but both must inevitably
                    fall &#8211; I trust to rise again in a better shape. I have
                    collected much miscellaneous matter relative to this place;
                    so much indeed that my chief reason for sending over Thalaba
                    for publication, will be to make roo[MS torn] &amp; leisure
                    for other publications on my return.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> translation<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Piccolomini, or the First Part
                            of Wallenstein, a Drama in Five Acts. Translated
                            from the German of Frederick Schiller by S. T.
                            Coleridge</title> (1800) and <title>The Death of
                            Wallenstein. A Tragedy in Five Acts. Translated from
                            the German of Frederick Schiller by S. T.
                            Coleridge</title> (1800).</note> is admirable &#8211; but
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> who can write as well as Schiller<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Christoph
                        Friedrich von Schiller (1759&#8211;1805), German
                        playwright.</note> ought not to have translated. he has
                    done wrong, I think, in removing so far<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge told Davy of his
                        move to Keswick in a letter of July 15 [16] 1800 (E.L.
                        Griggs (ed.), <title>The Collected Letters of Samuel
                            Taylor Coleridge</title>, 6 vols (Oxford,
                        1956&#8211;1971), I, pp. 604&#8211;607), though his family joined
                        him on 24 July 1800. Wordsworth was living at Dove
                        Cottage in nearby Grasmere.</note> from his other
                    friends &amp; wholly giving himself to Wordsworth. it is
                    wrong on his own account, &amp; more so on his wifes, who is
                    now at an unreachable distance from all her sisters. What of
                    the Life of Lessing?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge had projected a life of the German dramatist
                        Gotthold Lessing (1729&#8211;1781). It was not written.</note>
                    the <hi rend="ital">Essay on the Genius of Schiller</hi>
                    amused me.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Oracle</title>, 4 April 1800, for
                        example, announced that &#8216;In the Press and speedily to be
                        published&#8217; was an &#8216;Essay on the Genius of Schiller&#8217;. It
                        did not appear.</note> it is not the first nor the
                    second time that he has advertised what has not been
                    written. Remember me to <ref target="people.html#TobinJamesWebbe">Tobin</ref>. he
                    will ask what is the use of Thalaba, &amp; condemn me with
                    all a Metaphysicians apathy. <del rend="strikethrough">he
                        will x</del> I know he must detest the Hexameters, &amp;
                    suspect my metre will not come off much better. but his ears
                    are not much better than his eyes.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The abolitionist James Webbe Tobin had
                        suffered from increasingly poor eyesight since the
                        mid-1790s; hence his nickname &#8216;Blind Tobin&#8217;.</note> God
                    bless him! I know no one more zealous in a good cause.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am induced to think with the Portugueze
                    that consumption is an infectious disorder &#8211; by what has
                    been told me here. if it really be so, its frequency in
                    England may, in some degree, be ascribed to the prevalence
                    of the contrary opinion. you will know where there is any
                    possible means of ascertaining it, by examining the breath
                    given out by patients whose lungs are decidedly affected. &#8211;
                    I see the author of Gebir has been translating from the
                    Arabic &amp; Persian.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">[Walter Savage Landor], <title>Poems from
                            the Arabic and Persian; with notes by the author of
                            Gebir</title> (1800).</note> can there possibly be
                    Arabic &amp; Persian poetry which the author of Gebir may be
                    excused for translating? &#8211; God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1">yrs affectionately RS.</signed>
          <address rend="left">
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>. </placeName>
          </address>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>