<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce421</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.412</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Boston Public Library, MSS Acc
                        461.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="412" type="letter">
        <head>412. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>,
                        <date when="1799-05-20">20 May 1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/
                            M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ with M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge/ Stowey near
                        Bridgewater/ Somersetshire/ Single <lb />Postmark:
                        CMA/21/99 <lb />MS: Boston Public Library, MSS Acc
                        461<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref>.</placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1799-05-20"> Monday 20. May. 1799.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At last my dear Edith I can write of my
                    return with certainty. <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> will
                    not come to Bristol till some days after me. therefore I
                    will take my place by Sundays mail, &amp; if no accident
                    intervene hope to be at <ref target="places.html#Westbury">Westbury</ref> to dinner on this day week. you will
                    therefore I suppose leave <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref> on Saturday if no Sunday coach goes &#8211;
                    &amp; by this time this day week my dear Edith we shall have
                    met once more. six days more &#8211; &amp; &lt;a&gt; mail-coach
                    night &#8211; the pleasantest night my Edith that I have past
                    since I left you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had a letter today from <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> with
                    the news of his fathers<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Burnett (d. 1799), a farmer at
                        Huntspill, Somerset.</note> death, &amp; am about to
                    write to him. the death of a parent is, where parents have
                    done their duty, a severe &amp; irreparable loss; but it is
                    an event the probability of which has ever been
                    contemplated, &amp; which affects us less deeply as it
                    happens in the common course of nature. it is the death of
                    the young, of children, friends &amp; those we love still
                    more dearly, that desolates life. I should hope that in our
                    next state of existence death will not be permitted; at
                    least that the ties of affection will not be cut asunder,
                    but that when it be time to proceed to some more advanced
                    being, friends &amp; families may emigrate together. I must
                    not lose you thro eternity my Edith &#8211; at least if I thought
                    it a thing probable it would deaden all earthly enjoyment. I
                    shall on finishing this write to <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> &#8211; not
                    that there is any thing in the common consolation still to
                    be said, for all that I could say he knows &#8211; but to be
                    silent on these occasions looks like unkindness &amp; indeed
                    is unkind; &amp; the very sight of a letter from a friend
                    alleviates painful feelings in some degree by breaking in
                    upon them. I am anxious to know if Burnetts father has left
                    him anything, if it be but a few hundred pounds, enough to
                    float him in his studies I shall be easy. but <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George</ref> has had
                    enemies at home whom I wish were now to be buried instead of
                    the poor old man. The sooner he can come to us the better.
                    to stay at Huntspill, unless business detains him, will be
                    only making himself uncomfortable &amp; benefitting
                    nobody.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But Edith let me turn to pleasanter subjects.
                    three weeks have I been absent &#8211; &amp; the last week of
                    absence is begun. <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> I hope
                    that it will be many many months before we are seperated for
                    a day again. about our summer plans I have written in my
                    last &#8211; we may go where we please, &amp; no place seems to
                    lie more conveniently situated than Devonshire, or to offers
                    situations more beautiful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del rend="strikethrough">Perhaps I am writing</del> I know
                    not that I shall write again, the next week will be crowded
                    with business, &amp; with what possible matter could I fill
                    another letter? you hear all the little unimportant
                    uninteresting occupations that fritter away my time from
                    eight in the morning till eleven at night, the two
                    pleasantest periods in the day, because when I get up I
                    reflect that another day is begun, &amp; when I lie down
                    comfort myself with the thought that it is over. time does
                    not hang so heavily at home. Saturday evening we were at the
                        Smiths<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                        Woodroffe Smith (c. 1747&#8211;1811), a wealthy Quaker
                        merchant, who lived at Stockwell Park, Surrey, near the
                        Bedfords. In 1789 he married as his second wife Anne
                        Reynolds (dates unknown) of Carshalton.</note> here,
                        <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenors</ref> Quaker friends &#8211; I wishd myself at
                    home, wished myself here, anywhere where a pen or a book
                    might have relieved me from the tedium of strange society.
                    they are according to all that has been told me very good
                    people. but he seems to be sixty years old, &amp; his wife
                    does not look above thirty. this is a vile &amp; unnatural
                    disproportion. I have no conception of husband &#8211; &amp; wife
                    &#8211; feelings between two persons so differently aged. Edith
                    could you share the identity of a husband old enough to be
                    your father? &#8211; I do not like the Quakers. many good points
                    they have, &amp; like most sects act upon the perception of
                    some important truth. but there is a profession of kindness,
                    an affected meekness &amp; amiability about them which
                    always puts me upon my guard. they are so plaguey civil that
                    they must be insincere.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> you tell me nothing about <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref> in your letter
                    &#8211; how you like the place, how you like the people, how you
                    are received &amp; all those little things which would be
                    dull to anyone but me, but in which I should be much
                    interested. however all this will be matter for
                    conversation. you will &lt;not&gt; I think be persuaded to
                    remain at <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref> so
                    as to let me arrive &amp; look for you &amp; not find you.
                    it is true you will have been but a fortnight at <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref>, but you will
                    have been some months with your sister, &amp; it is her you
                    wishd to see not <ref target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref>. I do not stay in London one hour after my
                    business is done, but drive from the dinner <del rend="strikethrough">table</del> at Grays Inn to the
                    Coach.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have had many little interruptions in
                    writing this letter. <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> is
                    here working by the fire at one of his out-of-the-way plans.
                    a neighbour dropt in to tea &amp; <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>
                    returned from angling <del rend="strikethrough">for</del>
                    with a huge trout which we all got up to see weighd. &#8211; you
                    have had vile weather for the country &#8211; I am afraid so as to
                    prevent you from much exercise &#8211; Edith I have to scold you
                    for saying nothing of your health &#8211; not a word &#8211; whether or
                    not the change of air has done you good &#8211; &amp; surely you
                    know that this is a subject which must interest me. ought I
                    not to insist upon a letter on purpose to remedy this?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I expect to get your books<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the edition of
                        Jean-Pierre Claris de Florian (1755&#8211;1794) which Southey
                        had bought for Edith during his stay in London; see
                        Robert Southey to Edith Southey, 9 May 1799, Letter
                        405.</note> tomorrow. my others I shall send down before
                    me, all that I shall want, because in the mail there is
                    generally more luggage to be carried than there is room to
                    stow it in. but your little books shall go in my hand
                    Edith.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &amp; now God bless you my dear dear girl &#8211;
                    if I do <del rend="strikethrough">not</del> but find you
                    well when I reach <ref target="places.html#Westbury">Westbury</ref> I will not complain of four weeks wasted
                    so unprofitably &amp; unpleasantly here. not that either or
                    you would purchase the pleasure of meeting by the sacrifice
                    of four weeks &#8211; but the pleasure is not the less real. once
                    more God bless you my Edith.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>