<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce821</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.812</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington
                        Library, RS 38.  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I,
                        pp. 222-225.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.812" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="812" type="letter">
        <head>812. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>,
                        <date when="1803-07-27">27 July [1803]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/
                        John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
            <lb />Endorsement: RS/ July 27, 1803<lb />MS: Huntington
                        Library, RS 38<lb />Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I,
                        pp. 222-225.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1803-07-27">July 27.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <hi rend="ital">estrado</hi> is not
                    exactly the <hi rend="ital">dais</hi>, tho had I recollected
                    that word it would have been better than the original. the
                    dais is the raised part of great halls &#8211; the <hi rend="ital">estrado</hi> was in every room, &amp; is often used <hi rend="ital">plurally</hi>. I cannot tell what it was. In
                    Portugal it is still not the common custom to use chairs.
                    the female peasantry &amp; servants usually squat down like
                    the Moors, very sensibly, for in houses that have no fire
                    places, &amp; doors &amp; windows that never shut close the
                    petticoats thus keep the feet warm. there are round mats
                    sold for them to squat upon; they puzzled me for some time,
                    seeing them in the shops. In that part of Portugal which was
                    last Moorish, the beds are laid upon a square platform about
                    half a foot high &#8211; this is perhaps something like the old
                        <hi rend="ital">estrado</hi>. once &amp; once only I saw
                    it reach across a room like a <hi rend="ital">dais</hi>.
                    some such platform in days of dirt, when the floors were
                    strewn with rushes, was probably placed for the gentle Dames
                    &amp; Damsels to squat upon. you will allow it to have been
                    very necessary at one period when Kts, Lords, &amp; Kings
                    lived in such hourly dangers that they kept their horses
                    ready saddled in their bed chambers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Are you right in imputing inconsistency to
                    the character of Lisvarte?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis
                            of Gaul</title> (1803) the father of Oriana,
                        Amadis&#8217;s beloved.</note> He is always proud &#8211; but while
                    his pride is well exerted it is not seen to be a vice.
                    suspicion is a part of his character which does not appear
                    in the first book, but which is no way incompatible with the
                    qualities that do appear. it opens upon you indeed, unawares
                    &#8211; as the door is to do upon the bed chamber that is fit for
                    a Bishop. the thing existed tho it had not been laid open.
                    The best preserved character is Orianas. interesting &#8211; yet
                    full of sexual littleness &#8211; &amp; true woman to the
                    last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a picture of female morals is that book!
                    every good damsel her friend&#8217;s bawd! the most
                    important corollary which I extract from the book goes to
                    lessen still farther the little merit of Henrique<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Prince Henry &#8216;the Navigator&#8217;
                        (1394-1460), patron of Portuguese voyages of discovery
                        down the west coast of Africa.</note> the patron of
                    discovery, for the notion of finding out unknown Islands was
                    common when Amadis was written. the lack of Latin is
                        Montalvos<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Garci
                        Rodriguez de Montalvo (d. 1504), Spanish author who
                        arranged the first publication of the story of Amadis of
                        Gaul in 1508 and wrote the first sequel, <title>Las
                            Sergas de Esplandian</title> (1510).</note> &#8211; not
                        Lobeiras.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Vasco
                        de Lobeira (d. 1403), medieval troubadour who Southey
                        mistakenly believed to be the originator of Amadis of
                        Gaul.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The main fault in the story certainly is the
                    want of one equal enemy &#8211; of a peer with whom Amadis may be
                    tried &#8211; for Arcalaus<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A wizard who persecutes the hero in <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title> (1803).</note> is a poor villain, &amp;
                        <hi rend="ital">Patin</hi>
          <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Brother of the Emperor of Rome who
                        contested a notable battle against the hero in
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803).</note> only a
                        <hi rend="ital">gander</hi>. yet there is a great
                    variety of incident &#8211; a wonderful <del rend="strikethrough">variety</del> &lt;change&gt; of <del rend="strikethrough">tune</del> tones produced from a
                    single string. &amp; the battles are the best I know. they
                    must be good if you can extract a system of armour from
                    them. I shall be glad of it for a better purpose than a
                    frontispiece to Amadis &#8211; it will help my history. I often
                    found my armorial vocabulary scant, &amp; was obliged to
                    give the strait forward meaning of the thing, having no name
                    for it. but I did give every thing scrupulously.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Arcadia<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Philip Sidney (1554-1586;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>Arcadia</title>
                        (1590).</note> is the work of a noble intellect &#8211; almost
                    Shakesperian in its powers of language. yet it is too
                    intricate in story, too tangled with episodes. You like it
                    better than Amadis because with all its trickery of thought
                    there is a pomp of fancy &amp; a power of words in the
                    narration peculiar to England &amp; to the summer season of
                    English genius. but the character of Amadis is naked
                    narration &#8211; the plain fact plainly told with little variety
                    of phrase. I scarcely know any book so completely <hi rend="ital">prose</hi>. but Sidney was a Poet &#8211; a great
                    &amp; admirable poet, tho he wrote bad <hi rend="ital">verses</hi> &amp; worse <hi rend="ital">metre</hi>: yet
                    some of his sonnets <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> have
                    a fine &amp; knight-like flow of thought &amp; feeling.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You &amp; <ref target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> puzzle me
                    by your Nicostrata<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In
                        legend, Nicostrata (or Carmenta) was the daughter of
                        Ionius, King of Arcadia. She and her son settled on the
                        site of the future city of Rome, where she invented the
                        alphabet used in Latin and taught it to the local
                        people. Rickman and Turner had drawn Southey&#8217;s attention
                        to a Latin verse quoted in Pietro Crinito (1475-1507),
                            <title>De Honesta Disciplina</title> (1504), Book
                        17, which told this story and claimed that an alphabet
                        was taught to the Goths by Gulfilas (c. 311-382), Arian
                        bishop of the Visigoths, before they settled in Spain.
                        In fact, Gulfilas invented a specific Gothic alphabet
                        when he translated the Bible into Gothic. The Visigoths
                        did not reject Arianism for Catholicism until 589 and
                        their Kingdom in Spain lasted until the Arab invasion of
                        711-712. The Gothic rite remained widespread in the
                        Spanish Church until the 11th century.</note> &#8211; which is
                    indeed no wonder for I have scarcely any documents yet for
                    the Gothic period of Spanish history nor indeed, except in
                    the laws, shall I enter at all minutely into that period.
                    That black court-hand cannot be what he introduced &#8211; that
                    must be the <hi rend="ital">French or Roman</hi> letter
                    introduced by authority when the poor Gulfilans were
                    ejected.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Pray, pray set at Malthus.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Malthus (1766-1834;
                            <title>DNB</title>). He had just published a second
                        edition of his <title>An Essay on the Principle of
                            Population</title> (1803), identifying himself as
                        the author for the first time.</note> put some stones
                    into my sling to knock down that clumsy Goliath<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>1 Samuel</title> 17
                        tells the story of Goliath, a giant of the Philistine
                        people.</note> of the philosophistuli of the day. send
                    me what you will I shall not scruple at plain language. it
                    is my hearts desire to put his rascally book to death &amp;
                    damnation. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> farewell</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
          <date when="1803-07-27">Wednesday July 27.</date>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> Our market-folk this day unanimously
                        refuse to take the small bank of England bills. Bristol
                            paper<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Bank
                            notes issued by Bristol banks.</note> they receive
                        without hesitation. </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>