<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce377</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.368</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington
                        Library, HM 4818 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 245&#8211;248.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.368" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="368" type="letter">
        <head>368. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref>, <date when="1799-01-04">4 January 1799</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Surry Street/
                        Norwich<lb />Stamped: BRISTOL<lb />Postmark: [partial] B/ JA/ 4/
                        9<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 28 Jan. 1799<lb />MS: Huntington
                        Library, HM 4818 <lb />Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 245&#8211;248.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you my dear friend for the trouble you have taken in
                    settling <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> &amp; the
                    interest you discover for his welfare. <ref target="people.html#MauriceMichael">Maurices</ref> letter is a very handsome one, I wish I could answer it to
                    my own satisfaction, but it is a difficult task to express obligation that one
                    cannot repay. Perhaps at Midsummer I may be near enough to house him, as I am
                        <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxxxxx xxxxx</del> have some thoughts of
                    passing a few weeks at Cambridge when our time is expired here, for the sake of
                    the Libraries.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am anxious to know what prospect of success <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> has at Brentford. the plan
                    is so far better than his former ones as it does not leave him at once to his
                    own resources. reviewing too is a good way of breaking him in to work; the
                    subject is given &amp; the task required, no time need be lost in beating about
                    the bushes to start something to pursue. Yet this new prospect offers little or
                    nothing more to ambition than his present situation. however it will employ him,
                    &amp; employment is what he wants.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should ascribe the review of <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottles</ref> Edda,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Amos Simon Cottle&#8217;s <title>Icelandic Poetry, or
                            the Edda of Saemund Translated into English Verse</title> (1797),
                        reviewed by Taylor in the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 27 (December 1798),
                        381&#8211;388.</note> &amp; the version of Vafthrudnismal in the M Magazine to
                        you<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor&#8217;s translation of &#8216;The Meal
                        of Vathruthni&#8217;, <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 6 (December 1798),
                        451&#8211;455.</note> if I thought you understood the Icelandic language. is that
                    the case? he was in a hurry, &amp; he wanted northern learning, but seemed to
                    have no idea of knowing how or where to look for it. the Edda fell into his
                    hands &amp; delighted him &#8211; <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">his
                        brother</ref> who knows no language but English wanted to read it, &amp; he
                    had begun a prose translation when I advised him to versify it. in the course of
                    six weeks he had the book half printed. all this was not as it should have been,
                    however his book will make the Runic tales more familiar, &amp; may perhaps give
                    a good direction to the genius of some young man into whose hands it may fall.
                    It would be my intention if I could speculate upon <del rend="strikethrough">what</del> leisure some three years hence, to build up a Runic song, - but
                    I must clear the ground first. my head has at present the materials for three
                    great works in it, each deserving a whole &amp; undivided attention. The
                    Kalendar, of which I hope this year to publish one volume.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Kalendar&#8217;, a sequence modelled on Ovid&#8217;s
                        (43 BC&#8211;AD 17) <title>Fasti</title>, was never completed.</note> Madoc<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The 15-book version written in
                        1797&#8211;1799.</note> which I expect to finish this summer, for nine books are
                    done, &amp; The Dom Danael.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">An early plan
                        for <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> Of this last I will
                    sketch you the outline.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know the Mohammedan tradition of the Garden of Irem. A female
                    Arab &amp; her son, a boy of about twelve years old, have escaped the
                    destruction of their tribe &amp; are wandering at night in the deserts. they
                    find themselves in the Garden, &amp; one Adite still existing in it, who when
                    his nation were destroyed, had for some deed of goodness been saved from their
                    damnation, &amp; left to live in that utter solitude till he thought himself
                    prepared to die. at times Azrael appeard to him &amp; enquired if he was ready,
                    but tho tortured by lonely existence still he dared not meet his judgement. As
                    he concludes his tale the Angel <del rend="strikethrough">of Death</del> stands
                    before them &amp; offers death <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> to the woman
                    &amp; the Adite. She is a devout Mussel-woman I suppose it must be. &amp;
                    encourages the Adite. Azrael raises his sword &amp; the drops of bitterness fall
                    on them. the design of this is to impress strongly with devotion the boy,
                    reserved for a great exploit, the destruction of the Dom Danael.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A wandering tribe find him. he grows up among them, &amp;
                    forgetful that he has been marked out for the especial service of the prophet,
                    attaches himself to Oneiza. some miracle summons him &#8211; he is sent to learn
                    preparatory knowledge for his journey from Harut &amp; Marut at Babel &#8211; &amp;
                    from the Simorg.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Magicians lay snares for him. he is entrapped by Aladeules,
                    the account of whose Paradise Purchas gives from Marco Polo.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Purchas (1577&#8211;1626; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Purchas his Pilgrimage</title>, 2nd edn (London, 1614), p. 237,
                        deriving his account from Marco Polo (1254&#8211;1324), <title>Travels of Marco
                            Polo</title>, Book 1.</note> this he destroys &#8211; but he finds Oneiza in
                    his harem, &amp; dwells with her in the delightful regions of Cashmeer. her
                    death by the judgement of God rouses him. he arrives at a place like the Port
                    des Francais <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> which Perouse discovered.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Francois de Galeup, Comte de La
                        Perouse (1741&#8211;1788). On his voyage to the Pacific he discovered in 1786 a
                        bay in Alaska, which he named Port des Francais (now Lituya Bay).</note> a
                    bay surrounded by glaciers, profoundly silent, &amp; where no wind ever ruffled
                    the waters. a vessel receives him, [MS cut] the Spirits of all who had failed in
                    the adventure navigate it, [MS cut] their punishment, to sail in those cold seas
                        <del rend="strikethrough">txxx</del> &lt;till&gt; the adventure was
                    accomplished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a very vague idea of what passes under the roots of the
                    sea. however when all is accomplished a voice from Heaven bids Thamama ask his
                    reward. he resigns himself like the Argive brethren<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Catillus and Corus, two brothers who rushed into the
                        forefront of battle against Aeneas, <title>Aeneid</title>, book 7, line
                        672.</note> to God &#8211; the Sansar, the icy wind of death pervades him, &amp;
                    he is welcomed in Paradise by Oneizas houri form. you see a rude outline &#8211; but
                    it may be made a glorious picture I hesitate whether to write in blank verse or
                    in stanzas. there is but too much time to consider.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.
                            </salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey. &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;<date when="1799-01-04">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 4. 99.</date>
          </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Pray make my respects to your mother.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sarah Taylor, n&#233;e Wright (d. 1811).</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>