<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce441</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.432</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Beinecke
                        Library, Chauncey Brewster Tinker MS Collection, GEN MSS 310, Box 13, folder
                        554.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from
                            the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        81&#8211;83.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="432" type="letter">
        <head>432. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1799-09-03">[started before and continued after] 3 September
                        [1799]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/
                        John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Richmond Green/ Surry./
                        Single<lb />Stamped: EXETER<lb />Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ SP.5./ 99 F.NOON; A/
                        SEP 5/ 99<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 47/ 1799/ Robert Southey/
                        Exeter 3 September/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 5 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/
                            ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 7 d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb />MS: Beinecke
                        Library, Chauncey Brewster Tinker MS Collection, GEN MSS 310, Box 13, folder
                        554<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from
                            the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        81&#8211;83.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write to you from Ottery where I have been uncomfortably
                    detained five days by the impossibility of finding lodgings anywhere in its
                    neighbourhood. I wishd to be as near as possible on <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> account &amp;
                    additionally so as there is the probability of seeing you here &#8211; tomorrow
                    however we go to Exeter where there can be no doubt of house room &#8211; &amp; eleven
                    miles is a very walkable distance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have now seen <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">George
                        Coleridge</ref>. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">his
                        brother</ref> &amp; you had taught me to respect him. in many things he
                    reminds me of you &#8211; there is the resemblance that two persons who have lived
                    much together &amp; with attached affections, bear to each other. something too
                    he reminds me of <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &#8211; of
                    his equalness &amp; kindness of <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> character,
                    but he is not so chearful as <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncle</ref> nor has his situation been so favourable. he told me that from
                    the age of eighteen he had never had leisure to read a book thro.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are three classes of people in whose society I find
                    pleasure. those in whom I meet with similarity of opinion &#8211; those who from a
                    similarity of feeling tolerate difference of opinion, &amp; those to whom long
                    acquaintance has attached me, who neither think nor feel with me, but who have
                    the same recollections &amp; can talk of other times &amp; other scenes.
                    accustomed to seclusion or to the company of those who know me &amp; to whom I
                    can let out every thought as it rises, without the danger of being judged by a
                    solitary expression, I am uncomfortable among strangers. A man loses many
                    privileges when he is known to the world. go where I will my name has gone
                    before me, &amp; strangers either receive me with expectations that I cannot
                    gratify, or with evil prepossessions that I cannot remove. it is only in a stage
                    coach that I am on an equal footing with an companions &amp; it is there that I
                    talk the most &amp; leave them in the best humour with me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just learnt that you do not visit Devonshire &#8211; I however
                    have the expectation of seeing you in Hampshire during the winter. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">George Coleridge</ref> has been very
                    friendly towards me &amp; I felt that his opinion of me had been influenced by
                    you. he has <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">his brothers</ref>
                    forehead &#8211; but no other resemblance. it is wonderful how the strong feelings
                    induced in composition change the countenance. strong thought is labour &#8211; an
                    exercise essential to the minds health, or the face of a thinking man like the
                    legs of a porter &amp; the arms of a blacksmith indicate how he has been
                    employed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you for procuring the Zendavesta<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Abraham-Hyacinthe Anquetil Du Perron (1731&#8211;1805),
                            <title>Zend-Avesta</title> (1771), a translation into French of some of
                        the key sacred writings of Zoroastrianism. The book was no. 3135 in the sale
                        catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; for so I suppose it to be &#8211; which
                    has arrived at Bristol for me. when we meet I will pay you for it. I expect <del rend="strikethrough">to find much folly</del> in going thro it to derive
                    wisdom from perusing much folly. something I shall one day build upon the base
                    of Zoroaster. but what I know not. to Mango Capac<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Manco Capac was the legendary founder of the Inca Empire in
                        the 12th or 13th centuries.</note> I feel myself pledged &#8211; &amp; if I can
                    see the propriety of blending ought supernatural with philosophical narration he
                    shall be brought from Persia. my head is full of plans &#8211; it seems as tho all
                    that I have yet done is the mere apprenticeship of poetry &#8211; the rude work which
                    has taught me only how to manage my tools.</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <date when="1799-09-03">Tuesday. Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 3.</date> We are lodged
                    at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tuckers. Fore-Street-Hill &#8211; Exeter.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the retired stationer and bookseller
                        Richard Tucker (fl. 1779&#8211;1784), whose business had occupied premises on
                        Fore-Street, Exeter.</note> here we shall remain till Michaelmas<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">29 September 1799.</note> &amp; here then you
                    will direct. since beginning this letter I bore part in an interesting
                    conversation with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeGeorge">George
                        Coleridge</ref> upon the tendency of Xtianity. his brother Edward<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Coleridge (1760&#8211;1843), a clergyman and
                        schoolmaster.</note> who seldom talks much to the purpose, talkd only to
                    confuse &amp; misunderstand &#8211; but afterwards when we walked out he understood us
                    better. we were talking upon the equalitarian doctrines of the Gospel, a
                    doctrine which you know I see there &amp; which is intimately <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> blended with all my opinions &amp; systems,
                    their foundation indeed, their life &amp; their soul. I could soon grow
                    unreserved with him &amp; talk from immediate impulse. We were all a good deal
                    amused by the old Lady<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Ann Coleridge, n&#233;e
                        Bowden (1727&#8211;1801), Coleridge&#8217;s mother.</note> &#8211; she could not hear what was
                    going on, but seeing <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel</ref> arguing with his brothers, took it for gra[MS torn] that he
                    must have been wrong &amp; cried out ah if your poo[MS torn] had been alive! hed
                    soon have convinced you!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In Exeter I find a humble imitation of Lisbon filth. but I also
                    find two good sale libraries of old books. you will smile at the catalogue title
                    of a Portugueze book which I bought here &#8211; it is an account <del rend="strikethrough">of the</del>
          <hi rend="ital">das cousas que fizeram os Padres da companhia de Jesus</hi>, in
                    the East Indies &amp; in Africa.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Portugueze translates as &#8216;of the things done by the Fathers (i.e. Catholic
                        priests) of the Jesuit Order&#8217;. The book referred to is <title>Rela&#231;am Annual
                            das Cousas que Fizeram os Padres da Companhia de Jesu nas partes da
                            India Oriental</title>. The auction catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, nos
                        3483-3484, indicates that he owned two volumes, the first (published in
                        1607) dealt with the years 1601&#8211;1605, the second (published 1611) covered
                        1607 and 1608.</note> &amp; this the catalogues maker has called <hi rend="ital">Fizeramo&#8217;s</hi> account &amp;c &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> is better than she has been
                    for many months. I find a sort of health-thermometer in the hair. my own curls
                    crisp &amp; strong in proportion to the state of the whole system or becomes
                    weak &amp; straightened. perhaps by &amp; by the connection will be discovered
                    between the colour of the hair &#8211; &amp; its quantity &amp; its crispness, <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> &amp; the constitution. physiology is yet it
                    its infancy. have you received the Annual Anthology?<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>