<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce404</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.395</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I,
                        pp. 66&#8211;68 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.395" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="395" type="letter">
        <head>395. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1799-04-05">5 April 1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Chester Circuit<lb />Postmark: BRISTOL/ APR 5
                        99<lb />Endorsement: April 5 99<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                            from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I,
                        pp. 66&#8211;68 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My last letter which was written before I received your
                    accusation of laziness will I think acquit me of it. Queen Mary<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s proposed play on &#8216;The Days of Queen
                        Mary&#8217;, set in the time of Mary I (1516&#8211;1558; Queen of England, 1553&#8211;1558);
                        see <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 190&#8211;192.</note> I have begun &#8722; &amp; but begun.
                    for my way is not clear thro the first act. the story has great advantages &amp;
                    it would be difficult to select any so unlike that of other dramas. The elder
                    Brutus has been dramatized by Lee.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathaniel Lee (1653&#8211;1692; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Lucius Junius Brutus,
                            Father of his Country</title> (1681), based on the life of one of the
                        legendary founders of the Roman Republic in 509 BC.</note> Lee lived at that
                    time when the French Romances were in vogue &amp; made more use of them than a
                    man of such genius ought to have done. he has made his play out of Clelia,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Madelaine de Scudery (1607&#8211;1701),
                            <title>Clelie</title> (1654&#8211;1661).</note> &amp; bad enough it is, with
                    some brilliant exceptions as in every thing he wrote. the subject would be very
                    difficult. his sins are scarcely dignifyed enough for tragedy &#8722; &amp; his
                    character seems almost above it. it is for the painter &#8722; not the poet. I have
                    seen an account of a picture by David<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques-Louis David (1748&#8211;1825), <title>The Lictors Bring to Brutus the
                            Bodies of His Sons</title> (1789).</note> on this subject which appeared
                    to me more finely conceived than any thing I ever saw or heard of else. Rousseau
                    thought of dramatizing the story of Lucretia.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Legendary Roman noblewoman and sister of Lucius Junius
                        Brutus. She was raped by the son of the last King of Rome and this event
                        precipitated the rebellion led by Brutus and the foundation of the Roman
                        Republic.</note> in that case Brutus would be a strikingly dramatic
                    character. but these subjects will not do &#8722; unless indeed one was to write a
                    loyal play <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del> make Tarquin<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lucius Tarquinius Superbus, in legend the last
                        King of Rome, 534&#8211;509 BC.</note> the hero, &amp; introduce God save the
                    King.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The difficulty I find in every subject that has occurred to me is
                    to make enough of it. I cannot wire-draw a <del rend="strikethrough">subject</del> story. this will seem odd to you who think me prolix &amp;
                    dilated. however in Queen Mary there is enough I have no other doubt respecting
                    it but that of its suiting the feelings of an audience. there will be no
                    clap-traps. no loyalty &#8722; nothing about Britannia rule the waves. &amp; however
                    orthodox my sufferers may be, they were dissenter then &#8722; &amp; that will be
                    sorely against them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The theatrical taste of the public is certainly very bad. <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;</del> but the managers are more to blame than the
                    public. they never give them an opportunity of supporting any thing good. they
                    bring forward Boadens Tragedies &amp; Reynolds&#8217;s Comedies!<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">James Boaden (1762&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>) and
                        Frederic Reynolds (1764&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), popular playwrights of
                        the 1790s.</note> &#8722; the play which they rejected of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref>
          <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Osorio&#8217; (1797).</note> was very faulty in
                    delineation of character &#8211; but it abounded with stage effect, with passages
                    equal to any in our language &#8211; &amp; with poetry even to an excess. I do not
                    think an audience could have condemned it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your story of the old man dying at Elizabeths<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth I (1533&#8211;1603; reigned 1558&#8211;1603;
                            <title>DNB</title>). Wynn&#8217;s letter has not survived, and his story is
                        untraced.</note> succession is new to me. it is very fine. one could have
                    died with joy at such an event.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know I am fond of Monodramas. the dramatic turn which my
                    thoughts have for some time taken, has suggested to me the thought of narrating
                    in &lt;dialogue&gt; poems not much longer, such historical, or other, facts <del rend="strikethrough">which</del> &lt;as&gt; would make noble scenes
                    only.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The German plays have always something ridiculous &#8722; yet
                        Kotzebue<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">August von Kotzebue
                        (1761&#8211;1819), German playwright. English translations of his works included
                            <title>Count Benyowski, or the Conspiracy of Kamtschatka</title> (1798)
                        and <title>The Reconciliation, or Birth-Day</title> (1799).</note> seems to
                    me possessed of unsurpassed &amp; unsurpassable genius. I wonder his plays are
                    acted here &#8722; they are so thoroughly Jacobinical in tendency. they create<del rend="strikethrough">d</del> Jacobinical feelings &#8722; almost irresistibly &#8722; in
                    every one that I have yet seen (Benyowsky excepted) some old prejudice or old
                    principle is attacked. there is a very good comedy of his lately translated &#8722;
                    the Reconciliation. full of those quick strokes of feeling that like Sterne<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Laurence Sterne (1713-1768;
                            <title>DNB</title>).</note> surprize you into a tear before you have
                    finished a smile.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Song of which I had the credit<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;On a Golden Cup, with Embossed Figures, Dedicated to the God
                        of Mirth by the Harmonic Club&#8217;, <title>Courier</title>, 11 March
                        1799.</note> proves to be Sothebys.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">William Sotheby (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), poet. He published
                            <title>Oberon, a Poem, from the German of Wieland</title> (1798), a
                        translation of the poem by Christoph Wieland (1733&#8211;1813).</note> a man with
                    whom I am sometimes confounded. he gave me his address some months since &amp; I
                    shall visit him when I come to London. Sotheby has considerable talents as a
                    poet &#8722; but he is not [MS torn]kely to improve &#8722; as I judge him to be forty. his
                    Ober[MS obscured] translated as well as the admirers of Wieland ever expect it
                    to be &#8722; but it falls sadly short they tell me. &amp; all the puffs in the world
                    will never make it popular. Oberon must not stand next to the Orlando
                        Furioso.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Lodovico Ariosto
                        (1474&#8211;1534), author of <title>Orlando Furioso</title> (1532).</note> I shall
                    beg leave to put my own Dom-Danael<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                        early plan for <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> between
                    them.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1799-04-05">Friday. Apr. 5. 99.</date>
          </p>
          <p>I do not continue to mend. the Spring has been too cold as yet. We have no
                        news of <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">Ediths brother</ref> &#8722; &amp;
                        little hope of any except that he may be a prisoner.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>