<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce758</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.749</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington Library, HM 4837 .  Previously 
                        published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp.
                        438-440 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.749" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="749" type="letter">
        <head>749. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>,
                        <date when="1803-01-11">11 January 1803</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/
                            M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor
                            Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street/
                        Norwich<lb />Postmarks: BRISTOL/ JAN 1803; B/ JAN 13/
                        1803<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 17
                        Jan<lb />MS: Huntington Library, HM 4837 <lb />Previously
                        published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the
                            Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp.
                        438-440 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> Last night &#8211; dear <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>
                    &#8211; I commissioned an Embassador to pay five pounds to <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>. by
                    this days post I learn that this was too late &#8211; &amp; that
                    the debt is transferrd to you. half will go in this letter &#8211;
                    the other in course as soon as this is acknowledged &#8211; but do
                    not you give me a mere line of acknowledgement. consider me
                    as a lover of letter-reading, however deficient in letter
                    writing from half a dozen causes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> I had written you half a letter when a
                    very absurd explanation took place, which rendered that half
                    useless. he has thought proper to quarrel with me. he
                    complains that I did not behave well to him in London &#8211; that
                    my manners were always those of a superiour, always
                    expressing a familiar contempt, that I had not visited him
                    enough. All I could reply was that I had never felt or
                    expressed myself as to him but with affection. familiar I
                    was indeed, as became me with one of my oldest friends &#8211;
                    that I did not visit him because, he being single, I made
                    him visit me &#8211; that I saw no one friend so often in London &#8211;
                    that I went to no public sight or amusement without him, &#8722;
                    that he dined with me whenever I could persuade him, &amp;
                    that twice or thrice every week I did not remind him <del rend="strikethrough">of</del>. But this was only the
                    effect of a growing dislike towards me &#8211; not the cause. this
                    is evident. he tells me that I &amp; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> never treated him properly. mark you
                    this word <hi rend="ital">treated</hi> is in a
                    physico-mental sense &#8211; &#8220;Every human being &#8211; &amp; now <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>
                    I quote his words &#8211; can influence the mind of another human
                    being <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> whom he is placed&#8211;
                    near, &amp; upon this great truth all the principles of
                    education defend.&#8221; Well! it seems <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> nor I had directed his mind to
                    profitable studies &amp; we had never advised him what to
                    do. &#8211; upon this I reminded him of my constant cry &#8211; <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> employ
                    yourself! &#8211; the advice I had given him from the time of his
                    going to <ref target="places.html#Yarmouth">Yarmouth</ref>
                    &amp; the specific plans which I had from time to time
                    pointed out. But he was determined to quarrel with me, &amp;
                    replied that the advice had not been given properly. I had
                    not <hi rend="ital">treated</hi> him well. I could not avoid
                    answering that I had ever regarded him as my friend &#8211; not my
                    patient, &amp; as for advice, if it had failed, it was not
                    because the medicines were bad but because they were not
                    taken. he desired not to see me while he was here. his mind
                    he confessed was not in a state to judge deliberately &#8211; but
                    his feelings could not be mistaken, if when he was well he
                    found out that he was wrong in judging of me as he did &#8211; he
                    would then let me know &#8211; I begged him to take care how he
                    fostered this dislike, told him that by the time he had
                    found it out, the habit of hatred would be confirmed &#8211; &amp;
                    besought him very earnestly not to estrange himself from his
                    oldest friend than whom he had none who loved him better.
                    you are come here <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George</ref> &#8211; said I &#8211; for your health. you say
                    company, is necessary for it &#8211; &amp; yet you will not come
                    to that house where you would be always most welcome. You
                    will excuse me &#8211; <del rend="strikethrough">said</del> he
                    replied &#8211; if I tell you these are mere words. I bore this
                        <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> lie direct twice
                    before I bade him remember I had some pride &amp; some
                    feeling as well as himself &#8211; then left him to his own
                    ways.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now indeed envy is at the bottom of all this.
                    as for my own feelings upon the subject you will guess what
                    they needs must be. not anger, for old habits of affections
                    are not so soon worn out &#8211; I am merely passive in this
                    quarrel &#8211; ready to excuse it upon any plea of diseased head
                    or diseased digestion that he may make. but it has altered
                    my mind towards him, &amp; in spite of regret I am fully
                    awake to the extraordinary folly of his language &amp;
                    actions. he is as completely driven mad by his studies as
                    ever Quixote<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Miguel
                        de Cervantes Saavedra (1547-1616), <title>Don
                            Quixote</title> (1605-1615).</note> or Loyola<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">St Ignatius of Loyola
                        (1491-1556), founder of the Jesuit Order.</note> was
                    before him. a few worthless books of metaphysics are all he
                    has ever read &#8211; these he has fed upon, &amp; is now bringing
                    them &lt;up&gt; by crude mouthfuls. he walks thro the
                    streets with his head lifted &amp; his eyes looking round to
                    see who hears him, conversing that every body may hear him
                    upon his &#8220;high moral <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del>
                    views of things&#8221; &amp; &#8220;principles of conduct different from
                    common men.&#8221; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All this will give you pain. I tell it you as
                    the friend of both. when you write to him &#8211; if you mention
                    the subject at all, say of me that I am sorry he has done
                    this &#8211; that I [MS illegible]rly deny any intentional
                    disrespect (God knows I never felt it) &#8211; &amp; that at any
                    time I shall rejoice to shake him by the hand</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am still unsettled &#8211; disappointed of <ref target="places.html#MaesGywn">Maes Gwyn</ref> &amp;
                    looking out for some country dwelling within reach of
                    Bristol. you are unhappily too far east &#8211; too far from all
                    other friends &#8211; &amp; from all chances of seeing them by the
                    accidents of life. Else &#8211; with enough common opinions &amp;
                    mutual regard to form a fit base for intimacy &#8211; &amp; with
                    enough disparity always to keep conversation wakeful &#8211; you
                    &amp; I should be good neighbours, &amp; in the best &amp;
                    sacredest sense of the word good friends. there is yet
                    another bar to the possibility of this. I am but loosely
                    attached to English ground &amp; will strike as few roots
                    into it as I can. here in the west the intercourse with
                    Portugal is far easier, there I must go in about two years &#8211;
                    &amp; there if possible I would willingly fix my final
                    abode, &amp; spend my life <del rend="strikethrough">too</del> speaking Portugueze &amp; writing
                    English.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Weak eyes still annoy me &amp; keep me idle.
                    I can only write Poetry &#8211; which is hard when prose pleases
                    me better. Madoc<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had completed a version of <title>Madoc</title>
                        in 1797-1799. He was revising it for publication, but it
                        did not appear until 1805.</note> is on the anvil for
                    the last time &#8211; probably I must publish it next winter; not
                    for the love of <hi rend="ital">Fame </hi>
          <del rend="strikethrough"> few consider</del> but of a worse
                    counsellor bad as she is &#8211; malesuada <hi rend="ital">Fames</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Virgil (70&#8211;19 BC), <title>Aeneid</title>, Book 6, line
                        276. The Latin translates as &#8216;crime-provoking
                        Hunger&#8217;.</note> with an Odyssey fault of structure, it
                    will be a good poem, of that I feel most prophetic
                    assurance. I am correcting it with merciless vigilance,
                    shortening &amp; shortening. distilling vin[MS torn] into
                    alcohol. The Edinburgh Review<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 1
                        (October 1802), 63-83 carried <ref target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Francis
                            Jeffrey&#8217;s</ref> hostile review of <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> is well done: their
                    principles of poetry thoroughly false, but ably pleaded.
                    their account of the story of Thalaba very false. not so
                    likely to be misrespresentd wilfully as from negligence, for
                    they mistake the events so grossly that they cannot have
                    read it with attention I am well pleased to be abused with
                        <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>.
                    it is the best omen that I shall be remembered with them.
                    yet it is odd enough that my fellow conspirator <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>
                    should be almost a stranger to me &#8211; a man with whom I have
                    scarcely had any intercourse. not even of common
                    acquaintanceship.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. in spite of Norfolk weather I
                    am in good health. the spirits always stand at the same
                    point. six months ago I thought I was as happy as man could
                    be &#8211; but little <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> shows me I was mistaken. my love to <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <date when="1803-01-11">Tuesday. Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.
                        11. 1803.</date>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>My name has got into the papers as translator of
                            Amadis.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation of <title>Amadis of
                                Gaul</title> (1803); see, for example,
                                <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803),
                            975.</note> I am endeavour[MS torn] conceal the
                        truth. John Southwell Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> will
                        claim the book &amp; explain the mistak[MS torn]</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>