<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce751</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.742</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Berg
                        Collection, New York Public Library.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York,
                        1965), I, pp. 298-299.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="742" type="letter">
        <head>742. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Charles
                        Biddlecombe</ref>, <date when="1802-12-11">11 December
                        1802</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ Charles Biddlecombe Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Burton/ Ringwood/
                        Single<lb />Postmark: [partial] TOL/ DEC 22<lb />MS: Berg
                        Collection, New York Public Library<lb />Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York,
                        1965), I, pp. 298-299.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is so long since I have heard from you,
                    &amp; I am so tortoise-paced a correspondent, that as a
                    thing of course I should believe myself to be the defaulter,
                    if it were not for remembering that the last letter between
                    us was my acknowledgement of the fifty pounds. Howbeit I am
                        <del rend="strikethrough">not xx</del> clearly acquitted
                    &#8211; for you perhaps have lost sight of me, &amp; supposed that
                    I had removed to Cumberland as was my design. that scheme
                    was unexpectedly frustrated. I still remain at Bristol,
                    unsettled still &#8211; &amp; still expecting a settlement. At
                    present treating for a house in Glamorganshire &#8211; a very
                    delightful place near Neath. so beautifully situated that if
                    as there is every probability, it should be my home next
                    spring, I think the country fine enough to ask you to come
                    &amp; let me show it you. for it is worth a journey longer
                    than from Hampshire.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">My little
                        girl</ref>, now fourteen weeks old, grows well &amp;
                    healthy. she has just had the cowpox. this is our chief
                    news. a child makes a huge alteration in a family. I talk
                    nonsense very fluently to her, &amp; am a better nurse than
                    you would perhaps imagine. hitherto she has lived wholly
                    upon mothers milk &#8211; the natural food, &amp; is a fine
                    specimen she is that the natural food is the best. I hope
                        <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> may
                    continue able to support her till her teeth come. For myself
                    I have been unwell from head to foot, but have got rid of
                    all complaints except weak eyes. which annoy me terribly &#8211;
                    &amp; injure me too for they are my trade tools. this
                    Laplandish weather as your old friend Lady Strathmore<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Eleanor Bowes
                        (1749-1800; <title>DNB</title>), heiress. She had lived
                        at Christchurch in later life and Southey had met her
                        there in 1797.</note> called it, neither pleases nor
                    hurts me. I keep a brave fire, &amp; when I go out wear a
                    great coat. but begin to think it is time to turn dormouse,
                    &amp; shut myself up for the winter. My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is with me,
                    &amp; likes half pay better than actual service, which I do
                    not wonder at. So much for home politics. you will guess all
                    the lesser details &#8211; how I stick to my folios, &amp;
                    continue as good a customer to the paper merchant as
                    ever.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For the politics of the great world, things
                    more important than interesting, I find them sufficiently
                    promising. Addington<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757-1844;
                            <title>DNB</title>), The Speaker 1789-1801, Prime
                        Minister 1801-1804, Home Secretary 1812-1822.</note> I
                    am sure is an honest &amp; well-intentioned man. his remark
                    upon the Liberty of the Press set him very high in my good
                    graces. &amp; Lord Hawkesbury<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Jenkinson, 1st Earl of Liverpool
                        (1727-1808; <title>DNB</title>), President of the Board
                        of Trade 1786-1804.</note> has of late talked so wisely
                    that I have forgiven all the sins of young Jenkinson.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Jenkinson,
                        later 2nd Earl of Liverpool (1770-1828;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Foreign Secretary 1801-1804,
                        Home Secretary 1804-1806, 1807-1809, Prime Minister
                        1812-1827.</note> I like their proceedings in the
                    foolish or mad business of Despard.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Marcus Despard (1751-1803;
                            <title>DNB</title>), Irish radical and
                        revolutionary. He was imprisoned between 1798 and 1801
                        under particularly harsh conditions and re-arrested on
                        16 November 1802. He was tried, convicted of treason and
                        executed in 1803.</note> the old rascals would have
                    suspended the Habeas Corpus &amp; filled the Bastile. there
                    will be a trial now &#8211; &amp; therefore I fear there is some
                    truth in the story. If it be so Despard must be a very
                    foolish man, but they have made him a traitor, private
                    revenge must have been his actuating &amp; overruling
                        feeling<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>, &amp; God
                    knows he has been heavily sinned against! the man in this
                    kingdom who has suffered most, who has been the marked
                    victim of ministerial oppression &#8211; fetterd, imprisoned in a
                    solitary cell till the frost ulcered his feet, his character
                    blasted &#8211; &amp; his crime proved &#8211; no trial allowed, no
                    possible justice &#8211; for forsooth there is a Bill of
                        Indemnity!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        Indemnity Act of 1802 pardoned all state officials who
                        might have exceeded their powers.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no fear of war. Bonaparte<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                        (1769-1821, First Consul 1799-1804, Emperor of the
                        French 1804-1814).</note> great rascal as he is (&amp;
                    if oaths flowed as glibly from the pen as the tongue he
                    would have had a curse now) &amp; fool as he is to my utter
                    disappointment will not go to war with us, for what <del rend="strikethrough">he</del> can he gain by it? he will
                    be as little desirous to cope with our fleets, as we can be
                    to encounter his armies. the same causes for peace will
                    operate whatever be the fate of France, whether he be
                    supplanted by some Adventurer like himself, or sacrificed as
                    he <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> deserves to public
                    Justice &amp; Freedom upon the scaffold, which God grant. In
                    the strange turn which things have taken here what most
                    pleases me is the returning temper of the country, that
                    liberty of thought &amp; of speech are again allowed us,
                    &amp; that &lt;any&gt; Englishman may differ with his
                    neighbour &amp; still be his friend.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now &#8211; let me hear of yourself &#8211; of your
                    little girl<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The name
                        of Biddlecombe&#8217;s child is unknown. She was born in
                        1799.</note> &#8211; of your Mother.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Biddlecombe&#8217;s first name and dates
                        are unknown.</note> &amp; of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Coleman,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                        acquaintance of Southey&#8217;s from his time at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>; his first
                        name and dates are unknown.</note> whom I hope yet one
                    day to shake by the hand &amp; thank for all the trouble
                    that I have given him. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> joins me
                    in remembrance &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> desires not to be forgotten.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <lb />
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#StJamesPlace">12. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> James&#8217;s Place. Kingsdown</ref>. Bristol.</placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1802-12-11">December 11. 1802.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>