<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce448</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.439</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS has
                        not survived.  Previously  published: Monthly Magazine, 8
                        (November 1799), 770&#8211;772 [from where the text is taken]. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.439" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="439" type="letter">
        <head>439. Robert Southey to the <ref target="people.html#AikinJohn">Editor of the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>
          </ref>, <date when="1799-10">October
                        [1799]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS has
                        not survived<lb />Previously published: <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 8
                        (November 1799), 770&#8211;772 [from where the text is taken]. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>SIR,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> As a subscription edition of all Chatterton&#8217;s remains<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Bristol poet Thomas Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>). Southey and Cottle's edition of his <title>Works</title> was eventually published in 1803.</note> is
                    about to be published for the benefit of his sister and niece,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Newton (1749&#8211;1804) and her daughter.</note>
                    I beg leave, by means of your Magazine, to invite the public attention to those
                    circumstances which render this act of justice necessary.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It might have been supposed that the interest which the fate of
                    Chatterton excited in the public mind, would, in some measure, have supplied his
                    loss to his family, by procuring for them active and benevolent friends. The
                    publication of all his works for their emolument, would at that time have
                    secured to them the comforts of life. Your readers, Sir, will probably learn
                    with surprize, that the whole sum they have ever received from the profits of
                    his productions, amounts only to seventeen guineas and six pence. In this I do
                    not include the voluntary assistance of those individuals on whose justice they
                    had no claim. They remember with gratitude the kindness of Dr. Glynn, of Mr.
                        Bryant,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Glynn (1719&#8211;1800;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Jacob Bryant (1717&#8211;1804; <title>DNB</title>),
                        antiquarians who took the view that Chatterton&#8217;s Rowley papers were genuine,
                        see their collaboration, <title>Observations on the Poems of Thomas
                            Rowley</title> (1781).</note> above all of <ref target="people.html#MoreHannah">Miss Hannah More</ref> and her sisters.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Hannah More (1745&#8211;1833;
                        <title>DNB</title>), writer and propagandist for evangelical and
                        conservative causes. Her sisters were Mary (1738&#8211;1813), Elizabeth
                        (1740&#8211;1816), Sarah (1743&#8211;1819) and Martha (1747&#8211;1819).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The papers and poems attributed to Rowley, had been procured from
                    Chatterton, during his life time, chiefly by Mr. Barrett<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Barrett (1727&#8211;1789: <title>DNB</title>), surgeon and
                        Bristol antiquarian, author of <title>History and Antiquities of
                            Bristol</title> (1789), which accepted the Rowley papers as geniune.
                        Southey&#8217;s father was one of the subscribers to Barrett&#8217;s
                            <title>History</title>.</note> and Mr. Catcott;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">George Symes Catcott (1729&#8211;1802), pewterer and patron of
                        Chatterton.</note> from the latter, the poems were purchased for fifty
                    pounds, of which six guineas were given to the mother and sister. A great part
                    of Mr. Barrett&#8217;s History of Bristol is composed of Chatterton&#8217;s communications;
                    the only return the family ever received from him was his surgical assistance,
                    gratuitously afforded to the sister, Mrs. Newton, once in a complaint of the
                    breast, once in curing a whitlow on her finger.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When Chatterton was more particularly the object of public
                    curiosity, a clergyman called upon his sister, presented her half a guinea, and
                    requested to see what ever letters of her brother she had preserved. She
                    produced them. He then begged permission to take them away <hi rend="ital">for
                        one hour</hi>, assigning as a reason, that it would be too painful to his
                    feelings to read them in the presence of that sister, to whom they were
                    addressed. On the same pretext he procured the letters in Mrs. Chatterton&#8217;s<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sarah Chatterton, n&#233;e Young (1731&#8211;1796),
                        Thomas Chatterton&#8217;s mother.</note> possession, who lived separately from her
                    daughter; these also, he <hi rend="ital">promised to return in an hour</hi>, and
                    the present of a guinea, and the language of consolatory friendship prevented
                    all suspicion; indeed, so consolatory and so full of religion was his language
                    to the mother, that she said she almost looked upon him as a guardian angel.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A fortnight elapsed, the letters had not been returned, and they
                    knew not the name of the person to whom they had entrusted them. At the end of
                    the fortnight Mrs. Chatterton received a letter from that person, <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. H&#8212;&#8212; C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph
                            Cottle</ref> both disapproved of Croft&#8217;s exploitation of manuscripts
                        obtained from members of Thomas Chatterton&#8217;s (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>)
                        family.</note> &#8220;Be not alarmed, Mrs. Chatterton,&#8221; he said, &#8220;all the little
                    treasures shall be faithfully returned to you again;&#8221; with the originals he
                    promised to send transcripts of all the letters, with which the curiosity of
                    strangers might be gratified, while the hand writing of Chatterton should be
                    preserved. He again consoled Mrs. Chatterton for the fate of her son. &#8220;Perhaps,&#8221;
                    said he, &#8220;he now beholds with pleasure the deserved progress his reputation is
                    making every day, and the friends and the assistances which his name brings to
                    you and to his sister:&#8221; the date of the letter was Lincoln&#8217;s Inn, July 27th
                    1778.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In a second letter, August 24th 1778, <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref> requested the sister to
                    write to him, whatever she and her mother could recollect, concerning
                    Chatterton. &#8220;Believe me you are writing to one who respects his memory, and
                    wishes you both well;&#8221; the promise of returning the letters and magazines
                    containing Chatterton&#8217;s pieces, which he had borrowed at the same time, were
                    repeated; and in the course of the Autumn they were accordingly returned.
                    Nothing more was heard till, in the following July, to the astonishment of the
                    family, <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref> published the
                    letters, and the information he had obtained from Mrs. Newton, in his Love and
                        Madness.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Croft, <title>Love
                            and Madness</title> (1780).</note> The mother wrote to him, and
                    upbraided him for duplicity; he replied, by sending ten pounds, to be divided
                    between her and her daughter; again professing friendship for them, and saying,
                    &#8220;Be assured the family of Thomas Chatterton shall never be forgotten by <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">H&#8212;&#8212; C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Four months afterwards he again wrote to justify himself, and
                    used these expressions, &#8220;What has been done was with a view to pave the way for
                    services to your family; and I hope, sooner than you think, to be of more
                    service to you than any person who has hitherto enquired about your son, for I
                    have a true regard for his memory.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In November 1780, he wrote a fifth letter, desiring Mrs. Newton
                    would send him a particular account of her circumstances, as he was about to
                    promote a public subscription for her; and in April 1781, they received a note
                    from him, requiring an acknowledgement of the ten pounds.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref> dropt
                    his correspondence with the family; they heard no more of the <hi rend="ital">future services</hi> and the <hi rend="ital">public subscription</hi>. His
                    Love and Madness had a great and rapid sale, undoubtedly in a considerable
                    degree owing to the letters of Chatterton; and his purpose was served. Luckily
                    Mrs. Newton preserved his letters. In 1796, she was advised, by a gentleman to
                    whom she had shewn them,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph Cottle</ref>.</note> to write
                    to <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>; the following is a copy
                    of her letter.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> Sir,</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The name of Chatterton is, perhaps, yet familiar to your memory.
                    She, to whom he was endeared by the tender ties of nature, and who,
                    contemplating his many virtues, would remember his errors no more, begs leave to
                    address you with reference to your professions of attachment to the remainder of
                    his family. Several years have now elapsed since you obtained of me his
                    unpublished papers, and communicated them to the world. The disquietude I might
                    have felt at such a transaction, was removed by an apprehension, that while you
                    interested yourself, you would render considerable assistance to me. The
                    popularity of the concern was an adequate ground for my expectations, which were
                    heightened by the respectability of your connections in life. Justice to my
                    situation would long since have compelled me to address you, but have been, till
                    a few days past, unacquainted with your residence. If any thing in my favour be
                    practicable, to which I trust you will not be indisposed, your early attention
                    will greatly oblige,</p>
        <p rend="indent2"> Sir,</p>
        <p rend="indent3"> Your obedient humble servant</p>
        <p rend="indent6"> Mary Newton.</p>
        <p>
          <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">H&#8212;&#8212; C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>, <hi rend="ital">Esq.
                        Portman Square,</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <hi rend="ital">	London, June</hi>
            </placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1796-06-19">19<hi rend="ital">th</hi> 1796.</date>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>As no answer was returned, a second letter was addressed to <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>.</p>
        <lb />
        <p>Reverend Sir,</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A former letter of mine, addressed to you under the appellation
                    of <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">H&#8212;&#8212; C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>, Esq. may probably have
                    reached your hands; the same motive which urged me to engage in that, induces me
                    to trouble you with this, and I again solicit your attention to the remainder of
                    the family of Chatterton. Justice to myself, as I before observed, was the
                    reason of my forming the application, on which I had the satisfactory judgment
                    of some very respectable friends. As the subject of obtaining my brother&#8217;s
                    papers, has of late been particularly investigated here, I trust you will not
                    suffer an occasion for public censure, in a matter where my feelings are
                    considerably interested. I am, Reverend Sir,</p>
        <p rend="indent4"> Your obedient humble servant,</p>
        <p rend="indent6"> Mary Newton</p>
        <p>
          <date when="1796-08-04">
            <hi rend="ital">August</hi> 4, 1796.</date>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>&#8217;s answer, was as
                    follows.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> Mrs. Newton&#8217;s letter of August 4, is sent to me here; she is
                    either ill-advised, or she has not told her advisers the money which I gave her,
                    when I had the copies of the letters, and <hi rend="ital">afterwards</hi>. The
                    sort of <hi rend="ital">threatening</hi> letter which Mrs. Newton&#8217;s is, will
                    never succeed with me: but if the clergyman of the parish will do me the favour
                    to write me word, through Mrs. Newton, what Chatterton&#8217;s relations consist of,
                    and what characters they bear, I will <hi rend="ital">try</hi>, by every thing
                    in my power, to serve them; yet certainly not, if any of them pretend to have
                    the smallest <hi rend="ital">claim</hi> on me.</p>
        <p rend="right">
          <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">H&#8212;&#8212; C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>
        </p>
        <p>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <hi rend="ital">Exmouth, Devon,</hi>
            </placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1796-09-01">
            <hi rend="ital">September</hi> 1, 1796.</date>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1"> The money <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>
                    alludes to, is the guinea given to Mrs. Chatterton and the half guinea to her
                    daughter, when he <hi rend="ital">borrowed the letters for an hour</hi>, and the
                    ten pounds sent after he had published them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref> has been privately
                    addressed upon the subject, without effect; his conduct is now made public, in
                    the hope that general liberality may be excited by general indignation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The mother of Chatterton died in poverty; she suffered three
                    years with a cancer, and till her death, experienced the kindness of the Miss
                    Mores. Mrs Newton supports herself by teaching children to read; she is now
                    advancing in years, and her sight begins to fail. She is a widow with one
                    daughter. It is hoped that the profits of the proposed publication will render
                    her old age comfortable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The edition will comprize whatever Chatterton left. Miscellanies,
                    the pieces attributed to Rowley, and the letters published by <ref target="people.html#CroftHerbert">Mr. C&#8212;&#8212;</ref>; some unpublished poems have
                    been procured, and some magazine pieces which had escaped the collector of the
                    Miscellanies. Dr. Gregory<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">George Gregory
                        (1754&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman and author of a <title>Life of
                            Chatterton</title> (1789).</note> has promised to adapt the life of this
                    extraordinary young man to the work; it will make two octavo volumes. The price
                    sixteen shillings, the money to be paid on delivery. Mr. Kearsley<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The London bookseller and publisher George
                        Kearsley II (fl. 1790s&#8211;1810s).</note> receives subscriptions. The edition
                    will be under my direction, and every care shall be taken to render it correct
                    and complete.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="right">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <hi rend="ital">Bristol, </hi>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1799-10">
              <hi rend="ital"> October</hi>, 1799.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>