<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce457</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.448</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.448" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="448" type="letter">
        <head>448. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1799-10-20">20 October 1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ <del rend="strikethrough">Richmond Green/Surry</del>/ N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 4 Tavistock Street/ Bedford Square/ London
                        Single<lb />Stamped: CHRIST/CHURCH<lb />Postmarks: F./ OCT 21/ 99; 9 OCLOCK/
                        OC. 21/ 99 NIGHT; Unpaid Penny Post<lb />Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                        45. 1799/ Robert Southey/ No place 20 Oct:/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 21
                            d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>/ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: 13 March<lb />MS:
                        Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder
                        14<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1799-10-20">Sunday. Oct. 20. 99.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have acknowledged the receipt of the bill yesterday had
                    there been any post to London. there was no inconvenience whatever in our not
                    receiving it sooner.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In about ten days our future habitation will be made habitable.
                    the former tenant has quitted &#8211; &amp; the carpenter &amp; the mason &amp; the
                    whitewashes &amp; the painter are busy in repairing the dilapidations of many
                    years. two beggarly cottages will soon be revolutionized into a decent dwelling.
                    these necessary alterations are not at our expences &#8211; the little improvement
                    which savour of luxury we set about ourselves as soon as we get in, such as
                    papering &amp; filling up an ugly corner with a convenient cupboard. the house
                    will be small, but large enough to be comfortable &amp; to have a spare bed
                    room, a sine qua non with me. the garden is a large piece of ground, &amp; quite
                    empty, so that I may please myself in filling it, &amp; have already in my head
                    allotted out its various divisions of potatoes, peas, cabbages, artichokes,
                    currant &amp; gooseberry bushes, &amp; the near turf plat where a few larger
                    fruit trees may be ornamentally planted &#8211; planting is a trifling expence, &amp;
                    I shall at least have the pleasure of seeing the trees grow &#8211; tho perhaps the
                    changes of life may prevent me from enjoying any other advantage. a spring rises
                    close by the garden &amp; fills a fishpond at the bottom. I mean to take much of
                    my due exercise in the useful employment of gardening, which will be putting out
                    time upon good interest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I mentioned to you if I recollect aright some time ago, that we
                    were uneasy respecting a <ref target="people.html#FrickerGeorge">brother of
                        Edith</ref>, who went to sea &amp; had not been heard of. after being driven
                    by storms into Spain &amp; walking thro that country into Portugal he is
                    returned. the boy is about fifteen, &amp; has been much neglected, but he is a
                    good boy, &amp; thoroughly sick of the sea life <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> which I believe he originally adopted rather from want of any
                    better employ than from inclination. As soon as we are settled I mean to send
                    for him, &amp; do what I can in the way of informing him, by setting about this
                    properly I can save time which is the most important thing. my after views are
                    to make a printer of him. because it is a business which he may exercise without
                    a long apprenticeship &#8211; &lt;which&gt; requires perhaps a smaller capital than
                    any other, &amp; because whenever he shall be able to exercise it I can at once
                    put into his hands three fourths of <del rend="strikethrough">that</del>
                    employment necessary for his support.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made some progress in my metrical Romance, Thalaba the
                    Destroyer. a poem from which I expect credit &amp; emolument. it will give me
                    pleasure to read it to you when you visit <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>. the extent will be ten books, of which the fourth is nearly
                    finished. it will probably be ready for publication in the spring. The second
                        Anthology<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (1800).</note> soon goes to press &#8211; this is a work
                    which chiefly interests me as it is connected with many friends &#8211; a <del rend="strikethrough">sort of</del> memorial of those who are distant. These
                    then are my employments, I wish I could give you as good an account of my health
                    &#8211; but that certainly does not improve.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My opinions upon all important subjects have long since ceased to
                    fluctuate. I repose upon Christianity, aware of the arguments against it, &amp;
                    flinging like JJ Rousseau, the weight of hope into the scale of reason.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Jacques Rousseau (1712&#8211;1778), &#8216;Letter
                        to Voltaire&#8217;, 18 August 1756.</note> there is a preponderance of argument in
                    its favour certainly, yet I perceive my own belief more the effect of volition
                    than conviction; my reason might possibly be biased from it, but my affections
                    could not. it is adapted to my wants &amp; to my wishes, it is a matter of
                    feeling with me. &#8211; is not this faith in its true meaning? &#8211; the mysteries
                    attached to the orthodox creed shock my reason &amp; disgust me. to define the
                    Deity, is to increase Atheism. the Athanasian &amp; Nicene creeds<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Statements of Christian orthodoxy from the 4th
                        or 5th centuries.</note> make me imagine Atheism comparitively wise &amp;
                    pious &#8211; but I walk abroad &amp; see the Deity in all things &#8211; I close my eyes
                    &amp; I feel his presence. surely this is faith.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So far you will readily comprehend me &#8211; but you will not perhaps
                    understand how my political opinions are founded upon feelings precisely the
                    same. I examine the extremes of society &amp; know that they are not fitted to
                    the nature of man &#8211; that both extremes necessarily deprave him. I am &lt;too&gt;
                    metaphysical <del rend="strikethrough">enough</del> &lt;not&gt; to know that our
                    characters are for the most part the effect of surrounding circumstances, &amp;
                    I am too pious to believe that God can have made us naturally sinful, therefore
                    necessarily wretched. hence the love of equality which is rooted in my heart
                    &amp; blended with all <del rend="strikethrough">xx xx</del> my associations. I
                    see evil produced by existing establishments &amp; know that it might be better
                    &amp; am with all the ardour &amp; sincerity of my soul a Republican. On all
                    points that <del rend="strikethrough">may</del> can come into action there is
                    little difference between us. with most of my friends I agree in some essential
                    point, scarcely with any in all.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yrs with affection</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Keenan<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Keenan (fl. c. 1780&#8211;1819),
                            Irish portrait painter, then living in Exeter. Keenan painted two
                            portraits of Southey.</note> paints miniatures &#8211; &amp; very beautifully.
                        of the likeness I cannot judge having only seen the pictures. in his larger
                        portraits he is very succesful. have you seen a poem called Gebir?<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor,
                                <title>Gebir</title> (1798), although the poem was published
                            anonymously.</note> it appears to me the miraculous work of a Madman.
                        the fine parts in it are like flashes of lightning at midnight &#8211; a picture
                        of which the greater part is indistinguishably dark, but all that you can
                        distinguish &#8211; the unsurpassable strokes of Rafael or Buonarotti.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Raphael Sanzio (1483&#8211;1520) and Michelangelo
                            di Lodovico Buonarotti Simoni (1475&#8211;1564), both Italian renaissance
                            painters.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>