<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce888</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.partTwoIntro</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
                        manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
                        teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
                        author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
                        Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
                        Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
                            permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
                            ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
                        It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
                        basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
                        Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
                        of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>Lynda Pratt</author>
            <title>Part II, Indroduction</title>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <author>
              <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
            </author>
            <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
              <pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
                        length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
                        in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
                        decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
                        2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef target="#g5 #g21" scheme="#genre" />
        <catRef target="./people.html" scheme="#people" />
        <catRef target="./places.html" scheme="#places" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change n="7" when="2011-08-15" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="6" when="2011-07-06" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="5" when="2011-03-20" who="#AB">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="4" when="2011-02-21" who="#AB">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="3" when="2010-08-15" who="#AB">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="2" when="2010-07-22" who="#LM">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change n="1" when="2010-06-27" who="#AB">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="PartTwoIntro">
        <head>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Two</head>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Introduction</hi> by Ian Packer and Lynda Pratt<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Part Two</title> is dedicated to our
                        parents, May and John Packer, June Osborn and Colin Pratt, in loving
                        memory.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <title>Part Two</title> is the first-ever collected edition of the
                    surviving letters written by Southey between 1798 and 1803. The letters
                    published here begin with Southey writing to the <title>Monthly Magazine</title>
                    in January 1798 about Spanish and Portuguese poetry, a subject of lifelong
                    interest; and end on New Year&#8217;s Eve 1803 with him anticipating a return to
                        <title>Madoc</title>, his intended transatlantic poetic magnum opus.
                        <title>Part Two</title> follows the editorial conventions described in About
                    this Edition and publishes newly transcribed, fully annotated texts, bringing
                    together in one place correspondence scattered between 37 archives in North
                    America and the United Kingdom. It comprises 596 letters, of which 199 are
                    published for the first time, and 107 are published in full for the first time.
                    In addition, 5 letters that appeared pseudonymously in the <title>Monthly
                        Magazine</title> are here newly attributed to Southey.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The letters in <title>Part Two</title> were sent to some 40 very
                    diverse individuals: including friends from childhood and school (Charles
                    Danvers, Grosvenor Bedford and Charles Wynn), from university (Nicholas
                    Lightfoot), from radical youth (Samuel Taylor Coleridge and George Dyer) and
                    from professional life (Joseph Cottle and Daniel Stuart). The years 1798-1803
                    saw the emergence of important new Southeyan relationships and correspondences,
                    notably with the statistician John Rickman, the translator William Taylor, the
                    scientist and poet Humphry Davy, and the writer Mary Barker. Whilst some of
                    Southey&#8217;s epistolary interactions, notably those with Bedford, Cottle and Wynn,
                    were to be of lifelong duration, others in this period were the product of
                    temporary expediency. For example, a letter sent in 1798 to the Liverpudlian man
                    of letters and social campaigner William Roscoe in a vain attempt to track down
                    the maverick, poet William Gilbert (Letter 339); and one in 1803 to the
                    bibliographer and antiquary Joseph Haslewood on a matter connected to Southey
                    and Joseph Cottle&#8217;s three-volume edition of Chatterton (Letter 694). Although
                    nearly 600 letters survive, letter-fragments and references within surviving
                    letters to ones now lost remind us of the fragile, selective nature of what has
                    come down to us. It is clear from this edition, that some important
                    correspondences now exist only in part, notably with Coleridge, George Dyer,
                    Stuart and Cottle.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The six years covered by <title>Part Two</title> were a turbulent
                    and crucial time for Southey. They are also a period of his career that has been
                    relatively neglected, when he was neither the incendiary radical of his youth or
                    the combustible Tory of his middle and old age. In 1798 Southey was a restless
                    creature. Unsettled personally and professionally, he moved between a series of
                    rented houses in the South West of England and London, and was torn between the
                    conflicting options of a legal or a literary career. By the end of 1803 his life
                    was beginning to assume, outwardly at least, a more settled appearance. He had
                    opted decisively for a literary career and in September of that year taken up
                    residence at Greta Hall, Keswick. His relocation, reluctant and temporary at
                    first, proved permanent and additionally set him on the road to being a &#8216;Lake&#8217;
                    poet, a label Southey loathed. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The letters published here allow for a more accurate, detailed,
                    and nuanced mapping of Southey&#8217;s life, works and interactions with and impact
                    upon his contemporaries during these years than has previously been possible.
                    The events they encompass include his reconciliation with Coleridge in 1799; his
                    public and private responses to <title>Lyrical Ballads</title> (1798); his
                    reaction to the rise of Napoleon and the continuing conflict between Britain and
                    revolutionary France; his second and final visit to Portugal in 1800-1801, and
                    the resultant hardening of his anti-Catholicism; his unhappy stint as a
                    secretary to the Irish Chancellor Isaac Corry in 1801-1802; his reaction to the
                    execution of the United Irishman Robert Emmett in 1803; and his emotional
                    bludgeoning by the deaths in relentless succession between 1801-1803 of three
                    Margarets, his cousin, mother and first child. His correspondence also records
                    the increasing emergence of Southey as a literary professional. Between 1798 and
                    1803, he wrote for the <title>Morning Post</title>, <title>Critical
                        Review</title>, and <title>Monthly Magazine</title>. His major book
                    publications included the annotated Islamic romance <title>Thalaba the
                        Destroyer</title> (1801), a new volume of <title>Poems</title> (1799), two
                    volumes of the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799 and 1800), and revised
                    versions of his 1797 verse collection, <title>Joan of Arc</title> and
                        <title>Letters Written During a Short Residence in Spain and
                        Portugal</title>. He edited the works of his fellow Bristolian Thomas
                    Chatterton and translated the romance <title>Amadis of Gaul</title>. In
                    addition, he completed a fifteen-book version of the revisionist transatlantic
                    epic <title>Madoc</title>, produced early drafts of what became <title>The Curse
                        of Kehama</title>, and embarked on a planned prose magnum opus, a &#8216;History
                    of Portugal&#8217;. This rather terrifying list does not include projected but
                    unexecuted projects such as an epic on the flood, a literary history of
                    Portugal, a hexametrical epic on Mohammed (to be co-written with Coleridge) and
                    numerous shorter poems sketched out in his correspondence and in his
                        <title>Common-Place Books</title>. The letters published in <title>Part
                        Two</title> provide crucial new information about all these projects,
                    including early drafts of <title>Thalaba</title>, <title>Madoc</title>, gothic
                    ballads, revisionist &#8216;English Eclogues&#8217; and numerous other shorter poems. In so
                    doing <title>Part Two</title> supplies fresh evidence for how Southey the
                    &#8216;entire man of letters&#8217; and one of the most prolific authors of his age came
                    into being.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We hope that by making annotated, scholarly texts of the letters
                    from 1798-1803 available for the first time, this edition will contribute to a
                    richer, more complex, understanding of this crucial period for Southey and for
                    British Romanticism as a whole.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>