<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce877</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.868</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken
                        from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850).  Previously  published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 237-239 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="868" type="letter">
        <head>868. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Richard
                        Duppa</ref> [fragment], <date when="1803-12-14">14 December 1803</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS untraced; text is taken
                        from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850)<lb />Previously published:
                        Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 237-239 [in
                        part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref target="places.html#GretaHall">Greta Hall</ref>, Keswick,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1803-12-14">Dec. 14. 1803.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Duppa,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not had the heart to write to you, though the long silence
                    has lain like a load upon my conscience. When we parted I had as much present
                    happiness as man could wish, and was full of all cheerful hopes: however, no
                    man, if he be good for any thing, but is the better for suffering. It has long
                    been my habit to look for the good that is to be found in every thing, and that
                    alchemy is worth more than the grand secret of all the adepts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had almost completed my arrangements for removing to Richmond
                    at Christmas, and here we are at the uttermost end of the north, and here for
                    some time we shall probably remain; how long, God knows. I am steady in my
                    pursuits, for they depend upon myself; but my plans and fortunes, being of the
                        <hi rend="ital">&#964;&#940; &#959;&#973;&#954; &#941;&#966;
                        &#942;&#956;&#943;&#965;</hi>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;What
                        is not in my power&#8217;.</note> are more mutable; they are fairly afloat, and
                    the winds are more powerful than the steersman. <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> caught the alarm &#8211; the
                        Bonaparte<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                        (1769-1821, First Consul 1799-1804, Emperor of the French 1804-1814).</note>
                    ague or English influenza &#8211; after I left town, and sent to me to postpone my
                        Bibliotheca,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s plan for a
                        &#8216;Bibliotheca Britannica&#8217;, a chronological history of all
                        literature published in Britain.</note> at the very time when I wished the
                    engagement off my mind, not being in a state of mind to contemplate it with
                    courage. He shall now wait my convenience, and I shall probably finish off my
                    own works of choice here, where, living cheaper, I have more leisure. My
                        History<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished &#8216;History
                        of Portugal&#8217;.</note> is in a state of rapid progression. The last time I saw
                    Mr. &#8212;&#8212; in town he gave me a draft for fifty pounds as his subscription, he said,
                    to this work. I tell you this because you know him, and, therefore, not to tell
                    you would make me feel ungrateful for an act of uncommon liberality, done in the
                    handsomest way possible. I little thought, at the time, how soon an unhappy
                    circumstance would render the sum needful. This work I am alternating and
                    relieving by putting Madoc<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
                        completed a version of <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799 and was revising it
                        for publication. It did not appear until 1805.</note> to the press, and my
                    annual job of reviewing interrupts both for awhile; but, happily, this job
                    comes, like Christmas, but once a year, and I have almost killed off my
                    contemporaries. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Haslitt</ref>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hazlitt, writer and artist, had visited the Lake
                        District in 1803. After an encounter with a local girl, whom he reputedly
                        spanked, his stay came to an abrupt and highly controversial end.</note>
                    whom you saw at Paris, has been here; a man of real genius. He has made a very
                    fine picture of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
                    for <ref target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref>,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir George Beaumont, art patron and
                        painter, had commissioned portraits of Coleridge, Hartley Coleridge and
                        William Wordsworth from Hazlitt.</note> which is said to be in
                        Titian&#8217;s<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Tiziano Vecelli (c.
                        1473/1490-1576), Italian painter.</note> manner; he has also painted <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, but so dismally,
                    though <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref> face
                    is his idea of physiognomical perfection, that one of his friends, on seeing it,
                    exclaimed, &#8216;At the gallows &#8211; deeply affected by his deserved fate &#8211; yet
                    determined to die like a man;&#8217; and if you saw the picture, you would admire the
                    criticism. We have a neighbour here who also knows you &#8211; Wilkinson,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Wilkinson (1764-1831), Canon of Carlisle
                        Cathedral and producer of <title>Select Views in Cumberland, Westmoreland
                            and Lancashire</title> (1810). In late 1803 he was living at
                        Ormathwaite, near Keswick.</note> a clergyman, who draws, if not with much
                    genius, with great industry and most useful fidelity. I have learnt a good deal
                    by examining his collection of etchings.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Holcroft,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Holcroft
                        (1745-1809; <title>DNB</title>), radical, dramatist and novelist.</note> I
                    hear, has discovered, to his own exceeding delight, prophetic portraits of
                    himself and <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>
                    among the damned in your Michael Angelo.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Duppa, <title>A Selection of Twelve Heads from the Last Judgement
                            of Michael Angelo</title> (1801).</note> I have found out a more
                    flattering antetype of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge&#8217;s</ref> face in Duns Scotus.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John Duns Scotus (c. 1265-1308; <title>DNB</title>),
                        Franciscan friar and theologian. Coleridge had been studying his
                        works.</note> Come you yourself and judge of the resemblances. <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> and our lakes and
                    mountains are worth a longer journey. Autumn is the best season to see the
                    country, but spring, and even winter, is better than summer, for in settled fine
                    weather there are none of those goings on in heaven which at other times give
                    these scenes such an endless variety.
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; You will find this
                    house a good station for viewing the lakes; it is, in fact, situated on perhaps
                    the very finest single spot in the whole lake country, and we can show you
                    things which the tourists never hear of. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">. &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> desires to be remembered to
                    you; she is but in indifferent health. I myself am as well as I ever was. The
                    weather has been, and is, very severe, but it has not as yet hurt me; however,
                    it must be owned the white bears have the advantage of us in England, and still
                    more the dormice. If their torpor could be introduced into the human system, it
                    would be a most rare invention. I should roll myself up at the end of October,
                    and give orders to be waked by the chimney-sweeper on May-day.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R. Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>