<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce594</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.585</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary
                        Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard,
                        1967), pp. 5-8.  Previously  published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I,
                        pp. 176&#8211;180 [dated Lisbon 1801 and 21 October
                        1801].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.585" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="585" type="letter">
        <head>585. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>, <date when="1801-06-15">[mid-June-]21 October 1801</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway
                        Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of Robert Southey to Mary
                        Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard,
                        1967), pp. 5-8<lb />Previously published: John Wood
                        Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of
                            Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I,
                        pp. 176&#8211;180 [dated Lisbon 1801 and 21 October
                        1801].</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> What shall I say &#8211; what will you say &#8211; of my
                    long &amp; abominable silence? &#8211; Will two long journies<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey made two long
                        excursions from Lisbon in March and April 1801, visiting
                        central and southern Portugal; see Adolfo Cabral,
                            <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in
                            Portugal 1800-1801 and a Visit to France
                            1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 15-61.</note> &#8211;
                    much sight-seeing abroad &amp; a room full of folios at home
                    help me out in my defence? &#8211; Or is it not better to plead
                    guilty &amp; throw myself on your mercy? &#8211; At last I am
                    writing, &amp; it is of the greatest consequence to me that
                    the letter should reach England safely &#8211; because I am going
                    in the packet with it. We have been three weeks in a state
                    of wash-&amp;-wear preparation &amp; expectation &amp;
                    disappointment. day after day fixed &amp; our departure day
                    after day delayed by state affairs.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The brief war between Spain and Portugal,
                        known as &#8216;the War of the Oranges&#8217;. The only fighting was
                        between 20 May and 6 June 1801 in the Portuguese
                        province of Alentejo.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of the campaign in Portugal you can have
                    formed but very imperfect ideas. No General ever brought an
                    enemy so soon to terms as the Duke de Lafoes<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Joao Carlos de Braganca e
                        Ligne de Sousa Tavares Mascarenhas de Silva, Duke of
                        Lafoes (1719-1806), Secretary of State (prime minister)
                        6 January&#8211;21 May 1801, and commander of the Portuguese
                        army sent to resist the Spanish invasion.</note> has
                    done. The campaign lasted nineteen days. The Duke set out
                    from Lisbon when the Spaniards were at <hi rend="ital">his</hi> headquarters. The army had neither food nor
                    ammunition. He indeed sent carriers to bring him water from
                    the Fonte da Praia here for his own drinking &#8211; &amp; this
                    was the only instance of any supplies being sent. When
                    tidings were brought him of the Enemys movements he clapped
                    his hands to his head &#8211; O my God what can Luiz Pinto<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis Pinto de Sousa
                        Coutinho, Viscount of Balsemao (1735-1804), Portuguese
                        Secretary of State (prime minister) 1788-1801. He was
                        dismissed on 6 January 1801, but remained in the
                        ministry as Foreign Secretary until 21 May 1801 and
                        returned as Secretary of State in 1803. He was the chief
                        negotiator with Spain in 1801.</note> be about! &#8211; Luiz
                    Pinto was signing &amp; sealing at Badajoz<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Portugal and Spain ended
                        their brief conflict with the Treaty of Badajoz, signed
                        on 6 June 1801. Portugal agreed to close its ports to
                        British ships, pay Spain&#8217;s costs incurred in the war and
                        cede the border town of Olivenca to Spain.</note> what
                    terms France &amp; Spain in their mercy might grant &#8211; What
                    those terms are we do not yet know &#8211; The murder is daily
                    expected to come out &#8211; &amp; the packet is waiting for this
                    state secret &#8211; to the very great annoyance of a poor
                    Passenger who does not care one button about the business of
                    the state, &amp; has business of his own in England. &#8211; But
                    you must not imagine that while the seat of war was only
                    fourscore miles from Lisbon, no preparations were made in
                    the Capital. true it is nobody knew what was going on in the
                    armies. We were as ignorant here as you could be in England
                    &#8211; but the Portuguese made ready for the worst &amp; called
                    upon their neverfailing allies &#8211; the whole army of Saints &#8211;
                    The theatres were shut &#8211; processions made &amp; Ladies of
                    rank followed Nosso Senhor<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A statue representing Jesus as Our Lord
                        of the Sufferings.</note> bare footed thro the streets.
                    He was placed in the Cathedral by the High Altar with
                    candles &amp; soldiers round him, &amp; then for days did
                    the Devout kiss his heel, after touching it with each eye.
                    He was to save the country, &amp; as he did not make his
                    appearance till it was well known what was doing at Badajoz
                    &#8211; the infallible Image retains his credit, &amp; is the
                    Author of the Peace.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When the wise rulers of this country combined
                    with other wise rulers in this wise war, they said they were
                    going to be Pall-bearers at the funeral of France. they
                    digged a pit &#8211; you know the text,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Psalms</title> 57: 6, &#8216;they have
                        digged a pit before me, into the midst whereof they are
                        fallen themselves&#8217;.</note> &amp; here is the comment.
                    ridiculous as this burlesque war has been still its
                    consequences will be serious to Portugal. her commerce will
                    be clipped &#8211; &amp; as the armies have trampled down the
                    corn-country &#8211; the want of provisions in those inland parts
                    where it cannot be conveyed will be dreadful. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And there I left off &#8211; &amp; we embarked &#8211;
                    &amp; here I am in the Bay of Biscay as deplorable an object
                    as you can picture. Surely old Beelzebub must have a large
                    navy manned by sea-sick souls &#8211; it were a braver punishment
                    than any that ever Dante<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Dante Alighieri (1265-1321), whose
                            <title>Divine Comedy</title> (1308-1321) described
                        the sufferings of the damned in Hell.</note> dreamt. its
                    degrees &amp; varieties of torture would be infinite, &amp;
                    the wicked might purify slighter crimes by a short cruise in
                    the Flying Dutchman<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In legend a ghost ship that is doomed to sail the seas
                        for eternity.</note> &#8211; or be frozen up in the North Seas
                    in the Royal Satan. &#8211; I am vexed to see by your letter that
                        <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref> sent
                    you the <hi rend="ital">quarto</hi> edition of Joan of
                        Arc;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Joan
                            of Arc</title> (1796), rather than the second
                        edition of 1798.</note> which is as inferior to the
                    later copy &#8211; as a distance of two years ought to make it. at
                    the best it is faulty enough. but it was my intention that
                    you should have the best. The Vision<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The ninth book of
                            <title>Joan of Arc</title> (Bristol and London,
                        1796), pp. 308-363, described the eponymous heroine&#8217;s
                        vision of the future. It was omitted from <title>Joan of
                            Arc</title> (1798) and reworked as &#8216;The Vision of
                        the Maid of Orleans&#8217; in <title>Poems</title>, 2 vols
                        (Bristol, 1799), II, pp. [1]-69.</note> is very bad as
                    to its <hi rend="ital">composition</hi>, to use a painters
                    phrase, tho well painted &amp; in colors that will not fade.
                    in dramatic or epic writing all visions are faulty. if they
                    anticipate they do harm &#8211; if not &#8211; to what purpose are they
                    there? the one in question in about one thousand lines does
                    not carry on the action of the poem one minute, &amp; it
                    might have been extended to any length. I cannot think a
                    mole would improve a womans face tho it had the colors of
                    the rainbow or the peacocks tail. You have perhaps by this
                    time seen Thalaba, who must now be about a month old;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the
                            Destroyer</title> was published in June 1801.</note>
                    my next poetical employment it would be difficult to decide,
                    as half a dozen unborn subjects are battling who shall enter
                    the world first, &amp; all of them are secondary objects to
                    my great labour, the History of Portugal, on which I have
                    expended much time &amp; much money. this will be the work
                    of years.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s life work, the &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;,
                        was never completed.</note>
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
          <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Dublin">Dublin</ref>.</placeName>
          </address>
          <date when="1801-10-21">21. October 1801</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> is the half written sheet which has
                    been lying in my desk, &amp; travelling in my pocket book
                    now nearly six months. I send it &#8211; to help my last in
                    pleading pardon &#8211; &amp; because it contains some Portugueze
                    anecdotes. there is room enough in the sheet for memoirs of
                    myself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I came here in consequence of an invitation
                    from <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Mr. Corry</ref>,
                    to be his private Secretary. a good situation, &amp;
                    promising future fortune. I have been here just a week,
                    &amp; daily expect to return to England, &#8211; My way must be
                    straight to <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
                    for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>,
                    &amp; thence to London. I hope &amp; believe you will write
                    me &#8211; something that shall be like a good natured look &amp;
                    a friendly shake by the hand. direct it <ref target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &#8211; Cumberland.
                    &#8211; &amp; let me find it on my arrival.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Give me an introduction to Charlotte
                        Smith<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte
                        Turner Smith (1749-1806; <title>DNB</title>), poet and
                        novelist; author, among many other works, of
                            <title>Celestina</title> (1791) and <title>The Old
                            Manor House</title> (1793).</note> &#8211; that is &#8211; send
                    me her address &amp; tell her I will call: I wish to see her
                    for she is a favourite novelist with me, far above more
                    popular names &#8211; &amp; also by a very odd association the
                    cause of my present situation. &#8211; I took in when a boy a
                    periodical work with prints of ruins. there was a view of
                    the ruins at Christ Church in Hampshire. those said ruins
                    are introduced either in Celestina of the Old Manor
                        House<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The ruins
                        at Christchurch are described in Charlotte Smith,
                            <title>The Old Manor House</title>, 4 vols (London,
                        1793), IV, pp. 202-205.</note> &#8211; I think in the latter.
                    one summer<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                        lived at <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>,
                        near Christchurch, in June-September 1797 and again in
                        October-December 1799.</note> I went to the sea, &amp;
                    for no earthly reason else but the remembrance of that print
                    &amp; that novel &#8211; chose Christ Church for my abode. &amp;
                    there made a friendship with <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">the man</ref> who
                    accompanied Mr. Abbot<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John Rickman was private secretary to
                        Charles Abbot, Lord Colchester (1757&#8211;1829;
                            <title>DNB</title>), who was the Chief Secretary for
                        Ireland from July 1801 to January 1802, and then The
                        Speaker 1802-1817.</note> as Private Secretary here,
                    &amp; has been the means of employing me in the same
                    capacity to the Chancellor of the Exchequer.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref target="people.html#CorryIsaac">Isaac
                        Corry</ref>.</note> &#8211; All this is foolish prattle &#8211; but
                    it is odd &amp; strictly true.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> So God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>