<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce428</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.419</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47888.  Previously  published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 74&#8211;76.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="419" type="letter">
        <head>419. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith
                        Southey</ref>, <date when="1799-06-30">30 June 1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/
                        at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottles/ Wine Street/ Bristol/ Single<lb />Stamped:
                        RINGWOOD<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47888<lb />Previously published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 74&#8211;76.</note>
        </head>
        <p>Sunday. <address>
            <placeName>
              <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref>
            </placeName>
          </address>:
                        <date when="1799-06-30">June 30. 99</date>
        </p>
        <p>My dear Edith</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am fearful that the Post Boy will pass before I can fill the
                    sheet &#8211; therefore it will be advisable to begin at the wrong end &amp; tell you
                    what you will be most anxious to know. the inside of the house I have not yet
                    seen but on the ground floor there are three rooms, one of which is the kitchen.
                    into this the street door opens. they are boarded. there is also a back kitchen.
                    the sitting rooms are in front (plague on the builders &#8211; the back-kitchen
                    behind. when I go over the houses I shall see how improveable they are. We are
                    not likely to get possession before Michaelmas!!!<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">29 September 1799. Michaelmas was one of the traditional
                        quarter days when rents were paid and properties changed hands.</note> So
                        <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my Mother</ref> may send <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> off, &amp; you &amp; I will
                    take a journey. the garden is a good size, quite large enough to supply us with
                    vegetables, &amp; is said to be prime ground. there is a stable &amp; a pigeon
                    house, which we will stock, as the pigeons feed themselves. the house is as far
                    from the road as <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Biddlecombes</ref>. tho open to it &#8211; but there is a railing
                    about the premises which is to be placed there. <del rend="strikethrough">it</del> at the bottom of the garden is a fish-pond. all this you see is
                    sumptuous. <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">B.</ref> would have
                    bought it but they could not make out a clear title. he has taken it for 5
                    years. we hold of him. &amp; I shall arrange matters so that the goods may be
                    sent &amp; housed. soon. So much for this. now for my travels here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was too late for the Salisbury Coach.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">For Southey&#8217;s journal of this trip see <title>Common-Place
                            Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV,
                        pp. 517&#8211;518.</note> I mounted the Oxford Mail &amp; rode to the Globe at
                    Newton. thence I walkd about six miles crossing over to the Warminster &amp;
                    Frome Road. the Coach for which I was too late in the morning here <hi rend="ital">overtook</hi> me. I mounted it. eat some bread &amp; cheese at
                    an alehouse where they stopt, &amp; proceeded to Warminster. here it was to dine
                    &#8211; &amp; as I found it would not be at Salisbury <del rend="strikethrough">xxxx</del> before six, I thought it would be too late then to reach
                    Fordingbridge that night. so I altered my plan for the campaign. left the coach
                    at Warminster &amp; trudged away for Shaftsbury. read my poem about walking in
                    the heat &amp; learn how I felt.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;A
                        Midsummer Poem&#8217;, published anonymously in the <title>Morning Post</title>,
                        28 June 1799.</note> My way led me within sight of Beckfords magnificent
                        building.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Fonthill Abbey, the
                        creation of William Beckford (1760&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>).</note> at an
                    alehouse I got some cold meat &amp; strong beer. nothing but strong beer would
                    suit me. by seven o-clock I found myself at Shaftsbury 15 miles from Warminster
                    &#8211; after riding 20 miles &amp; walking 21. I looked about the town but did
                    nothing there. <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> it stands commandingly on an
                    eminence &#8211; I could even distinguish Glastonbury tho more than 30 miles from
                    it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At 6 I rose &amp; set out on foot for Blandford, 12 miles to
                    breakfast chiefly over the downs. I met crows in abundance, two weazels, &amp;
                    one humble bee on the way. who seemed to have as little chance of finding a
                    breakfast as myself, for the deuce a flower grew on the short scant turf. the
                    hill sides were in some places quite naked &#8211; washed bare by the rains &#8211; the
                    skeletons of <del rend="strikethrough">vegetation</del> earth. I had a fine
                    walk. &amp; the clouds canopied me with most cool comfort. after breakfast I
                    pushd on ten miles for Winborne again over downs. this was a tough pull. but
                    still the clouds shaded me &#8211; there I got pickled salmon, &amp; more strong beer.
                    then I proceeded tho somewhat faint &amp; wearily, 12 miles more to Christ
                    Church. I entered under S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Catherines Hill, &amp; found my
                    way over the marsh &amp; thro the fields behind our old habitation. here I met a
                    hospitable welcome. <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">B.</ref> is
                    well &amp; in as good spirits as ever. his mother is as well as ever &#8211; his cream
                    as good &amp; her tea as weak. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Corbyn<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; presumably an acquaintance of
                        Southey from his residence at Burton, July&#8211;September 1797.</note> is here to
                    dinner &amp; do not forget to tell <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my
                        Mother</ref> that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Coleman<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; presumably an acquaintance of Southey from his
                        residence at Burton, July&#8211;September 1797.</note> enquires for her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I purpose setting off tomorrow if <ref target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref> will let me. in
                    that case I hope to get home on Tuesday night, for my limbs are so supple &amp;
                    I feel so little fatigue as to depend upon my legs in case I miss the coach.
                    indeed I am better able to walk to day than when I left home. the morning has
                    been taken up in walking. the dinner now hurries me, &amp; I momently expect to
                    hear the horn.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From all I see I think the house will be very convenient &amp;
                    comfortable. we must stay at Bristol till our money comes, &amp; then go
                    somewhere, either to Wales or Devonshire. <del rend="strikethrough">my</del>
                    remember me to <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Danvers</ref>. God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>