<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce565</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.556</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D.  Previously  published: Adolfo Cabral (ed.), Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800–1801 and a Visit to France
                            1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp. 134–137.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="556" type="letter">
<head>556. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1800-10-30">30 October 1800</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ 5. Stone Buildings/ Lincolns Inn/
                        London<lb/>Stamped: [illegible]<lb/>Postmark: [partial] NO/ 2/ 1800
                        <lb/>Endorsement: Oct. 30/ 1800<lb/>MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                        4811D<lb/>Previously published: Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800–1801 and a Visit to France
                            1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 134–137.</note>
</head>
<opener>
<salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> I have a letter already written for you which will sail next week
                    with the parcel that contains Thalaba, but the state of my finances occasions me
                    to write before that Packet sails. I draw upon <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> thro his Uncle &amp; partner here.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Coppendale (d. 1833), a prominent English merchant in
                        Portugal.</note> will you make your draft payable to him. he is at Richmond
                    Green.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> In the Irish way I must refer you to the letter that you have not
                    received for an answer to your last; &amp; gallop thro this as fast as I can
                    lest the Post should leave me behind. – the Yellow Fever has not yet reached us
                    &amp; the hubbub of invasion has long subsided. Of the paper money I have before
                    detailed the evil consequences at present a new financial <del rend="strikethrough">operation</del> &lt;operation&gt; is about to be
                    adopted, not in opposition to system &amp; experience – but in sheer ignorance –
                    the copper is to be called in, recoined, &amp; issued at double its value – to
                    the great advantage of our Birmingham traders, who have already sent over a
                    brave cargo of bank notes. provisions are most enormously dear – <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> every one raising the price of his commodity
                    to repay the discount which he loses. <del rend="strikethrough">the poor
                        &amp;</del> the servants of government suffer the whole loss – &amp; the
                    poor pay the advance upon every thing with no increase of <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> wages adequate. the wisdom of thus defrauding
                    their army &amp; navy officers of a fifth part of their pay is too obvious to
                    need a comment. moreover they have reformed the army – that is taken away the
                    regiments from their Colonels – &amp; left the old officers who have grown grey
                    in the service with less than they had thirty years ago.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> You know the precarious state of Lisbon. the earthquake may
                    shatter it today. it may be only warned by its annual slight shocks. the state
                    stands upon as uncertain a foundation. the court is poor, &amp; blindly &amp;
                    beastily ignorant. provisions dearer than in any other part of Europe. the
                        Princes<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767–1826; King of
                        Portugal 1816–1826), Prince Regent 1799–1816.</note> character you know.
                    &amp; the people know. I saw him lately at Mafra following S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Francis &amp; his <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del>
                    flour-&amp;-water-Deity round the town, &amp; feasting &lt;a&gt; <del rend="strikethrough">the</del> set of beggarly friars – the most ignorant
                    &amp; blackguard of all the monastic orders &amp; thus he spends his time, &amp;
                    lies down at night with the idea that he has done his duty in the day. He has
                    had a monument made for the Prince of Waldeck<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Christian August von Waldeck (1744–1798), Marshal of the
                        Portuguese army 1797–1798. His monument finally found a place in the English
                        Cemetery in Lisbon.</note> who died here. a costly &amp; handsome piece of
                    sculpture which he wished to see when it was finished. But the German Princeling
                    was a Protestant – &amp; the Regent of Portugal would not enter a heretical
                    burying ground. the monument has therefore been put up for the present in one of
                    the convents that he may see it!</p>
<p rend="indent1"> But with all this court devotion a spirit of toleration exists
                    formerly unknown in Portugal. there is no doubt that he would think it a good
                    deed to burn a few Jews, &amp; that the mob would think it good fun. mobs are
                    never tolerant. Were you to roast a Socinian in England there would be a holyday
                    over the Kingdom &amp; all the church bells would ring. to the ministry &amp;
                    higher clergy this moderation or indifference must be imputed. the friars if I
                    may judge by what I have seen &amp; heard envy the fate of their brethren in
                    France, &amp; like them would gladly join a revolution which – whatever it did
                    to the other classes of society, certainly gave liberty to them. A Portugueze of
                    good family had <del rend="strikethrough">in</del> a sister in a French nunnery.
                    on the dissolution of the convents he immediately secured her an admission here
                    &amp; wrote to her to come with all speed from the land of Atheism. she replied
                    – she was very much obliged to him – but she was married.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> To the prevalence of indifference or infidelity I attribute this
                    sort of toleration. my man observed to me one day that no miracles were worked
                    now – &amp; the reason was there was not faith. Sir said he, there was a man in
                    my country who was very ill &amp; he wanted to have a relic &amp; there was none
                    to be had. so one of his friends cut a piece of dry stick, &amp; wrapt it up in
                    a linen cloth &amp; put it into bed to him, &amp; told him that was a piece of
                        S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Somebody staff. &amp; the man got <del rend="strikethrough">up</del> well – for his faith cured him. Is not the
                    failure of miracles like the silence of the Oracles? the juggle is over –
                    perhaps the people are too wise to be cheated, perhaps the clergy are too
                    wealthy to cheat. their predecessors made their fortune – &amp; they have given
                    over trade &amp; are enjoying it.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> But all is silently done. No hand has laid the Axe to the great
                    Upas Tree the canker from France has reached it – &amp; it is ready to fall with
                    the rottenness of age. the few books that are published could not be hostile to
                    the established systems – if the Authors wished – &amp; the Saints have usually
                    their fair portion of pages – a full tythe in kind.</p>
<p rend="center">–</p>
<p>About India my mind fluctuates. my inclination is against it decidedly – &amp; in
                    the opposite scale perhaps curiosity is a heavier weight than prudence. [MS
                    torn] it is certain that a hot climate suits me. perhaps is even necessary. if
                    that should prove the case it will be Hobsons choice. but India is too hot for
                    comfort – &amp; I have an abhorrence of East-Indianised Englishmen. the South of
                    Europe would [MS obscured]redly be my choice – if I could chuse. I like this
                    country so well that I should be content to exchange the society &amp; the fire
                    &amp; the fogs &amp; the bread &amp; butter of England for the filth &amp; the
                    fruit &amp; the sun of Portugal, with no better equipage thro life than a
                    jack-ass.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am going a round-about journey to Batalha &amp; Alcobaça &amp;
                    Thomar &amp; Santarem.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">All these places
                        contained medieval monasteries and convents that might contain useful
                        manuscripts on Portuguese history and literature.</note> either on a mule or
                    a <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">An ass: Bedford’s nickname was ‘Dapple’, Sancho
                        Panza’s ass in Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra (1547–1616), <title>Don
                            Quixote</title> (1605–15).</note>
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> goes with me – &amp; a young
                        Englishman<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Waterhouse (dates
                        unknown), an English merchant in Lisbon.</note> whom I like. our plan for
                    the campaign is not quite arranged. – News we have none. save that the deaths at
                    Seville are five hundred daily! &amp; that we are in danger of being starved by
                    the expedition whom we half expect here – &amp; who are &amp; have been some
                    time upon a short allowance of <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> salt
                    provisions – by way of dieting for the scurvy which is raging among them. we
                    shall have the land stript if they arrive. God bless you. write soon &amp; write
                    often.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> yrs affectionately</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>
<date when="1800-10-30">October 30. 1800.</date>
</p>
<p>I have got a Portugueze version of the Guerras Civiles.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">An untraced Portuguese version of Gines
                            Perez de Hita (1544–1619?),<title> Historia de los Vandos, De Los
                                Cegries, y Abencerrages, Cavalleros Moros De Granada, y Las Civiles
                                Guerras Que Huvo En Ella, Hasta Que El Rey Don Fernando El Quinto La
                                Gano</title> (1595–1619).</note> will you believe that the Idiot
                        translator has omitted all the Ballads?!!! – I have found however a little
                        volume of Ballads about the Cid<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Juan
                            de Escobar (fl. C17th), <title>Historia Del Muy Valeroso Cavallero El
                                Cid Ruy Diez de Bivar, En Romances</title> (1632), no. 3449 in the
                            sale catalogue of Southey's library.</note> – &amp; another volume of
                        Spanish Ballads<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Lorenzo de Sepulveda
                            (c. 1505–c. 1580), <title>Romances Nuevamente Sacados De Historias
                                Antiguas De La Cronica De Espana</title> (1566), no. 3448 in the
                            sale catalogue of Southey's library.</note> which is not come home from
                        the booksellers. its date <del rend="strikethrough">1596</del> &lt;1566&gt;
                            <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxx xxxxxx xxxxxxxxx</del>. the Devil is
                        always tempting me here in the shape of a Spanish book. indeed Lisbon would
                        be a book-Paradise to me – if I was not somewhat in the situation of
                            Tantalus.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology,
                            Tantalus was condemned to a fate whereby food and water were always
                            within reach, but receded whenever he wished to eat or drink.</note>
                        Romances are not to be found. where can they be scattered? one would almost
                        suspect that abominable curate &amp; barbarous Barber of having treated
                        every library in Spain with the same inquisitorial severity as Don
                            Quixotes.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In Miguel de Cervantes
                            Saavedra (1547–1616), <title>Don Quixote</title> (1605–1615), Part 1,
                            Book 1, chapter 6, the barber, Master Nicholas, and the curate, Pedro
                            Perez, stage a mock Inquistion of Don Quixote’s books on
                            chivalry.</note>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
