<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2010-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.662b</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2010-08-15">August 15, 2010</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47891.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the
							Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 186-189.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="662b" type="letter">
        <head>662b. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">John King</ref>, <date when="1802-03-16">16 March 1802</date> [translation]<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
						King./ Pneumatic Institution/ Bristol &#8211; Hot-Wells<lb />Stamped: BATH<lb />Seal: [partial, illegible]<lb />Endorsement: March 16
						1802; The right hons Isaac Corry &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c/ G<hi rend="sup">t</hi> George S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
						Westminster<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 47891<lb />Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the
							Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 186-189.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not easy for a man who does not know how to speak or write in French, to write a letter in this
					language without a grammar or dictionary. Oh well! he will take time to learn. and if you want to be irritated by reading letters
					of the greatest barbarity, here is your correspondent &#8211; you know I do not like the French language. it does not have the softness
					of Italian, nor the delicacy of Portuguese, nor the majesty of Spanish. French poetry is to my taste detestable &#8211; for an epigram,
					for a song, it is good enough. for an epic &#8211; for tragedy &#8211; holy God! what harmony. what a frightfully strange mouth is needed to
					pronounce it. A man of genius such as Voltaire &#8211; or the even greater Rousseau, will overcome the language. in fact in order to
					produce good work, a good worker is more valuable than good instruments.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You know of the arrangement that I
					have made with Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> for the works of
					Chatterton. my friend <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has drawn a view of the Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Mary Redclift<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Despite Southey&#8217;s praise, this drawing was not used in <title>The
							Works of Thomas Chatterton</title> (1803), edited by Southey and Joseph Cottle.</note> for the frontispiece &#8211; it will be a
					beautiful engraving. but another will be required for the other volume, and <ref target="people.html#DuppaRichard">Mr Duppa</ref>
					a knowledgeable artist, (perhaps you will have heard of the heads adapted from Michelangelo&#8217;s Last Judgment that he has
						published?)<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Duppa, <title>A Selection of Twelve Heads from the Last Judgement
							of Michael Angelo</title> (1801).</note> has suggested to me that the best subject would be the view of the interior of
					the apartment in which the collection of supposed manuscripts was deposited. I make so bold as to beg you to make the drawing<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John King&#8217;s drawing was used for the engraving opposite the title page of <title>The Works
							of Thomas Chatterton</title>, 3 vols (London, 1803), II, unpaginated. It was entitled &#8216;Interior of the Room in Redcliff
						Church where Rowleys Manuscripts were Said to have been Deposited&#8217;.</note> &#8211; there is no need for me to excuse myself from
					soliciting humbly an act that can be called charitable. I think the antique chamber &#8211; and the old chest would also make a
					sufficiently pretty and very appropriate illustration.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The climate of my homeland is so execrable that
					today, in the spring, my hand shivers so much with the cold, notwithstanding I am so close to the fire that my legs are well
					roasted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Believe me my friend that I &lt;have formed&gt; with the greatest and truest satisfaction, the hope
					that I will have you for my companion during my exile in Ireland. To live in a wild land &#8211; amongst the most strange and barbarous
					people, without a single friend &#8211; this prospect of the future was very terrible &#8211; Even curiosity will not last long without a
					companion. I have considered a tour of Killarney. and to the North to see the famous rocks of the Giants,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. the Giants Causeway in County Antrim.</note> on which journey <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> has promised to be my associate. I will not be sorry if I am able to exchange him as a traveller for you. The
					mountains and waterfalls of Wicklow will not be equal to those of your sublime land, nor the Fortunate Isles<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Canary Islands.</note> that you have visited. But I believe it will be worthy of your
					paintbrush.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Unfortunately for the science of Galvani S. Patric did not leave one of these<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Luigi Galvani (1737-1798), Italian doctor and physicist, had conducted experiments on frogs and
						shown the link between electricity and muscular activity. In legend, St Patrick (5th century) had cleared Ireland of
						snakes.</note> &#8211; oh I am stupidly ignorant of this beast &#8211; what are they called? your friends &#8211; the little animals so slender
					and cold-blooded &lt;by nature&gt; of which you have murdered so many thousands with your scientific cold-bloodedness? all the
					venom of the island since that &lt;time&gt; has passed into the human inhabitants. If you had one of these people &#8211;in your
					laboratory, you could only analyse his potatoes and his whiskey, these are their primary constituents &#8211; <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> has suggested that they are a truly antediluvian race, whose
					ancestors did not want to enter the Ark with Noah,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The story of Noah and the Ark is told in
							<title>Genesis</title>, 6-9.</note> but escaped in a small boat, that landed on Mount Taur&#233;!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A pun that links the origins of the Irish to bulls, as Taurus was a bull in Greek legend.</note> as for me I
					have another theory more favourable to the nation&#8217;s vanity. I believe that they are from a much nobler origin than the other
					peoples of the world, because &#8211; all the others are from the loins of Noah. &#8211; by Jove<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The
						chief of the gods in Roman mythology.</note> it is worth nothing in this execrable language &#8211; because &#8211; I mean because other
					people spring from the loins of Noah, &amp; they from the Sirloins of Pasiphae&#8217;s lover.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Another story linking the Irish to bulls. Pasiphae was the wife of Minos, King of Crete. She fell in love with a white bull
						and their child was the Minotaur.</note> there is a very aristocratic descent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The final treaty<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Treaty of Amiens, between Britain and France, was signed on 25 March 1802.</note> is
					expected every day, every hour I can say. a friend<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William Taylor.</note> who has
					needlessly been waiting some weeks for a passport to France, has this morning received intelligence from the Immigration Office
					that he will be able to go in a few days without restrictions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you read Schiller&#8217;s tragedy about Joan
					of Arc? <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Friedrich Schiller (1759-1805), <title>Die Jungfrau von Orleans</title>
						(1801).</note> They say that La Pucelle a witch is in love with an English officer &#8211; ! <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Mr Cottle</ref> the great Poet &#8211; who first blew the epic trumpet, and since the Jewish trumpet<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle, <title>Alfred, an Epic Poem, in Twenty Four Books</title> (1800) and <title>A New Version of the
							Psalms of David</title> (1801).</note> &#8211; at present is printing in his own press a new poem on a subject which is not so
					new, &amp; has already been treated &#8211; it is a sermon &lt;in verse&gt; preached by John the Baptist<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle, <title>John the Baptist: a Poem</title> (1802). An earlier version had appeared in Cottle&#8217;s
							<title>Poems</title> (1795).</note> &#8211; it will be a desirable study when you are not able to sleep, because it is really
					soporific, &amp; it is the most agreeable way to take one&#8217;s medicine by the eyes than [MS obscured] the mouth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am hoping in a little while to write passably in French &#8211; this was written without effort, with the same
					disregard of the laws of grammar that the first Consul<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769-1821,
						First Consul 1799-1804, Emperor of the French 1804-1814).</note> has demonstrated for all the other laws &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> I have the honour to be &#8211; that is to say I am truly</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> &amp; with regard</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> your friend</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Here I have received a letter from our good friend <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> &#8211; to which I will
						reply the day after tomorrow.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>