<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce407</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.398</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Huntington
                        Library, HM 4821 .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 271&#8211;276.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.398" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="398" type="letter">
        <head>398. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William
                        Taylor</ref>, <date when="1799-04-15">15 April 1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Surry Street./
                        Norwich/ Single<lb />Postmarks: BRISTOL/ APR 15 99; B/ AP/ 16/
                        99<lb />Endorsement: Ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 7 May<lb />MS: Huntington
                        Library, HM 4821<lb /> Previously published: J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A
                            Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of
                            Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 271&#8211;276.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your allegory of the Seas<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor&#8217;s &#8216;The Seas&#8217;, published in <title>Annual Anthology</title> (Bristol,
                        1799), pp. 233&#8211;236 and sent to Southey on 25 March 1799 (J.W. Robberds
                        (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor
                            of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, p, 270).</note> is as
                    ingenious as <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> any I remember to have seen. the
                    negligence of the versification I do not perceive &#8211; perhaps from versifying
                    myself with more negligence than should be allowed. if there be any inaccuracy
                    in the allegory it is making Taste cast a dwelling eye where Inspiration first
                    waved his seraph wings. The Rovers Apology<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor sent his &#8216;Rover&#8217;s Apology&#8217; to Southey on 25 March
                        1799, but it was not included in the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1799)
                        (J.W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late
                            William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), I, p.
                        270).</note> scans &#8211; but would not be <del rend="strikethrough">metr</del>
                    harmonious if read by one who did not understand the metre. now when the
                    classical metres are adopted in a modern language the <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> accents should be so arranged as to produce the <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> necessary cadence, tho read by one unlearned.
                    I will try to mould your sapphics to this. with my own I never yet had patience
                    &#8211; but I have a great desire to render the metre popular, not only as it is in
                    itself beautiful, but as a step toward naturalizing hexameters. does not an
                    English &amp; still more a German hexameter take up a longer time in repetition
                    than a Greek or Latin one on account of the greater number of letters in the
                    syllables? <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> the letters in a line must be
                    nearly a fourth more. &#8211; <del rend="strikethrough">&amp; if</del> could we
                    retrench one of the first four feet? the metre would not be difficult after one
                    had written a hundred lines.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Dom Daniel<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The early
                        working-title for <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> I
                    shall as you advised write in stanzas, partly to avoid a sameness of style which
                    in blank verse would be almost inevitable. but I do not think it will be
                    advisable to confine myself to a regular stanza. this license lessens the
                    fetters of rhyme, &amp; the ear will not be disappointed if the rhymes are not
                    placed too distant from each other to be readily remembered. I think that
                    writing in stanzas will correct the feebleness you observe, simplicity would be
                    out of character &#8211; I must build a Saracenic mosque &#8211; not a Quaker meeting
                    house.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> &amp; his <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">young assistant</ref> are doing wonders at
                    the Pneumatic Institution &#8211; but not by the gasses.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Pneumatic Institute, Dowry Square, Bristol, had opened
                        earlier in 1799. It was dedicated to using gases to treat disease.</note>
                    what they wanted for consumptions seems to be found in the fox glove
                        tincture.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">For Thomas Beddoes&#8217;s
                        advocacy of the use of fox-glove see his <title>Essay on the Causes, Early
                            Signs, and Prevention of Pulmonary Consumption for the Use of Parents
                            and Preceptors</title> (Bristol, 1799), pp. 265&#8211;271.</note> another
                    stimulant for the absorbents they have found in the gazeous oxyd of azote &#8211; at
                    least such it appears to be from the feelings of the few who have yet breathed
                        it.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">For their experiments with
                        nitrous oxide, see Thomas Beddoes, <title>Notice of Some Observations Made
                            at the Medical Pneumatic Institution</title> (1799) and Humphry Davy,
                            <title>Researches, Chemical and Philosophical, Chiefly Concerning
                            Nitrous Oxide, or Dephlogisticated Nitrous Air, and its
                            Respiration</title> (1800).</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> has made a curious botanical
                    discovery, he has detected a coating of flint on all canes &amp; grasses. a boy
                    playing with two canes struck fire from them, &amp; this led to the
                        discovery.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;boy&#8217; was a son of
                        William Coates (dates unknown). The incident is described in Joseph Cottle,
                            <title>Reminiscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert
                            Southey</title> (London, 1847), p. 271. Davy&#8217;s findings were published
                        in William Nicholson (1753&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>) (ed.), <title>A Journal
                            of Natural Philosophy, Chemistry, and the Arts</title>, 3 (May 1800), 56&#8211;59.</note> If <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref>
                    had enough previous knowledge of medicine he might profit more here than by any
                    clinical lectures in Europe.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is with
                    me on his way to London to pass for a Lieutenancy. he has been helping me to cut
                    up Madocs ships &amp; build <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> galleys with
                    them. There is a marine on board the Mars who persuaded his father to murder his
                    mother, &amp; then turnd Kings evidence &amp; brought his father to the
                        gallows.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">For Southey&#8217;s outline of the
                        story see <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 193. He did not work it up into a ballad.</note>
                    by the help of the devil I think of working up this mans history with a ballad.
                    by the by Ferriar of Manchester has abused you for using the word
                        hurry-skurry<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Manchester-based
                        physician and writer John Ferriar (1761&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Illustrations of Sterne, with other Essays and Verses</title>
                        (London, 1798), p. 306. William Taylor had used the phrase &#8216;hurry-skurry&#8217; in
                        his translation of Gottfried August B&#252;rger (1748&#8211;1794), &#8216;Lenora&#8217; in the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (March 1796), 135&#8211;137.</note> &#8211; it
                    struck me that you had possibly placed it for some German phrase of a like
                    nature. is this the case? for I have his book to review.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">If Southey wrote this review, it was not
                        published.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Barker is painting a picture from Mary the Maid of the Inn, but
                    from what part of the story I have not learnt.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Barker (1767&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>). Barker was
                        painting a picture based on &#8216;Mary&#8217;, first published in Southey&#8217;s
                            <title>Poems</title> (Bristol, 1797), pp. [159]&#8211;182.</note> he might
                    have found better subjects in my better pieces.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Anthony<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The Devil &amp; St Anthony&#8217;; see Southey to William Taylor,
                        18 March 1799, Letter 391.</note> has no morality at all. sophistry may be
                    expected from the Devil whose object in arguing is to puzzle his adversary. the
                    Eclogue was written before <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyds</ref>
                    Lines on the Fast, &amp; Letter to the Anti-Jacobine<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Lloyd&#8217;s <title>Lines Suggested by the Fast, Appointed
                            on Wednesday, February 27, 1799</title> (1799) and <title>A Letter to
                            the Anti-Jacobin Reviewers</title> (1799).</note> had reached me &#8211; but
                    Satan defends himself exactly upon the same principle that <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> defends existing
                    establishments. <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> is wasting
                    great talents in crude &amp; hasty productions. he wants to print the play<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor had been shown an early version of
                        Lloyd&#8217;s <title>The Duke d&#8217;Ormond</title> (1822); see William Taylor to
                        Robert Southey, 26 September 1798, J.W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of
                            the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2
                        vols (London, 1843), I, pp. 226&#8211;227.</note> you saw &#8211; &amp; in the incorrect
                    state in which you saw it. I have attempted to dissuade &amp; I hope with
                    success. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am looking with some impatience for your life of Burger.
                    excepting the two Ballads which you translated his other productions that have
                    been Englished are of no great excellence.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">William Taylor&#8217;s translations of Gottfried August B&#252;rger
                        (1748&#8211;1794), &#8216;Lenora&#8217; and &#8216;The Lass of Fair Wone&#8217; had been published in the
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (March 1796), 135&#8211;137 and
                            <title>Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (April 1796), 223&#8211;234.</note> the
                    Lenora indeed is enough &#8211; it cannot be surpassed &amp; will not probably be
                    equalled &#8211; yet the Parsons Daughter struck me as the finer poem. the story of
                    Lenore once conceived the execution was not difficult for a man of genius, but
                    the excellence of the other ballad arises wholly from the mode of narration &#8211;
                    &amp; tho such a tale might have occurred to a thousand poets, it is a thousand
                    to one that none of them had found out the best way of relating it. thanks to
                    the number of translators I no longer hunger &amp; thirst for the language as I
                    did some time since.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> prose plays I apprehend suffer little from translation. it is
                    only Klopstock<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Friedrich Gottlieb
                        Klopstock (1724&#8211;1803), whose plays include <title>Der Tod Adams</title>
                        (1757), <title>Salomo</title> (1764), and <title>Die
                            Hermannsschlacht</title> (1769).</note> that I long to read &#8211; &amp;
                    Bodmers Noah<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Bodmer (1698&#8211;1783),
                            <title>Noachide</title> (1752). For Southey&#8217;s verdict, &#8216;a bad poem&#8217;, see
                            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, p. 2.</note> on account of the subject &#8211; but the
                    book is not <del rend="strikethrough">xxxxxxxxx</del> getatable, or I should ere
                    this have poked my way thro it with a dictionary.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Almanach<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                            <title>Annual Anthology</title>, the first volume of which appeared in
                        1799.</note> stands still in deference to a book of <ref target="people.html#BeddoesThomas">Beddoes</ref> on consumption.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Beddoes, <title>Essay on the Causes,
                            Early Signs, and Prevention of Pulmonary Consumption for the Use of
                            Parents and Preceptors</title> (1799).</note> a Clergyman,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified; possibly the Revd Christopher
                        Hardy Sherive (d. 1800), Rector of Bridport, who contributed to the 1800
                        edition of the <title>Annual Anthology</title>.</note> in consequence of the
                    advertisement called on <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle</ref>
                    &amp; promised to bring him from a friend some poems which would be &#8220;an ornament
                    to the volume.&#8221; they have not yet arrived. from <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> I shall have some &#8211; the early
                    productions of genius.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Davy&#8217;s only
                        signed contribution to <title>Annual Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1799) was
                        &#8216;Extract from an unfinished Poem on Mounts-Bay&#8217;, pp. 281&#8211;286. But the
                        following poems, signed &#8216;D.&#8217; were also by him: &#8216;The Sons of Genius&#8217;, pp.
                        93&#8211;99, &#8216;The Song of Pleasure&#8217;, pp. 120&#8211;125, &#8216;Ode to St Michael&#8217;s Mount, in
                        Cornwall&#8217;, pp. 172&#8211;176, &#8216;The Tempest&#8217;, pp. 179&#8211;180.</note> he is a
                    miraculous young man whose talents I can only wonder at. <ref target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> among other things has sent me
                    a ballad with unlimited liberty of alteration.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">This ballad was not printed in either <title>Annual
                            Anthology</title> (1799) or (1800).</note> it is so full of beauties
                    that I must <del rend="strikethrough">take</del> employ much time in clearing
                    away its faults. I shall throw in one of the unpublishd Eclogues you saw.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;The Last of the Family&#8217;,
                        published in the <title>Annual Anthology</title> (Bristol, 1799), pp.
                        165&#8211;171.</note> I know not how those poems generally please. one of my
                        friends<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to
                        Wynn&#8217;s criticism; see Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 9
                        April 1799 (Letter 397).</note> wrote on a first reading to abuse them. he
                    read them again &amp; sent me the amende honorable.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. a satisfactory apology.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#MauriceMichael">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Maurice</ref>
                    writes me a good account of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>. he finds him sufficiently attentive &amp; that being the case
                    he must get on rapidly. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I shall be in London on May day. if you do not write before that time direct
                        under cover to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">C W Williams
                            Wynn</ref> Esq. Stone Buildings, Lincolns Inn. if I can find a companion
                        between the terms I shall take a walk, round Kent, or to see the wonders of
                        Derbyshire.</p>
          <p>
            <date when="1799-04-15">Monday. April 15. 99.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>