<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce452</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.443</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4811D.  Previously  published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 86&#8211;88.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.443" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="443" type="letter">
        <head>443. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin
                        Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1799-10-10">10 October 1799</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                            Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Wynnstay/ Wrexham/ Denbighshire<lb />Stamped:
                        CHRIST/ CHURCH<lb />Postmark: E/ OCT 11/ 99<lb />Endorsement: Oct 10
                        99<lb />MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4811D<lb />Previously published:
                        John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp. 86&#8211;88.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="left">
            <address>
              <placeName>Christ-Church. Hampshire.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1799-10-10"> Oct 10. 99</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> We reached this place Tuesday night last. there is one advantage
                    in the neighbourhood of the sea, that if we are about to have the world purified
                    by a second deluge, there may be boats at hand. moreover Spithead is at no great
                    distance &amp; a first rate has as good accommodations as Noahs ark could have
                    had.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received an ugly piece of intelligence on my arrival here.
                    casting an eye over the paper <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    saw that the Sylph brig (<ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref>
                    ship) was safely lodged in Ferrol harbour.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">It was widely reported in the British Press in early October
                        1799, e.g. <title>St James&#8217;s Chronicle</title>, 5 October 1799, that the
                        brig, <hi rend="ital">Sylph</hi>, on which <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom Southey</ref> was serving, had been
                        captured and was at the Spanish port of Ferrol.</note> whether there had
                    been any previous action or not we do not know, &amp; it will probably be long
                    before any intelligence can reach us.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Almost I envy you your domestic feelings at <ref target="places.html#Wynnstay">Wynnstay</ref>. with the most domestic
                    propensities &amp; root-striking readiness, since my childhood I have never felt
                    myself at home. still looking on to some settled dwelling place I have still
                    been disappointed. here I am settling <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref>, &amp; we are now all hurry &amp; discomfort. the moment I
                    can at all endure confinement I will remove to London; at present I continue in
                    the same state &#8211; well when in the use of great exercise, disordered by a days
                    indolence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am anxious to see what reception one of the Series of
                        Plays<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">None of the plays published in
                        Joanna Baillie (1762&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Series of Plays: In
                            Which it is Attempted to Delineate the Stonger Passions of the
                            Mind</title> (1798) were staged until <title>De Montfort</title> in
                        1800.</note> will meet with if brought on the stage. dramatic writing is
                    very difficult. to make common tragedies or comedies is easy childsplay &#8211; I
                    should find it easier to satisfy an audience than to satisfy myself. Our stage
                    seems to have reached the very depth of degradation. it is impossible to sink
                    below Pizarro.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Brinsley Sheridan
                        (1751&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Pizarro</title> (1799) was a huge
                        success, performed 31 times at Drury Lane, London between 24 May and 29 June
                        1799. A combination of August von Kotzebue&#8217;s (1761&#8211;1819) <title>Die
                            Sonnenjungfrau</title> (1788) and <title>Die Spanier in Peru</title>
                        (1796), Sheridan&#8217;s play focused on the conquest of the Incan Empire by
                        Francisco Pizarro (1471/6&#8211;1541).</note> Kotzebues play might have passed as
                    the worst possible, if Sheridan had not proved the possibility of making it
                    worse. The London audience is a very good natured one. they will be pleased with
                    any thing, whatever the manager chuses to provide, the dullness of sentimental
                    comedy, the vulgarity of broad farce, the Lincolnshire-fen-flatness of Mr
                    Whaleys tragedy<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Sedgwick Whalley
                        (1746&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), clergyman and poet, whose <title>The Castle
                            of Montval</title> (1781) opened at Drury Lane on 23 April 1799 to a
                        lukewarm response.</note> &#8211; or the puppet show of Pizarro. all in their
                    turn! this however is in my favour. In looking back upon the list of English
                    plays it is astonishing among those that have obtained any celebrity to see how
                    few deserve it. Shakespere stands above all other names. I never feel so proud
                    of my country as when I remember that Milton &amp; Shakespere were Englishmen,
                    the two unequalable men. &amp; Bacon &amp; Newton in philosophy.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The scientists Francis Bacon (1561&#8211;1616;
                            <title>DNB</title>) and Isaac Newton (1643&#8211;1727;
                        <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; after these names we can equal the rest of
                    the world. How comes it that Wales has produced no great man? we take
                        Taliessin<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sixth-century Welsh bard
                        whose work is only known from the medieval <title>Book of
                        Taliesin</title>.</note> upon trust, probably much to his advantage but
                    since <del rend="strikethrough">play</del> &lt;they&gt; learnt to speak English
                    your countrymen have never said anything to be remembered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> did I tell you <del rend="strikethrough">xx</del> three months
                    ago that I had finished the outline of Madoc? I much wish you to see it, &amp;
                    would send it if I could trust my only copy to the chance of carriage. here it
                    lies unlookd at, till all the freshness of self-satisfaction be worn off, or
                    transferrd to some younger birth, &amp; then unsparingly to work. at present I
                    like it so well that it has half put me out of humour with all my older
                    writings. in my alteration I meant to have carried him to Florida, but the
                    perusal of Sotos expedition<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Hernando de
                        Soto (1496/7&#8211;1542) led a Spanish expedition which landed in Florida in 1539
                        and undertook a huge journey of exploration through the southern part of
                        North America, without finding a suitable place for a settlement.</note>
                    there has convinced me that the Welsh <del rend="strikethrough">would</del>
                    could not have succeeded in settling where the Spaniards attempted it in vain.
                    so I now think of the banks of the Orinoco or Maragnon. Brazil, Paraguay, or
                    El-dorado. with Mango Capac<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Legendary
                        founder of the Inca state.</note> it is impossible even for a poet to
                    identify him. at least without the sacrifice of all his companions &#8211; &amp; I
                    have not the heart to drown them.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Direct <ref target="places.html#Burton">Burton</ref> near</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Ringwood. Hampshire.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>