<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce352</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.343</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23.  Previously 
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                        Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    174&#8211;176.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.343" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="343" type="letter">
        <head>343. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1798-08-26">26 August
                        1798</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/
                        Grosvenor Ch. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Exchequer/ London/
                        Single<lb />Stamped: HEREFORD<lb />Postmark: G/ AU/ 30 /98<lb />Endorsement: 26
                        August 1798<lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 23<lb />Previously
                        published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                        Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp.
                    174&#8211;176.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1798-08-26">Sunday. Aug. 26. 1798</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter this day found me in a remote <del rend="strikethrough">Herefords</del> part of Herefordshire, the village from
                    whence one part of my ancestry sprung, where they were some 2 generations back
                    the great people, where their old mansion house is now untenanted &amp; in
                    ruins, &amp; where I am visiting a stranger among strangers.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s maternal relations, the Tylers,
                        originated from Dilwyn, Herefordshire; see Charles John Robinson, <title>The
                            Mansions of Herefordshire and Their Memories</title> (London, 1873), p.
                        93.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> of course is with me, indeed
                    one motive of my rambling was the hope that frequent change of air &amp; much
                    exercise might strengthen her. She is greatly recovered but far from being well.
                    We left home the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this month for Hereford to be with
                        <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref>, &amp; are now at
                    his Uncles<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a maternal uncle of
                            <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">William Bowyer
                            Thomas</ref>. A Francis Bowyer Esq. of Dilwyn was recorded in <title>An
                            Alphabetical List of the Poll for the County of Hereford, Taken at
                            Widemarsh, before Abraham Whittaker Esquire, Sheriff</title> (Hereford,
                        1796), p. 38.</note> at Dilwyn. from hence we return on Tuesday to Hereford;
                    the end of the week we go to Abberley, to the brother in law of poor <ref target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Seward</ref>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Severn
                        (1751&#8211;1828), Rector of Kyre and Abberley, Worcestershire, was married to a
                        sister of Edmund Seward.</note> &amp; our absence from home will not in all
                    exceed a month.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very &#8211; very &#8211; desirous of seeing Leopold Berchtold.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Leopold, Graf von Berchtold (1759&#8211;1809),
                        Austrian philanthropist.</note> would he were to remain till November in
                    town. I shall then come up to keep term &#8211; but before &#8211; a plague upon money say
                    I! I would come up on purpose if it were not for the expence. Will you send me
                    his book &#8211; because my Letters are in the press again &#8211; &amp; I should wish to
                    mention it there.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters Written
                            During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>, 2nd edn
                        (Bristol, 1799), pp. 290&#8211;295, mentions three of Berchtold&#8217;s books, but not
                        the gift Southey probably received, Berchtold&#8217;s <title>Nachtrict von dem im
                            St Antons-Spitale in Smirna mit dem allerbesten Erfolg gebrauchten
                            einfachen Mittel</title> (1797).</note> &amp; Grosvenor pray borrow for
                    me <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisles</ref> account of the
                    Surgical College at Madrid which I once analized for him, as I want to give some
                    account of it in an appendix<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Published as
                        &#8216;Account of the Royal College of Surgery at Madrid&#8217;, <title>Letters Written
                            During a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title>, 2nd edn
                        (Bristol, 1799), pp. 468&#8211;483. Southey was probably translating from a
                        Spanish original in the possession of Anthony Carlisle.</note> &amp; the
                    sketch I then took is imperfect. if you will send these books together to <ref target="places.html#Cottles">Cottles</ref> you will oblige me &#8211; &amp; I pray
                    you be not more dilatory than convenience requires. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no excuses to offer for silence &#8211; at least none worth
                    offering. riding &amp; walking are idle employments &#8211; &amp; when I am at home
                    you know not how much I have to do. My mind is never vacant &#8211; I turn from one
                    employment to another &#8211; &amp; change is to <del rend="strikethrough">be</del> me
                    as rest. you know I am now a housekeeper, &amp; as my additional charge have not
                    yet received any additional resources, my industry is all in requisition. in
                    this however <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> will
                    assist me when he can, &amp; in the mean time it is well that I can do without
                    it. I review a great deal &#8211; &amp; am surprized to find the months come round so
                    fast. besides this I have another regular employment which kills two birds with
                    one stone &amp; which I will one day explain to you, &amp; then the Law you know
                    &#8211; damn the Law. however I have lately found a second reason for reading a Law
                    book &#8211; &amp; shall sit at it hungrily.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present Grosvenor I hunger &amp; thirst to be in your
                        Library<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Grosvenor Bedford&#8217;s father
                        had a personal collection of books, which Southey had made use of since his
                        schooldays at Westminster.</note> &#8211; &amp; hope to satiate my appetite there
                    in November. do you know that I must keep three half weeks in the terms to
                    come?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write to you with little comfort out of a most villainous
                    ink-stand. I have never seen <ref target="people.html#RoscoeWilliam">Roscoes</ref> lines<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably William
                        Roscoe, <title>Address Spoken by Mr. Holman, at the Theatre Royal, Liverpool
                            on the Night Appropriated for the Benefit of the Children of the Late
                            Mr. Palmer</title> (1798). The highly-regarded and popular actor John
                        Palmer (1742?&#8211;1798; <title>DNB</title>) had died on 2 August, leaving
                        several children. The Liverpool benefit was followed by similar events at
                        the Haymarket and Drury Lane Theatres, London.</note> &#8211; &amp; do not expect
                        <hi rend="ital">much</hi> from him. he is an accomplished man &amp; a good
                    man, but one whose reputation will not last because it is not deserved. his book
                    is a weak book.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Roscoe,
                            <title>The Life of Lorenzo de&#8217; Medici</title> (1795).</note>
                        Tenhoves<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicolas Tenhove (dates
                        unknown), Dutch antiquarian. An English translation of his <title>Memoirs of
                            the House of Medici</title> appeared in 1797.</note> is worth a thousand
                    such. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Vision<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The Vision of
                        the Maid of Orleans&#8217;, published in <title>Poems</title>, 2 vols (Bristol,
                        1799), II, pp.[1]&#8211;69.</note> is not yet fit for the press. it will however
                    soon be there &amp; I shall add other pieces enough to make up a second volume.
                    I have some good ballads ready &amp; my English Eclogues will be among my best
                        things.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Poems</title> (1799)
                        included six ballads and six &#8216;English Eclogues&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Grosvenor you have an ugly great sheet half filld &#8211; I wish it
                    were smaller or fuller. There is a tide in the feelings of man, which taken at
                    the flood leads on to letter writing<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                        paraphrase of <title>Julius Caesar</title>, Act 4, scene 3, lines
                        218&#8211;220.</note> &#8211; now Grosvenor it was low water before I could get paper
                    &amp; ink, &amp; my pen &amp; ink are miserably uncomfortable. I cannot mend the
                    one &#8211; so </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly </salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> love. direct to <ref target="places.html#Cottles">Cottles</ref>. I shall soon return.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>