<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce563</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.554</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 121&#8211;124 [in part; dated &#8216;October
                        1800&#8217;]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), Robert Southey: Journals of a
                            Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and a Visit to France 1838
                        (Oxford, 1960), pp. 137&#8211;139 [in part; dated [30&#8211;31] October
                        1800].Dating note: This letter was written very shortly after Southey
                        returned to Lisbon on 28 October 1800.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="554" type="letter">
        <head>554. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                        Rickman</ref>, <date when="1800-10-29">[c. 29&#8211;31] October 1800</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Rickman<lb />Endorsements: Oct: 1800.; Oct. 1800<lb />MS:
                        Huntington Library, RS 10<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                        (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849-1850), II, pp. 121&#8211;124 [in part; dated &#8216;October
                        1800&#8217;]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a
                            Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and a Visit to France 1838</title>
                        (Oxford, 1960), pp. 137&#8211;139 [in part; dated [30&#8211;31] October
                        1800].<lb />Dating note: This letter was written very shortly after Southey
                        returned to Lisbon on 28 October 1800.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1800-10">Oct. 1800</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Rickman</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> At last the opportunity is arrived of sending my important
                        parcel.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The manuscript of
                            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> my private
                    instructions must be vague &#8211; to make the best bargain you can &#8211; &amp; on no
                    terms to sell the copy-right. a quarto edition of 500 is worth &#163;100. 1000 of the
                    small size should produce something more. <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey received &#163;115 for 1,000 octavo copies of
                            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> from Longman and Rees.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will probably offer to
                    advance the expence of publishing &amp; share the profits. this is not fair, as
                    brains ought to bear a higher interest than money. If you are not satisfied with
                    his terms offer it to Arch<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John and
                        Arthur Arch (fl. 1792&#8211;1838), publishers, booksellers and stationers, whose
                        premises were at this time at 23 Gracechurch St, London.</note> in
                    Gracechurch Street. or to Philips<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard
                        Phillips (1767&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>).</note> of the Monthly Magazine, a
                    man who can afford to pay a good price because he can advertize &amp; puff his
                    own property every month. the sale of the book is not doubtful. my name would
                    carry it thro an edition, tho it were worthless. Perhaps the fate of Alfred the
                        Long<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle, <title>Alfred, An
                            Epic Poem, in Twenty-four Books</title> (1800).</note> may have
                    intimidated <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; sickened
                    him of poetry &amp; Bristol. stipulate for at least twelve copies for the
                    author.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In literature, as in the playthings of school-boys &amp; the
                    frippery of women there are the ins &amp; outs of fashion. sonnets &amp; satires
                    &amp; essays have their day &#8211; &amp; my Joan of Arc<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796), with a
                        revised second edition published in 1798.</note> has revived the epomania
                    that Boileau<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicolas Boileau-Despreaux
                        (1636&#8211;1711), <title>L&#8217;Art Poetique</title> (1674).</note> cured the French
                    of 120 years ago. but it is not every one who can shoot in the bow of
                        Ulysses,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In Homer&#8217;s
                            <title>Odyssey</title>, when Ulysses returned home, only he, not any of
                        his wife&#8217;s suitors, could draw his bow.</note> &amp; the gentlemen who think
                    they can bend the Bow because I made the string twang will find themselves
                    somewhat disappointed. Whenever that Poem requires a new edition I think &#8211; not
                    of correcting it &#8211; the ore deserves not to be new cast: but of prefixing a<del rend="strikethrough">n</del> fair estimate of its merits &amp; defects.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I can now explain to you the whole state of the paper-money &#8211; if
                    you can have patience to receive information in the scrip-scrap way that I
                    receive &amp; communicate. on issuing it six per cent interest was promised &#8211;
                    &amp; this interest they still profess to pay, but whoever applies for it is
                    sure to be wearied out with the eternal evasion that it is not his turn &#8211; there
                    are older bills &#8211; &amp; prior applicants. In paying any sum half may be tendered
                    in paper. but the smallest bills of half a moidore are very scarce. the more
                    current are of thirty shillings value (five milreas). They pay their officers
                    &amp;c <hi rend="ital">wholly</hi> in paper. of course this paper must be sold
                    at the discount &#8211; a loss of twenty per cent &#8211; where then half-paper is tendered
                    it is at par. whole payments are at the discount. But as this is variable &amp;
                    never for the better, every one puts a higher price upon his goods as the
                    insurance for the risque of loss.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Forged Bills have already been imported from England. The wise
                    financiers of this country are about to adopt another measure. to call in their
                    copper new coin it &amp; issue the ten-rea piece for twenty &#8211; at double its
                    value. meantime a clumsy agriculture renders all provision scarce &#8211; &amp; a
                    hungry foreign soldiery are ready to pay any price &#8211; when the People of England
                    discharge the bills. We expect the wise Expeditions here daily<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The British Army had sent an expeditionary force
                        to Holland in 1799. In 1800 there were rumours it would land in Portugal.
                        However, the next destination for a British Army was Egypt in 1801.</note> &#8211;
                    the 15000 men who are now <hi rend="ital">dieting upon a short allowance of salt
                        beef for the scurvy</hi>. literally true! we have letters of lamentations! &#8211;
                    moreover we are threatened from England with five thousand Dutch troops. a
                    pleasant addition to society. when I tell you that thro the summer nine
                    shillings have been paid at <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref> for
                    the daily keep of a horse &#8211; after all allowances for tavern-extortion you will
                    see the scarcity &amp; dearness of fodder. The expences of our troops when they
                    first arrived &#8211; are now for the same number of men, in the proportion of 4 to 9.
                    more than doubled. this is roguery for the price of provisions is not doubled
                    quite, nor of any article.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Foreign Jews are tolerated in Lisbon &#8211; that it is they are in no
                    danger from the Inquisition, tho forbidden to exercise the ceremonials of their
                    faith. the intercourse with Barbary brings a few Moors here &#8211; so that the devout
                    Portugueze are accustomed to the sight of Turks &#8211; Jews &#8211; &amp; Heretics. you
                    remember <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davys</ref> story of the
                    Cornishmans remark when his master said, now John we are in Devonshire. &#8211; &#8220;I
                    don&#8217;t see but the Pigs have got tails the same as along o we.&#8221; if the nations
                    here have sense enough to make a similar inference, they will be one degree
                    wiser than their forefathers. Lisbon grows. many a cornfield in which I have
                    walked five years ago is now covered with houses; &#8211; this is a short-lived
                    increase of population &#8211; a fine February day. for the English tenant these
                    habitations, &amp; when the army shall be recalled the houses will be desolate.
                    but the city exhibits an unequivocal sign of recovering industry &amp; opulence.
                    the gaps in the new streets that have stood vacant since the disgrace of
                        Pombal,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Jose de Carvalho e Melo,
                        Marquis of Pombal (1699&#8211;1782), Prime Minister of Portugal 1750&#8211;1777.</note>
                    are now filled up or filling. these are not rests for passage-birds. but large
                    &amp; magnificent houses for the merchants. But Commerce will for a long while
                    be as in America &#8211; a sordid &#8211; selfish &#8211; money-getting drudgery, encouraging no
                    art, &amp; ignorant of every science. it is not genius that is wanted in
                    Portugal. genius exists every where, but encouragement or the hope of
                    encouragement must waken it to action, &amp; here no ambition can exist &#8211; except
                    the desire of place &amp; court-pageantry. a man of letters &#8211; a philosopher
                    would starve here. a fine singer &amp; a female dancer are followed as in
                    London. tis almost reason enough to prescribe music from a commonwealth &#8211; that
                    Despotism encourages no other science. the <del rend="strikethrough">idiot</del>
                    &lt;ass&gt; Kings of Europe <del rend="strikethrough">seem</del> are always
                    showing there is. The Italian Opera is in my mind not only high treason against
                    common sense, but mischievous in its effects. nothing is attended to but the
                    music &#8211; the drama is simply a substratum for the tune. &amp; the mind lies
                    fallow while the sensual ear is gratified. the encouragement of a national
                    theatre may call up talents that shall confer honour upon the nation. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My first publication will probably be the literary part of the
                        history<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey never completed his
                        proposed &#8216;literary history&#8217; of Spain and Portugal.</note> &#8211; which is too
                    important to be treated of in an appendix or in seperate &amp; interrupting
                    chapters. Lisbon is rich in the books which suit my purpose &#8211; but I alas! am not
                    rich &#8211; &amp; endure somewhat of the tortures of Tantalus.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, Tantalus was condemned to a
                        fate whereby food and water were always within reach, but receded whenever
                        he wished to eat or drink.</note> the public Library<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The Real Biblioteca Publica da Corte,
                        established in 1796. It inherited many works collected by the Jesuits before
                        their expulsion from Portugal in 1759, and in 1797 acquired the records of
                        the Inquisition.</note> is indeed far more accessible than our Museums
                    &amp;c in England. but the books are under wire cases, &amp; the freedom of
                    research is miserably shackled by the necessity of asking the Librarian for
                    every volume you wish to consult. to hunt a subject thro a series of authors is
                    thus rendered almost impossible. &#8211; the Academy<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Either the Royal Academy of Portuguese History, founded in
                        1720, or Royal Academy of Sciences, founded in 1779.</note> however have
                    much facilitated my labour by publishing many of their old chronicles in a
                    buyable shape &#8211; &amp; also the old laws of Portugal. &#8211; There is a Frenchman
                        here<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Abb&#233; Du Boys (dates
                        unknown).</note> busy upon the history of Brazil &#8211; his materials are
                    excellent &amp; he is indefatigable. but I am apprehensive for his [MS torn] &#8211;
                    even if his person should escape. the ministry know what he is abo[Ms torn]
                    &amp; you need not be told with what an absurd secresy they secrete from the
                    world all information respecting that country. &#8211; the population of Brazil is
                    said to double that of the mother &amp; now dependant country. So heavy a branch
                    cannot long remain upon so rotten a trunk.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you. write to me. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> remembrance &#8211; </salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>What money you may get for Thalaba remit to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>. Richmond Green. Surry. <del rend="strikethrough">write</del>
            <hi rend="ital">it must bring me 100 guineas</hi> &#8211; to apprentice my
                        brother <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> with a
                        surgeon &#8211; Poor <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottle</ref>!<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <ref target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottle</ref> had died on 28 September 1800.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>