<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce514</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.505</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850).  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 53&#8211;56 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and
                            a Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp. 69&#8211;71 [in
                        part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.505" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="505" type="letter">
        <head>505. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel
                        Taylor Coleridge</ref> [fragment], <date when="1800-04-01">1 April
                        1800</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">MS: MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                            Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                        1849&#8211;1850)<lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                            <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                        (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, pp. 53&#8211;56 [in part]; Adolfo Cabral (ed.),
                            <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800&#8211;1801 and
                            a Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 69&#8211;71 [in
                        part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Bristol.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1800-04-01"> April 1. 1800.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Coleridge,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The day of our departure is now definitely fixed. We leave
                    Bristol next week, on Thursday. I do not wish to see you before we go; the time
                    is too short, and, moreover, the company of a friend who is soon to be left for
                    a long absence is not desirable. A few words upon business. For the Third
                        Anthology<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A successor to
                            <title>Annual Anthology</title> (1800), which never appeared.</note>
          <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> and <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> will be my delegates:
                    should you be in Bristol, of course the plenipotentiaryship is vested in you.
                    The Chatterton subscription<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and
                        Cottle&#8217;s edition of <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title>
                        (1803).</note> will not fill in less than twelve months: if illness or aught
                    more cogent detain me beyond that period, I pray you to let that duty devolve
                    upon you; there will be nothing but the task of arrangement. <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref> has a copy of Madoc.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A fair copy of the 15-book
                            <title>Madoc</title> 1797&#8211;1799; now Beinecke Library, Tinker MS
                        1938.</note> The written books of Thalaba will be left with <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The first eight books of <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801); now National Library of Wales, MS 1487A.</note> A man when he goes
                    abroad should make his will; and this is all my wealth: be my executor, in case
                    I am summoned upon the grand tour of the universe, and do with them, and with
                    whatever you may find of mine, what may be most advantageous for <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, for my brothers <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> and <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>, and for <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is not much danger in a voyage to Lisbon; my illness
                    threatens little, and faith will probably render the proposed remedy
                    efficacious. In Portugal I shall have but little society; with the English there
                    I have no common feeling. Of course I shall enjoy enough leisure for all my
                    employments. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My uncle</ref> has a
                    good library, and I shall not find retirement irksome.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our summer will probably be passed at <ref target="places.html#Cintra">Cintra</ref>, a place which may be deemed a cool
                    paradise in that climate. I do not look forward to any circumstance with so much
                    emotion as to hearing again the brook which runs by <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle&#8217;s</ref> door. I never beheld
                    a spot that invited to so deep tranquillity. My purposed employments you know.
                    The History<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished &#8216;History
                        of Portugal&#8217;.</note> will be a great and serious work, and I shall labour at
                    preparing the materials assiduously. The various journies necessary in that
                    pursuit will fill a journal, and grow into a saleable volume. On this I
                    calculate: this is a harvest which may be expected; perhaps also a few mushrooms
                    may spring up.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If peace will permit me, I shall return along the south of Spain
                    and over the Pyrenees. <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> little
                    likes her expedition; she wants a female companion, but this cannot be had, and
                    she must learn to be contented without one: moreover, there is at Lisbon a lady
                    of her own age,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Ann Tonkin
                        (dates unknown), daughter of Lisbon-based friends of <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Herbert Hill</ref>. Southey had
                        met her during his first visit to Portugal.</note> for whom I have a
                    considerable regard, and who will not be sorry to see once more an acquaintance
                    with more brains than a calf. She will be our neighbour. <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My uncle</ref> also is a man for whom
                    it is impossible not to feel affection. I wish we were there; the journey is
                    troublesome, and the voyage shockingly unpleasant, from sickness and the
                    constant feeling of insecurity: however, if we have but mild weather, I shall
                    not be displeased at one more lesson in sea scenery.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should willingly have seen <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Moses</ref> again: when I return
                    he will be a new being, and I shall not find the queer boy whom I have been
                    remembering. God bless him! We are all changing; one wishes sometimes that God
                    had bestowed upon us something of his immutability. Age, infirmities, blunted
                    feelings, blunted intellect, these are but comfortless expectancies! but we
                    shall be boys again in the next world.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Coleridge, write often to me. As <hi rend="ital">you</hi> must
                    pay English postage, write upon large paper; as <hi rend="ital">I</hi> must pay
                    Portuguese by weight, let it be thin. My direction need only be, with the <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Rev. Herbert Hill</ref>, Lisbon; he
                    has taken a house for us. We shall thus govern ourselves, and the plea of
                    illness will guarantee me from cards and company and ball-rooms! No! no! I do
                    not wear my old cocked hat again! it cannot, certainly, fit me now.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I take with me for the voyage your poems, the Lyrics, the Lyrical
                    Ballads, and Gebir;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge,
                            <title>Poems</title> (1797); an unidentified edition of Robert Burns
                        (1759&#8211;1796; <title>DNB</title>); Coleridge and Wordsworth, <title>Lyrical
                            Ballads</title> (1798); Walter Savage Landor, <title>Gebir</title>
                        (1798); see Robert Southey to Samuel Taylor Coleridge, [1] May [1800],
                        Letter 516.</note> and, except a few books designed for presents, these make
                    all my library. I like Gebir more and more: if you ever meet its author, tell
                    him I took it with me on a voyage.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;
                    &#160;&#160; . &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .
                    &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; .</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you!</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R. S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>