<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce729</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.720</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library,
                        Add MS 47888.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
                            Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 288-290.Dating note: The letter was begun on Tuesday 21
                        September 1802, not 20 September as stated by Southey.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="720" type="letter">
        <head>720. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith
                        Southey</ref>, <date when="1802-09-21">[21-]23 September [1802]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Kingsdown/ Bristol/ Single<lb />MS: British Library,
                        Add MS 47888<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New
                            Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 288-290.<lb />Dating note: The letter was begun on Tuesday 21
                        September 1802, not 20 September as stated by Southey.</note>
        </head>
        <p>You will have received a letter from Pyle. this goes from Swansea, Tuesday
                    evening 20th Sept. We reached Neath yesterday &amp; after dinner delivered our
                    credentials to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davies.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">David Davis (1778-1846), Unitarian minister and schoolmaster
                        in Neath 1801-1827. His father, David Davis (1745-1827; <title>DNB</title>),
                        was an old friend of the publisher <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Owen
                            Rees&#8217;s</ref> father, Josiah Rees (1744-1804; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
                    that evening we walked to look at a house which perhaps is to be let furnished &#8211;
                    as I think nobody will buy it. it is a lovely place &#8211; but too small. the
                    furniture most expensively elegant &#8211; more showy than good &#8211; a huge swing looking
                    glass as big as I am. five bed rooms but all too little. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> says there is not room to swing a
                    cat &#8211; but I do not want or mean to swing a cat &#8211; but my books would actually
                    fill the house &#8211; &amp; what to do with the boxes! this morning we were
                    introduced to the surgeon at Neath &#8211; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gronow.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Gronow (d. 1830) of Court Herbert, who
                        described himself as &#8216;Surgeon, Apothecary and Man Mid-wife&#8217;.</note> poor man
                    he is in great affliction about one of his children who is dying of dropsy. he
                    tells me of a house &#8211; furnished, which by all accounts will do exactly. on our
                    return to Neath we are to see it. it lies eight miles &#8211; or rather seven &amp; a
                    half from Neath &#8211; but the canal passes within a field of the house &#8211; &amp;
                    affords daily conveyance for what may be wanted. the owner is a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Williams<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Rees Williams (d.
                        1812) of Aberpergym, prominent landowner and coal owner in the Vale of
                        Neath. He was a patron of the literary revival in Glamorganshire.</note> &#8211;
                    who lives in a larger house near &#8211; a married man with a family, who wants a
                    neighbour &#8211; there is moreover a Unitarian Minister &lt;Morgan<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Morgan (1737-1813), pastor and
                        schoolmaster at Blaen-gwrach in the Vale of Neath, 1772-1810.</note> by
                    name&gt; said to be a very clever man. We are to visit M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                    Williams on our return &amp; see this place which is in the finest part of a
                    fine country &#8211; near the river &#8211; &amp; still nearer the canal which brings coals
                    from the pit about six miles off. there is a good garden &#8211; &amp; a field before
                    the house we may have for a cow. I am much pleased with Gronow who seems an
                    interesting man &amp; was uncommonly civil. he is an independant man in his
                    circumstances &#8211; &amp; it would be a great convenience to have the frequent
                    opportunity of seeing him visiting M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Williams as <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> a friend &#8211; &amp; indeed the neighbourhood
                    medically.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We had a very pleasant walk under the guidage of a Mr Smith<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">An unidentified friend of the Unitarian
                        minister David Davis.</note> who lives with Davies &#8211; down to the sands &#8211;
                    &amp; so to Swansea. here I have cut my beautiful blister &#8211; changed my linen &#8211;
                    &amp; am now writing to you &amp; pausing at due intervals to swear for my
                    dinner &#8211; which no ordering &amp; no swearing seems to accelerate.</p>
        <p rend="center"> _____</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> found an acquaintance at Swansea
                    &#8211; &amp; so my letter writing was broken off. the country round that town is not
                    beautiful &#8211; not to be compared with Neath. we had a hard march yesterday of
                    eight &amp; twenty miles thro a hilly tract. which brought us to Caermarthen &#8211;
                    but at the expence of my other foot who I believe must be indulged with a days
                    rest here. we go from hence (Caermarthen) to Llanidlo, 15 miles an easy stage to
                    see Dinevor, thence by Gellignon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rees&#8217;s<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Josiah Rees, Unitarian minister at Gellionen
                        church 1767-1804 and editor of the first Welsh-language periodical,
                            <title>Trysorfa Gwybodaeth</title> (1770); father of the publisher <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Owen Rees</ref>.</note> again to Neath. If
                    you will write by Saturdays mail directed post office Neath &#8211; Glamorganshire the
                    letter will reach me &#8211; &amp; indeed I am anxious to hear of you &#8211; tho but a line
                    to say that you &amp; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">the
                        child</ref> are well. this will reach you tomorrow.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The passion these people have for whitelime is very striking,
                    chimney backs &#8211; church towers &#8211; house-roofs &#8211; garden walls &#8211; even to a single
                    stone in a garden bank &#8211; all are whitelimed &#8211; &amp; this they tell us about once
                    a month. the little stones round their graves whitelimed too. You know the
                    graves are all planted with flowers. the country has disappointed me in most
                    places &#8211; but about Neath it is remarkably fine &amp; the house of which we are
                    in hopes is in the richest part in a vale among mountains. If it turn out a
                    desirable residence which by all accounts seems very probable we shall directly
                    strike home &amp; be with you about Tuesday. the house is called Maes Gwyn. the
                    canal lands coals within a field of the house &#8211; &amp; would bring meat regularly
                    from the Neath butcher. we should soon have a dairy of our own. I started an
                    objection of distance from medical assistance. Gronow answered he rode there in
                    half an hour. I believe him by his looks to be a man whose talents might be
                    trusted, &amp; am sure we should often see him. Of course I shall conclude
                    nothing till I see you &amp; know your opinion. but this seems a very promising
                    place. the climate excellent &#8211; &amp; regular vessels to Bristol which will bring
                    down any body to see us for half-a-crown! a fine conveyance for books &#8211; grocery
                    &#8211; wine &#8211; &amp; porter &#8211; till we learn to brew our own beer. there are also
                    vessels to London &#8211; so that my books will go the whole way by water.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our umbrellas have been of the greatest use. we have regularly
                    mounted them as parasols &amp; swung our hats from the coat button. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is short enough to fasten his
                    umbrella under the belt in his waistcoat pocket. very Robinson Crusoe<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The hero of Daniel Defoe&#8217;s (c. 1659-1731;
                            <title>DNB</title>) <title>Robinson Crusoe</title> (1719), made himself
                        an umbrella on his desert island.</note> figures. add to this an improvement
                    of mine &#8211; the turning up the cuffs of the coat &#8211; which else get wet with
                    perspiration &#8211; it has been cruelly hot. I eat as if I were travelling in
                    Portugal &amp; drink like a fish. but as for Welsh ale alas we have only begged
                    one bottle in the whole way &#8211; &amp; that was the Landlady&#8217;s private stock.
                    oh it was <hi rend="ital">bono!</hi> Bristol porter is the liquor every where &#8211;
                    &amp; excellently good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We dined in the travellers room at Swansea. there came in after
                    dinner the balloon adventurer Barrett<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Barrett (fl. 1780-1814; <title>DNB</title>), balloonist and writer
                        on the occult. His publications included <title>The Magus, or Celestial
                            Intelligencer; Being a Complete System of Occult Philosophy</title>
                        (1801). Barrett had recently given an exhibition of ballooning at
                        Swansea.</note> to spunge a glass of wine. tell <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> I have seen a greater rogue than
                        Solomon.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Solomon (1768/9-1819;
                            <title>DNB</title>), manufacturer and promoter of the best-selling quack
                        medicine &#8216;Cordial Balm of Gilead&#8217;.</note> this same Barrett who took in the
                    people at Greenwich &#8211; &amp; who wrote a book called the Magus &#8211; of which I have
                    seen the title page &amp; his own rascally portrait as frontispiece. My
                    gentleman professes to teach the occult sciences. unhappily I did not know this
                    was the fellow when I saw him else I would have gone thro his sciences &#8211; &amp;
                    he puts all the letters in the Alphabet after his name to look like honorary
                    titles. A dog &#8211; he had better break his neck from a balloon to save the country
                    the expence of hanging him. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tomorrow for Dinevor. today my toes have a holiday. poor toes
                    they have been sorely galled. my feet never used me so badly before but the
                    grand blister is getting well &amp; we shall get on bravely. if Maes Gwyn should
                    not do &#8211; we come home by way of the waterfalls to Merthyr eat a dinner with <ref target="people.html#MaberGeorge">Maber</ref> &#8211; &amp; so from Abergavenny to
                    Tintern &amp; home &#8211; which we shall in that case reach by the fortnights end.
                    you will hear of us as soon as we have seen Maes Gwyn. neglect not to write as
                    soon as you receive this. how is <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Danvers</ref>? remembrance there. God bless you <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1802-09-23">Thursday 23. Sept.</date>
            <placeName>Caermarthen.</placeName>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>