<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce582</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.573</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>British Library, Add MS
                        30928.  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        135-140; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and a
                            Visit to France 1838 (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                        157-160 [in part].</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="573" type="letter">
<head>573. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1801-03-28">28 March
                        1801</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Danvers/ 9 S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> James’s Place/
                        Kingsdown./ Bristol/ Single<lb/>Stamped:
                        FALMOUTH<lb/>MS: British Library, Add MS
                        30928<lb/>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                            <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), I, pp.
                        135-140; Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey:
                            Journals of a Residence in Portugal 1800-1801 and a
                            Visit to France 1838</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp.
                        157-160 [in part].</note>
</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date when="1801-03-28">March 28. 1801.</date>
<address>
<placeName>Lisbon.</placeName>
</address>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
</opener>
<p rend="indent1"> You have not written – &amp; I am rather
                    anxious lest the new Thalaba book should not have reached
                    you. I sent a copy to <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to guard
                    against the accident.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 February
                        1801, Letter 567.</note>
<ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>
                    advertises it a <hi rend="ital">poetical</hi> romance – on
                    the half-title you will take care to use the more proper
                    word <hi rend="ital">metrical</hi>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title>
                        (1801) was sub-titled ‘A Metrical Romance’. It was
                        advertised (or rather, mis-advertised) as a ‘Poetical
                        Romance’ in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 29
                        January and 5 February 1801.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1">
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">My Mother</ref>
                    will show you her letter by this packet<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Margaret Southey
                        [28 March 1801], Letter 574.</note> – the rest of our
                    journey may be comprest into the present sheet.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">For this expedition see
                        Southey’s journal, published in <title>Adolfo Cabral,
                            Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal
                            1800-1801 and a Visit to France 1838</title>
                        (Oxford, 1960), pp. 15-33.</note> I rather hoped than
                    expected to reach Coimbra.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Medieval capital of Portugal and site of
                        the University of Coimbra, founded in 1290.</note>
<ref target="people.html#SetonBarbara">Miss Seton</ref>
                    &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
                    proved such excellent travellers that we reached it. I never
                    saw a city so nobly situated – a view so altogether glorious
                    as opened upon us from its near heights. the preceding day
                    we had<del rend="strikethrough">x</del> been wetted, &amp;
                    for three days threatened with dark &amp; lowering clouds.
                    of course the Sun was welcome – it dried us &amp; warmed us,
                    &amp; made every thing chearful. the country is hilly &amp;
                    well watered – olives &amp; oranges every where, &amp;
                    cypresses thick as poplars about London. mountains bounded
                    the scene – the farthest object was one snowy summit of the
                    Estrella, glittering in the sun. down the southern boundary
                    a few clouds were floating, so beamy white that they seemed
                    like light condensed to visible shape &amp; substance. The
                    city with its fine convents shone on an eminence over the
                    Mondego, now in the fullness of its waters. Coimbra is the
                    spot of which the historian &amp; the poet scarcely ever
                    loses sight – whatever was interesting in the history or
                    literature of Portugal centered here – &amp; I looked at the
                    city with the strong recollection of old times &amp; old
                    heroes. Knowing what to expect within I was prepared for the
                    contrast – yet was it impossible not to feel disappointment
                    at quitting so rich a scene to enter narrow &amp; stinking
                    streets, crowded with blackguard students, or with
                    townspeople rendered vicious &amp; knavish &amp; impudent by
                    the contagion of the University. the first object was
                    disgusting – passing under an old gateway – the prison
                    fronted us. &amp; two gallows-faced fellows fastened with
                    chains round their necks were standing in the street
                    begging. We met several other prisoners dragging their
                    fetters thro the town on the same employment. Every where in
                    Coimbra some relic of antiquity presents itself, but every
                    where it is mixed with modern patches. In the monastery of
                    Santa Cruz, one of the oldest &amp; most famous
                    establishments in the kingdom I saw nothing so remarkable as
                    – the poultry yard. the royal tombs were comparatively
                    modern &amp; miserably poor after what we had seen at
                    Alcobaça &amp; Batalha. the sword of Alfonso Henrique<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Afonso I (1109-1185,
                        King of Portugal 1139-1185). Buried at the Monastery of
                        Santa Cruz in Coimbra. His sword was said to be so large
                        it took ten men to carry it.</note> was mislaid – nor
                    did I regret not seeing <del rend="strikethrough">x</del>
                    what I knew not to be genuine. Relics affected me little –
                    what was a finger of Saint Antony<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">St Antony of Padua (1195-1231).</note>
                    after I had seen a thorn from the Holy Crown of Crucifixion
                    – &amp; a drop of the Redeemers blood? – the Revelations in
                    a set of Tiles pleased me better. the truth or falsehood of
                    a poetical figure is said to be appreciable by painting it –
                    if the rule may be extended to religion certainly the Beast
                    &amp; the Vials &amp; the Old Dragon did not look very
                    believable. But the Poultry Yard was perfect – it was one of
                    the quadrangles converted to this useful purpose – cut with
                    canals of running water over which were several small
                    temples – &amp; such geese &amp; ducks – &amp; another sort
                    of wild water bird to me unknown! – so fat – they ought to
                    have been roasted in the Alcobaça kitchen. I did long to buy
                    beg or steal a dinner. </p>
<p rend="indent1"> The Fountain of Tears was far the most
                    heart-interesting object in this vicinity. it is the spot
                    where Ignes de Castro<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Ines de Castro (1325-1355), lover of Pedro I
                        (1320-1367, King of Portugal 1357-1367). She was
                        murdered on the orders of Pedro’s father, Afonso IV
                        (1291-1357, King of Portugal 1325-1357).</note> was
                    accustomed to meet her husband Pedro, &amp; weep for him in
                    his absence. certainly her dwelling-house was in the
                    adjoining garden &amp; from thence she was dragged to be
                    murdered at the feet of the King her father in law. there is
                    a famous passage in Camoens<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Luis Vaz de Camoens (1524-1580),
                            <title>Os Lusiades</title> (1572), Canto 3, stanzas
                        118-136.</note> upon this subject. it is very bad &amp;
                    therefore very much admired by all poetry-dabblers, being a
                    complete specimen of false taste. but bad poetry does not
                    affect the fact – &amp; the loves of Iñes &amp; Pedro are
                    historically interesting. I – who have long planned a
                    tragedy upon the subject<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
<title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed.
                        John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp.
                        189-190.</note> – stood upon my own scene. two cedars –
                    most magnificent, most antient trees – stand one on each
                    side the fountain. I do believe, &amp; not because I wish to
                    believe it – that Inez sat under their shade four hundred
                    years ago. Who is there who has not when he stood under a
                    fine tree, felt the littleness of mans existence? &amp;
                    these cedars might have made the main beams of Solomons
                    temple – of such luxuriant size is their growth. there is
                    beside them one modern tree – bless the hand that planted
                    it! – a great willow – whose boughs bend into the water.
                    behind the fountain rises a high hill, green with corn &amp;
                    spotted with the shades of olive trees. the whole scene is
                    in my eye – even with the vividness of actual sight. –</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Of Museums &amp; Colleges &amp; Public
                    Buildings – what is to be said? would you not yawn over the
                    description – as we did over the sight? things that might
                    each have excited admiration if seen simply, cloy in a
                    collection, like a dinner of sweet-meats. Of more importance
                    is the moral picture of Coimbra – the spring from whence
                    Portugal is watered. it is Westminster &amp; Oxford united –
                    at once school &amp; university. the students are attached
                    to English literature – indeed to medical studies it is
                    become indispensable. they are also votaries to the French
                    principles. but – a set of more impudent blackguards never
                    were assembled in one city. they followed us with such
                    impertinence that had we not been with two Professors<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Soares
                        Franco (1772-1844), later Professor of Medicine at the
                        University of Coimbra; and Felix Avellar Brotero
                        (1744-1828), Professor of Botany at the University of
                        Coimbra.</note> both men of manners &amp; authority, we
                    should not have past without being insulted – &amp; as it
                    was, I found it difficult to abstain from knocking some of
                    them down. wherever we went there was a mob of these fellows
                    behind us. so it is their custom to annoy foreigners – &amp;
                    two of them for impertinence carried a little further,
                    received a severe drubbing from one of our acquaintance, not
                    long before our visit.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I can only skim the cream of our after
                    journey. our party was swoln to the very inconvenient number
                    of eight when the Miss Petries<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Two sisters resident in Portugal,
                        possibly connected to Martin Petrie (d. 1805), a
                        Commissary in the British Army.</note> rejoined us &amp;
                    brought with them two men of their acquaintance.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The brother of the Misses
                        Petrie, possibly William Petrie (d. 1842), later
                        Commissary-General in the British Army; and an army
                        surgeon called Burrows (first name and dates
                        unknown).</note> with our followers we made a formidable
                    appearance winding at length up the rocky lanes like a
                    caravan. At Aldea de Cruz the only Estalagem had been
                    converted into a saltfish warehouse. Corregidor of the Place
                    very handsomely sent beds for the Ladies – but two of our
                    party actually lay upon piles of saltfish – &amp; I slept
                    sweetly under them. At Thomar we were entertained by a
                    Frenchman. M. Verdier<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Timoteo Lecussan Verdier (1754-1831),
                        Portuguese man of letters and mill-owner. He was of
                        French origin.</note> to whom I had letters. a man of
                    most uncommon learning &amp; genius – who has wasted his
                    talents &amp; fortune in establishing a great cotton
                    manufactory. his wife<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Elena Frizoni (dates unknown).</note> is
                    very very clever – they have several children who all speak
                    four languages which – with music &amp; drawing their mother
                    has taught them. here I feasted upon all my favourite
                    conversation dishes. it was the sort of family that novels
                    sometimes represent – but which I never elsewhere saw
                    realized. curse the manufactory. that a man who ought to be
                    at the head of a great nation should be managing mills &amp;
                    wheels! – We returned fourscore miles down the Tagus by
                    water, &amp; reached Lisbon after an absence of twenty
                    days.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> One anecdote is worth mentioning. we were
                    every where the sight of the neighbourhood – a boy on his
                    way to school stopt to see <del rend="strikethrough">him</del> us. he had his book under his arm &amp; I was
                    anxious to see what a fine clever looking boy about 14 might
                    be learning. it was “Directions for a converted Sinner.”
                    poor boy! I longed for the translation of Robinson
                        Crusoe<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel
                        Defoe (c. 1659-1731; <title>DNB</title>),
                            <title>Robinson Crusoe</title> (1719). The first
                        Portuguese translation was <title>Vida e Aventuras de
                            Robinson Crusoe. Traduzido da Lingua Franceza por
                            Henrique Leitao de Souza Mascarenhas</title>
                        (1785).</note> to give him.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> Of our return. We expect Portugal to make her
                        peace<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Spain had
                        declared war on Portugal on 27 February 1801 and a
                        Spanish invasion was widely expected.</note> by the
                    expulsion of the English. my <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Uncle</ref> is
                    actually packing up all his books – &amp; I am writing in
                    the dirt of that employment. according to all appearances
                    only a general peace can prev[MS obscured] the last blow to
                    our commerce. I am little affected – except indeed that the
                    war with Spain has cut off my supply of books &amp; very
                    very very materially affected me – as the only remedy will
                    be to visit Lord Bute<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">John Stuart, 1st Marquess of Bute
                        (1744-1814; <title>DNB</title>), Ambassador to Spain
                        1795-1796.</note> &amp; quarter myself upon him &amp;
                    his library. In May we hope to be in England – that is in
                    Bristol. my after plans may be considered there. they will
                    probably – for Madocs sake take me into Wales – &amp; then
                    to the Lakes – I must work hard, for here my expences have
                    exceeded my means – unavoidably rather than unwisely. the
                    sale of Thalaba is of importance to me. if it be as it ought
                    I shall gallop thro the Curse of Keradou.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s plan for what
                        became <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810),
                            <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood
                        Warter, 4 series (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp.
                        12-15.</note> my history must be slower work.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s uncompleted
                        ‘History of Portugal’.</note> pyramids are not built in
                    a day – &amp; I mean mine to outlive &amp; out-age the
                    Egyptian ones. our love to <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        D.</ref>
</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
<signed rend="indent2"> R S.</signed>
</closer>
<lb/>
<postscript>
<p>
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> sadly
                        wanted the cloak on her journey – which her sisters<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith’s unmarried
                            sisters <ref target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Martha and Eliza Fricker</ref>.</note> so very
                        idly &amp; uncivilly refused to purchase. she was much
                        disappointed at opening the box – &amp; much
                        inconvenienced &amp; still more hurt. you have received
                        15£ I trust from <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John
                            May</ref> – &amp; I hope paid <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> the
                        extra amount of the first bill.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith ... first bill: Written upside
                            down in the space between the date and salutation on
                            the first page.</note>
</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
