<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce680</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.671</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.671" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="671" type="letter">
        <head>671. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1802-04-18">18 April [1802]</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Kingsdown/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped: BATH<lb />MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write because <ref target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace Bedford</ref> is going to Bath &amp; can so far frank the letter.
                        <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Kings</ref> did not go by <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">Losh</ref> as you imagined but by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Keenan<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Keenan,
                        n&#233;e MacKinnon, wife of John Keenan (fl. c. 1780-1819), Irish portrait
                        painter, whom Southey had met in Exeter in 1799. Keenan painted two
                        portraits of Southey.</note> who I thought would have made Bristol in her
                    way to Exeter. Tell <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Rex</ref> to make his
                        vignette<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The subject of the
                        &#8216;vignettte&#8217; was the muniment room in St Mary Redcliffe, Bristol, where
                        Thomas Chatterton had supposedly discovered manuscripts by the monk Thomas
                        Rowley (c. 1400-1470). John King&#8217;s drawing was used for the engraving
                        opposite the title page of <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title>, 3
                        vols (London, 1803), II, unpaginated. It was entitled &#8216;Interior of the Room
                        in Redcliff Church where Rowleys Manuscripts were Said to have been
                        Deposited&#8217;. The youth, the scroll and King himself were all omitted from the
                        final version.</note> just what size he thinks best proportioned to an
                    octavo title page. I should object to the youth &amp; scroll because that seems
                    to admit that the papers were found there, which assuredly they were not. a
                    visitor may be put there &#8211; he himself if he likes it making the drawing. I have
                    this morning seen his friend M. Voullaire<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">He could be connected to the J.A. Voullaire (first name and dates unknown),
                        whose French translation of <title>The Vicar of Wakefield</title> was
                        published in 1811.</note> &amp; as far as half an hours conversation can
                    justify, admire him much. I am going in spite of half a hundred other
                    occupations to acquire by his help a grammatical command of French. On Tuesday
                    evening he commences his visits &#8211; &amp; if I do not profit by them &#8211; in
                    conscience it will be the fault of the scholar.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> is here. it was a mistake
                    of Jibletts<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> that he
                    was going to Bristol. Lord Stanhope<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Burnett&#8217;s erstwhile employer, Charles (&#8216;Citizen&#8217;) Stanhope, 3rd Earl
                        Stanhope (1753-1816; <title>DNB</title>), eventually paid him &#163;200, a year&#8217;s
                        salary.</note> has not yet given him the salary &#8211; but he will I suppose
                    receive it as soon as they meet. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George</ref> feels a little too comfortable upon the certainty of a years
                    funds. however I hope that I have found him a job from <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> &#8211; to translate a French book, which
                    will at least keep him two months, &amp; perhaps introduce him to more work till
                    he find a steadier &amp; better employ. &#8211; In my last letter to <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> I mentioned that preliminaries were
                    going on between me &amp; the booksellers. I have undertaken to reduce Amadis de
                    Gaule into three duodecimo volumes for them, anonymously.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s translation of the romance
                            <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> appeared in four volumes in 1803.</note>
          <del rend="strikethrough">not like</del> Tressan in his french abridgement has
                    too much modernised the language &amp; Frenchified the feeling of the book.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis Elizabeth de la Vergne de Broussin,
                        Comte de Tressan (1705-1783), <title>Traduction Libre d&#8217;Amadis de
                            Gaule</title> (1780).</note> I take the old English translation,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Anthony Munday (c. 1560-1633;
                            <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Ancient, Famous and Honourable History
                            of Amadis de Gaule</title> (1589-1619).</note> &amp; compress it, as
                    nearly as may be into the &lt;same&gt; language &#8211; which <del rend="strikethrough">x</del> is by no means obsolete &#8211; not more so than the
                    Bible, &amp; <del rend="strikethrough">this</del> best suits the character of
                    the book. I prefix an Essay on Romance. for this they offered me, with my name
                    to the <hi rend="ital">Essay only</hi>, 100 &#163;. It would have been imprudent to
                    let my name appear &#8211; because the notion that I am <del rend="strikethrough">of</del> a man of business may help me on in the world. they then offered
                    60 &#163; when the book was done, &amp; when 750 were sold the remaining 40. &#163;. I
                    have bargained for 30 &#163; more if a second 750 sell. the definitive answer is not
                    yet come &#8211; but I have no doubt they will accede to the terms. <ref target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref> said so, &amp; only the formality
                    remains of <ref target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> assent. Now as
                    my name is not to be publickly known, neither should it privately. I am trying
                    to persuade them to have vignettes, which if I can effect I would beg <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> to design, &amp; take the fair
                    price for them which the booksellers usually pay. &amp; so sure am I that with
                    the subjects which I should chuse, a print in the title page would encrease the
                    sale of the book, that if they will not otherwise accede, I will propose to them
                    to risque a ten pounds of my own certain profit. There is a farther view in this
                    job. if the book sells which is highly probable from its name &amp; excellence,
                    they will go thro the whole army of Romances in the same manner &#8211; indeed this is
                    meant as an experiment with that in view.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sales were good enough for Longman and Rees to commission and publish
                        Southey&#8217;s translations of <title>Palmerin of England</title> (1807) and the
                            <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (1808).</note> Now I believe that
                    Edith can help me at this work, &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> also &#8211; whom, if the book sells &amp; the
                    plan proceed I could thus enable comfortably &amp; respectably to maintain
                    herself. you see another reason for anonymousness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have talked more with <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> about the probability of your brother Johns<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably the surgeon and apothecary, John
                        Danvers (d. 1812), then of Woolwich, London, declared bankrupt in
                            <title>The National Register</title> (3 July 1808), 426.</note> setting
                    up in London. he thinks there would be little chance of success. that the trade
                    here is overstocked, &amp; that to succeed many <del rend="strikethrough">&amp;
                        xxx</del> friends are necessary, &amp; money enough to be able to wait for
                    practise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref>
                    had no partner. he managed all <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                        Uncles</ref> church affairs, granting leases &amp;c &#8211; which must now be put
                    into the hands of a stranger, instead of a friend. the money which he had in his
                    hands will of course be paid by his Executors &#8211; but God knows when &#8211; nor can I
                    draw for it upon them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> is just called to walk with
                    me to <ref target="places.html#Brixton">Brixton</ref> &#8211; where this must go to
                    the Postman. so perforce I conclude. We shall see you in a month &#8211; &amp; I hope
                    we <del rend="strikethrough">sha</del> may find <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> D.</ref> well. I
                    think she will be amused &amp; interested with the progress of Amadis which is
                    truly a delightful book.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
          <lb />
          <date when="1802-04-18">Sunday April 18.</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>