<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
<author>
<name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
</author>
<editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>General Editor, </resp>
<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt>
<edition>
<date>2011-08-15</date>
</edition>
</editionStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<idno type="nines">rce799</idno>
<idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.790</idno>
<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
<date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
<availability status="restricted">
<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
<addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
<addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
<addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
<addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
<addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</p>
<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<p>MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick Jnr, ‘The Letters
                        of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826’ (unpublished PhD,
                        Harvard, 1967), pp. 44-48 [where it is dated 1 June
                        1803].  Not previously published.</p>
<p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
<p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
<p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<quotation>
<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
</quotation>
<hyphenation eol="none">
<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
<p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
</hyphenation>
<normalization method="markup">
<p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
</normalization>
<normalization>
<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
</normalization>
</editorialDecl>
<classDecl>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
<category xml:id="g1">
<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g2">
<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g3">
<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g4">
<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g5">
<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g7">
<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g6">
<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g8">
<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g9">
<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g10">
<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g11">
<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g12">
<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g13">
<catDesc>History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g14">
<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g15">
<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g16">
<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g17">
<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g18">
<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g19">
<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g20">
<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g21">
<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g22">
<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g23">
<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g24">
<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g25">
<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g26">
<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g27">
<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g28">
<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g29">
<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g30">
<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g31">
<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g32">
<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g33">
<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
</category>
<category xml:id="g34">
<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
<category xml:id="people">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
<taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
<category xml:id="places">
<catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
</category>
</taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/>
<catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/>
<catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
<list>
<item>XSLT Transforming</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name>Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>corrections from proofing</item>
</list>
</change>
<change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
<label>Changed by</label>
<name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
<list>
<item>Part II added</item>
</list>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div n="790" type="letter">
<head>790. Robert Southey and <ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith
                        Southey</ref> to <ref target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary Barker</ref>,
                        <date when="1803-05-30">[late May-]1 June 1803</date>
<note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ Miss Barker/ Congreve/ near
                        Penkridge/ Staffordshire<lb/>Postmark: [partial] TOL 803<lb/>MS: MS
                        untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick Jnr, ‘The Letters
                        of Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826’ (unpublished PhD,
                        Harvard, 1967), pp. 44-48 [where it is dated 1 June
                        1803]<lb/>Unpublished.</note>
</head>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3"> D. D. stands for Daughter Drivel</l>
<l rend="indent3">
<ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">M. S.</ref> for Margaret
                        Snivel.</l>
<l rend="indent4"> N.B. she has a cold in her head.</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Her mouth it is from ear to ear,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> Her forehead bunches out – </l>
<l rend="indent3"> She has a cold in her grey eyes,</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And her nose is like a snout.</l>
</lg>
<p rend="indent1"> Better late than never if not among the Proverbs of King
                        Solomon,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Solomon (c. 1011-931 BC,
                        King of Israel c. 971-931 BC) was traditionally ascribed authorship of the
                            <title>Book of Proverbs</title>.</note> is one of my proverbs &amp; will
                    serve as a text to a long delayed letter.</p>
<p rend="indent1"> We are still in quest of a house &amp; still without success –
                    but – whenever you come the better pleased shall we be: <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> is gone to fight the French
                    &amp; we can offer you his bed – to have offered you half of it you know would
                    not have been exactly proper. And here is <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> almost old
                    enough to learn the rest of her commandments, for you must know I have made a
                    sort of synopsis of the law &amp; gospel adapted for her tender years &amp;
                    condensed into one commandment. ‘thou shalt not heydiddlediddle thy father.’ If
                    you were here I should have one job which would I am sure please you to do for
                    me – to copy a drawing – a likeness – a <hi rend="ital">portrait</hi>, drawn in
                    India – &amp; from the life of the Simorg.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In Persian mythology, a fabulous bird; it features in
                            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 11.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> And I will show you here a clump of trees whose fluted &amp;
                    twisted trunks, &amp; bare roots, would beyond all comparison form the finest
                    study for a painter that ever I beheld. &amp; which are worth coming from <ref target="places.html#Congreve">Congreve</ref> to study. do trees grow in
                    Staffordshire? &amp; I will show you the Boiling Well<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Boiling-Well, a spring near <ref target="places.html#StokesCroft">Stoke’s Croft</ref>, Bristol; described
                        in Southey’s <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 11, lines
                        361-373.</note> which no painter can paint &amp; if you attempt any thing in
                    the Cipriani style<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Giovanni Battista
                        Cipriani (1727–1785) introduced the Italian high baroque designs for
                        ceilings and interiors into England in 1755 and was one of the founding
                        members of the Royal Academy.</note> – the little naked Loves – I will show
                    you a live Cupid.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Danvers’s
                        dog.</note> And I will show you Garci Ferrandez<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Garci Ferrandez’ was dated ‘Bristol, 1801’ in
                            Southey’s<title> Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837-1838),
                        VI, p. 121. However it does not seem to have been published until nearly a
                        decade after its composition, first appearing in the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                            Register for 1809</title>, 2 vols (Edinburgh, 1811), II, pp.
                        637-641.</note> finished, &amp; K Ramiro &amp; his wicked Wife,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘King Ramiro’, <title>Morning Post</title>, 9
                        September 1803.</note> &amp; Queen Urraca &amp; the five Martyrs of
                        Morocco.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Queen Urraca, And The Five
                        Martyrs of Morocco’, <title>Morning Post</title>, 1 September 1803.</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> One other inducement I know not if it be quite delicate to
                    mention. a gentleman – a single gentleman – &amp; a great favourite of yours who
                    you saw in London – &amp; – who admires you greatly, is come to reside in
                    Bristol – &amp; – if you come to visit us who knows what may happen? I however
                    do beforehand stipulate &amp; insist that I do have a large portion of the
                    wedding cake if you should espouse the Author of Alfred.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle, <title>Alfred, An Epic Poem, in Twenty-Four
                            Books</title> (1800).</note>
</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I have done a world of work here in Bristol. Amadis<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s translation of <title>Amadis of
                            Gaul</title> (1803).</note> four volumes – of which two are printed
                    &amp; the other two printing &amp; all my part done. if you do not like that
                    book I’ll cut my ears off, if indeed it would not be more proper to
                    inflict that operation upon yours. &amp; so many dull books I have reviewed that
                    I have used up all my stock of paper. &amp; some Madoc &amp; some Kehama &amp; a
                    great deal of History.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
                        finished a version of <title>Madoc</title> in 1797-1799 and was revising it
                        for publication; he had also reached Book 3 of <title>The Curse of
                            Kehama</title> (1810) and was working on his unfinished ‘History of
                        Portugal’.</note> – Oh – I thought I had something to say. <ref target="people.html#SmithElizabeth">A Lady</ref> whom I know &amp; like very
                    much, has made a curious collection of hand writings. now if you could give me a
                    scrap – a letter would be better – of Charlotte Smiths<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte Smith (1749-1806; <title>DNB</title>), poet and
                        novelist, and friend of Mary Barker.</note> – &amp; of Mrs Inchbalds<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Inchbald (1753–1821;
                            <title>DNB</title>), novelist and dramatist.</note> for that collection,
                    to give her – I should be very much obliged by being thus enabled to oblige
                    her.</p>
<p>[start of section in Edith Southey’s hand]</p>
<p rend="indent1"> I am glad there is no date to this letter for I should be ashamed
                    were you to know how long it has lain in this unfinished state, &amp; all my
                    fault, I requested it might be left for me to finish but this god daughter of
                    yours occupies so much of my time I have no leisure for anything. This is a
                    pretty scrawl of Southeys &amp; some nonsense I think, notwithstanding, I beg
                    you will attend to its contents I mean the part which concerns your coming, to
                    Bristol do lay by your <hi rend="ital">Weasel</hi>
<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">A pun on ‘easel’.</note> &amp; come, bring some of your small
                    Tackle with you, you will find plenty of employment in this neighbourhood, I
                    expect you will paint all our pictures, Southey says if he cannot get a <hi rend="ital">Weasel</hi> here for you he has no doubt but he can procure a
                        <hi rend="ital">Ferret</hi> there being several Rabbit Warrens near us, how
                    exceedingly witty he is, How do you like this his first Poem upon <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref>, you must come
                    to see her, from his description you will think her a little monster. I assure
                    you she is not so ugly. her eyes are not grey, neither are they sore. her face
                    is full of intelligence she is almost too lively, she will soon manage me, if
                    she want anything of me she can help herself. as you are such an excellent
                    manager of children do come &amp; be here at the weaning, yet no I shall not
                    wean her these three months &amp; we will not wait so long for your coming as
                    that. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> has cut
                    one tooth at last. &amp; left off her cap –</p>
<p>[end of section in Edith Southey’s hand]</p>
<lg type="stanza">
<l rend="indent3"> Miss Snivel in great sooth</l>
<l rend="indent4"> Has got a snag tooth.</l>
<l rend="indent3"> And by very good hap</l>
<l rend="indent4"> She has left off her cap</l>
</lg>
<p>[start of section in Edith Southey’s hand]</p>
<p>it was not enough for me to tell you in Prose but he must tak <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> pen &amp; tell it you in verse – If I were
                    you I should be provok <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del> burn his letters
                    before I had read them half thro with his trumpery Poetry. I have been obliged
                    at last to send Bella<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Southeys’
                        servant, she died in 1804.</note> home to Cumberland, she has scarcely been
                    well a month together since we left London, she had the Influenza &amp; has not
                    been well since I hope you all escaped it at <ref target="places.html#Congreve">Congreve</ref>. we were all ill in the house, except <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary</ref>, we lost our good friend &amp;
                    neighbour <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">Mrs. Danvers</ref>, of whom you
                    must have heard us speak very frequently. I am afraid there was some truth in
                    what you heard in the stage Coach concerning the Keenans,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">John Keenan (fl. 1780–1819), portrait painter
                        and miniaturist. Mrs Keenan (dates unknown) was the sister of Daniel
                        MacKinnon (fl. 1800s), whose <title>Tour through the British West
                            Indies</title> (1804) was reviewed by Southey in the <title>Annual
                            Review for 1804</title>, 3 (1805), 50–56. Mrs Keenan apparently went to
                        Boulogne with Miss Barker in 1819 and was still there with her daughter when
                        Southey visited Boulogne in 1825.</note> a very intimate friend of Mrs
                    Keenans told Southey the reason Mrs. K. did not remain in London with her
                    husband was because he kept a mistress, drank a good deal, &amp; neglected his
                    business. if it be true (I fear it is for this young lady corresponds with Mrs
                    K.) I am exceedingly sorry for her, she expects daily to be confined, dont you
                    think he must be a great hypocrite?</p>
<p rend="indent1"> many persons who saw Southeys picture in the Exhibition<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John Keenan’s portrait of Southey,
                        exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1803.</note> were exceedingly pleased with
                    it, they said there was no occasion to look in the Catalogue for it, it was so
                    good a likeness. Pray write soon and say when we shall see you, &amp; dont fret
                    yourself to <hi rend="ital">Fiddle-strings</hi> about the subject of your last
                    letter to me.</p>
<closer>
<salute rend="indent2"> God bless you –</salute>
<signed rend="indent3">
<ref target="people.html#FrickerEdith">E-S</ref>
</signed>
</closer>
<postscript>
<p>June the first. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">Margaret</ref> is nine months old to day. <ref target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> send their love to you.
                        remember me to your Sister.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary
                            Barker had at least two sisters whose names and dates are
                            unrecorded.</note>
</p>
<p>[end of section in Edith Southey’s hand]</p>
</postscript>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
