<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2010-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.663</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2010-08-15">August 15, 2010</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 30928.  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 272-275.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-08-15" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2010-07-22" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2010-06-27" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>TEI Encoding</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="663" type="letter">
        <head>663. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles Danvers</ref>, <date when="1802-03-23">23 March 1802</date>
          <note place="foot" resp="editors" type="headnote">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Danvers/ Kingsdown/ Bristol<lb />Stamped: [illegible]<lb />Postmark: CMR/ 23/ 802<lb />Endorsements: 1-9-6 on address sheet, plus other numbers on 29 r: 4-7- / 1-10-6 / 2-16-6 / 4-7-. [These are possibly lottery tickets.]<lb />MS: British Library, Add MS 30928<lb />Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), I, pp. 272-275.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">	For three reasons I have delayed writing so long &#8211; because now <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is arrived I wanted to tell you what he said about your brother,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably the surgeon and apothecary, John Danvers, then of Woolwich, London, declared bankrupt in <title>The National Register</title> (3 July 1808), 426.</note> but <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> is so busy that there is no seeing him, and as he sleeps at a Coffee house &#8211; no finding him. I am fearful he has no interest in the military line &#8211; &amp; still more so that the Aid de Camps are generally friends of the General. secondly &#8211; because I wanted the said <ref target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> to get a frank for you &amp; <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> to whom I have written some days since, &amp; still keep his letter in durance &#8211; &amp; thirdly in expectation of receiving money from <ref target="people.html#ThomasWilliamBowyer">Thomas</ref> &amp; forwarding it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Your letter came last night. this morning I went to Bish<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Bish (fl. 1790-1826), a well-known lottery office-keeper at 4 Cornhill, London.</note> &#8211; but they can do no business till <hi rend="ital">after three</hi>. I shall purchase these in time for tomorrows twenty thousand. Tomorrow or next day I will enquire concerning the sermons.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sermons, By the Late Rev. David Jardine, of Bath. Published from the Original Manuscripts, by the Rev. John Prior Estlin</title> (1798).</note> I have a heavy job upon my hands. To day the Museum<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The British Museum, London, founded in 1759.</note> doors were opened to me &amp; alack &amp;-a-well-a-day I find not less than 1500 unpublished lines of Chatterton to transcribe from manuscripts not always the most legible. however this will give the book a value.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Joseph Cottle&#8217;s planned subscription edition of <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title>, eventually published in 1803.</note> tho between you &amp; I, neither you or I are likely to be delighted with poetry upon temporary or local subjects &#8211; wit &amp; genius wasted. tis a toil to read Churchill.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The satirical poet Charles Churchill (1732-1764; <title>DNB</title>).</note> A bookseller offered me fifty pounds worth of books last week to edit the works of Sir Charles Hanbury Williams.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Hanbury Williams (1708-1759; <title>DNB</title>), diplomat and writer. Southey&#8217;s refusal of the commission, even though his own name would not have appeared in the published edition, was undoubtedly connected to Williams&#8217;s reputation for obscenity. It is fascinating to speculate how Southey would have dealt with verses such as these from Williams&#8217;s an &#8216;Ode to Horatio Townshend&#8217; (1740): &#8216;Come to my Breast, my Lovely Boy!/ Thou Source of Greek &amp; Roman Joy!/ And let my Arms entwine&#8217; ye;/ Behold my strong erected Tarse,/ Display your plump, &amp; milk-white arse,/ Young, blooming, Ligurine!&#8217; The editors are extremely grateful to Dr Richard Butterwick for supplying this example.</note> lead us not into temptation! &#8211; I looked over the papers &#8211; I liked his wit &#8211; I did not like his dullness &#8211; but fifty pounds of books would have gilt that pill &#8211; but my gentleman was not quite so decent as he should be &#8211; &amp; so I lost my books. my name was not required for the work.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">			As for <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Cottell</ref>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">			He&#8217;s exceedingly well</l>
          <l rend="indent4">				And another po<hi rend="ital">emm</hi> he has writed,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">			About John the Baptizer,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle&#8217;s &#8216;John the Baptist&#8217; had first appeared in his <title>Poems</title> (1795). In 1802 he published a new version, <title>John the Baptist: A Poem</title>.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">			Twill not make you wiser</l>
          <l rend="indent4">				Nor will you be over-delighted.</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">			It was you may guess</l>
          <l rend="indent3">			The first fruits of his press &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent4">				To me he presented a copy &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">			Some Bards ere they sing</l>
          <l rend="indent3">			Quaff from Castaly spring,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Castalian Spring at Delphi, the well of poetic inspiration, as it was the centre of a cult of Apollo, Greek god of poetry.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent4">				But <ref target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph</ref> takes <del rend="strikethrough">a xxx</del> syrup of poppy.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A soporific.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">	I see much of <ref target="people.html#LoshJames">Losh</ref> who desires to be remembered to you. it is not unlikely that you may see him soon, as he talks of going to Bath before his return to Newcastle. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Skey<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Skey (dates unknown). Probably a physician practising in or near Bristol.</note>  called here yesterday, he also desired to be mentioned <del rend="strikethrough">when</del> in my next letter. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">George Burnett</ref> still abideth with the Earl,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Burnett&#8217;s then employer, the controversial politician and inventor Charles (&#8216;Citizen&#8217;) Stanhope, 3rd Earl Stanhope (1753-1816; <title>DNB</title>).</note> he eateth with him, drinketh with him, &amp; seditionizeth &#8211; for which he is well qualified, coming from a good school. Of <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> no tidings have yet been received. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdith">Edith</ref> is still in the same poor &amp; pitiable &amp; pill-taking way. we are soon going for two or three days to Cheshunt &#8211; to visit two <ref target="people.html#DoliognonLouisa">old Ladies</ref>, who were so exceedingly kind to me when a school boy that I have never felt any thing like resentment <del rend="strikethrough">for</del> &lt;at&gt; the way in which they avoided me for some years<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">They would have avoided Southey because of the controversy surrounding his expulsion from Westminster School in 1792 over the authorship of a blasphemous essay in the schoolboy magazine <title>The Flagellant</title>.</note> &#8211; I was a good deal affected at the manner in which one of this family made the amende honorable<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. a satisfactory apology. The apology was made by Mrs Dolignon&#8217;s daughter, Mrs Dauncey, who was married to Philip Dauncey (d. 1819), a barrister.</note> &#8211; for it lay upon their conscience &#8211; . This change will do <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdith">Edith</ref> good &#8211; &amp; you will think me right in resolving to plead her health as a cause, God knows, a valid one, for an early removal to Bristol. I will come if possible before the end of the next month.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref> is still waiting for his passport or rather for the Definitive Treaty which assuredly will soon be here.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Treaty of Amiens, between Britain and France, was signed on 25 March 1802.</note> he dines with me to day, &amp; we go to hear <ref target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> lecture upon Galvinism in the evening.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Davy was lecturing at the Royal Institution. Luigi Galvani (1737-1798), Italian doctor and physicist, had conducted experiments on frogs and shown the link between electricity and muscular activity.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Joseph Lovell<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The brother of the late Robert Lovell (see <ref target="people.html#Lovellfamily">Lovell family</ref>).</note> has at last extorted from his rascally father a promise of twenty pounds for <ref target="people.html#LovellRobert">Roberts</ref> expence till the next year. upon this he must board with his grandmother, &amp; go merely for instruction to <ref target="people.html#EstlinJohnPrior">Estlin</ref>. when we come to Bristol I suppose <ref target="people.html#LovellMary">Mary</ref> will live with him as before at my expence &#8211; for in lodgings he cannot be with me, nor indeed should I like it in a house. he would disturb me, or I must restrain him. &amp; moreover without some particular cause for affection I am not fond of children. &#8211; What do you mean about D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fox?<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Long Fox (1761-1835), proprietor of a lunatic asylum at Brislington, near Bristol.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">	My History<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s projected &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> would wholly employ me but for the Chatterton business<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Joseph Cottle&#8217;s planned subscription edition of <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title>, eventually published in 1803.</note> which takes up more time than is agreable. next week that will be in the press. I shall send the old poems first that the spelling &amp; management of the page may be under my own eye.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">	Every review of a book, every notice of a work published, in the Monthly Magazine, or at the end of a Volume &#8211; is to be taxed as an advertisement.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The extension of the advertisement tax in 1802 was part of a package of fund-raising measures. It was not repealed until 1853.</note> this will operate as a tax upon literature fully equal to the duty on paper should that be repealed.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">An excise duty on paper had been charged since 1712. It was not repealed until 1861.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">	Our love to <ref target="people.html#DanversMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Danvers</ref>.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">		God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">			Robert Southey.</signed>
          <date>Tuesday. March 23. 1802.</date>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Quarter &#8211; 41,920 </p>
          <p>Eighth &#8211; 9,654 &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160; &#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#8211; for which I have paid 1-10-6. balance the prizes were 6-10-6</p>
          <p> the new tickets &#8211; 8-1- </p>
          <p rend="indent3">			&amp; so good luck t&#8217;ye! <note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Quarter...t&#8217;ye: Written upside down at the end of the letter. The numbers refer to lottery tickets.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>