<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 2: 1798-1803 </title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2011-08-15</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="nines">rce872</idno>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.863</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2011-08-15">August 15, 2011</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>.  Previously  published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                            Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 340-342.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.863" />
          </analytic>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-08-15" n="4">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming after latest corrections</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#LM" when="2011-07-06" n="3">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
        <list>
          <item>XSLT Transforming</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-03-20" n="2">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>corrections from proofing</item>
        </list>
      </change>
      <change who="#AB" when="2011-02-21" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name xml:id="AB">Averill Buchanan</name>
        <list>
          <item>Part II added</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="863" type="letter">
        <head>863. Robert Southey to <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Charles
                        Danvers</ref>, <date when="1803-12-09">9 December
                        1803</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                        Danvers/ Bristol./ Single<lb />Stamped:
                        [illegible]<lb />Postmark: [partial] E/ DEC 12.<lb />MS:
                        British Library, Add MS 47890<lb />Previously published:
                        Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                            Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                        I, pp. 340-342.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline rend="right">
            <date when="1803-12-09">Friday Dec. 9. 1803.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <epigraph>
          <p rend="right">
            <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> goes off in a few days for
                            Madeira.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge did not leave for Madeira. He went to
                            Malta in April 1804.</note>
          </p>
        </epigraph>
        <opener>
          <salute>Dear Danvers</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am grieved to hear of your ill health &#8211; for
                    Gods sake take every possible precaution. <ref target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref>
                    recommends a leathern waistcoat next the skin as better than
                    flannel &#8211; soft washing-leather. he says this is the best
                    preservative against our destructive climate. Of course this
                    can cure no complaint, but it may prevent fresh colds &amp;
                    any aggravation. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My chief motive for writing thus immediately
                    on the receipt of yours is a suspicion that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyMargaretEdithdau">my vagabond
                        brother Edward</ref> may apply to you for money, in
                    which case you must refuse him. He writes to me some ten
                    days ago that <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his
                        Aunt</ref> has persuaded him to leave his ship that he
                    &#8220;might smooth the pillow of her declining age&#8221; &amp;c &#8211;
                    accordingly he had done so &#8211; quarrelled with her afterwards
                    &#8211; &amp; then knew not what he should have done if some M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Barham<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Barham Foster-Barham (1763-1822), a
                        wealthy merchant in the West India trade and partner in
                        Plummer, Barham &amp; Co. How Edward Southey had made
                        his acquaintance is unclear.</note> of Exeter had not
                    invited him to spend his Christmas there. the whelp then
                    writes to let me know this &#8211; to say he will follow what line
                    of life I chuse &#8211; &amp; to ask for money. I lost no time in
                    telling him he must go to sea again &amp; sent him twenty
                    shillings just to pay his washing bills till a ship could be
                    procured &#8211; not chusing to supply him with more. this letter
                    of his was directed to Bristol. Yesterday another letter
                    with the same direction found me out, from some low
                    tradesman by the writing enclosing a bill for five pounds
                    thirteen, for acceptance drawn on me by this wretched boy &#8211;
                    &amp; stating that <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E. S.</ref> had said I was
                    duly advised. After consulting with <ref target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, &amp; knowing that such conduct must
                    be decidedly stopt at the first I have refused to accept the
                    bill &amp; told the holder that not being advised of the
                    cause &amp; occasion I was at a loss to conceive what could
                    have been the circumstances that could have justified a
                    respectable tradesman in cashing a bill for a boy of
                    fifteen. I wrote to him to tell him he might learn by this
                    lesson how I was resolved to act toward him, &#8211; for every
                    good purpose I was ready to exert myself for his assistance
                    to my utmost &#8211; but never would become his accomplice in any
                    wrong action by giving my after consent or connivance.
                    Unless I had acted thus you will feel that I should never be
                    safe. the Boy as you know has no shame &#8211; &amp; I fear no
                    principle or feeling of good to supply its place. The little
                    that he can suffer now may prevent a more severe evil
                    hereafter. on what pretext he had taken up the money I know
                    not &#8211; this is certain that there can have been no good one &#8211;
                    &amp; that if I permitted him to incur debts upon my credit
                    at his mercy &#8211; I should very soon become involved myself. It
                    is by no means impossible that he may apply to you, it would
                    be quite in character with that impudence which will be his
                    ruin. <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> will
                    procure him a ship &amp; I shall supply him with means to
                    join it. from the present scrape he must get out as he can
                    by refunding or returning what he may have received. the
                    more he is frightened the better. if he writes to you you
                    will know in what tone to answer him &#8211; &amp; I beseech you
                    if <ref target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Tyler</ref> should make any such
                    application for him or for herself answer to the same
                    purport. Of the curses of life worthless relations are the
                    worst &#8211; I may apply <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>
                    lines &amp; say of Death that my mind &#8211; Mourns less for what
                    he takes away Than what he leaves behind!<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth,
                            <title>Lyrical Ballads, with Other Poems</title>, 2
                        vols (London, 1800), II, p. 129, &#8216;The Fountain&#8217;, lines
                        35-36.</note> It is a sad thing to have ties of duty
                    where there is neither affection nor esteem. I love <ref target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> for he has a
                    warm heart &amp; would go thro fire &amp; water for me as I
                    would for him. as for the other two &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>
                    will be a spendthrift &amp; a coxcomb &#8211; or rather is so &#8211;
                    tho he will do well in worldly way at last &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">the other</ref> bids
                    fair to become either a swindler or a strolling player.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Should you see M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                        Wroughton<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Joanna Wroughton n&#233;e Townley (dates unknown),
                        first wife of Richard Wroughton (1748-1822;
                            <title>DNB</title>), actor and theatre manager. She
                        had probably given Charles Danvers some money towards
                        the proposed &#8211; but unrealised &#8211; subscription edition of
                            <title>Madoc</title>.</note> again pray return her
                    the subscription. the moment I become any persons debtor in
                    that way I am no longer at liberty to act freely about the
                    poem. it is my intention now to publish it next winter &#8211; but
                    many possible circumstances may prevent this. I may be
                    called abroad &#8211; I may be disabled by ill health &#8211; by
                    accidents &#8211; prevented by other employments &#8211; or induced to
                    change the mode of publication for want of success. this
                    last is very probable, indeed most probable. I rather try
                    the experiment to satisfy those who would say why did you
                    not do so &#8211; than from any expectation of even tolerable
                    encouragement. less than 300 names will not render it
                    prudent to publish on my own account &#8211; I feel assured that
                    not a third of that number will be procured &#8211; I may look for
                    about [MS torn] from you &amp; <ref target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, &amp; there
                    is no other person who will procure me half-a-dozen. You see
                    then that it would be imprudent to publish proposals. the
                    failure of a public attempt would lower the <del rend="strikethrough">po</del> value of the poem when I
                    shall be obliged to carry it to market. I get on with the
                    recomposition &#8211; for such in fact it is. the discovery of
                    little Hoel &amp; his mother whose name now is Llaian, is
                    just finished &#8211; making my thirteenth bookling.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madoc</title> (1805),
                        Part 1, Book 14.</note> the next must be wholly new &#8211;
                    then <del rend="strikethrough">only</del> I have only to
                    recast the old metal as far as his return. about a thousand
                    lines must be woven into the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &amp;
                        8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> books as you have them &#8211; the
                    latter part of the poem will receive no material alteration
                    as to story or arrangement.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had intolerable weather that has half
                    frozen me. &amp; almost made me resolve not to settle in
                    Cumberland. however I am well thank God, &amp; in as
                    ostensible spirits as those about me could wish. <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> has
                    applied to <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">May</ref> for
                    money &#8211; &amp; <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">May</ref>
                    has supplied him. I am as you may suppose justly offended.
                    you know not how I have been pestered with unpleasant
                    information of late &#8211; <ref target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref>
                    sent off to Edinburgh against my opinion &#8211; without <ref target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref>
                    knowledge &amp; against the approbation of his friends
                    merely because he was so intolerably idle that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Martineau<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip Meadows Martineau (1752-1829),
                        surgeon at the Norfolk and Norwich Hospital and a member
                        of the Martineau family, prominent Unitarians in
                        Norwich. Henry Herbert Southey had studied under him,
                        but had entered the University of Edinburgh in November
                        1803.</note> very properly refused to keep him. <ref target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> a
                    vagabond, &amp; this shameless fellow <ref target="people.html#BurnettGeorge">Burnett</ref> begging
                    upon the strength of <del rend="strikethrough">my</del> his
                    intimacy with me. &#8211; from what you say of poor <ref target="people.html#KingJohn">Kings</ref> child<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Zoe King
                        (1803-1881).</note> I conclude it must have been
                    scrophalous tho you do not say so. you wish me more children
                    &#8211; I am not sure that I can join in the wish, considering the
                    fear I should feel &amp; the strong probability that I
                    should not love another so well because it would not be the
                    same. It is well that these things are not in our own
                    choice. &#8211; pray write speedily of your own health &#8211; for in
                    truth <ref target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>
                    I shall now feel no other uneasiness so strongly as for
                    that.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you &#8211; R. S. </salute>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>Draw on <ref target="people.html#MayJohn">May</ref> for
                        the charges you may bear.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>