<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3786" type="letter"><head>3786. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BartonBernard">Bernard Barton</ref>, <date when="1822-01-27">27 January 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 297–298; Lucy Barton, <title>Poems and Letters by Bernard Barton</title> (London, 1849), pp. xvii–xviii [in part].</note></head>
            
            
            <opener>  <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-01-27">27 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1822</date></dateline>
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I should have answered your letter yesterday, if it had not found me with six proof sheets on the table, three of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Kirke Whites</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of the ‘Preface’ to the 9th edition of Southey’s <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title>, 3 vols (London, 1822), III, pp. [iii]–xvi. The third, ‘supplementary volume’ was newly added in 1822 and contained additional letters and poems by Kirke White.</note> &#38; three of my own.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">Both your Dedications are very good, – the second very beautiful, tho a little hurt by the alteration, – the alteration however is advisable, – not that it would give offence, but that it is right to avoid any thing which might maliciously be pointed out as offensive.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Bernard Barton, <title>Napoleon and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), p. [v], was dedicated to George IV. Barton had asked Southey’s advice about the dedication; see Southey to Bernard Barton, 18 August 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3713.</note> The volume cannot be presented more fitly that by Sir Aug. Frazer.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Augustus Simon Frazer (1776–1835, <title>DNB</title>), commander of horse artillery in the Peninsular War. Frazer was a brother-in-law of Barton’s friend Edward Moor and had offered his papers to help with Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> I have no doubt but that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> will be gratified by it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I was much pleased with the Poets Lot, – no, – not with his lot, – but with the verses in which he describes it. But let me ask you, – are you not pursuing your studies intemperately, &#38; to the danger of your health?? To be writing “long after midnight”, &#38; “with a miserable headache” <del>xxx</del> is what no man can do with impunity; &#38; what no pressure of business, no ardour of composition, has ever made me do.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘The Poet’s Lot’ was not published until <title>Poetic Vigils</title> (London, 1824), pp. 111–117; it did not include the lines to which Southey objected.</note> I beseech you remember the fate of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Kirke White</ref>; – &#38; remember that if you sacrifice your health (not to say your life) in the same manner, you will be held up in your own community as a Warning, – not as an example for imitation. The spirit which disturbed poor Scott of Amwell<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Scott of Amwell (1731–1782; <title>DNB</title>), Quaker, poet and expert on turnpike trusts and the Poor Law. In <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (July 1814), 480–504 (500–501), Southey had drawn attention to the account of Scott’s death in Alexander Chalmers (1759–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of the English Poets, from Chaucer to Cowper</title>, 21 vols (London, 1810), XVII, pp. 445–452. Scott had been troubled by fears about his own worth.</note> in his last illness will fasten <del>xx</del> upon your name; &#38; your fate will be instanced to prove the <del>in cxxxxxxx</del> inconsistency of your pursuits with that sobriety &#38; evenness of mind which Quakerism requires &#38; is intended to produce.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> You will take this as it is meant, I am sure.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My friend, go early to bed: – &#38; if you eat suppers, read afterwards but never compose, that you may lie down <del>xx</del> with a quiet intellect. There is an intellectual, as well as a religious peace of mind; – &#38; without the former, be assured there can be no health for a poet.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you –</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">  Yrs very truly</salute>
            <signed rend="indent3">RSouthey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
