<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3807" type="letter"><head>3807. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1822-02-27">27 February [1822]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 27 Feby<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 430. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: Dating from the reference to Southey’s transcription of the journal he had kept during his tour of Scotland in 1819. This was completed by September 1822; see Southey to John Rickman, 9 September 1822, Letter 3895.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear R.</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am quite sorry the franks should have given you vexation as well as trouble.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman had provided a governmental frank to allow proofs of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832) to avoid postal charges.</note> The evil is nothing. – I had not the conscience to send them back, profiting so largely as I do by the privilege of franking. –</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs C.</ref> returns thanks in <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughters</ref> name, the young Lady being on a visit at <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>. The version is indeed perfectly natural, – it could not have been better.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have a good intention as soon as the Scotch Journal<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been sending Rickman the fair copy of the journal he kept during their tour of Scotland in August–September 1819. This was later published as <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> is finished, of putting my other journals in a legible form, &#38; transmitting them in like manner for <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Mrs R.s</ref> amusement, – if it will amuse her to travel with me to Waterloo, – &#38; to the Alps.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s journals covering his visit to the site of the Battle of Waterloo in 1815 and his tour of the Continent in May–August 1817. The former were later published as <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902).</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
               <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
           <postscript> <p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-02-27">27 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
