<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3832" type="letter"><head>3832. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#BartonBernard">Bernard Barton</ref>], <date when="1822-05-01">1 May 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Brown University Library. ALS; 2p. (c).<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-05-01">1 May. 1822.</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">If your former letters had required an answer, or if I could have given any useful advice in reply upon the matter to which they related, I certainly should have replied to them, however much I had been engaged at the time. But this not being the case, &#38; thinking it probable your volume<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bernard Barton, <title>Napoleon, and Other Poems</title> (1822), p. [v], was dedicated to George IV. Barton had asked Southey’s advice about this; see Southey to Bernard Barton, 18 August 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3713.</note> might be inclosed in a parcel from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>, which is at this time upon the road, I waited for its arrival, as a more convenient season. It was too late to <del>xxxxxx</del> intreat you (which I should otherwise have done) not to make application to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref>, whose answer to any such application I could with certainty have anticipated.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Your publisher</ref> seems to have suggested the best plan.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Barton wished to place a copy of his book in the Royal Library at Windsor.</note> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> <del>Clar</del> Stanier Clarke however is no longer the Kings Librarian.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George Stanier Clarke (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>) was the domestic chaplain and librarian to George IV 1799–1821, and Historiographer Royal 1812–1834.</note> Sumner<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Sumner (1790–1874; <title>DNB</title>) was the domestic chaplain and librarian to George IV 1821–1826. He became Bishop of Llandaff 1826–1827, and Bishop of Winchester 1827–1869.</note> is his successors name &#38; you had better address it to him, with a note requesting that he will place it in the royal library, as you have no other means of introducing it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">No person would rejoice more than I should do, if your book were to produce consequences as desirable as you have ever even in a dream thought possible. Thirty or forty years ago, it might most probably have done so. The times are very different now. A poet was then as rare a creature as a Bird of Paradise, – they are now as common as starlings. A courteous acknowledgement of your book I doubt not you will receive, I wish I could see a probability of any thing more substantial. Something has been said of an Academy<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Royal Society of Literature, founded in 1820.</note> which would have rewards to bestow, – but I know nothing more of it than what the newspapers informed me, &#38; the scheme seemed to have been formed by persons very little acquainted with the actual state of literature in this country. Nevertheless if it takes effect, I should be very glad that you were to profit by it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am sorry my silence should have occasioned you any uneasiness. You would not have wondered at it, if you knew how many &#38; how pressing my employments are, &#38; how much of my time is consumed in answering letters. That it <del>did</del> had not proceeded from any diminution of respect &#38; good will you would ere long have seen. I <del>have</del> am writing a paper for the Q.R.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 1–46, published 15 February 1823. (Gregoire’s book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.) Southey’s review (pp. 4–5) included a lengthy recommendation of Barton’s poetry for its ‘pure and religious spirit’, and quoted Barton’s poem ‘The Pool of Bethesda’, from <title>Napoleon, and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), pp. [182]–185, in its entirety.</note> in which some mention will be made of the Quakers, &#38; I shall not let pass that occasion of mentioning their poet.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent1">Farewell &#38; believe me</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">Yours very truly</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
