<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3844" type="letter"><head>3844. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>,<date when="1822-05-22"> 22 May 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend N Lightfoot./ Crediton. – / Devonshire<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Endorsement: May-22<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-05-22">22 May. 1822.</date>
            
            <salute>My dear Lightfoot</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">The pleasure which I always feel in receiving a letter from you is in the present case somewhat abated by finding that you did not receive my last reply. For certainly I wrote one, &#38; tho its loss on the way is of no other consequence, yet I am sorry to think I should have so long seemed guilty of neglect towards an old friend whom I often think of, &#38; sometimes see in a dream. – Be assured that no letter of yours will ever long remain<del>ed</del> unanswered by me, while I am able to answer it.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> In the month of July I shall be, God willing, where I am now, – that is to say, where I like best to be, – at home, in the quiet &#38; steady exercise of my vocation. I wish you would be persuaded to pass that month with me, &#38; take some delightful excursions among these Lakes &#38; Mountains, while we are yet able to enjoy them. I know not what alteration time may have made in you, but for myself I can feel that eight &#38; twenty years which have <del>gone by</del>&#60;elapsed&#62; since you &#38; I shook hands at our last parting, have left very perceptible effects upon my earthly part. Some of the strength of manhood, &#38; all the enterprize of youth are gone. I should be very unwilling now to walk the whole of a long summers day. Yet on the whole there are probably few men in better trim at the completion of their 48<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year. Come then while it is yet in my power to show you that I can handle an oar upon Derwentwater, as well as I ever did upon the Isis. All that I learnt at Oxford was to row &#38; to swim.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> My old friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is at last where he ought to be, high in <del>ad</del> office.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had joined the Cabinet in January 1822, with the office of President of the Board of Control. This post gave him ultimate responsibility for overseeing the affairs of the East India Company and the government of its possessions in India.</note> The patronage which he possesses is I suppose considerable: of course it is confined to India, but in <del>all</del> such things their must be a way of accommodation by exchange, – for instance, it might suit <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">the Foreign Secretary</ref> to ask him for a Writership,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had the authority to nominate young men to the role of Writer in the East India Company, the most junior administrative post.</note> – &#38; let him in return <del>nom</del> recommend to the next Consulship which might be vacant. I am speaking, not from knowledge, but from what may fairly be presumed. <ref type="m" target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Phillimore</ref> owes his appointment to him<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Phillimore had been appointed to the Board of Control on 8 February 1822, serving until 1828.</note> (I dare say you remember him at Christ Church,) &#38; probably <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeckwellRobertHenry">Peckwell</ref> also, who is now Sir Robert Blosset.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Blosset had been appointed Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Judicature of Bengal and was knighted on 19 April 1822.</note> But I believe the perpetual plague of solicitation which patronage always draws after it, makes it a dear purchase.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">My brother Edward</ref> was in London last year for some weeks: he thought himself very ill, &#38; went there to be under <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother Henrys</ref> care, who is a physician. He wrote to me when he left town, having been restored to health, &#38; I have not heard of him since: There is no possibility of rescuing him from the way of life which he has chosen for himself; – &#38; all that we can do is to assist him when he is in need. The best thing I can say of him is that is not forward to call for assistance.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> If I have ever felt any thing like regret at having been deprived of the property which ought to have been mine,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">On the death of his third cousin, John Southey Somerville, 15th Lord Somerville (1765–1819; <title>DNB</title>), Southey believed he should have inherited the estates in Somerset that Somerville had been bequeathed under the complex will of his great-uncle, John Cannon Southey (d. 1768).</note> it is because that property would have brought me into the West of England, &#38; fixed me there, within half a days journey of you. I shall find my way to you, next year perhaps, when I must visit London; – but I hope you will let me see you here first, where there is so much to be seen, that if you travelled hither <del>x</del> merely to see the country, you would think the labour well bestowed I should have some pride in showing you my books, &#38; much pleasure in introducing <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my wife</ref> &#38; children to you. They are indeed all children as yet, except <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the eldest</ref>, who has just completed her 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year. She is at Harrogate at present, for her health, &#38; I hope the purpose of her journey has been answered. Next week we expect her home. I am truly obliged to you &#38; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768–1856) on 13 July 1801.</note> for wishing to see her, or any of her sisters. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">My little boy</ref> is little more than three years old; so that if he lives to grow up, &#38; I to see it (how many chances are there in the way of both!) I shall be an old man before he is a young one. Here you have a blessing which has not fallen to my lot. I am glad to hear so good an account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">your eldest son</ref>; – he, I trust, will find his way here some long vacation. Is it your wish that he should look to advancement in the University, – or that he should assist you, &#38; take your place, whenever you feel weary of it?</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have often thought how much happier both you &#38; I have been than if we had obtained fellowships at <ref type="m" target="places.html#BalliolOxford">Balliol</ref>, &#38; risen in due course of years to all the dignity of <del>xxxx</del> great wigs. How many years of domestic enjoyment should we have lost! – &#38; what is there in this world which can compensate for them! – I have a book in hand which will contain my speculations upon the progress &#38; prospects of society.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> &#38; I have another, which will appear some time before it, containing a view of our Ecclesiastical History,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> written in the hope of doing &#60;some&#62; service to the rising generation. Both will procure me some of that abuse to which I have long been accustomed; &#38; I hope &#38; believe that for the same reason, you will like them both, when they reach you. God bless you my dear friend. Present my best regards to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot – &#38; my goddaughter,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806–1882), Southey’s god-daughter.</note> – &#38; tell me that you will spend your midsummer holydays here -</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> yrs affectionately</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed></closer>
            
           <postscript> <p rend="indent0">I send this direct, rather than risk the chance of a second miscarriage by inclosing it for a frank.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The postscript is written at the head of the first page of the letter.</note></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
