<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3877" type="letter"><head>3877. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1822-07-27">27 July 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/>
               Endorsement: July 27 1822./ R Southey<lb/>
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am not sure whether I requested you that the proofs of this concluding chapter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 15 of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 756–806.</note> might be sent to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> as well as me, that they may be perused by one or two persons<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">These included <ref type="m" target="people.html#CourtenayThomas">Thomas Peregrine Courtenay</ref>, who as Paymaster General 1807–1811 had been on the retreat to Corunna in 1808–1809.</note> who were in Sir J Moores army.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Moore (1761–1809; <title>DNB</title>), commander of British forces on the retreat to Corunna.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> A page or two of corrections is all that remains to be sent – they are more properly additions, drawn from papers which I did not receive till the sheets to which they relate were printed</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Some time ago I mentioned to you as desiderata the historical writings of Francisco de Olivarez – they are ‘the war in Catalonia’ – Anecdotes of Chief in the Catalonian war, &#38; Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy from the reign of Ferdinand &#38; Isabel to the usurpation of Joseph Buonaparte.”<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; and 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693.</note> Pray get them if it be possible, – the two former I want at this time for the commencement of the second volume.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute>
               <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed></closer>
            
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-07-27">July 27. 1822.</date> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
