<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3894" type="letter"><head>3894. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>,<date when="1822-09-09"> 9 September 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               Endorsement: 9 Sept 1822/ R Southey Esq<lb/>
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">The insertions which are dove-taild to a nicety in these half sheets compleat all that I have to do with the first volume.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), published at the end of 1822.</note> Do you publish it forthwith, – or wait till the winter?</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I go to press with the second volume, as soon as I receive some promised communications from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Mr B. Frere</ref>.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">In the course of the week I shall <del>tra</del> send up the first part of an article upon Gregoires Hist. des Sectes Religieuses.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> It will be an entertaining &#38; curious paper. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco Whites</ref> book<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Letters from Spain, by Don Leucadio Doblado</title> (1822). Southey did not review this for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> &#38; the State of Spain will be my next subject.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I requested you some time ago to procure a history of the War in Catalonia, &#38; also ‘Anecdotes of the Leaders in thar war’ both by Francisco de Olivarez.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; and 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877.</note> – They are quite necessary for my second volume</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs very truly</salute>
              <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-09-09">9 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1822.</date> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick.</ref></placeName></address></p>
            <lb/>
            <p>It is so very long since I have had a proof of the B of the Church,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> that I think the last portion of copy must have been mislaid – or forgotten</p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
