<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3916" type="letter"><head>3916. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1822-11-12">12 November 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: R Southey to JR/ 22<lb/>
               MS: The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Wilson Library, James Saxon Childers Papers. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note>
            </head>
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-11-12">12 Nov. 1822.</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> Thank you most heartily for what you say of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>. Upon due consideration we think that both the pleasure &#38; the advantage of her visit will be increased by delaying it. She is but in her fourteenth year, &#38; will be better able a little while hence to afford &#38; enjoy this sort of holy day. – For myself I shall very gladly take up my quarters, during part of my stay, in Palace Yard. The Dii Penates<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The household deities in Roman religion.</note> of that house ought to know me well, for I frequented it three &#38; thirty years ago,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">While Southey was at Westminster School 1788–1792, his closest friend, Grosvenor Charles Bedford, lived in New Palace Yard, as his father, Charles Bedford, was an official in the Exchequer. The house was occupied by Rickman at this time.</note> ate plum cake &#38; drank <hi rend="ital">sack</hi><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A fortified wine from Spain; sherry is a type of sack.</note> there regularly on Lord Mayors day,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord Mayor’s Day, at this time held on 9 November, marked the installation of the new Lord Mayor of the City of London.</note> – &#38; began in the library there, those studies of manners &#38; mythology, which led to Thalaba &#38; Madoc &#38; Kehama.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s poems <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), <title>Madoc</title> (1805) and <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> My pleasantest school boy recollections are connected with that house.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You will receive my first volume<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> early next month: &#38; not very long after it the view of our church history<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> which I am now proceeding with. I believe no person feels the want of a Collection of our early historians more than I do at this time. Large portions to my purpose are in the Acta Sanctorum.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, 53 vols (1643–1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – I shall make an interesting, &#38; I hope a useful book.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">Dr Wordsworth</ref> is well-placed. There could hardly be a fitter man for that station.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Christopher Wordsworth was Master of Trinity College, Cambridge 1820–1841.</note> <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> I think will be as fit for the Editorship,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was campaigning to ensure that John Taylor Coleridge succeeded William Gifford as editor of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> which I believe he will have. There will be more difficulty with Barrow<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Barrow, 1st Baronet (1764–1848; <title>DNB</title>), the Second Secretary to the Admiralty 1804–1806, 1807–1845 and a regular contributor to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> than any other contributor. His articles are almost always <del>ill tem</del> ill natured &#38; unjust. I do not remember that he has ever in any one instance allowed a traveller his due merit. And yet he must be managed, as a person whom it will not do to offend.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I have written to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> in strong reprehension of the articles respecting America.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey to [John Murray], 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note> And he has desired me to slide as well as I can into a different strain.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s response was his review of Timothy Dwight (1752–1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821–1822), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1–40, published 17 April 1824. Dwight’s book was no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> A great deal of mischief has been done. It is something however to stop it for the future. And luckily while I alter the language of the QR at home, I can go very far toward affecting a correspondent change at Boston, – where I have good communications.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
