<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3933" type="letter"><head>3933. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-12-15">15 December 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ <del>G C B</del>/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 18 DE 18/ 1822<lb/>
               Endorsements: 15. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1822.; 16. Decr.1822<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 354–355.</note>
            </head>
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Mackenzie<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had asked for a copy of the first volume of <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832) to be delivered to Colin Alexander Mackenzie (1778?–1851), a wealthy Scot who was employed on a number of delicate diplomatic missions and may well have been a government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of the Commissioners of Liquidation, Arbitration and Deposit, who adjudicated on claims by British citizens for loss of property against the French government. Southey dined with him in Paris on 17 and 19 May 1817, and Mackenzie provided information for Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>.</note> enabled me to make the narrative of Romanas escape<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mackenzie had related to Southey his role in the evacuation of the Spanish Division of the North from northern Europe in August 1808, <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 657–659. The Division’s commander was Pedro Caro, 3rd Marquis of La Romana (1761–1811).</note> as compleat as you see it, – by delivering me in writing, what he related to me at Paris. To Sir Augustus Fraser<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Augustus Simon Frazer (1776–1835; <title>DNB</title>), a career soldier, had seen service in the Peninsular campaign as a highly effective senior commander of horse artillery.</note> I am obliged, thro his brother in law <ref type="m" target="people.html#MoorEdwardMajor">Major Moor</ref> for the largest body of communications which I have been able to obtain, consisting of a series of his letters describing the whole <del>course</del> progress of the army while he was with it from <del>the</del> 1810 to the end of the war, transcribed into a large volume, with plans &#38;c, as at one time intended for publication, – an intention I believe laid aside in part because of the announcement of my undertaking. Certainly I shall derive more advantage from these letters than from any other series of documents. You will therefore allow that both Sir Augustus (whom I have never seen) &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MoorEdwardMajor">Major Moor</ref> who transcribed the letters &#38; offered them to me, are richly entitled to this return. I think I mentioned in my list that both copies should be consigned to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> care, he being Moor’s publisher. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MoorEdwardMajor">Moor</ref> is author of the Hindoo Pantheon &#38; of course intimate with my friends Yamen, Seeva &#38;c.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Moor, <title>The Hindu Pantheon</title> (1810), which described the gods Yamen (Yama) and Seeva (Shiva), who had also featured in Southey’s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Now for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>. Tho I am indebted to him for many civilities I should not on that score alone send him a book which he would otherwise buy without hesitation. But there are things relating to his own Department,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Herries was Commissary-in-Chief 1811–1816.</note> for which in the subsequent volumes I shall want information from him.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My dear Grosvenor more than half that eleemosynary list consists of persons without whose aid the book could not have been composed, – e – g – <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">Marquis Wellesley</ref> – Whittingham,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant-General Sir Samuel Ford Whittingham (1772–1841; <title>DNB</title>), commander of Spanish forces 1808–1814.</note> – <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">his brother</ref> – <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymple</ref> &#38;c &#38;c, &#38; these as much belong to the charges of the work, as the printers or stationers bill. From ten to twelve copies stand on the score of private feeling, &#38; will be received either as acknowledgements for kindness, – or as memorials of friendship, – carrying with them in either case an ideal value, which you very well know &#60;how&#62; to appreciate. – I have, God knows, received a great many acts of kindness, – none of which have I <del>have</del> ever forgotten, <del>whxx</del>. &#60;But&#62; I shall go out of the world on the debtor side of the account &#60;at last&#62;, – not for want of will, but of means. <del>x xxxxx</del></p>
            <p rend="indent1">As for your own copy, – pay me for it by giving me a good portrait of yourself, – in place of the ill likeness which poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> made.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
               <signed rend="indent">RS</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-12-15">15 Dec. 1822.</date> <address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
