<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3947" type="letter"><head>3947. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1823-01-04">4 January 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
Endorsement: RS to JR/ Jany 4 1823<lb/>
MS: Huntington Library, RS 427. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I have had a very civil letter written by <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnightonSirWilliam">Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Knighton</ref> ex officio to acknowledge my book,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832), dedicated to George IV.</note> – with the special favour of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Kings</ref> signifying his approbation of the letter – in his own hand. How happy would this make a man “who hangs on Princes’ favour”!<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Henry VIII</title>, Act 3, scene 2, line 367.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">The Whigs I hear are up in arms against the book, – they will like the second volume worse, for there I shall write their misdeeds, &#38; put them upon record where they will be read. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref> is said to be very sore. I am sorry for this, because he is a man whom it is impossible not to like.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> wishes I had endeavoured to conciliate all parties. He might have known that this is impossible. I had but one course to pursue, – the straight forward one of writing honestly. They cannot hate me worse than they do, &#38; they shall not hate me for nothing.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am getting on with the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> volume, but cannot put it to press till I obtain a Spanish history of the war in Catalonia, which <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has been more than six months getting for me.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note> The second vol. will come down to Massenas retreat,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">André Massena (1758–1817) commanded the invasion of Portugal in 1810–1811. Southey did not deal with his retreat until <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), III, pp. 127–154.</note> – &#38; my documents are as full &#38; as satisfactory as I could wish.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">	Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rickman</ref> – Many &#38; happy new years to you &#38; yours –</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
				<signed rend="indent4">RS.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent1"><date when="1823-01-04">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 4. 1823</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
