<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3974" type="letter"><head>3974. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1823-03-03">3 March 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear Wynn</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am very much obliged to you for your aid at the Colonial Office.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey was investigating whether he might emigrate to Canada.</note> The next business is to learn what steps are to be taken, – understanding, as I do, that the promised facilities imply a grant of lands. Would not the best &#38; easiest method of proceeding be for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S.</ref>to call upon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilmot?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Wilmot-Horton (1784–1841; <title>DNB</title>), Under-Secretary of State for War and the Colonies 1821–1828 and an indefatigable promoter of emigration schemes. He was later Governor of Ceylon 1831–1837.</note> If you approve of this, have the goodness to say to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilmot that he will do so, &#38; give him a line (at 15 <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q. Anne Street</ref>) to let him know that you have so done. Or advise me, if any other mode be better. </p>
            <p rend="indent1">I did not know that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother Tom</ref> had written to Lord Bathurst,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Bathurst, 3rd Earl Bathurst (1762–1834; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War and the Colonies 1812–1827.</note> till your inclosure informed me of it.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">Burnets is a book which I should very much like to take for the subject of a paper.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Gilbert Burnet (1643–1715; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of his own Time: from the Restoration of King Charles II, to the Conclusion of the Treaty of Peace at Utrecht, in the Reign of Queen Anne</title> (1724–1734). A new edition by Martin Routh (1755–1854; <title>DNB</title>) appeared in 1823, and was reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 165–213, published 27–28 September 1823. The book was no. 498 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – You will not however be surprized that the more I look into English history, – the more I feel the want of an adequate historical library, – &#38; the consequent chasms in my knowledge of its different periods. – At this time I grievously feel the want of a Corpus Hist.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A ‘corpus historicus’, or body of history, i.e. a state-sponsored series of publications of British historical documents.</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
	   <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
            <lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-03-03">3 March. 1823.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
