<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3982" type="letter"><head>3982. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1823-03-18">18 March 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 21 MR 21/ 1823<lb/>
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.132. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear H.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is waiting the result of some Letters which he &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">his wife</ref> have written to the Fenwicks,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey had possibly written to Dr John Ralph Fenwick (c. 1762–1855) and his wife Dorothy, née Spearman (dates unknown). Fenwick lived in Durham when Tom Southey farmed in the county and was well known to Henry Herbert Southey. He was a wealthy local radical. Whoever the Fenwicks were, Tom Southey owed them money and was seeking to cancel his debt before emigrating to Canada.</note> – before he writes to you. I believe they are cherishing some expectations from that quarter which are without any reasonable foundation. He talks of sailing from Maryport, where it seems there are good opportunities of obtaining passage to Quebec, – &#38; of taking his family at once, instead of going over to prepare for them, which he at first intended. They calculate upon hospitality both at Quebec &#38; Montreal from her relation Matthew Bell,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Matthew Bell (1769–1849), a wealthy merchant, iron manufacturer and land speculator, originally from Berwick-upon-Tweed. He was a relation of Sarah Southey.</note> who has establishments at both places. – But the difficulty of raising means will soon, I fear, appear like a Lion in the way.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Proverbs</title>, 26: 13: ‘The slothful man saith, There is a lion in the way; a lion is in the streets.’</note> He must however try what can be raised upon his own resources, – &#38; when it comes to the point I will do all I can to assist. But I hold out no prospect of this at present, because he would think that assistance might as well be bestowed in eking out his income here, &#38; would make no effort at establishing his family <del>xx</del> as long as it were possible to put off the evil day. Indeed he has often said, that the great object for him is to <hi rend="ital">put on</hi>; – which is only another phrase for <hi rend="ital">putting off</hi>.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">He tells me has been writing to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Elmsley,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Elmsley (c. 1775–1831), née Hallowell, widow of John Elmsley (1762–1805), Chief Justice of Upper Canada 1796–1802 and of Lower Canada 1802–1805 and brother of Peter Elmsley.</note> – for no imaginable reason but the pleasure which he takes in writing letters. I have however for the present persuaded him that what remains to be done with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilmot<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Wilmot-Horton (1784–1841; <title>DNB</title>), Under-Secretary of State for War and the Colonies 1821–1828.</note> &#38; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robinson<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Beverley Robinson, 1st Baronet (1791–1863), Solicitor-General for Upper Canada 1815–1818, Attorney-General for Upper Canada 1818–1829, Chief Justice of Upper Canada 1829–1841 and of Canada West 1841–1862. At this time Robinson was in London, seeking to promote legislation to put Upper Canada’s finances on a sounder footing, resulting in the Canada Trade Act (1822).</note> may be better effected by you, than by his entering into correspondence with them.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">My mind, had I been in his circumstances, would long ago have been made up to this step. The serious obstacle is in the outset, – as for the other difficulties, they are such as every day will lessen, &#38; there is a pleasure in overcoming them. There is a sure prospect of independence for himself &#38; his children.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Hill Southey (b. 1811); Mary Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813–1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815–1864); Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816–1835); Sarah Louise Southey (1818–1850); Nelson Castle Southey (1820–1834); and Sophia Jane Southey (1822–1859). Thomas Castle Southey (1824–1896) completed the family.</note> He may be settled at ease on his own domain, – while you &#38; I are in harness.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you &#38; yours</salute>
		 <signed rend="indent3">  RS.</signed></closer>
 <lb/>           
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1823-03-18">March 18. 1823.</date></p>
<lb/>
	<p rend="indent1">I have had another tail added to my name to day – by the Royal Irish Academy.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been elected an Honorary Member of the Royal Irish Academy (founded 1785), a body that existed to promote Irish scientific and cultural activities and studies.</note></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
