<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4024" type="letter"><head>4024. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">John Abraham Heraud</ref>, <date when="1823-06-01">1 June 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> J. A. Heraud Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Carey Street/ Lincolns Inn <lb/>
Stamped: [illegible]<lb/>
Postmark: [illegible]<lb/>
MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p. <lb/>
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 246–247.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-06-01">1 June. 1823.</date></dateline></opener>

            <p rend="indent0">You would certainly have seen me had I been in London, &#38; you will see me there God willing before the summer is over.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">I wish there were not the necessity for doing something to increase your income, which your letter too surely shows there is. My recommendations of your Nero<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud had sent Southey his tragedy ‘Nero’, centred on Nero Claudius Caesar Drusus Germanicus (AD 37–68; Roman Emperor AD 54–68). Heraud did not publish this work.</note> can be of no avail. The question that a bookseller will ask is not whether it be a work of merit, but whether it is likely to sell. Without this assurance the praise which I should bestow – to wit – that it is a work of great power &#38; promise, would not suffice: nor indeed with it, unless the bookseller himself saw reason to expect a remunerating sale. You can do no harm by offering it to a publisher, – but I am afraid you will not find one who will take upon himself the risque of publication, – much less advance any thing for the copyright. Nor am I sure that eventually it would be serviceable to you to have it before the world. With all its merit it is a juvenile performance; &#38; you have already given proof of poetical genius.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">I am glad to hear of your lecturing, because it leads you to prose composition; &#38; it by writing for magazines that you may with most facility help out your ways &#38; means. But your great object with this view should be to get a piece upon the stage, something of the mixed drama rather than tragedy, of an attractive, romantic character, – designed to please, <del>xxx</del> rather than to affect too deeply. Construct the plan first if you succeed in that, you have little or nothing to learn in execution.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The Deluge<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud was planning an epic poem, eventually published as <title>The Judgement of the Flood</title> (1834). Southey discouraged him from publishing hastily or by subscription.</note> is not a subject upon which you can derive any aid from books. The Bible is the sole history of that early age of the world, &#38; every thing relating to manners must be matter of invention, not research. What the circumstances of the world then were it is impossible to know: your business therefore is to describe them such as they may with some appearance of reason be supposed to have been. There is a German poem upon the subject, in hexameters, by Bodmer;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Bodmer (1698–1783), <title>Noachide</title> (1752).</note> – of which a bad translation in <del>prose</del> inflated prose was published some fifty years ago.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Collyer (d. 1776; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Noah. Attempted from the German of Mr. Bodmer. In Twelve Books</title> (1767), no. 311 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I must not omit to notice what you say <del>xxx</del> concerning dedicating your Nero. If the play be published (which I think is not likely) there is no man of letters who would not be gratified by such a compliment. I would recommend you therefore to address it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Sir W. Scott</ref>, – a most kind hearted man. His good wishes &#38; good word might be worth something to you: – mine you have, &#38; unluckily they can be of little value.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">You have taken a bold step in marrying.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud married <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeraudAnnElizabeth">Ann Elizabeth Baddams</ref> on 15 May 1823.</note> I will not call it an imprudent one, because it will not be so if you can depend &#60;upon&#62; yourselves for strict frugality &#38; good management. Without these necessary virtues you will have every thing to fear; with them you may have every thing to hope. – God bless you! I shall look for you as soon as I arrive in town, which will probably be in the course of next month – </p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">farewell, &#38; believe me</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">yrs faithfully</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
