<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4087" type="letter"><head>4087. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1823-11-19">19 November 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ Lymington/ Hampshire<lb/>
Stamped: T. P./ Tooting<lb/>
Postmark: [illegible]<lb/>
Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 38 To Miss Caroline Bowles<lb/>
MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 45–47.</note></head>


            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-11-19">19 Nov. 1823</date></dateline></opener>

            <p rend="indent1">I should feel more uneasy than I have done under the impossibility of replying sooner to your last most welcome letter, if I had not commissioned Dame Elizabeth<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), sister of William Peachy’s first wife, Emma Peachy, and friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>).</note> (so named when we lay side by side in the boat of the Peak Cavern,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Peak Cavern, also known as the Devil’s Arse, is a cavern near Castleton, Derbyshire. At this time it contained a low tunnel that could only be accessed by lying flat in a boat.</note> like two figures on an old monument) to tell you I would write on the first possible opportunity. The endless round of occupations &#38; engagements in which I am involved in London, you can hardly conceive: they are such as literally not to leave me an interval of rest. Yesterday I got to this quiet Rectory after a most fatiguing morning. To day I have, as a matter not to be delayed, written a short letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LambCharles">Charles Lamb</ref>, which can hardly fail of making him heartily sorry for what he has done, &#38; if he can forgive himself as easily as I forgive him, we shall meet again upon our old terms.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had commended Lamb’s <title>Essays of Elia</title> (1823) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 524, published 8 July 1823, but commented that the book ‘wants only a sounder religious feeling, to be as delightful as it is original’. Lamb took offence and responded with ‘Letter of Elia to Robert Southey, Esquire’, <title>London Magazine</title>, 8 (October 1823), 400–407. Southey wrote to Lamb to try and mend the quarrel, Southey to Charles Lamb, [19 November 1823], Letter 4088.</note> <del>That</del> This done, I set out with you for the forest of merry Sherwood.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">A tale of Robin Hood might without impropriety be as little regular in its structure as he was in his way of life.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">This incomplete work was published as ‘Robin Hood’ in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [1]–36. </note> I think a <del>xxx</del> striking introduction might be made by the funeral of his mother (dying in childbed of him) the immediate departure of the Earl his father to the Crusades, &#38; the delivery of the infant to a kinsman Sir Ranulph as guardian, &#38; the parental care of Father Hugh, the Earls foster-brother. Twelve years may be allowed to elapse, during which the boy has grown wild, his guardian being always engaged in political turmoils, &#38; the Priest an indulgent man: <del>xxxx xxx</del> The Earls heart is then brought home from the Holy Land to be <del>xxx</del> deposited in the same grave with his wife. And then an interval of seven or eight years more, when the proper story of the poem commences – with a service for the souls of the Earl &#38; his Wife. After the service Father Hugh takes the opportunity of mildly lecturing <del>Robin</del> the young Earl Robert, for his propensities to forest sports, &#38; inferior company, &#38; his utter neglect of knightly accomplishments, – it having previously been shown that this had arisen from his guardians constant absence, &#38; entire neglect. It appears now that <del>Ranulph xxx family</del> intention is to <del>xxx</del> bring about a marriage between Robert, &#38; his only <del>dau</del> child Aveline. – But Aveline has already given her heart to Gilbert with the white hand, a Squire of Low Degree, &#38; Robin as his comrades have from childhood called him declares his determination never to marry any body but Maid Marian the Millers daughter. Marian is a skylark, – &#38; Aveline a turtle dove. Gilbert of a gentle, poetical disposition, &#38; yet Robin &#38; he are bosom friends</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">Ranulph arrives to effect the marriage, &#38; in his anger at a refusal which disappoints the plan of securing the estates for his own family, sends off Marian (as a villeins daughter) to be directly married, &#38; commits Aveline to the custody of a severe Lady Abbess. Robin collects his comrades, rescues his own love first, then storms the nunnery, carries off Aveline for Gilbert, &#38; away they go to the forest</p>
                     <p rend="indent1">Then for a rich pastoral book, describing the life of the outlaws</p>
	<p rend="indent1">Ranulph is now one of <del>King</del> Johns<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John (1166–1216; King of England 1199–1216; <title>DNB</title>).</note> favourites, &#38; on the watch to arrest &#38; make away with King Richard<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard I (1157–1199; King of England 1189–1199; <title>DNB</title>). He was absent on the Third Crusade 1190–1192 and was held hostage in Austria and Germany 1192–1194.</note> on his return from captivity. The story is to be wound up by Robin Hood’s delivering Cour de Lion from this danger, being reinstated in his rank &#38;c, but resigning them all to Gilbert &#38; Aveline, &#38; chusing to pass his days always as the King of the forest. It will be easy enough to make out this part of the fable, – which indeed will shape itself while the rest is in progress.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">How like you this, my friend &#38; partner dear? Are these not rich capabilities, to be dreamt of now, – to be talked of soon, – &#38; then to be realized.</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">But I must conclude, – not to lose the post, &#38; for the same reason must do without a frank. You may direct to me under cover to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi></ref> New Palace Yard. – Only one word more, – I <hi rend="ital">hope</hi> I have put your books<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles’s <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) and <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822) were not reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> in a way of being reviewed in the Quarterly.</p>
                  <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
                     <salute rend="indent2">Yours affectionately</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
	<postscript><p rend="indent1">I cannot tell you when I <del>xxx</del> move westward yet. Tell you me what coaches pass near you from the Westward.</p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
