<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4105" type="letter"><head>4105. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">John Taylor</ref>], <date when="1823-12-22">22 December 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14183. ALS; 1p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-12-22">22 Dec. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I should perhaps have made leisure for writing to you sooner concerning these last sheets,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was helping to censor Landor’s <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824) for publication. </note> if I could have better satisfied myself as to what should be expunged.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">Were I to consult my own judgement only I should certainly omit two speeches in pp. 228–9, which might be struck out without leaving a chasm. If however the two lines which are offensive to good manners<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably, Dialogue XII of <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, p. 228, between ‘Prince Maurocordato’ and ‘General Colocotroni’: ‘a remonstrance against the letting of urine at the corners of streets, or lanes, or stable doors’; this passage and the surrounding two speeches were retained.</note> be got rid of, the rest may pass</p>
                  <p rend="indent1">p 231 I would omit – <del>In as</del> from “at present to the bottom of the page,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">This passage was omitted on p. 231. It attacked monarchy.</note> &#38; in p 241 from He has reason – to every thing that <hi rend="ital">is</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue XIII of <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 237–258, was between Vittorio Alfieri (1749–1803), Italian dramatist and ‘Salomon the Florentine Jew’. This passage was omitted. It was probably a criticism of aristocracy.</note> – What cannot be made unexceptionable we must be content with making less offensive. The opinions may be right, or wrong. The personalities (even if the facts are true) are unbecoming &#38; unworthy. And with these expurgations the sheets I think may be struck off. </p>
                     <p rend="indent1">I am obliged to you for the Magazines.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor had sent Southey copies of the <title>London Magazine</title>, which he published 1821–1829. Southey had introduced Henry Taylor to John Taylor, and Henry Taylor had gone on to contribute to the <title>London Magazine</title>.</note> And I thank you also on <del>Henry Taylors</del>  account. If I had not been well assured of his talents &#38; acquirements I should not have introduced him to you, but the attention which that introduction has obtained deserves my thanks as much as it has gone beyond my expectations.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Yrs very truly</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
