<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4116" type="letter"><head>4116. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HeathcoteWm">William Heathcote</ref>, <date when="1824-01-02">2 January [1824]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ William Heathcote Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Winchester<lb/>
               Postmark: JA/ 2/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsement: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Jan 2. 1823<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: Hampshire Record Office, 63M84/234/23. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Dating note: Dating from postmark; Southey misdates by a calendar year.</note>
            </head>
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName>London.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-01-02">2 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> I ought sooner to have acknowledged your obliging letter; but you know enough of my hurried manner of life in London to account for &#38; excuse an involuntary appearance of neglect. I should regret not seeing you at Winchester more, if it were not likely that we may arrive in town the same day, &#38; &#60;even&#62; not impossible that we may fall in upon the road. For I shall leave Lymington by the stage on Tuesday with the intention of proceeding to London by the first conveyance, &#38; it may easily happen that good Fortune may appoint you a place in the same coach. – Mine is a harassed life at present. This evening I set off for Devonshire, &#38; before I reach home in the middle of February must travel not less than a thousand miles.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Errol</ref> was better on Thursday, &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref> is not uneasy concerning him.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Before I received your letter my place had been taken for Exeter, &#38; engagements made at every point of my circuit. A very wearying one it will be; – one day at most places, two at another, &#38; only four with <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">the old friend</ref> for whose sake I undertake the journey. – On the second day after my return I start again, with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> then, for <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref> – Ipswich &#38; Cambridge – a fortnights round. Then a three days visit at Richmond, after which I shall put myself into the Carlisle mail, &#38; feel at rest when nothing remains to be done but to be whirled over three hundred miles.</p>
          <closer>  <salute rend="indent1">Believe my my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  Yrs very truly</salute>
            <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey</signed></closer>
   <lb/>         
          <postscript>  <p>My best regards to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Heathcote &#38; Miss Bigg.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Heathcote (1773–1855) and Alethea Bigg (1777–1847), two sisters of Catherine Hill, who shared a house at 12 Cathedral Close, Winchester.</note> </p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
