<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4183" type="letter"><head>4183. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>,<date when="1824-05-06"> 6 May 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ 10 MY 10/ 1824<lb/>
               Endorsements: 6 May 1824.<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), V, pp. 175–177 [in part].</note></head>
            
        <opener>    
           <dateline><address><placeName> <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address>. <date when="1824-05-06">6 May 1824.</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">In the evil habit of answering familiar letters without having them before me, I forgot to notice your question respecting the nitrous oxyde; which however I should not have done had the thing been as hopeful as you supposed it to be.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had inhaled nitrous oxide in 1799 as part of the experiments at the Pneumatic Institution in Bristol. See Thomas Beddoes, <title>Notice of Some Observations Made at the Medical Pneumatic Institution</title> (Bristol and London, 1799), p. 11, where Southey’s reaction to the inhalation is described thus: ‘For many hours after this experiment, he imagined that his taste and smell were more acute, and is certain that he felt unusually strong and cheerful. In a second experiment, he felt pleasure still superior – and has since poetically remarked, that he supposes the atmosphere of the highest of all possible heavens to be composed of this gas.’</note> What I said was simply this, that the excitement produced by the inhalation was not followed by any consequent debility or exhaustion; on the contrary that it appeared to quicken all the senses during the remainder of the day. – One case occurred in which the gas seemed to produce a good effect upon a palsied patient.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Beddoes, <title>Notice of Some Observations Made at the Medical Pneumatic Institution</title> (Bristol and London, 1799), p. 19, described the unnamed tailor’s case: a gradual recovery from a paralysis brought on by ‘a course of excessive debauchery, especially with regard to fermented liquors’.</note> A fellow <del>in the institu</del> who had lost the use of his hands (a taylor by trade) was so far cured, – that he was turned out of the house for picking <del>xx</del> pockets. -</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The difficulty in finding 200 subscribers<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was seeking subscribers for Tom Southey’s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827).</note> arises from this, my dear Grosvenor, – that our friends are never so ready to bestir themselves in our affairs, as our enemies. There are half a score persons in the world who would take some pains to serve me, – &#38; there are half a hundred who would take a great deal more to injure me. The former would gladly do any thing for me which lay in their way: – the latter would go out of theirs to do any thing against me – . I do not say this complainingly, for no man was ever less disposed to be querulous; &#38; perhaps no one <del>hxx</del> ever had more friends upon whose friendship he might justly pride himself. But it is the way of the world, – &#38; the simple reason is, that enmity is a stronger feeling than good will</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#InglisSirRobert">Sir Robert Inglis</ref> has sent me some names, Lord Sidmouth<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757–1844; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1801–1804, Home Secretary 1812–1822.</note> &#38; Bexley<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Vansittart (1766–1851; <title>DNB</title>), 1st Baron Bexley, Chancellor of the Exchequer 1812–1823.</note> are among them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  You have far too may engagements to make it in anyway looked for that you should call upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>. But if your horse happens to have you on his back at any time when you are in that part of the New Road to which Baker Street leads, &#38; you should enquire for her at N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 16 York Place, &#38; find her at home, – she would be heartily glad to see you, &#38; you would think your call well-bestowed by her introducing you to that very <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> whom you do not know. For <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> is familiar with your name, – &#38; is, of all women whom I have ever known, the one whom all who know her have concurred in liking best. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> is taking lessons from Fielding.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">There were four Fielding brothers, all fashionable painters of watercolours: Theodore Henry Adolphus Fielding (1781–1851; <title>DNB</title>); Anthony Vandyke Copley Fielding (1787–1855; <title>DNB</title>); Thales Fielding (1793–1837; <title>DNB</title>) and Newton Smith Fielding (1799–1856; <title>DNB</title>).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am reviewing Hayleys life<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of John Johnson (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263–311.</note> for the desire of lucre, – a motive which according to a writer in – the Ladys Magazine, induced me to compile the Book of the Church, – &#38; is indeed, according to this well informed person, the leading principle of my literary life.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Lady’s Magazine; or, Mirror of the Belles-Lettres, Fine Arts, Music, Drama, Fashions, &#38;c</title>. n.s., 5 (February 1824), 109, on Southey and <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824): ‘from the united impulse of vanity and a thirst for lucre, he writes and compiles with eagerness and rapidity.’ </note> How thoroughly should I be revenged upon such miserable wretches as this, if it were possible for them to know <del>wxx</del> with what infinite contempt I regard them! Hayleys life will be easily abridged, – I shall treat him as a gentleman &#38; a scholar ought to be treated without dissembling his faults as a writer, &#38; introduce as much as may be needful of the literary history of his time, – that is of the time in which he flourished – for flourish once he did, &#38; for some years was in <del>a popular poet what one</del> sphere of fancy what Spring is at this time in another.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Winter, known as Thomas Spring (1795–1851), a bare-knuckle boxer who was heavyweight champion of England 1821–1824.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Shall I tell you what books I have in reading at this time, – that you may see how many ingredients are required for garnishing a calf’s head. – A batch of volumes from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> relating to the events of the last ten years in Spain: – &#60;Bp. Parkers de Rebus sui Temporis,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Parker (1640–1688; <title>DNB</title>), <title>De Rebus Sui Temporis Commentariorum Libri Quatuor</title> (1726), no. 2095 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Parker was Bishop of Oxford 1686–1688.</note> -&#62; Cardinal D’Ossats letters:<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Arnaud d’Ossat (1537–1604), <title>Lettres du Cardinal d’Ossat</title> (1708), no. 851 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – the Memoirs of the 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Duke de Bourbon:<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Histoire de la Vie, Faicts Heroiques, et Voyages de tres Valeureux Prince Louys III, Duc de Bourbon</title> (1642), no. 327 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – Whitakers Pierce Ploughman:<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Dunham Whitaker (1759–1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Pierce the Ploughman’s Crede, Edited from the Edition of 1553</title> (1814), no. 1416 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> the Mirror for Magistrates,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Mirror for Magistrates</title> (1555), a collection of English poems. Southey possessed an edition of 1815 by <ref type="m" target="people.html#HaslewoodJoseph">Joseph Haslewood</ref>, no. 1879 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> – the collection of State Poems:<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Andrew Marvell (1621–1678; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Collection of Poems on Affairs of State by A. M. and Other Eminent Wits</title> (1689). Southey possessed an edition from 1702–1707, no. 2271 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> – Tiraboschi,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Girolami Tiraboschi (1731–1794), <title>Storia della Litteratura Italiana</title> (1777–1786), no. 2859 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – &#38; the Nibelungen in its original old German, &#38; its modern German version,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Gustav Gottlieb Busching (1783–1829),<title> Das Lied der Nibelungen</title> (1815), no. 265 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> the one helping me to understand the other. – Some of them I read after supper – some while taking my daily walk, – the rest in odds &#38; ends of time, laying down the pen when it does not flow freely, &#38; taking up a book for five or ten minutes by way of breathing myself.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I am much concerned at what you say of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>. He said in a letter to me some two months ago that his digestive powers were out of order, &#38; that if they continued so he should forego his intended journey into France, rather than be out of the way of medical advice. – So you have fallen in with Bigge,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles William Bigge (1773–1849), a landowner, banker and colliery owner in Northumberland. Southey and Bedford had known him at Westminster School.</note> – he is a great person in Northumberland. – Did I tell you that young Levett<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Levett (1775–1845), Rector of Ingestre 1809–1829, Deene 1811–1825, Church Eaton 1825–1829, and an old friend of Southey from Westminster School. His wife is unidentified.</note> &#38; his wife met me, on my late travels, in Hampshire? He has no children &#38; having a good income with his wife (about 700 £ a year I was told) had resigned a living of about the same amount from a very honourable motive. It had been given him by Lord somebody<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Chetwynd-Talbot, 2nd Earl Talbot (1777–1849; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Lieutenant of Ireland 1817–1821. He was a contemporary of Edward Levett at Christ Church, Oxford, and had been married to Frances Thomasine Lambart (d. 1819). Levett certainly had not broken with Talbot, as the latter appointed Levett to the Rectory of Church Eaton in 1825. The story of the reprobate peer may therefore refer to Robert Brudenell, 6th Earl of Cardigan (1760–1837), who appointed Levett as Rector of Deene in 1811. Cardigan was not, though, an Oxford contemporary of Levett.</note> – a College friend: – that Lord, after leading an exemplary domestic life till he was nearer 50 than 40 – chose to plant a mistress near his own abode in so scandalous a manner, that Levett found it necessary for his own feelings to withdraw from the neighbourhood, &#38; break off <del>in this manner</del> all connection with a man whom he could not reclaim &#38; who had forfeited all claim to his esteem. – We met very cordially, &#38; on both sides there would be a good disposition to meet again.</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
