<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4212" type="letter"><head>4212. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>,<date when="1824-07-08"> 8 July 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Sir Walter Scott Bart./ Abbotsford / Melrose<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Endorsement: 109<lb/>
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 3899. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Wilfred Partington, <title>The Private Letter-Books of Sir Walter Scott. Selections from the Abbotsford manuscripts ... Edited by Wilfred Partington</title> (London, 1930), pp. 80–82.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-07-08">8 July. 1824.</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Scott</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> owed me some reparation for sending me last week an account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsleys</ref> death, which thank God, has proved to be untrue, &#38; there are hopes of his recovery. She has made good amends for this needless sorrow (a heavy one the loss of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> would be!), by the real pleasure which it has given me to hear from you. The last &#60;letter&#62; which I received was written just after <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Ticknor</ref> left you, early in 1819,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Walter Scott to Robert Southey, 4 April 1819, John Gibson Lockhart, <title>Memoirs of the Life of Sir Walter Scott</title>, 7 vols (London, 1837–1838), VI, pp. 237–241.</note> – &#38; the last which I wrote was addrest to you in London to offer <del>xxx</del> a very hearty congratulation upon the honorary addition to your name.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Scott was created a baronet on 22 April 1820. Southey’s letter of congratulation does not seem to survive.</note> But I hate accounts of every kind, – so if two or three books of mine since that time have not found their way to you – as they ought to have done according to my directions – requiescant in pace.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Rest in peace’. Southey was referring to his <title>Vision of Judgement</title> (1821) and <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832). </note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> It was a mortification to me that I did not see you during my Scotch tour five years ago. But I past thro Selkirk at midnight in the mail, to join a party at Edinburgh, whom I brought home with me by the Glasgow road.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey arrived in Edinburgh at 5:15 a.m. on 17 August 1819, having travelled by mail coach from Carlisle. There he met his travelling companions, John and Susannah Rickman, their children, William (1812–1886) and Frances Rickman (dates unknown) and a Miss Pigott. It is difficult to be sure of her identity, but she might have been Emma Pigott (dates unknown), younger daughter and co-heiress of James Pigott (d. 1822) of Fitz-Hall, Iping, Sussex. She married, in 1824, Edward Brice Bunny (d. 1867) of Speen Hill, Berkshire. Their return journey to Keswick via Glasgow took place from 27 September–1 October 1819; see <title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), pp. 1–4, 254–269.</note> I saw a great deal of Scotland during that journey, &#38; was so interested with what I saw that I live in hopes of one day seeing the rest. I had resolution enough to keep a minute journal, which may probably see the light when the booksellers come to pick my bones &#38; make their last meal of me.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Journal of a Tour in Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (1929).</note> It was worth doing, for <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> was one of my companions so that I saw his piers, his roads &#38; the Caledonian Canal in progress, &#38; had all the information which I could desire concerning them, &#38; the localities every where.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, who is almost always on the move, has lately returned from the south.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth had visited London in March 1824, returning in June after a round of visits to friends in East Anglia and the Midlands.</note> How he is employed I know not, not having seen him since my own return in February last: but we shall probably see another crop of Odes &#38; Sonnets, in due season, – for the older he grows the more prolific he <del>xx</del> becomes. My springs are not dry, but they have ceased to flow. You remember poor Daniels complaint in his old age, </p>
            
            <lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">– Time has done to me this wrong</l>
               <l rend="indent3">To make me write too much &#38; live too long.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Daniel (1562–1619; <title>DNB</title>). Southey slightly misquotes from Daniel’s poem, ‘To the Prince’, lines 107–108, which was prefixed to his play <title>Philotas</title> (1604). The original text reads ‘But yeeres hath done this wrong,/ To make me write too much, and liue to long.’</note></l></lg>
            
           <p rend="indent1"> Time has brought no such injury to me as yet, but it has made me much more willing to learn than to teach, &#38; the <del>xx</del> eagerness with which I pursue my researches is much greater than the inclination which I feel for composing their results. Were it not that this also is a mode of learning (&#38; sometimes the best) I should find composition but an irksome task. At present I am printing the second volume of the Peninsular War,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> &#38; making collections for a longer series of historical works than I shall live to finish.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s unfinished ‘History of Portugal’.</note> As a proof however that my right hand hath not quite forgotten its cunning,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Psalms</title> 137: 5.</note> I will send you an Ode written upon occasion of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Kings</ref> visit to your country;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Scotland, an Ode, Written after the King’s Visit to that Country. By Robert Southey, Esq. Poet Laureat’, <title>The Bijou: Or Annual of Literature and the Arts</title> (London, 1828), pp. 81–88.</note> – one of my annual tasks, &#38; yet written with good will. It must travel to London for a frank. I will send it because it expresses a friendly [MS missing] as well as a British feeling.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  It would give me great pleasure if I could accept your hospitable invitation. There are few things which I should like so well – but we are looking for a succession of guests who will engage us till the autumn is advanced: &#38; what with indisposition which always lays me up at this time of year (this year more severely than usual) – &#38; engagements of society &#38; exercise which follow, – I find myself very much the slave of the desk during the other months.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> unites with me in kindest respects to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">Lady Scott</ref>.</p>
          <closer> <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me Dear Sir Walter</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  yrs most truly</salute>
         <signed rend="indent3">   Robert Southey</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
