<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4244" type="letter"><head>4244. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-09-10">10 September 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] Portsmouth Fourteenth Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1824/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ Lymington/ Hants/ Fr/ JRickman<lb/>
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 64 To Miss Caroline Bowles<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 3p. <lb/>
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 69–70.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-09-10">10 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1824</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>Dear Caroline</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Thank you for your verses,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles had offered to contribute ‘The Mariner’s Hymn’, later published in <title>Solitary Hours</title> (London, 1826), pp. 22–24, to Alfred Pettet’s <title>Original Sacred Music</title> (London, n.d., c. 1825–1827); when it was rejected it was replaced by ‘I weep, but not rebellious tears’, later published in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [227]–228.</note> – which I transcribed rather than part with the original, &#38; sent to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PettetAlfred">the poor musician</ref>. – I send you his Prospectus – &#38; take it for granted that he will send you the Work.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am fairly rid of my annual disease,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s annual attack of hay fever.</note> &#38; in other respects materially better than when my last was written, so much so that I was on the summit of Helvellin last week. Send me as good an account of your own amendment, &#38; we will look on to many meetings, – some of them I hope here – in this lovely land.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Soon I shall have more verses to send you.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Bowles were beginning work on ‘Robin Hood’. The resulting incomplete poem was published in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [1]–36.</note> You have <hi rend="ital">not</hi> proved yourself a defaulter yet. And I have more schemes for you. I have plans for three or four plays which you could execute, – for you will not pretend to deny or doubt that you can write dramatically.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Today we heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, &#38; of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> is still near Portsmouth, in high health &#38; spirits. Of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> I heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> under whose roof she is at this time. If she is not contented there, it will not be for want of kindness on the part of the family; – for if a dog was to scratch at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoots</ref> door with my name on his collar, he would be taken into the parlour, &#38; made as much of as your poor old Ranger, – whom I remember <del>with xx</del> in a manner that proves the truth of the old saying.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> This is a hasty letter – but I shall soon write again when I transmit a few more stanzas, – &#38; two half letters are better than one whole one</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you	</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
