<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4246" type="letter"><head>4246. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1824-09-11">11 September [1824]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: to/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmarks: E/ 14 SE 14/ 1824; [partial] OON.10/ SP.14/ 1824<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 248. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><date when="1824-09-11">Saturday 11 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
            
           <p rend="indent1"> I have just received your letter &#38; hasten to answer it, while I can, for <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> is with me for 24 hours, &#38; we shall have the Vicar<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">James Lynn (1776–1855), Perpetual Curate of Strood 1805–1814, Rector of Caldbeck 1814–1820, Vicar of Crosthwaite, Keswick 1820–1855.</note> in the evening. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> has been with his cousin <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> for the last week, where being of an age to like male companions better than female ones, he has probably been well amused. He stays his own time, &#38; tells me he shall return to day. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> who goes to Penrith tomorrow, will see that a place is taken for him in the mail of Thursday next, which reaches London on Friday night, by ten o clock I believe. <del>I xxxx xxxxx xxxx xx xxxx Cumberland xxx xxxxxxx xxx xxxxxx</del> It is almost certain that there will be a place; but if there should not, I shall be informed of it, &#38; will in that case of course apprize you that his going must be delayed for a day. He was very well when I saw him the day before yesterday.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> wrote to me about three weeks ago in reply to a letter which required a prescription. He spoke of passing much of his time upon the Hertfordshire road.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey was probably visiting his wife Louisa Southey’s family, as Mary Gonne, his mother-in-law, lived in Hertfordshire. </note> Other news from London I have none. I know nothing of the QR except that an article of mine which I corrected in the proofs ten weeks ago, has not been inserted, – &#38; that it has not been thought worth while either by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> or <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to say a word to me upon the subject.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of John Johnson (1769–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263–311. Southey had expected it to appear in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (January 1824), published 28 August 1824.</note> But if they carry their heads high, I shall raise mine. Meantime I am not ill employed in many ways, &#38; shall soon have printed a quarter of my second volume.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">The Bp of Limerick</ref> would fain have carried me to Ireland. It would have been very inconvenient to have gone, &#38; I had just at that time a malady which rendered it impossible. But I have half promised to visit him in May next, when I shall make the attempt to escape my summer catarrh by running away from it. At present I am well.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am living just now, &#38; have for the last six months, upon the Church.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> By &#38; by I may think of living upon the State.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write a companion volume, ‘The Book of the State’.</note> But I shall probably get rid of some verse first,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> &#38; probably also bring forth my Dialogues (which are now far advanced) upon the Progress &#38; Prospects of Society.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> writes me an excellent account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> who is now under his roof. She has the good fortune to make friends wherever she goes but there she had them ready made, for any thing which bears my name would find a warm reception there.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Let me hear how the Wickhamites<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Winchester College, in reference to the school’s founder, William of Wykeham (1320/4 – 1404). <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Errol Hill</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert Hill Jnr</ref> were pupils at Winchester School.</note> are going on. It will be a good thing to have that disease<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">There had been an outbreak of measles at Winchester School.</note> over, – one of the most perilous passes upon the road of childhood. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> has had some good mountain discipline, &#38; has I think enjoyed himself. He has made an acquaintance too in young William Calvert,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">William Calvert (1810–1841), the youngest son of William Calvert and later a surgeon in Bombay. He was admitted to Westminster School in 1824 but left in 1825.</note> who is going to Westminster. – &#38; who is in manners talent &#38; disposition <del>xxx</del> &#60;a boy&#62; with whom I should <del>wish him</del> be glad if he were to become intimate.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> desires his love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillGeorgiana">Georgiana</ref>, says he shall be very glad to see her one of these days, &#38; promises to send a kiss by <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>.</p>
               <closer> <salute rend="indent1">Love to my <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">Aunt</ref>. All well –</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">  God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> RS. </signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
