<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4267" type="letter"><head>4267. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1824-10-21">21 October 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 446–447.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener>  <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1824-10-21"> Oct. 21. 1824</date></dateline>
            
          <salute>  My dear Neville,</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I received yesterday the frank containing your letter and the first sheet of “Sir T. Browne.”<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">This refers to Sir Thomas Browne (1605–1682; <title>DNB</title>), a Norwich resident, doctor and writer on a huge range of subjects. ‘The Whole Works and Correspondence of Sir Thomas Browne, Knt. M. D. of Norwich’ was at this time advertised as forthcoming with Longmans, for example, in the <title>London Courier and Evening Gazette</title>, 2 October 1824. This was an early indication of Simon Wilkin’s edition, which did not appear until 1835–1836, though from the contents of this letter, he appears to have begun experimenting with printing the book as early as 1824. Southey acquired a copy and it became no. 376 in the sale catalogue of his library. </note> It cannot be worth while to send that sheet back, as I have no remarks to make upon it, further than to say that it is in every respect what could be wished. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Mr. Wilkin</ref> seems to have taken infinite pains in collecting editions and MSS., and nothing can be better than the printing. It might be worth while to try whether or not the appearance would be improved by printing the notes in columns. I am inclined to think it would be pleasanter for the eye where the type is so small, and also as distinguishing them in a more marked manner from the text.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This advice was followed by Wilkin. </note> This might be tried upon a single page. I am quite certain that in a folio the eye is less fatigued when the page is divided into columns, than when it has to move to and fro along a long line; and the effect must be the same in small printing upon an octavo page. A man thinks of these things as he approaches the age at which it becomes necessary for him to economise his sight.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Having written so recently, I have nothing to add, except to request that you will present my compliments to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilkinSimon">Mr. Wilkin</ref>, and tell him I am very glad he has taken the edition into his own hands, for I verily believe he will bestow upon it more diligence than any other person would or could have done. I have no memoranda upon the subject which could be of any use to him, but I will be of all the use I can when the work is published, and with the least possible delay. I hope there will be a portrait, and the name given in an autograph.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">An engraving of Browne’s portrait was included as an unpaginated frontispiece to the first volume of Wilkin’s edition, but Browne’s name was not printed as an autograph.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Our best remembrances to your fire–side and domestic circle. God bless you, my dear Neville,</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="salute1">Yours affectionately,</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
