<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4291" type="letter"><head>4291. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1824-12-12">12 December 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               Endorsement: Fr./ RS./ 12 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1824<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 455. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
        <opener>  <salute>  My dear R.</salute></opener>
          <p rend="indent1">  Thank you for the Salmon report in which I found more amusement than you anticipated.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Report from the Select Committee on the State of the Salmon Fisheries of the United Kingdom, and on the Modes of Improving Them (1824).</note> I could have had no conception that the destruction made by seals &#38; porpoises is so great as is there stated.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The winter I think will hardly pass over without a rebellion in Ireland<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Catholic Association had been formed in Ireland in 1823 to campaign for Catholic Emancipation. In 1824 it developed into a mass movement and pressure started to build for political reform.</note> – which I must say is well deserved by those who proceed upon the vile system of deserting their friends in the hope of conciliating their enemies. It is well that the objects of separation &#38; Catholic ascendancy should be broadly avowed, – &#38; as the crisis is inevitable, it cannot come too soon. I only hope the mischief may not extend here; – but certain it is that the English Radicals have had Agents in Ireland. The common revolutionary purpose cannot however prove a bond of union, when the rebellion assumes, as it will without delay or disguise, the character of a religious war.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Great as this evil will be, it is nothing when compared to that which would arise from the introduction of the Whig Liberals into the Cabinet, at which <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Canning</ref> is said to be aiming. Overture have been made to Lord Lansdowne<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquess of Lansdowne (1780–1863; <title>DNB</title>), a leading Whig and Chancellor of the Exchequer 1806–1807. When Canning became Prime Minister in 1827, Lansdowne joined his government as Home Secretary 1827–1828. He was later Lord President of the Council 1830–1834, 1835–1841, 1846–1852.</note> for himself &#38; Mackintosh,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir James Mackintosh (1765–1832; <title>DNB</title>), a lawyer, author and Whig MP for Nairnshire 1813–1818, MP for Knaresborough 1818–1832.</note> – but the former will not come in without Lords Grey<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Grey, 2nd Earl Grey (1764–1845; <title>DNB</title>), leading Whig and Prime Minister 1830–1834.</note> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Holland</ref>, – &#38; to <del>bring in</del> admit the last of these Lords would be giving up every thing, unless he were as good at <hi rend="ital">unsaying</hi> as <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">his Uncle</ref>, which I think he would not be, being more sincere in wrong-headedness. The object is to get rid of Lord Bathurst,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Bathurst, 3rd Earl Bathurst (1762–1834; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for War and the Colonies 1812–1827.</note> &#38; the other opponents of the Catholick question. But I trust that upon such an attempt, the whole confederacy would be kicked out, – for myself I would on such an occasion put on my iron-shod clogs to give a kick with the more effect.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> writes very good letters home, – &#38; is, she ought to be, very sensible of all the kindness she is receiving. I am glad to hear of her equestrian feats, – she has learnt more confidence in that useful art, than she could have had any opportunity of acquiring here.</p>
           <closer><salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
