<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Triangulating (Textual) History: What Early Black British Narratives Teach Us about
                    the Future to Come</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Elizabeth Fay </name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition>2024-12-10</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado
                    Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/ editor(s) and
                        advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
                        should be forwarded to Romantic Circles: <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition"
                    >praxis.2024.antislavery.fay</idno>
                <idno type="resource"
                    >antislavery</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">“Triangulating (Textual) History: What Early Black British Narratives Teach Us about
                            the Future to Come
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                                <surname>Fay</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr
                            target="praxis/antislavery/praxis.2024.antislavery.fay"/>
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"
                            >Romanticism and Anti-Slavery Literatures: Pedagogies and Contexts </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher> Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University
                                of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">December 11, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    
                    
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " to &#8220; or
                        &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed except in the case of
                        diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                        keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
                        such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
                        been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy
                    corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E"
                    xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
                    xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on
                        2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy
                    corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E"
                    xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on
                        2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Wingfield</name>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="abstract">
                <p>When we teach our students about the slave trade and the abolition movement, an Atlantic studies perspective that involves 
                    the circum-Atlantic trade of goods and persons is necessary to disrupt a white Anglo-American dialogue of historical persons 
                    and texts with a more fluid set of networks and relationships. In order to situate an Atlanticist pedagogy, I enlist the historical 
                    nautical strategy of triangulation between Africa, the Caribbean, and Britain in its metaphorical sense: the triangulation of three 
                    narratives within contextual materials; the triangulation of literary interpretation with historical and current interpretive concepts 
                    and methods; the triangulation of Atlantic coasts and land entities; and the triangulation of the strategic terms “fluidity,” “circulation,” 
                    and “movement” borrowed from nonliterary fields of study. Effectively, an Atlantic approach has the depth and breadth to put history, economic 
                    trade, political movements, and maritime realities in relation to rhetorical and figurative analysis of literary texts. </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Triangulating (Textual) History: What Early Black British Narratives Teach Us about
                    the Future to Come </head>    
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Elizabeth Fay</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>(University of Massachusetts Boston)</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
          
            <p>Romantic period studies has tended to focus on those literary and cultural concerns
                that apply to Anglo-American relations in terms of a transatlanticism belonging to a
                determinate timeframe. However, the Romantic period was an age of global capitalism,
                plundered resources, and cross-contamination; therefore, enlarging the
                Anglo-American dialogue of public voices and efficacious texts more expansively
                makes sense, as Bernard Bailyn and Joselyn M. Almeida have argued in separate
                contexts. Although I will be focusing here on the triangular relation of Africa,
                Britain, and British holdings in the Caribbean, folding into that relation the
                French colony of Saint Domingue and the American city Philadelphia for two of the
                texts discussed, the same argument for expanding the field of analysis holds for
                colonizers, the colonized, and brutalized or enslaved peoples of other territories
                within panatlantic land masses. The point of engaging with these histories, the
                ideologies that produced them, and the testimonies of survivors is that the concerns
                of the Atlantic world remain central to the concerns of today’s Atlantic and global
                reality. Historically, too, a more expansive treatment of the Romantic-era Atlantic
                world could put the trading circuits of the West Indies and the East Indies in
                dialogue; or one might make the connection for students between the working of West
                Indian plantations and the not-too-different circumstances of the diamond mines
                today in mineral-rich countries like the Democratic Republic of the Congo, nations
                whose people see no profit from the rapacious mining of their land by others. In
                terms of the transatlantic, this more expanded perspective is the interdisciplinary
                domain of Atlantic World studies, which involves a deep sense of history from plate
                changes in the ocean’s bottom to human geography (which, for example, examines
                migration patterns over centuries, death tolls among enslaved people, and movement
                between Caribbean islands and plantations).<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> Boelhower’s seminal essay remains
                            foundational for Atlantic studies.</note></p>
                
            <p>The dilemma of what can be crammed into a class discussion arises when the materials
                concerning the sites of literary production and dissemination (important for
                emphasizing the precarity of narratives and testimonials of enslaved peoples) can be
                enriched through contextualizing documents, such as those of charity organizations
                or Parliamentary records of abolitionist and other conservative documents. Yet I
                want to argue instead for a more engaged Atlanticist lens to broaden how we situate
                and affirm the complexities of Atlantic life for students, the malleable nature of
                Atlantic identity, and its opportunities for self-reinvention.<note place="foot" resp="author"> I also want
                            to caution against restricting ourselves to the British imperial when
                            teaching the Romantic period: the Black Atlantic intersects with the Red
                            Atlantic (the circulation, exchanges, and material productions of
                            indigenous peoples in the Atlantic and coastal regions of the Americas,
                            as well as their travels to Britain, Europe, and Africa), and the
                            Hispanic and Lusophone Atlantic world whose historical importance loomed
                            large in the period, as well as the Francophone Atlantic, all of which
                            extend our teaching about British Empire through these other
                            circulations and imperial networks.</note> To think
                pedagogically using such a lens has allowed me to think more broadly geographically
                and temporally in order to situate the revolutionary aspects of Atlantic life in the
                Romantic period. My main strategy is one I adapted from the nautical strategy of
                triangulation to teach literary interpretation of narratives and testimonials of
                enslaved persons, historical texts or information, related texts and websites in
                groups of three, and to apply Atlantic studies concepts and methods in connection
                with literary analysis. The strategy of triangulation has been richly explored in
                the work of Bailyn, Jeremy Smith, Almeida, Rebecca Cole Heinowitz, and others.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See also
                            Aguirre (2005), Brown (2008), Heinowitz (2010), Robson (2011), Tutino
                            (2016), and Cañizares-Esguerra (2018).</note> Against the
                Anglo-American oppositional model, triangulation is not just adding a middle term to
                create a dialectical engagement; rather, it involves the fluid movement of dynamic
                relationality among multiple and variable subjects. In this way texts can be
                revisited several times to re-see them, and the strategic terms “fluidity,”
                “circulation,” and “movement” help students approach the revisiting as necessary and
                deepening rather than repetitive. This strategy has helped me unpack with my
                students a vitally mobile and contingent arena in which texts embodying this dynamic
                can be read against those stemming from empire, against each other, and within a
                network of unstable conditions and circumstances.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> See in particular Almeida 69, 105–6,
                            197, 200, 325; and Bailyn (2005).</note></p>
                
            <p>Moreover, broadening the historical horizon from an Atlantic World perspective allows
                students to view the slave trade, abolition, and radical politics during the
                Romantic period as conversant with our contemporary politics. The courageous voices
                of those enslaved during the Romantic period take on a new legitimacy for my most
                recent students, compared with the way earlier student cohorts had responded to such
                texts; current students can more readily hear and empathize with the outrage of
                those from so long ago. This outrage responds to the authority of lived experience.
                While students understand that the value of <hi rend="italic">this</hi> singular
                life made clear in individually voiced accounts was politically important to the
                abolitionist cause, the personal and communal resilience that such accounts express
                was necessary then and comes across all these many years later to be heard in all
                its dignity. These voices, then, can be further complicated (rather than polarizing
                them against the claims of colonists and politicians) with the biographies of
                figures like Baron de Vastey, who Marlene Daut has argued was signal for the
                development of a “[B]lack Atlantic humanism.” In counterpoint to Toussaint
                L’Ouverture’s rhetorical promotion of brotherhood across color lines, Vastey, a
                Haitian of biracial descent and Toussaint’s contemporary, critiques colonial
                dependencies on slavery. The slave trade and the high morbidity of slave labor,
                Vastey unceasingly argued, reveals that a free-market economy is merely an
                ideological justification for the inexcusability of racism.</p>
                
            <p>Using material like Daut’s <hi rend="italic">Baron de Vastey and The Origins of Black
                    Atlantic Humanism</hi> (2017) to set the triangle trade within cosmopolitan
                humanism, as well as other globalizing contextual materials (the competition between
                goods produced in the East Indies and the West Indies, for instance), expands the
                horizon of how we teach the transatlantic and the Atlantic world, but only if those
                singular voices are heard as integrated with larger contexts. Accounts of formerly
                enslaved persons are important for our students because, although mediated for a
                white audience, they make disclosures about lived experience that novels can only
                gesture to, especially for those students who resist the empathy necessarily
                involved in reading actual accounts, and worse, the documentation of abusive planter
                    practices.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            See Thomas’s excellent <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Slave
                                Narratives</hi> (2000), which has greatly helped me in teaching
                            Black British writing, as well as Aljoe’s <hi rend="italic">Creole
                                Testimonies</hi> (2012), which distinguishes between the testimonial
                            and the narrative in terms of authorial voice and rhetorical strategy.
                            More recently, Chander and Matthew’s “Abolitionist Interruptions” has
                            extended how to think about slave narrative and about antislavery
                            literature as a genre.</note> While I rely on the arguments of
                Mark Salber Phillips for understanding historical distance through the narrative
                function, that gut-level pain is also interpretatively valid. To make connections
                between textual accounts in a way that makes for meaningful interpretation, I have
                found that starting with an emotionally rather than physically painful event can
                translate what students may be feeling into something we can discuss and then extend
                to other connections between the texts that are more politicized, and therefore more
                rhetorically inflected.</p>
                
            <p>For instance, in my recent course offering, I asked students to look at a similar
                event in Mary Prince’s and Olaudah Equiano’s narratives, and then to contrast it
                with Toussaint’s experience.<note place="foot" resp="author"> I found Todorova’s essay on Prince and Boulukos’s
                            and Mallipeddi’s essays on Equiano extremely helpful for triangulating
                            these texts for students.</note> Prince’s account of the end of
                childhood, when her mistress sends her to work at another house, is charged with the
                distress of the twelve-year-old girl; but the moment when her mother has to take her
                and her sisters to the slave market to be sold after the death of her mistress,
                despite the distance of years at the time of writing, is suffused with emotional
                pain at confronting this final separation from family and home. Beginning with the
                day before, she writes: “Oh dear! I cannot bear to think of that day,—it is too
                much.—It recalls the great grief that filled my heart, and the woeful thoughts that
                passed to and fro through my mind, whilst listening to the pitiful words of my poor
                mother, weeping for the loss of her children” (3). In describing the next morning,
                Prince uses funereal language to depict the emotional death she and her mother feel
                at this moment: “The black morning at length came. . . . Whilst she was putting on
                us the new osnaburgs in which we were to be sold, she said, in a sorrowful voice, (I
                shall never forget it!) ‘See, I am
                <hi rend="italic">shrouding </hi>my poor children; what a task
                for a mother!’” (3). This chilling moment, in which the mother has to sell her own
                children at the slave market, is heartrending in itself, while Prince’s use of
                language and word choice feels authentic rather than rhetorically distant (“I shall
                never forget it!”); the imagery of a funeral rather than a marketplace symbolizes
                the death of the subject-self that being sold is meant to create. But the
                exclamations and the never-forgotten emotion reveal, just as surely, that Prince has
                held on to her subjectivity in a way that students can now see is revealed
                throughout her narrative; Prince is a strong woman, one who can advocate through her
                story, and so provide a heroic model of fortitude in the face of extreme
                suffering.</p>
                
            <p>Equiano has a similar and compelling story to tell about the rending of a family.
                Although his begins with his sister’s and his abduction by African “slavers,” his
                parents never to be seen again, their strong sibling bond sustains them until the
                fatal moment when they are broken apart.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> “Slavers” was the term commonly used in
                            the period for those engaged in capturing or gathering individuals for
                            selling to others.</note> I ask students to closely examine the
                two scenes, Prince’s and Equiano’s, to compare the affective impact of their uses of
                rhetoric.</p>
                
            <p>One day . . . I saw one of those people come into the yard of our next neighbour but
                one, to kidnap, there being many stout young people in it. Immediately on this I
                gave the alarm. . . . But alas! ere long it was my fate to be thus attacked, and to
                be carried off, when none of the grown people were nigh. . . . But alas! we were
                soon deprived of even the small comfort of weeping together. . . . [F]or my sister
                and I were then separated, while we lay clasped in each other’s arms. (62)</p>
                
            <p>Rhetorically, the “But, alas!” repetition has a lot of work to do, but for a modern
                reader, it can’t carry the weight of the experienced trauma in the way that Prince’s
                “Oh dear! I cannot bear to think of that day,—it is too much.—” still does. If
                Equiano’s response to the loss of his sister is different from Prince’s and perhaps
                strikes the reader as pathos-filled rather than grief-stricken—so that students try
                to locate the difference in experienced pain contextually—I’ve found it helpful to
                shift their attention to seeing that the way the story is told can change the
                emotional register, and that the way emotion is being put to use should not
                influence us to value or devalue one person’s pain over another’s, given our
                historical biases. Critical context thus informs students’ understanding of the
                disruptive force of the Atlantic trade during this period and the valuation of
                bodies in a marketplace that took no account of pain.<note place="foot" resp="author"> The Portuguese created a
                            slave-trade category for the standard measure in valuing Black lives,
                            the “pieza” (“piece”). Drawing on C. L. R. James’s research, Wynter
                            explains that a pieza “was a man of twenty-five years, approximately, in
                            good health, calculated to give a certain amount of physical labor. He
                            served as the general equivalent of physical labor value against which
                            all the others could be measure—with for example, three teenagers
                            equaling one pieza and older men and women thrown in a job lot as
                            refuse” (Wynter 81, as cited by Mignolo, 114).</note> Equiano
                openly states that his own father owned enslaved people, a repugnant fact for many
                students; he also explains the practice of African enslavers in terms of kidnapping
                and domestic servitude and in opposition to the brutality of the triangle slave
                trade. This sometimes leads students to dismiss Equiano’s narrative. But by getting
                students to look for resemblance rather than difference, they can then see that like
                Prince, Equiano also tries to find a sense of home when he is with kinder people,
                and yet whereas she finds her real sense of “home” in her own strong sense of self,
                he continually remakes himself, transforming himself fluidly through the
                circulations of ship voyages he participates in. He makes himself into an Atlantic
                identity, so that he’s at home everywhere—on shipboard, in Philadelphia, in London,
                and so on—whereas we sense that Prince is never at home except within herself. And
                his rhetorical style is not just due to the temporal distance between the act of
                writing and biographical events; Equiano is becalmed as he writes his narrative,
                stilled by the land he now inhabits and the perhaps unyielding political audience he
                addresses.</p>
                
            <p>In his <hi rend="italic">The Black Jacobins</hi> (1938), which tells the history of
                St. Domingue and Toussaint L’Ouverture’s extraordinary transformation of the colony
                into a free state by 1803, C. L. R. James refuses the fiction of historical
                objectivity; students immediately respond to his passionate engagement with his
                story and his protagonist, and the book is filled with his exclamatory asides.
                Toussaint suffers none of the rending of family that Prince and Equiano experience,
                and so James’s indignation is focused on the abuses endemic to slavery and those
                historians who had covered it over. “A venal race of scholars, profiteering panders
                to national vanity, have conspired to obscure the truth about abolition,” he rails
                (51). By contrast, Toussaint “was so genuinely kind to the whites in their
                distressful condition that they could not fail to appreciate it” (157). James cannot
                but revel in the man’s political acuity and gracious use of political speech acts
                and his tolerance as a political leader for everyone in St. Domingue; his voice and
                message are clear in quotations from letters and speeches: “Learn, citizens, to
                appreciate the glory of your new political status. In acquiring the rights that the
                Constitution accords to all Frenchmen, do not forget the duties it imposes on you.
                Be but virtuous and you will be French men and good citizens. . . . Work together
                for the prosperity of San Domingo . . . [to] assure public well-being” (205). I
                point out to students how this passage, and Toussaint’s worry over “the fate of some
                unhappy whites who have been victims in this business” (157), is in stark contrast
                to James’s own assessment of white treatment of Blacks: “The difficulty was that
                though one could trap them like animals, . . . and beat both [man and animal] with
                the same stick, . . . they remained, despite their black skins and curly hair, quite
                invincibly human beings” (11).</p>
                
            <p>To situate James’s passionate history, I ask students to read Sylvia Wynter’s article
                on James, “Beyond the Categories of the Master Conception,” which clarifies her own
                theoretical adaptation of James’s Afro-Caribbean-based theory of capitalism as a
                colonial-based rather than a trade-based economy, one requiring enslaved labor
                rather than wage labor. The bourgeois development of capitalism that overthrew a
                monarchy-based economy depended on the development of a colonial scheme built on
                unpaid labor from colonists, indentured servants, and enslaved persons. The
                monarchial symbolics of blood (blood lineage, vassalage, war), as Wynter explains,
                was replaced by a symbolics of skin color, the effects of which still reverberate
                today. Wynter posits the human condition of “becoming [B]lack” to explain the way
                that discourse co-produces social experience along with colonial capitalism for
                anyone who, we could say, has not undergone “becoming white.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Mignolo (116). “Becoming white” is my addition so that
                        students understand the concept of race as a discursive
                    formation.</note> Discourse produces the knowledge that one is becoming
                Black in a repetition of experience that daily announces this condition, whether the
                year is 1800 or 2024.</p>
                
            <p>For students, then, firsthand accounts put the entire phenomenon of the slave trade
                into perspective, and for some students of color, especially those who are African,
                African American, or Caribbean American, firsthand accounts can be empowering, while
                secondhand accounts like James’s can reinforce that self-empowerment. These
                firsthand narratives give students a sense of what self-determining voices like
                Prince’s, Equiano’s, and Toussaint’s sounded like. The inner strength and the
                courage to simply live a life, or to trade up one’s own life-value, or to liberate a
                people, comes through in these narratives. Romantic literature gains a special
                meaning for these students, one that speaks to them in today’s contexts; it can also
                give them a history of strength, endurance, and courage. Texts from the more recent
                past, such as James’s, and from today’s headlines or popular genres add resonance to
                making personal connections with such a history. Identifying with texts from a
                different time and culture has resulted in multiple end-of-the-semester research
                papers on Equiano and women’s slave testimonials, as well as a comparative treatment
                of women’s escape narratives in the period. Recently a student has also used
                information from short lectures I gave on the slavery and human trafficking
                practices at this time on the Barbary Coast and in the Ottoman Empire to develop a
                paper on Equiano that sets him in a wider context of slaver practices historically
                and within the period.</p>
                
            <p>In using an Atlanticist lens to teach this material, I try to return our focus to the
                networks of colonialism wherever this approach makes sense, because more was at
                stake in the triangle slave trade than the economy of bodies. The forward trajectory
                of the larger stakes surely begins with the population decimation of northwestern
                Africa and the overpopulation of the West Indies, but they include the monoculture
                practices of Caribbean plantations (and continuing today with Caribbean banana
                plantations, for instance), which—concurrently with the rise in Western national
                gross products—also changed the natural resource structure of Caribbean terrain.
                Through increased commerce in peoples, animals, plants, and goods, the slave trade
                also grossly heightened the effects and pace of anthropocenic change, giving
                students a sense of how disastrous history can affect worlds as well as peoples.<note place="foot" resp="author"> See Carney
                            and Rosomoff’s <hi rend="italic">In the Shadow of Slavery</hi> (2009).
                            To teach students about the expansiveness of trade networks involving
                            African kingdoms, see Thornton’s authoritative <hi rend="italic">Africa
                                and Africans in the Making of the Atlantic World</hi>
                        (1992).</note></p>
                
            <p>But the textual analysis I’ve been putting forth still does not suggest the economy
                of movement that Atlantic life involves, and metaphor is a helpful intervention
                here, specifically the chronotope of the ship.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> This is the chronotope that Gilroy,
                            following Bakhtin, explicitly calls attention to in <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Black Atlantic</hi> (1993) (17).</note> That the ship
                should also be understood literally through viewing the virtual slave ship on the
                SlaveVoyages.org website gives the metaphor powerful resonance in its suggestion of
                mobility and flexible use. To image fluidity, movement (a term encompassing more
                than human mobility and displacement), and circulation of the Atlantic world, the
                metaphor of the Atlantic-ranging ship is perhaps unsurpassed. Whereas both fluidity
                and circulation take into account the stagnation of being becalmed, Equiano’s
                autobiography underscores how thriving among aquatic conditions requires
                understanding oneself, or at least one’s life, in terms of the vessel that sails
                such waters. Living in and on the Atlantic waterways requires at the very least
                having an abiding interest in shipping news and port landings; in order to flourish,
                however, of more value would be possessing a working knowledge of the vessel and,
                indeed, the classificatory terminology used for distinguishing vessels and their
                component parts. These, as Equiano’s life story reflects, were key not just to ship
                life but also to life itself: ship life <hi rend="italic">was</hi>, in a sense,
                Atlantic life. And learning to navigate—as Equiano does—requires a more flexible
                thinking, one based on a triangulating impulse that can reconcile oppositions
                through adjacencies and affiliations.</p>
                
            <p>Triangulation—not just the juxtaposition of three terms but the fluid and dynamic
                movement between them—is key, I argue, to teaching Romanticism in terms of Atlantic
                movement, whether we are working with the binaries of the Anglo-American
                transatlantic or with the multiple triangulations of the Caribbean islands and
                Atlantic littoral that are always in play or potentially so. Putting the Atlantic
                ship metaphor and triangulation together, we might consider what the triangle slave
                trade has culturally produced as our heritage, the disturbed flow of water and lives
                that Christina Sharpe argues in <hi rend="italic">In the Wake: On Blackness and
                    Being</hi> (2016) is demonstrably ongoing. The “wake” figures a disruptive
                dimension in the lives of African Americans that began with a cut across what had
                been, the ship cutting across the ocean’s own waves as it cuts into lives, cuts off
                lives, and changes human relations in monstrous ways. In this sense, the United
                States is in relation not only to Britain and the West African coast but also in
                relation to the ocean and its human footprint on land, an ongoing relation of
                turmoil. Understanding the West’s impact on the West Indies during this period gives
                students a way to place Romanticism within their twenty-first-century perspective,
                not only as a chapter in the difficult history of enslavement but also as part of an
                aspirational identity, of a heroism born of struggle that is evidenced in the
                narratives of formerly enslaved persons, where singular voices, accounts of
                uprisings and attempted uprisings, and the hopes and aspirations that fueled
                abolition and emancipation can be found.</p>
                
            <p>To think Atlantically allows me to pose one regulative idea—that of the world as a
                centered experience that affirms the uniqueness of the white enfranchised self that
                is supported by peripheral others, in contrast to the disenfranchised (the world, in
                other words, of the colonial economic system)—against another regulative idea of the
                Atlantic as a fluid world of multiple and mobile players. It allows me to keep my
                students focused on the dynamic, fluid relation between center and periphery, larger
                and local contexts, and what is counted (money, bodies, trade items) and what does
                not count (lives). These are also the problems of sovereignty, and what in years
                past Romantic studies mainly focused on; they have only been transformed, but not
                displaced, in the slave trade economy and are the problems that Equiano marshals so
                well for his tale of self-recovery, innovation, and reinvention.</p>
                
            <p>The triangulation of texts, contextualized through websites on the histories of
                abolition and the slave trade, as well as a web-video of life on a virtual slave
                ship, a reconstruction of <hi rend="italic">L’Aurore</hi> (see also Rediker), allows
                students to connect to the voices that so clearly and emphatically tell their story
                or the stories of others. Most recently, the three chosen texts were those of
                Prince, Equiano, and James, which when triangulated situate the African, West
                Indian, and St. Domingue experience in a deeply involved perspective that includes
                the newly independent United States.<note place="end"
                            > I find that research on slave testimonials
                            further helps students metabolize the truly painful passages of these
                            texts: both Thomas’s <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Slave
                                Narratives</hi> and Aljoe’s <hi rend="italic">Creole
                                Testimonies</hi> have proved invaluable here.</note> Thus
                Equiano’s, Prince’s, and Toussaint’s achievements (self-improvement,
                self-liberation, and the liberation of a people) participate in the very conditions
                that fueled the French Revolution, financed by France’s slave-trade-enriched
                bourgeoisie, and the English abolition movement, which, as James argues, was
                encouraged by William Pitt as prime minister to deflect other political tensions
                (53–4). But triangulation requires positioning and revisiting: following Prince’s
                story with Equiano’s is achronological, but his rhetorically sophisticated style,
                because it distances and softens raw experience, allows for a more appreciative
                revisiting of Prince’s rhetorical moves. The clear parallels between Prince’s story
                of British colonial enslavement and Toussaint’s political speechmaking as he
                liberates both his fellow slaves and his island from colonial legal, economic, and
                political control enable students to bring together the three texts through both
                formal and experiential commonalities and differences.</p>
                
            <p>To balance the firsthand narrative unit on Prince, Equiano, and the Haitian
                Revolution, I designed a second unit focusing on women’s experience in fictional
                texts. Beginning with the anonymously authored <hi rend="italic">The Woman of
                    Colour, A Tale</hi> (1808), the students then read Jane Austen’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi> (1814), a novel that creates comparisons
                between women whose wealth makes them decadent and women who regard morality as more
                valuable. In each case the heroine’s transplantation into a different family depends
                on a reliance on the wealth generated by exploiting legal and capitalist networks
                that masked over the horrors of enslavement. Olivia Fairfield is the daughter of a
                Jamaican plantation owner and the majestic Marcia, a gifted but enslaved African
                woman. The conditions of Mr. Fairfield’s will are that Olivia is to be married into,
                or become the dependent of, her relations, the English Merton family. Fanny Price is
                adopted into her uncle Bertram’s family as a charity case, and in this sense Olivia
                and Fanny have opposed relations to plantation wealth but are in a chiasmic relation
                to each other that students can appreciate: the biracial heroine brings wealth with
                her, the white heroine brings only her poverty. Sir Thomas makes his wealth from his
                own Antiguan plantations though his family members, like Olivia’s relations in the
                Merton family, are residents in England. In both novels the women of these families
                display the decadent lifestyles and egocentrism created by West Indian caste
                divisions, and so stand in for what Olivia calls “the most die-away lady on the
                whole island of Jamaica” (73).<note place="foot" resp="author"> When applied to women, “die-away” signified
                            “languorous” and overly sentimental.</note> Both Olivia and
                Fanny take the role of outside observer, Olivia through her Jamaican birth and
                biracial identity and Fanny through her parents’ downward social mobility. Both are
                treated by their adoptive families as different in appearance (Olivia is beautiful
                and biracial, while Fanny is small and plain) and in kind (Olivia has a Black
                mother, and Fanny has a disreputable father). And both make observations that
                explicitly (Olivia) or implicitly (Fanny) compare the women of their adoptive
                families to the “decadent” behavior of West Indian women.</p>
                
            <p>However, in both novels the authorial insistence on a moral tale to be made of plot
                and characters enables the Caribbean plantation system itself to be glossed over. In
                    <hi rend="italic">The Woman of Colour</hi> this gloss is effected through
                Olivia’s fond remembrances of life on her father’s plantation, her frequent remarks
                concerning her firm connection to her enslaved brethren, and her affectionate
                descriptions of her maid Dido, whose race and pidgin English make clear her formerly
                enslaved status. In <hi rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi>, the masking is provided
                by Fanny’s translation of her uncle’s business concerns into a paternal treatment of
                his enslaved workers stemming from his moral rectitude. When these two novels are
                triangulated with Leonora Sansay’s short novel <hi rend="italic">Secret History; or,
                    The Horrors of St. Domingo</hi>, which like <hi rend="italic">The Woman of
                    Colour</hi> was also published in 1808, the plantation system’s inequities are
                unmasked. The white American narrator, Mary, visiting with her sister Clara in 1803,
                makes frequent criticisms of the behavior and regulation of different castes of
                women, from “coloured women” in general contrast to “white women,” to distinctions
                between “Mulatto” women (light-skinned biracial women), Creoles (white women born in
                St. Domingue, soon to be Haiti), French women (immigrants and visitors from France),
                and outsiders like Mary. Not only do sartorial distinctions demarcate castes among
                women in St. Domingue, but “here female virtue is blasted in the bud by the
                contagious influence of example” (96).</p>
                
            <p>As Sansay presents it, the very Caribbean air taints moral choice since sexual
                attraction alone determines women’s (limited) agency, so that “the mulatto women are
                the hated but successful rivals of the Creole ladies,” for they not only appear to
                be sexier but are also often wealthy: “before the revolution their splendor, their
                elegance, their influence over the men, and the fortunes lavished on them by their
                infatuated lovers, so powerfully excited the jealousy of the white ladies, that they
                complained to the council of the ruin their [“mulatto” women’s] extravagance
                occasioned to many [white] families, and a decree was issued imposing restrictions
                on their dress” (95).<note place="foot" resp="author"> Mary doesn’t seem to
                        know that “Mulatto” wealth more usually came from sons inheriting land and
                        money from their white fathers. She also doesn’t acknowledge “Noirs”
                        (persons of African birth, freed by Toussaint’s revolution) or most of the
                        other caste divisions that regulated life in St. Domingue.</note>
                Contrasted with the decadence of sexually explicit behavior is the novel’s real
                focus on political revolution; Toussaint’s post-revolutionary reign is looked
                forward to as utopian in comparison to the invading French forces there to support
                the white plantation owners. The armed forces’ destructive violence is mirrored in
                acts of male sexual aggression, exemplified in the rape of Mary’s sister Clara by
                her abusive husband, St. Louis. Sex and politics come together in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Secret History</hi> in a manner that turns the lens on <hi rend="italic">The
                    Woman of Colour</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi>: suddenly
                students can realize how the sexual politics of those novels divide out into sexual
                aggression, the politics of race, and the loss of any moral compass when wealth
                depends on the unacknowledged suffering of enslaved laborers.</p>
                
            <p>To provide a component to this fictional unit that ties it back to the real-life
                narratives of Prince, Equiano, and Toussaint, I include here the first chapter of
                Sharpe’s <hi rend="italic">In the Wake</hi>. Sharpe’s meditations on, and
                theorization of, the historical effects of colonial schemes of skin color symbolism
                that Wynter analyzes yoke the development of colonial economies based on unpaid and
                enslaved labor. Sharpe’s reflections on her own and her family’s experience of the
                colonial symbolics of skin color (registered in Sansay’s delineation of the higher
                levels of St. Domingue’s caste system) illustrate so clearly how the colonial
                economy continues to mark the daily life of African Americans now. In the wake of
                the triangle slave trade, “the past that is not past reappears, always, to rupture
                the present” (9). Sharpe’s narrative, with its rhetorical insistence on the past’s
                ongoing harm, does more to make the connections between fiction and real-life
                narratives than news reports alone can do. As she notes, “Transatlantic slavery was
                and is the disaster” (5). Adding Sharpe’s critical reflections intermixed with
                personal narrative has the advantage of pulling the narrative and fictional units
                together because it enables further conversation about the economic and emotional
                risks of living in, and in the wake of, the triangle slave trade. This relates to
                Wynter’s analysis, which allows a conversation about colonial economies as a
                discourse concerning one’s relative worth.</p>
                
            <p>The question of personal versus fictionalized experience becomes a way to avoid
                simply comparing different encounters of slave and colonial life, racial prejudice,
                and degrees of gender violence. Instead this comparison allows readers to
                triangulate and thus revisit/revise these three elements of the slave trade that the
                two units raise, allowing additional questions, such as one of inclusion/exclusion:
                Who is an insider, we could ask, and who is excluded in the system of colonial
                economy? Prince, Equiano, and Olivia present different kinds of outsider status, for
                instance. Moreover, female characters’ treatment at the hands of (usually white) men
                provides a quite different way to think about movement as well as about the stormy
                violence of the colonial economy and requires thinking harder about the movement
                through the color caste system in both British and French colonial and postcolonial
                life.</p>
                
            <p>Regardless of the texts selected to teach students how to see the experience of
                enslaved persons as belonging to lives that mattered, what has made the most
                difference in teaching this topic has been to find ways to make historical texts
                relevant. In order to move beyond that framework, I have begun working with current
                events and Afrofuturism. A useful supplemental text for exploring Afrofuturism is an
                essay by the award-winning novelist N. K. Jemisin, “How Long ’til Black Future
                Month?,” which provides a quick introduction to the main ideas of Afrofuturism.<note place="foot" resp="author"> This is also
                            the title of a collection of short stories by Jemisin, who is best known
                            for her <hi rend="italic">Broken Earth </hi>trilogy
                            (2015–2017), which won three Hugo awards. See also
                    O’Connell.</note> Writers like Samuel Delany and Octavia Butler made
                science fiction the most significant genre for Afrofuturist literature and film;
                these are texts that recast enslavers and colonists through the sci-fi tradition of
                encounter narratives.<note place="foot" resp="author"> H. G. Wells’s <hi rend="italic">The Time
                                Machine</hi> (1895), <hi rend="italic">The War of the Worlds</hi>
                            (1898), and <hi rend="italic">The First Men in the Moon</hi> (1901)
                            established the tradition. Andre Norton’s <hi rend="italic">Witch
                                World</hi> series (1963–1968) and Arthur C. Clarke’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Space Odyssey</hi> series (1968–1997) are well-known
                            first-encounter narratives.</note> An easily referenced text
                for teaching is the 2018 film <hi rend="italic">Black Panther</hi>, in which the
                imbrication of past, present, and future is clearly dramatized. In the film, the
                villain, Klaue, is depicted as an archetypal white adventurer despoiling African
                resources, but rather than being characterized as European he is clearly meant to
                suggest a heritage from the two Boer states of colonial Africa, with their brutal
                treatment of those inhabiting what is now South Africa. The Black Panther, T’Challa,
                defeats this despoiler and thus revises the historical first encounter with white
                enslavers; instead, we have a failed encounter that strengthens the progressive
                futurism of the Wakanda nation. This is not the best example, however, since Klaue
                should have been colonized by the Wakandan citizens, so asking students why Klaue’s
                death at the hands of T’Challa is a departure from Afrofuturism helps them see how
                easy it is to accept more pasteurized versions of Black narratives.</p>
                
            <p>“First encounter” narratives, made standard through works such as H. G. Wells’s <hi
                    rend="italic">The War of the Worlds</hi> (1898), merge with “second encounter”
                narratives so that the slave trade and colonial past is the pattern through which
                alien encounter is perceived, with the alien becoming the colonized victim of such
                thinking, and yet like the historical enslaved person, a victim who bears gifts. To
                historical enslaved people’s cultural and ideological gifts, these imagined aliens
                add technological and politically liberating gifts. Contrasting this model with the
                plot of <hi rend="italic">Black Panther</hi> allowed my students to view Equiano’s
                representation of slavery, kind masters, and British political elites as pasteurized
                rather than simply self-serving (as students often read his narrative). Most
                importantly, connecting the texts they are studying with the regulative idea of
                Afrofuturism—that sovereign nations need the induction of alien life in order to
                become even more democratic, free, and at peace—allows students to consider the
                problem of both individual sovereignty and national sovereignty as the product of
                fluidity and movement. It is not a given, it can be taken away, and it must always
                be put into conversation with the interrelatedness of ocean and land.</p>
                
            <p>When we revisited Equiano’s narrative after the <hi rend="italic">Black Panther</hi>
                exercise, I focused class discussion on the plan for a free Black state in Sierra
                Leone that Equiano participates in near the very end of his narrative; my students
                were able to rethink the potential of such an undertaking while also understanding
                it as a charity project rather than a utopian one (it is planned by “some
                philanthropic individuals” [242]). Pitting this scheme, devised by white
                politicians, against the utopian nation of Wakanda also helps us see why Equiano
                would have been so wary of the project: it lacks Wakanda’s self-determination
                arising from individual participation <hi rend="italic">and</hi> the necessary
                funding and resources (individual sovereignty <hi rend="italic">and</hi> national
                sovereignty). Through the contextualizing lens of Afrofuturism, my students came to
                the recognition that any settlement, however utopian, displaces those who already
                inhabit the land, disturbing the eco-balance of lives lived for both the established
                inhabitants and for the newcomers. In other words, the past can’t be undone by
                charity and welfare schemes; the hard work has to be done here in this place, as
                both the abolitionist materials and the lesson of Wakanda’s self-determination make
                clear. A useful discussion point is already provided here in thinking about our own
                future regarding territorialization practices versus Atlantic fluidity, the
                circulation and triangulations of persons and things versus the requirement for
                self-determination and lives well lived.</p>
                
            <p>Just as the slave trade fueled white liberationist politics in both Britain’s
                American colonies and revolutionary France, so too has it grounded and set the stage
                for the more expansive empire through an increasingly laissez-faire liberally
                sanctioned world economy. Students begin to see the relation between things as they
                are and the horrifying, daily violence of the exchange in enslaved persons as
                mercantile objects. The necessity of teaching about the slave trade and the
                experience of enslavement alongside the heroized narratives of abolitionist
                political labor can be empowering in that it allows for the possibility of thinking
                about the future otherwise than in a traumatic and posthuman way. Certainly we must
                ask: What will prevail in the Atlantic world when environmental damage takes too
                great a toll on human habitations of the Caribbean? Or when the coastal cities and
                other human developments in the circum-Atlantic are submerged or simply destroyed?
                But a sense of play through more fluid boundaries allows space for students to
                imagine a different world-making from the one we have known and that currently goes
                on without our much noticing. It allows for thinking about different kinds of
                heroism, different ways of achieving self-determination against the apparently
                unstoppable weight of globalism. It allows for considering the ship in a stormy sea:
                fluidity and flexibility are the necessary survival skills, but they must be
                combined with a persistence to endure, a Mary-Prince-like self-heroism and a
                Toussaint-like tolerance. It seems to me that Atlanticism is poised to locate such
                an imagination, if we allow its triangulatory effects room to do this kind of
                work.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="citation">
                
            <head>Works Cited</head>
                
            <bibl>Aguirre, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Informal Empire.</hi> Univ. of Minnesota Press,
                2005.</bibl>
            <bibl>Aljoe, Nicole. <hi rend="italic">Creole Testimonies: Slave Narratives from the
                    British West Indies, 1709–1838</hi>. Palgrave Macmillan, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl>Almeida, Joselyn M. <hi rend="italic">Reimagining the Transatlantic, 1780–1890</hi>.
                Ashgate, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl>Anonymous. <hi rend="italic">The Woman of Colour, A Tale</hi>. Edited by Lyndon J.
                Dominique. Broadview, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl>Austen, Jane. <hi rend="italic">Mansfield Park</hi>. Edited by June Sturrock.
                Broadview, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl>Bailyn, Bernard. <hi rend="italic">Atlantic History: Concept and Contours.</hi>
                Harvard Univ. Press, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Black Panther</hi>. Directed by Ryan Coogler. Marvel Studios,
                2018.</bibl>
            <bibl>Boelhower, William. “‘I’ll teach you how to flow’: On Figuring Out Atlantic Studies.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Atlantic Studies</hi> 1, no. 1 (2004): 28–48.</bibl>
            <bibl>Boulukos, George E. “Olaudah Equiano and the Eighteenth-Century Debate on Africa.”
                    <hi rend="italic">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 40, no. 2 (2007): 241–55.</bibl>
            <bibl>Brown, Matthew.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Informal Empire in Latin America: Culture, Commerce and Capital. </hi>Blackwell,
                2008.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cañizares-Esguerra, Jorge,
                ed.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Entangled Empires: The Anglo-Iberian Atlantic, 1500–1830.</hi>
                Univ. of Pennsylvania Press, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl>Carney, Judith, and Richard Rosomoff. <hi rend="italic">In the Shadow of Slavery:
                    Africa’s Botanical Legacy in the Atlantic World</hi>. Univ. of California Press,
                2009.</bibl>
            <bibl>Chander, Manu Samriti, and Patricia A. Matthew. “Abolitionist Interruptions:
                Romanticism, Slavery, and Genre.” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review</hi>
                29, no. 4 (2018): 431–4.</bibl>
            <bibl>Daut, Marlene L. <hi rend="italic">Baron de Vastey and The Origins of Black Atlantic
                    Humanism</hi>. Palgrave Macmillan, 2017.</bibl>
            <bibl>Equiano, Olaudah. <hi rend="italic">The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah
                    Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African</hi>.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Written by Himself. </hi>1st ed., G. Vassa,
                1789.</bibl>
            <bibl>———.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano, or Gustavus Vassa, the African. Written by Himself. </hi>Edited
                by Angelo Costanzo. Broadview, 2001.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gilroy, Paul. <hi rend="italic">The Black Atlantic: Modernity and
                    Double-Consciousness</hi>. Harvard Univ. Press, 1993.</bibl>
            <bibl>Heinowitz, Rebecca Cole. <hi rend="italic">Spanish America and British Romanticism,
                    1777–1826.</hi> Cambridge Univ. Press, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl>James, C. L. R. <hi rend="italic">The Black Jacobins: Toussaint L’Ouverture and the
                    San Domingo Revolution.</hi> 2nd ed. Random House, 1989.</bibl>
            <bibl>Jemisin, N. K. “How Long ’til Black Future Month?” Blog post, Sept. 30, 2013. <ref
                    target="http://nkjemisin.com/2013/09/how-long-til-black-future-month/"
                    >http://nkjemisin.com/2013/09/how-long-til-black-future-month/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl>Maddison-MacFadyen, Margôt, ed. <hi rend="italic">The Mary Prince Website</hi>. <ref
                    target="https://www.maryprince.org/">https://www.maryprince.org/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mallipeddi, Ramesh. “Filiation to Affiliation: Kinship and Sentiment in Equiano’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Interesting Narrative.</hi>” <hi rend="italic">ELH</hi> 81, no. 3
                (2014): 923–54.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mignolo, Walter D. “Sylvia Wynter: What Does It Mean to Be Human?” In <hi
                    rend="italic">Sylvia Wynter: On Being Human as Praxis</hi>, edited by Katherine
                McKittrick, 106–23. Duke Univ. Press, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl>O’Connell, Hugh C. “‘We Are Change’: The Novum as Event in Nnedi Okorafor’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Lagoon</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Cambridge Journal of Postcolonial
                    Literary Inquiry</hi> 3, no. 3 (2016): 291–313.</bibl>
            <bibl>Phillips, Mark Salber. <hi rend="italic">On Historical Distance</hi>. Yale Univ.
                Press, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl>Prince, Mary. <hi rend="italic">The History of Mary Prince, a West Indian Slave.
                    Related by Herself. With a Supplement by the Editor. To Which is Added the
                    Narrative of Asa-Asa, a Captured African</hi>. F. Westley and A. H. Davis,
                1831.</bibl>
            <bibl>Rediker, Marcus. <hi rend="italic">The Slave Ship: A Human History</hi>. Viking,
                2007.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robson, Martin.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Britain, Portugal and South America in the Napoleonic Wars: Alliances and Diplomacy in Economic Maritime Conflict. </hi>Bloomsbury,
                2011.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sansay, Leonora. <hi rend="italic">Secret History; or, The Horrors of St. Domingo and
                    Laura</hi>. Edited by Michael Drexler. Broadview, 2007.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sharpe, Christina. <hi rend="italic">In the Wake: On Blackness and Being</hi>. Duke
                Univ. Press, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl>Slave Voyages. “Slave Ship in 3-D Video.” <hi rend="Hyperlink"
                    >https://www.slavevoyages.org/voyage/ship</hi>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Thomas, Helen. <hi rend="italic">Romanticism and Slave Narratives: Transatlantic
                    Testimonies</hi>. Cambridge Univ. Press, 2000.</bibl>
            <bibl>Thornton, John.
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Africa and Africans in the Making of the Atlantic World, 1400–1800. </hi>Cambridge
                Univ. Press, 1992.</bibl>
            <bibl>Todorova, Kremena T. “‘I Will Say the Truth to the English People’: The History of
                Mary Prince and the Meaning of English History.” <hi rend="italic">Texas Studies in
                    Literature and Language</hi> 43, no. 3 (2001): 285–302.</bibl>
            <bibl>Tutino, John,
                editor.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> New Countries: Capitalism, Revolutions, and Nations in the Americas, 1750–1870. </hi>Duke
                Univ. Press, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl>Wynter, Sylvia. “Beyond the Categories of the Master Conception: The Counterdoctrine
                of Jamesian Poiesis.” In <hi rend="italic">C. L. R. James’s Caribbean</hi>, edited
                by Paget Henry and Paul Buhle, 63–91. Duke Univ. Press, 1992.</bibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
