<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Emergent</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Debbie Lee </name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition>2024-12-11</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado
                    Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/ editor(s) and
                        advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
                        should be forwarded to Romantic Circles: <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition"
                    >praxis.2024.antislavery.lee</idno>
                <idno type="resource"
                    >antislavery</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Emergent
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Debbie</forename>
                                <surname>Lee</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr
                            target="praxis/antislavery/praxis.2024.antislavery.lee"/>
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"
                            >Romanticism and Anti-Slavery Literatures: Pedagogies and Contexts </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher> Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University
                                of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">December 11, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    
                    
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " to &#8220; or
                        &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed except in the case of
                        diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                        keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
                        such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
                        been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy
                    corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E"
                    xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
                    xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on
                        2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy
                    corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E"
                    xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on
                        2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Wingfield</name>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Emergent </head>    
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Debbie Lee</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>(Washington State University)</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
                
                <lg type="stanza">
                <l><hi rend="italic">an index</hi></l>
                
                <l>emergent:</l>
                <l>defined;</l>
                <l>as fragment;</l>
                <l>and the romantic period;</l>
                <l>as signifyin’;</l>
                <l>and police violence;</l>
                <l>and orality;</l>
                <l>as geometry;</l>
                <l>and abolition;</l>
                <l>as collectivity;</l>
                <l><hi rend="italic">see also</hi> emergency;</l>
                <l>and the future</l>
                </lg>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: defined;</head>
                
            <p>I like the word: emerge. What it conjures: Motion. Risk-taking. Ideas on the verge. </p>
                
            <p>adrienne maree brown wasn’t the first to highlight emergence for me, but her 2017
                book <hi rend="italic">Emergent Strategy: Shaping Change, Changing Worlds</hi>
                rooted me in the concept’s importance to teaching, writing, and being in these
                charged times. Emergent strategy originated as a business model in the 1970s meaning
                “a pattern of action that develops over time in an organization in the absence of a
                specific mission and goals, or despite a mission and goals” (Rivera). brown says
                that her engagement with the concept began with her reading of Black science-fiction
                author Octavia Butler’s notion of change as small, decentralized, and intentional.
                In brown’s introduction to “intentional adaptation,” she quotes Butler: “We are
                Earthseed / The life that perceives itself Changing” (46). From there, brown grew
                the idea to describe myriad forms of brokenness and transformation needed for a more
                just world.</p>
                
            <p>“Emergent” also aptly describes the pedagogical interventions in this volume, where
                scholar-teachers take risks and adapt as they develop new curriculums, such as
                Frances Botkin’s adaptation of the resourceful practice of <hi rend="italic"
                    >tunyuhan</hi>. The word, Botkin tells us, comes from a Jamaican proverb:
                “tunyuhan (turn your hand) and mek (make) fashion,” or “make the best use of any
                available resources to create something new.” Or Ivan Ortiz’s evocation of literary
                séance to make Black voices audible. Ortiz uses texts as mediums and mediations,
                especially those that crack open history, like M. NourbeSe Philip’s
                <hi rend="italic">Zong! </hi>(2008) poems broken across pages
                and centuries. There is also Elizabeth Fay’s emphasis on the violent movement of
                bodies and selves across the Atlantic, as well as Nicholas Blaisdell’s ability to
                link eighteenth- and nineteenth-century scholarship “to our present.” And Sean
                Gordon’s amplification of “dehiscence,” a practice described by Fred Moten as a
                Black studies “emergent poetics” (1743).</p>
                
            <p>Clearly, these examples show how an emergent strategy can vitalize the teaching of
                Romantic literature in 2024 and beyond. In the years before I read brown, I was
                drawn to anthropologist Kathleen Stewart’s idea of emergence, aligned with the
                changes in my scholarly work and my teaching some years ago. In her 2007 book <hi
                    rend="italic">Ordinary Affects</hi>, Stewart wrote about the “emergent present,”
                the shifting, fragmented, heightened moments of the everyday. Her book indexes
                potent encounters that we can’t quite categorize, intimate moments that merge with
                public issues and then evaporate like a mist only to reappear later in another form.
                Such moments, she says, “will shift people’s life trajectories in some small way,
                change them by literally changing their course for a minute or a day” (12). More
                often than not, I will add, emergent moments transform us as they remake the ghostly
                past in the embodied present.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: as fragment;</head>
                
            <p>In June 2013, I was at a house party in Chicago’s Belmont district, mingling with
                people in a leafy backyard. These were people I didn’t see at my university;
                founders of arts programs and alternative newspapers and activist organizations. A
                little Scotty dog dashed around. Everyone except me knew his name. The guests, hip
                and creative, wore mismatched stockings and skirts, asymmetrical hemlines, and
                bright earrings. They seemed cool, and I wanted to join in, but when I edged into a
                circle, people spoke past me. Hot dampness hung in the air, evoking a longing
                feeling, an ache for the experiences I didn’t have with these people but which they
                had with one another.</p>
                
            <p>The yard was crowded and sweaty, and I moved inside. Only one other person sat in the
                dimly lit living room where a melancholy tune of trombones and violins played. I
                drifted over and sat next to Marvin, as he later introduced himself. He raised his
                beer and smiled. The heat inside was suffocating yet Marvin wore a long black
                leather jacket and bowler cap, as if he’d come from a distant country where it was
                always cold. I didn’t want to bring up the weather because my eyes kept drifting to
                his cap, so I asked where he worked. “I don’t work now,” he said. There was
                something about this party that suppressed my normal social instincts. In any other
                context I would have talked about my job and family. But all I seemed to be able to
                do was listen.</p>
                
            <p>While Black and white people mingled outside, inside Marvin and I connected over
                parenting. I noticed he had a way of smiling that seemed new, as if he’d just
                rediscovered those muscles around his mouth. He told me how his daughter grew up
                while he was locked up, how he was getting to know her for the first time. He’d had
                a hard time finding a job since he got out of prison, he said. It was hard when
                you’d been in prison for so long. You had to toughen yourself up, and that made you
                awkward around people. He rubbed his eyebrow shyly. He had just bought his daughter
                a house with the compensation he received for being wrongfully accused.</p>
                
            <p>I thought of my own daughter as Marvin talked. She and I were estranged at the time.
                I had desperately tried to contact her to no avail. Forced alienation from a
                daughter, one of the deepest human hurts—it was a feeling I could touch. But as I
                looked into Marvin’s intense eyes, my internal screen went blank. How could I know
                wrongful conviction and forced separation from a child, from an entire family, in
                the context of the experience he related to me? I couldn’t. But he was telling me
                his story, and I listened.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: and the Romantic period;</head>
                
            <p>One of the most striking features of this volume is how the pastness of the British
                slave trade, abolition, and emancipation emerge in current poems, novels, plays,
                songs, and movies, across the internet, on the streets, and, crucially, within
                schools and classrooms. Patricia A. Matthew acknowledges that although early
                abolitionist texts are not “documentaries that teach us about the past,” they can
                speak to current race issues. Her students discuss slavery and abolition at a
                historic and geographic remove and yet feel the issues press closely on their lives
                as they learn to adapt one era’s practices to their own.</p>
                
            <p>Adaptation is central to Botkin’s method as well. She puts Marlon James’s
                contemporary novel <hi rend="italic">The Book of Night Women</hi> (2009) in dialogue
                with Romantic literature. James’s dizzying historical remix, Botkin says, features
                graphic scenes of trauma, which unsettle what students think they know about
                enslavement. At the same time, it informs their current experience. Likewise, Fay
                reveals that for her students, the Black Lives Matter protests of 2020 gave writers
                like Olaudah Equiano and Mary Prince “a new legitimacy” unheard of in previous
                generations of students. And Gordon, in an “Ethnic American Literature” course he
                designed in 2015, boldly led students to question their assumptions about “the
                ‘pastness’ of slavery, the progressiveness of liberal democracy, and the putative
                postracialism of the Obama administration.”</p>
                
            <p>Surely my conversation with Marvin held so much import for me because of how the past
                emerged in the present. For twelve of the years Marvin was in prison, I spent almost
                every waking moment steeped in literature of the slave trade, abolition, and
                emancipation during the British Romantic period. I wrote about that history in neat
                explications, complete with historical contexts and pages of citations, and bound in
                scholarly journals and books. But it was only when I stepped away from literary
                criticism and all I had learned that the meaning of that awful history started to
                emerge in a different way, rushing into my life in fleeting, transitory moments,
                informing and complicating the present. The Thirteenth Amendment abolished slavery
                with one major exception: slavery remained appropriate punishment for a crime. The
                Virginia Supreme Court defined convicts as synonymous with enslaved people.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Thanks to my
                            colleague Aaron Oforlea for inserting this sentence and offering other
                            insights in early drafts of this essay. See also Alexander
                        (2010).</note></p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: as signifying;</head>
                
            <p>I set upon the topic of the slave trade, abolition, and emancipation through a chance
                encounter with Henry Louis Gates Jr., when I was a meek graduate student at the
                University of Arizona. I had read Gates’s book <hi rend="italic">The Signifying
                    Monkey</hi> (1988), which had recently come out, and
                <hi rend="italic">The History of Mary Prince, a West Indian Slave </hi>(1831)
                in a postcolonial literature course, and was excited that he was giving a talk at
                the university. Gates spoke about race and the literary canon and about recovering
                texts written by formerly enslaved men and women. There was a dinner after the talk,
                and to my astonishment, I ended up seated elbow-to-elbow with the great scholar with
                the smiling eyes. He was casual and friendly, fluffing out his napkin and pouring me
                a glass of water before filling his own.</p>
                
            <p>In my time as a graduate student, I’d never read anything like <hi rend="italic">The
                    Signifying Monkey.</hi> I still recall being mesmerized by how Gates harnessed
                the African American vernacular tradition and the double-voiced Yoruba trickster Esu
                to develop the “signifyin’ figure” who danced through the pages of African American
                literature. “To rename is to revise,” Gates wrote, “and to revise is to Signify”
                (xxiii). Revise the method for my project, and maybe even shift the canon a bit, was
                what I wanted to do. The book emerged from the hundreds of others on my Ph.D.
                reading lists, not just because of Gates’s ideas, brilliant as they were, but
                because of how he himself had written a scholarly work so alive, multiplicious, and
                full of intellectual trickery. It struck me as, well, not entirely academic in
                style. How did he do it?</p>
                
            <p>In my eyes Gates may as well have been a movie star (and he would go on to become a
                TV celebrity and witness in free speech court proceedings). I was too nervous to
                utter a word, so I just stared at his nice old-fashioned wristwatch that fit the
                persona of someone with schedules to keep. But Gates must have asked what I was
                working on, because I distinctly remember telling him, in a stumbling monologue full
                of ums and ahs, about Romantic literature and how only a shred of scholarship about
                the slave trade and abolition had been produced. I had pored over Eva Beatrice
                Dyke’s 1942
                book<hi rend="italic"> The Negro in English Romantic Thought</hi>.
                I had attended Alan Richardson’s 1990 MLA panel. I was drawn to the topic, I told
                him, but I confessed my worry. As a non-Black person, did I have a right to pursue
                this research? Was it my story to tell? Perhaps I was also afraid to confront the
                culpability of my own European ancestry.</p>
                
            <p>Gates’s eyes grew serious through huge glasses resting on his cheeks. “Absolutely!”
                he said. I must “absolutely choose this topic” for my dissertation. Was I going to
                the archive? Texts, voices, needed to be brought to light. Though my work might
                never “signify,” I understood, it could have significance. Or maybe, as a white
                woman writing about the atrocities of Europeans, my work could signify on early
                white men and women.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: and police violence;</head>
                
            <p>A few months after I met Marvin, I had lunch with Alice, the woman who had hosted the
                house party. I told her about my conversation with Marvin. Though the conversation
                had lasted an hour at most, he kept surfacing in my thoughts. Was he okay? What had
                happened?</p>
                
            <p>Chicago cops were the worst, Alice said through frowning eyes and pursed lips as she
                told me his story. Some twenty years earlier, two women and three children were
                found dead in what appeared to be a house fire. The police questioned suspects, and
                their evidence suggested a family member had committed the murders and started the
                fire as a cover up. Instead of pursuing that lead, the police arrested two innocent
                men, Marvin and another man, Ronald Kitchen, who happened to live nearby.</p>
                
            <p>Alice pointed me to some online articles, and I later found more on my own.<note place="foot" resp="author">See
                            especially Baer’s recent <hi rend="italic">Beyond the Usual Beating</hi>
                            (2021).</note> Marvin and Ronald’s injustice started with
                Chicago police detective and commander Jon Burge, who spent eighteen years leading a
                campaign against innocent Black men. Before his crimes were exposed in 1990, Burge
                targeted some two hundred Black men, torturing, imprisoning, and killing many of
                them for crimes they did not commit. Burge had learned his craft in the Army during
                the Korean War, first as a military policeman and then in combat, facing a foe of a
                different race (Conroy). Burge unleashed his crimes unchallenged and even received
                numerous honors, including a Bronze Star. Today his career stands as one of the most
                egregious examples of serial police violence against Black men in U.S. history.</p>
                
            <p>When Marvin was exonerated in 2009, media stories emerged. In an interview with
                Marlene Martin of the Campaign to End the Death Penalty, Marvin told how police
                broke down the door to his sister’s house, kidnapped him, and then beat him. I felt
                the intensity of the injustice when, in the interview, Marvin related tender stories
                of his formative years growing up in a housing project. Though the buildings are now
                gone, he recalled a courtyard of flowers where he used to hang out. His favorite
                memory was a camping trip. A local pastor had organized the trip for him and a bunch
                of neighborhood kids. “He made sure we went on this weekend camping trip to show us
                another side of life,” Marvin said. “I’ll never forget that—it made such an
                impression on me” (Martin).</p>
                
            <p>I’ll never forget how at the lunch meeting, when I mentioned Marvin’s name, Alice
                smiled so wide, the lines around her eyes sprawled across her temples and down the
                sides of her face. Her face drew me in like a force. She nodded and peeked
                cautiously from over her glasses, as if the thought of him gave her a feeling of
                deep fondness with agony mixed in. Even after we parted, her expression appeared
                before me, slowly gathering resonance rather than settling something.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: and orality;</head>
                
            <p>The authors of the essays in this volume rightly champion firsthand accounts. Fay
                argues that “for some students of color . . . firsthand accounts can be empowering.”
                Ortiz shows how ballads are oral forms migrated to print, and how these forms now
                act as mediums for Black voices. Yet even in canonical literary works by non-Black
                writers, Black voices can be heard, as Toni Morrison points out in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Playing in the Dark</hi> (1992), giving expression to “social decay and
                economic division” of white culture (63).</p>
                
            <p>I spent what felt like a lifetime examining the documents of British antislavery,
                following trails, uncovering metaphors, reading works by mostly non-Black
                authors—the court cases, the tracts and polemics, the debates, the newspaper
                articles, the dubious scientific theories, the iconography, the mounds of
                antislavery poetry and plays and novels, and the thousands of travel texts. I was
                tireless in my research, mesmerized by how one source led to another and then
                another, by the physical act of filling out the request forms in the British
                Library, the Cambridge University Library, the University of London, and
                farther-flung archives in cities like Liverpool, Bristol, and Hull.<note place="foot" resp="author"> This archival
                            work became the basis of the eight-volume <hi rend="italic">Slavery,
                                Abolition, and Emancipation: Writings in the British Romantic
                                Period</hi>, published by Routledge (then Pickering and Chatto) in
                            1999. I served as co-general editor with Peter J. Kitson. Individual
                            volume editors were Sukhdev Sandu, David Dabydeen, Alan Richardson,
                            Jeffrey Cox, Srivinas Aravamudan, and Alan Bewell, with Anne K. Mellor
                            and James Walvin as advisory editors.</note></p>
                
            <p>I remember the feeling of heaviness created by the sheer number of documents in dark
                rooms guarded by stone-faced librarians, and I often fell ill thinking about how
                antislavery writings and contemporary literary theory rarely let the people taken
                from Africa or born into the system of enslavement speak for themselves.<note place="foot" resp="author"> As Saidiya
                            Hartman keenly observes in “Venus in Two Acts,” the archive of slavery
                            is a scandalous place where “infelicitous speech, obscene utterances,
                            and perilous commands give birth to the characters we stumble upon in
                            the archive. Given the condition in which we find them, the only
                            certainty is that we will lose them again, that they will expire or
                            elude our grasp or collapse under the pressure of inquiry”
                        (6).</note> I became increasingly concerned with finding those
                voices, even if they were often mediated through white institutions and scribes. I
                read the letters of the Sierra Leone settlers, which were scattered in libraries
                across England and the United States. In one collection, I stumbled upon a small
                account of enslaved women—mothers and daughters—wresting control of a plantation. In
                London a series of slave complaints emerged from the House of Commons Parliamentary
                papers dating to 1816. In select colonies including Berbice and Demerara, as I
                learned, the enslaved could report abuses to a British officer—called a “Fiscal”—who
                took down their words and filed them with the House of Commons. These complaints
                highlight aspects of Black culture hidden from most other accounts. I learned about
                working conditions, living quarters, the amount of food, clothing, and other
                supplies people had access to, and about their resistances and rebellions.</p>
                
            <p>One afternoon in the British Library I found myself reading the account of Tommy, a
                story that stays with me to this day:
                
            <quote>February 19, 1819. Negro Tommy, belonging to William Fraser: —Says, he is a cooper by
                trade, and employed as such by his master on plantation Goldstone Hall; that on
                Friday morning last he went in the boiling-house for nails, and there saw another
                cooper heading up sugars; Tommy went to one of the casks and took a lump of sugar
                for the purpose of sweetening three gallons of hot water; did not hide the same, but
                proceeded with it in his hand from the boiling-house; was met by his master, Mr.
                Fraser, who inquired where he got the sugar, Tommy informed him of his having taken
                it, and for what purpose, his master immediately ordered him to be laid down, tied
                to stakes, put two drivers over him, and one hundred lashes inflicted upon him. Mr.
                Fraser went to Tommy’s house and searched it, found in his tool chest a quantity of
                old nails, among which were also a very few new ones; Mr. Fraser went to the trouble
                of weighing them, there were fourteen pounds.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> This quote was lightly edited for
                            clarity; the full account is republished in the 2004 volume I co-edited
                            with Alan Richardson, <hi rend="italic">Early Black British Writing</hi>
                            (337–40). I’m especially grateful to Richardson for his pioneering work
                            on antislavery and Black writers during the Romantic period and for
                            mentoring me during my career.</note></quote>
                
            It took years for me to unravel the meaning of this testimony. Tommy’s actions
                replayed in my imagination until I saw his self-determination in every word of his
                complaint. By stealing sugar—the product of his own labor—Tommy was subverting
                capitalism, which slave labor made possible. Subverting but also using. By
                collecting a great quantity of nails, Tommy was exploiting capitalism. The fact that
                Fraser weighed the nails implies that he suspected Tommy was selling them.</p>
                
            <p>The account continues beyond the segment I’ve included here. In it, Tommy complains
                of not enough food and clothing, and of being harassed by Fraser, but his primary
                objection is the hundred lashes, when the legal limit was forty-one. The court
                interviewed various witnesses, each claiming Tommy received a different number of
                lashes. Finally, the court asked Tommy to “exhibit his posterior,” and he had very
                little sign of being lashed. Tommy explains: “I was favored by the drivers who threw
                the whips over me.”</p>
                
            <p>Between the lines, I saw, Tommy was complaining to the court about harassment and
                torture, but he was also announcing agency over the plantation system. When he said
                he was favored by the drivers, he was issuing a warning. Drivers were enslaved men
                who received larger food and clothing rations. They commanded other enslaved people,
                which made it dangerous for planters to upset a driver’s authority once it was
                established. Drivers could be mediators, cops, or potential rebel leaders.</p>
                
            <p>For me, what mattered most about Tommy’s story was how his firsthand account bubbled
                up through the testimony recorded by colonists. Although, at first glance, the
                court’s order for Tommy to remove his clothing might seem degrading, it also offers
                Tommy a chance to reveal how he has been able to retain his agency. Tommy proved how
                the drivers favored him by “exhibiting his posterior.” With that act, he was
                literally mooning them (and mooning is a word and concept dating back to 1600).
                “Kiss my ass,” he was saying. Most importantly, although Tommy was probably
                illiterate, he staged his action in a way that would be recorded in the colonial
                discourse for centuries to come. In other words, by showing the court his backside
                and letting them know he wasn’t powerless, he was signifying on the institution that
                sought to oppress him.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent; as geometry;</head>
                
            <p>My years of research across continents piecing together Britain’s antislavery project
                and searching for voices like Tommy’s and listening to stories like Marvin’s changed
                me. At Washington State University, I taught entire courses on the subject,
                highlighting the rebellions and revolutions in Jamaica, Saint Domingue, and
                elsewhere, as well as the many ways the enslaved survived, resisted, and overturned.
                I stood over photocopy machines and heavy-duty staplers creating handmade booklets
                for my students of these defiant texts. In the geometry of my classroom, we gathered
                in a perfect circle and read them aloud. As students took the words inside their
                bodies and made them live, we heard power shift from the institution of slavery to a
                group of Black women taking charge of a plantation or to a household servant
                poisoning an abusive white man.</p>
                
            <p>But my old-school ways were not nearly as inventive as the methods adopted in this
                volume. Methods like Botkin’s Zoom dialogue with Maroons or Fay’s triangulations, a
                practice she adapted from nautical strategy and scholar Christina Sharpe. Blaisdell
                also triangulates his work—reading Ottobah Cugoano, Mary Prince, and Friedrich
                Engels together helps him understand the relationship between nineteenth-century
                problems of unfree labor, free labor, and capitalism.</p>
                
            <p>“Emergence,” brown writes, “is our inheritance as a part of this universe; it is how
                we change” (3). She consults nature for lessons on teaching, organizing, and taking
                care of one another and oneself: birds flocking, earthworms burrowing, leaves
                decaying, roots going deep offer different instructions. But one of nature’s most
                fascinating forms—the fractal—is for brown the geometry of transformation. “What we
                practice at a small scale can reverberate to the largest scale,” she reminds us
                (42). I found this self-similar, iterative process evident across the essays of this
                volume, each piece unfolding like an offering for how to teach an abolitionist
                Romanticism.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
                
            <head>Emergent: and abolition;</head>
                
            <p>A few years ago, I read a review by Carvell Wallace in the <hi rend="italic">New York
                    Times</hi> of “The Good Lord Bird,” a TV miniseries about the nineteenth-century
                American abolitionist John Brown, produced by Ethan Hawke. “Can a white person ever
                usefully tell a slave story,” Wallace asked, “or, more specifically, can they tell a
                story that is useful to the descendants of the enslaved, rather than to their own
                egos or cinematic fantasies?”</p>
                
            <p>I felt a bright sting. Though the great Henry Louis Gates Jr. had once encouraged me
                to tell the stories of Black lives, I continue to wonder—can I? I sometimes doubt my
                ability to write about the stories of enslaved people by Romantic-era authors. I
                decided I would not watch the series.</p>
                
            <p>Yet I kept returning to the fact that abolition and enslaved people were the most
                pressing topic of the British Romantic period. At the time I started my research and
                writing, nothing could have been clearer to me. Several authors in this collection
                cite Samuel Taylor Coleridge’s sermon on abolition in 1795 on the steps of the
                Bristol docks in the heart of that city’s slave business; Equiano’s and Cugoano’s
                fierce agitation for abolition; and Prince’s narrative told to the London
                Anti-Slavery Society. Not to mention the millions of pages of antislavery writings
                by Black and white activist men and women.</p>
                
            <p>Antislavery was pursued with such intensity, it shouldn’t come as a surprise to find
                abolition, albeit much transformed since the Romantic period, emergent among some
                young activists today. Syrus Marcus Ware, a transgender scholar and artist, urges
                academics, writers, poets, activists, performers—everyone—to “approach abolition as
                the most loving thing that we can do for one another” (Ware). Last year I attended
                Ware’s workshop on abolition, in which participants listened to Angela Davis while
                we imagined futures full of love and freedom and justice. As Petra Kuppers, the
                workshop organizer, put it:
                
            <quote>This personal sensation of a white cis queer disabled woman feels far away from the
                project of ending slavery’s long reach, I know, and I feel immediately the concern
                of projecting my own sense of unfreedom, being denied access to my range-giving
                wheelchair, onto the experiences of people racialized as Black. But that’s what
                Syrus is offering to me here: charting my experience, my sense, from wherever I come
                from. Grounding a sense of justice in a personal felt, lived experience, in
                connection. So I let it stand, that moment of loosening the armor, and I touch into
                it to be present.” (Kuppers)</quote>
                
            The experience was visceral, uncomfortable, on the verge of something new for many of
                the participants.</p>
                
            <p>Many of the teacher-scholars in this volume embrace abolition. I see a wonderful,
                complementary rhythm between Ortiz’s call to listen to Romantic “sounds we would
                otherwise block out because they are too raucous, inarticulate, or inconvenient” and
                Ware’s invitation to embody the sounds of a world rooted in liberation and
                self-determination. I’m moved by Matthew’s account of how when students learn an
                “abolitionist Romanticism” they are also learning “about the intricacies of society,
                protest, and revolution.” As Alan Richardson observes in his response here, I too am
                heartened by Blaisdell’s report of being inspired by Granville Sharp working
                shoulder-to-shoulder with Equiano and Cugoano. Such collaborative abolitionism
                prompted Blaisdell to found a community tutoring center. Reading about his actions
                also brought to mind Ware’s words: The “abolitionist struggle . . . is 500 years
                strong,” he writes, and “now is a time to reflect on the history of the abolition
                movement and what the future could look like if we reach abolition in our lifetime”
                (Ware).</p>
                
            <p>I’ve also understood that the backward glances, missteps, doubts, and mistakes I make
                when writing and speaking about abolition are part of the fractal nature of
                learning. Shortly after I read the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> review about “The
                Good Lord Bird,” one of my African American students who writes eloquently about
                <hi rend="italic">The History of Mary Prince </hi>called me by
                Zoom and said, completely unsolicited, “You should watch that series!” The
                coincidence captured meant I had to respond.
                
            <quote>
                <p>“But can a white person really tell that story?” I told her about the review.</p>
            <p>She shrugged. “Different people have different views,” she said. “I like it.”</p>
                
            </quote>
            </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
                <head>Emergent: as collectivity;</head>
                
            <p>“What does it mean to function as a group in a changing environment?” asks Alexis
                Pauline Gumbs in <hi rend="italic">Undrowned: Black Feminist Lessons from Marine
                    Animals</hi> (2020), part of the Emergent Strategy series (51). Gumbs consults
                sea life, animals adept at fluidity, for teachable moments and parallels to the
                current work of abolition. Mothering and gathering in super pods are dolphin
                strategies just as communities of care and cooperatives have been part of the Black
                Diaspora for centuries.</p>
                
            <p>Caregiving. Collectivity. These ancient principles are emergent in this volume’s
                classroom practices. For instance, the way Matthew begins her courses with “a
                conversation about the various ways civic groups try to effect broad change and a
                low-stakes free-association exercise about the word <hi rend="italic">sugar</hi>.”
                The way Gordon encourages crosstalk by assigning student support groups for writing
                and responding. How Blaisdell had his students enact a letter-writing campaign
                against unjust school dress codes, where they learned “that the power of social
                change begins and is sustained through collective civic action.” And how MaMa G, the
                elder featured in Botkin’s essay, envisions opening a “borderless university,”
                rooted in Jamaica but developed online, to unite local and global communities in the
                growth and dissemination of Indigenous knowledge.</p>
                
            <p>Young Black feminist theorists and embodiment scholars like Gumbs, brown, Ware, and
                Kuppers—poets, memoirists, artists, scholars, and activists—also offer new
                cooperative models. Gumbs, for instance, collaborates with sperm whales—breathing,
                stretching, finding intentionality. Further, her brilliant book <hi rend="italic"
                    >Spill</hi> (2016) is a cross-generation, trans-temporal partnership with
                Hortense Spillers that calls to mind collaborations with history like Philip’s
                <hi rend="italic">Zong! </hi>poems, where meaning is “not to be
                ‘made’ but, rather, felt” (Wah), and the <hi rend="italic">Lost Privilege Company,
                    or the book of listening</hi> (2016), an assemblage from the archives of
                California’s Eugenics Records Office between 1910 and 1925 by an anonymous poetry
                collective.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: see also emergency;</head>
                
            <p>Marvin, the man I met at the Chicago house party, spent twenty-one years in prison
                while his friend Ronald Kitchen was sentenced to death. I never saw Marvin again,
                and I lost touch with Alice, but I didn’t forget them. The tangle of connections and
                resonances remained emergent for me, demanding my continuing attention.</p>
                
            <p>I learned that while Ronald was in prison, he became one of the “Death Row 10,” Black
                men tortured and wrongfully accused by Burge and his gang of corrupt cops. Ronald
                went on to write his story in his 2018 book <hi rend="italic">My Midnight Years:
                    Surviving Jon Burge’s Police Torture Ring and Death Row</hi>. In a 2019
                interview, he and one of his coauthors, Thai Jones, spoke about the police brutality
                that called to mind so many descriptions in British antislavery writing. They also
                spoke about the importance of storytelling.</p>
                
            <p>Marvin and Ronald may never have been exonerated if activists on the outside,
                including Ronald’s mother, and, it turns out, Alice and some of the people at her
                house party in June 2013, had not made their innocence a major story in Chicago. The
                activists’ work centered on building narratives around Martin and Ronald and other
                wrongly convicted Black men. “It was storytelling that really did work this amazing
                revolution in people’s consciousness,” said Jones (Kitchen). The stories eventually
                engaged the news media, lawmakers, and people like Jesse Jackson, finally forcing
                Chicago to pass a reparations package, the first of its kind in the country. The
                legislation provides compensation, restitution, and rehabilitation services for
                those tortured by Jon Burge.</p>
                
            <p>Recently, Marvin joined Alice for a presentation of Alice’s co-edited book, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Long Term: Resisting Life Sentences, Working toward
                    Freedom</hi> (2018). The book contains an essay by adrienne maree brown. Ronald
                is now an activist speaking out against police brutality and corruption. Even so,
                police continue to harass him. Whenever he’s back in Chicago visiting relatives, as
                he explained in the 2019 interview, police stop him numerous times, a reminder of
                the ruthless stop-and-frisk policies he grew up with on the South Side.</p>
                
            <p>Now, however, the routine is different. When the police pull him over, Ronald
                signifies. He always says, “Officer, why are you pulling me over?” The officer will
                reply: “Your seatbelt.” But Ronald has tinted windows, and he points this out.
                Finally, the officer says, “Is this your car?” “Yes, it is,” Ronald says in a calm,
                steady voice. “Where did you get this Mercedes Benz?” the officer demands. “Well,
                officer,” Ronald says, “you all bought this for me” (Kitchen).</p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head>Emergent: and the future</head>
                
            <p>What does the future of Romantic pedagogy look like? The essays in this volume offer
                some direction. In the spirit of multiplicity and nonlinearity, Botkin reports, “I
                incorporated interviews, images, and films to complement and challenge the
                conventions of literary historiography.” Gordon includes the speculative mode,
                teaching authors like Mat Johnson, Celu Amberstone, and Octavia Butler, while Fay
                focuses on Afrofuturism with the film <hi rend="italic">Black Panther</hi> (2018)
                and N. K. Jemisin’s “How Long ’til Black Future Month?” Such texts, she says,
                present a way of talking about the future in terms other than intergenerational
                trauma and posthumanism.</p>
                
            <p>I am grateful to Joselyn M. Almeida and Amelia Worsley for editing this powerful
                constellation of essays and for inviting me to respond and giving me room to offer a
                few of my own pedagogical practices. To begin with, I want to advocate for new ways
                of writing scholarship and assigning student work. Part of the power of brown’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Emergent Strategy</hi>, after all, is its form. An assemblage of
                narratives, memories, theories, spells, poetry, lists, assessment sheets, oral
                histories, questions, anecdotes, guiding quotations, icons, images, and
                Afro-futures. Such an approach to Romantic scholarship and classroom work can help
                liberate the field. I wholly support Kathleen Stewart’s argument that generalized
                terms like “neoliberalism, advanced capitalism, and globalization . . . do not in
                themselves begin to describe the situation we find ourselves in. The notion of a
                totalized system, of which everything is always already somehow a part, is not
                helpful (to say the least) in the effort to approach a weighted and reeling present”
                (5). Equally, I’m in line with brown’s recommendation that we need to “give each
                other more time to feel, to be in our humanity” (105).</p>
                
            <p>The center of my pedagogical practice today compels students to experiment with modes
                of expression and to co-create with whatever texts we’re discussing. I present them
                with dozens of forms, written and otherwise: letters, manifestos, photo essays,
                short films, fragments, artist books, mixed media collages, erasure poetry,
                assemblage poetry, catalogs, almanacs, and indexes, to name a few. I ask them to
                experiment on even the most scholarly projects. I also encourage them to feel. I
                value experience over explication of literary works, ordinary affects over
                totalizing systems. In my own writing, I’ve pursued an emergent scholarship, one
                mixed up and messy, nonlinear and adaptive, rooted in feeling and imagining as much
                as thinking. Which is why, these last years, I’ve been compiling a catalog of
                emotions to use as a resource. Not big, singular emotions like fear or shock or
                sudden love, but the complex, contradictory, ambivalent churning inside us as we try
                to find stability in an unstable universe, as we try to put past and present in
                place, as we try to find new forms and expressions for the emergent present.</p>
                
            <p>And then, suddenly, some appear from a corner of the world, and we are moved, as when
                Amanda Gorman stood at the podium during the presidential inauguration on January
                20, 2021, and her words, emerging, held us all—not just America, but the world:
                
                <quote>
            <p>We will rebuild, reconcile and recover</p>
            <p>and every known nook of our nation</p>
            <p>and every corner called our country,</p>
            <p>our people diverse and beautiful will emerge . . .</p>
                </quote>
            </p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div type="citation">
            <head>Works Cited</head>
                
            <bibl>Alexander, Michelle. <hi rend="italic">The New Jim Crow: Mass Incarceration in the
                    Age of Colorblindness</hi>. New Press, 2010.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Baer, Andrew. <hi rend="italic">Beyond the Usual Beating: The Jon Burge Police
                    Torture Scandal and Social Movements for Police Accountability in Chicago.</hi>
                Univ. of Chicago Press, 2021.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>brown, adrienne maree. <hi rend="italic">Emergent Strategy: Shaping Change, Changing
                    Worlds</hi>. AK Press, 2017.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Conroy, John. “Tools of Torture.” <hi rend="italic">Reader</hi>, Feb. 3, 2005. <ref
                    target="https://chicagoreader.com/news-politics/tools-of-torture/"
                    >https://chicagoreader.com/news-politics/tools-of-torture/</ref>.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Gates, Henry Louis, Jr. <hi rend="italic">The Signifying Monkey: A Theory of
                    Afro-American Literary Criticism</hi>. Oxford Univ. Press, 1988.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Gorman, Amanda. <hi rend="italic">The Hill We Climb: An Inaugural Poem for the
                    Country</hi>. Kindle ed. Viking, 2021.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Gumbs, Alexis Pauline. <hi rend="italic">Spill: Scenes of Black Feminist
                    Fugitivity.</hi> Duke Univ. Press, 2016.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Undrowned: Black Feminist Lessons from Marine Animals</hi>. AK
                Press, 2020.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Hartman, Saidiya. “Venus in Two Acts.” <hi rend="italic">Small Axe: A Caribbean
                    Journal of Criticism</hi> 12, no. 2 (2008): 1–14.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Kim, Alice, et al., eds. <hi rend="italic">The Long Term: Resisting Life Sentences,
                    Working toward Freedom</hi>. Haymarket Books, 2018.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Kitchen, Ronald. Interview and Q&amp;A with Thai Joes and Alice Green. Sanctuary for
                Independent Media. Troy, NY, Nov. 30, 2018. YouTube. <ref
                    target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w7yWUPcR9ow"
                    >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w7yWUPcR9ow</ref>.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Kuppers, Petra. “Response to Syrus Marcus Ware: Embodying abolition and dreaming the
                future into being.” EcoSomatics Archive: Field Notes from the 2020 EcoSomatics
                Symposium. <hi rend="italic">Jacket2</hi>, May 6, 2022. <ref
                    target="https://jacket2.org/article/ecosomatics-archive#ware_kuppers"
                    >https://jacket2.org/article/ecosomatics-archive#ware_kuppers</ref>.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Martin, Marlene. “A Free Man at Last.” <hi rend="italic">SocialistWorker.org</hi>,
                Mar. 26, 2010. <ref
                    target="file:///Users/djlee/Desktop/socialistworker.org/2010/03/26/a-free-man-at-last"
                    >socialistworker.org/2010/03/26/a-free-man-at-last</ref>.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Morrison, Toni. <hi rend="italic">Playing in the Dark: Whiteness and the Literary
                    Imagination</hi>. Harvard Univ. Press, 1992.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Moten, Fred. “Black Op.” <hi rend="italic">PMLA</hi> 123, no. 5 (2008): 1743–7.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Richardson, Alan, and Debbie Lee,
                eds.<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Early Black British Writing: Olaudah Equiano, Mary Prince, and Others</hi>.
                Houghton Mifflin, 2004.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Rivera, Gibrán. “Emergent Strategy.” <hi rend="italic">Interaction Institute for
                    Social Change</hi>, Sept. 11, 2012. <ref
                    target="https://interactioninstitute.org/emergent-strategy/"
                    >https://interactioninstitute.org/emergent-strategy/</ref>.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Stewart, Kathleen. <hi rend="italic">Ordinary Affects</hi>. Duke Univ. Press,
                2007.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Wah, Fred. “Reading M. NourbeSe Philip’s <hi rend="italic">Zong!</hi>” <hi
                    rend="italic">Jacket 2</hi>, Mar. 29, 2013. <ref
                    target="https://jacket2.org/article/reading-m-nourbese-philips-zong"
                    >https://jacket2.org/article/reading-m-nourbese-philips-zong</ref>.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Wallace, Carvell. “‘The Good Lord Bird’ Is Good TV. But Mix Art and Slavery at Your
                Peril.” <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, Oct. 6, 2020. <ref
                    target="file:///Users/djlee/Desktop/nytimes.com/2020/10/06/magazine/good-lord-bird-tv-slavery.html"
                    >nytimes.com/2020/10/06/magazine/good-lord-bird-tv-slavery.html</ref>.</bibl>
                
            <bibl>Ware, Syrus Marcus. “We Want Abolition in Our Lifetime.” <hi rend="italic">This</hi>,
                Nov. 5, 2020. <ref
                    target="file:///Users/djlee/Desktop/this.org/2020/11/05/we-want-abolition-in-our-lifetime"
                    >this.org/2020/11/05/we-want-abolition-in-our-lifetime</ref>.</bibl>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
