<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Romanticism and the Abolitionist Turn  </title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Patricia A. Matthew </name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition>2024-12-11</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University of Colorado
                    Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced
                        or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for
                        purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom
                        use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles
                        are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance
                        with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly
                        permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
                        requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/ editor(s) and
                        advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization
                        should be forwarded to Romantic Circles: <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following
                        conditions: <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose
                                without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms
                                other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount
                        them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to
                        have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the
                        Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a
                        continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make
                        a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
                        use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition"
                    >praxis.2024.antislavery.matthew</idno>
                <idno type="resource"
                    >antislavery</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Historical Agency and Civic Action through Antislavery Pedagogy 
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Patricia A.</forename>
                                <surname>Matthews</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr
                            target="praxis/antislavery/praxis.2024.antislavery.matthew"/>
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"
                            >Romanticism and Anti-Slavery Literatures: Pedagogies and Contexts </title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher> Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, University
                                of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">December 11, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    
                    
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " to &#8220; or
                        &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed except in the case of
                        diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
                        keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
                        such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
                        been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; font-size:
                    12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy
                    corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E"
                    xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
                    xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on
                        2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy
                    corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E"
                    xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at
                        http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on
                        2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                    <term subtype="tags"/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Wingfield</name>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="abstract">
               <p> This essay reflects on the process of revising Romanticism courses in response to student curiosity about how race, 
                primarily Blackness, operates in the period. It includes a discussion of how teaching texts by William Blake, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 
                Amelia Opie, Robert Southey, and William Wordsworth reveals to students how the period connects race to issues of representation, authorship, 
                gender, and social contracts. Sparked by observing how students debate race and representation when it unexpectedly appears in their readings
                from the Romantic period, this essay makes two claims: (1) taking up race and representation in the Romanticism classroom is not simply about 
                including texts by people of color but is also about recontextualizing the period as a whole; and (2) cultivating student interest in Romantic-era 
                racial politics offers them a model for how to think about race, representation, and politics in the twenty-first century. </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="essay">
                
                        <head>Romanticism and the Abolitionist Turn </head>    
                        <byline>
                            <docAuthor>Patricia A. Matthew</docAuthor>
                            <affiliation>(Montclair State University)</affiliation>
                        </byline>
                        
           <div type="section">
            <p>This essay reflects on the process of revising Romanticism courses in response to
                student curiosity about how race, primarily Blackness, operates in the period. It
                includes a discussion of how teaching texts by William Blake, Samuel Taylor
                Coleridge, Amelia Opie, Robert Southey, and William Wordsworth reveals to students
                how the period connects race to issues of representation, authorship, gender, and
                social contracts. Sparked by observing how students debate race and representation
                when it unexpectedly appears in their readings from the Romantic period, this essay
                makes two claims: (1) taking up race and representation in the Romanticism classroom
                is not simply about including texts by people of color but is also about
                recontextualizing the period as a whole; and (2) cultivating student interest in
                Romantic-era racial politics offers them a model for how to think about race,
                representation, and politics in the twenty-first century.</p>
               
            <p>My decision to design a class that focuses on Romantic-era abolitionist literature
                was sparked by a student debate about how to interpret William Blake’s “The Little
                Black Boy.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> I
                            am grateful to Amelia Worsley and Joselyn M. Almeida for their work on
                            this essay and to Manu Chander, Tina Iemma, and Deanna Koretsky for
                            reading recommendations.</note> It was in the spring of 2006,
                the semester before my tenure file was due and just a few years before the United
                States elected its first Black president. Students were reading the poem in my
                fairly traditional Romanticism survey course, one that focused on canonical poets
                (i.e., the “Big Six”) along with Mary Shelley’s <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi>
                (1818) and <hi rend="italic">Valperga</hi> (1823). The course paid very little
                attention to critical discussions about how these same writers responded to debates
                about England’s participation in the transatlantic slave trade, and for the first
                three years that I taught Blake’s poem, no student had challenged the line that we
                ended up discussing for a full 75-minute class period: “And I am black, but O! my
                soul is white” (line 2). On a handout that included the poem and a few warm-up
                questions, a student circled the line and wrote: “WTF??!!?” next to it.</p>
               
            <p>A rambunctious debate that I wasn’t quite prepared to moderate followed. As a
                specialist in Regency- and Romantic-era fiction, I knew enough about Black figures
                in eighteenth- and nineteenth-century literature to help students understand the
                presence of Black people in Romantic-era England.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author">On this topic see also Newman (2021),
                            Gerzina (1995), and Olusoga (2016).</note> I did not, however,
                know enough about the politics of race during the Romantic period to help my
                students think as carefully as I wanted them to about this line. Working through
                what my students needed to contextualize the line and sorting out how to cultivate
                the same analytical energy in response to their other readings contributed to this
                “abolitionist turn” in my teaching of Romanticism. In what follows I show how I made
                this transition in my undergraduate and graduate courses. I discuss critical essays
                that have been most useful for students and assignments that can potentially take
                the work of the class beyond the university classroom.</p>
               
            <p>Threaded through this reflection is an evaluation of how much of the success of these
                curricular revisions is because I responded to students’ unusually animated response
                to how race operates in the Romantic period. As I explain in my essay “Academic
                Freedom: Students and the Problem with Labels,” I expend a great deal of energy
                preserving class discussions as a space where students feel free to wrestle with
                complex ideas, free from expectations that they reflect a specific political point
                of view. I aim for what bell hooks calls “a central goal of transformative
                pedagogy”: making the classroom “a democratic setting where everyone feels a
                responsibility to contribute” (39). Teaching Romanticism with a focus on
                abolitionist culture has made this goal easier to reach. I have found that in
                learning about an abolitionist Romanticism, students are not only studying
                historical texts and their connection to a literary movement they had not recognized
                as infused with racialized imagery and philosophy but are also learning more about
                the intricacies of society, protest, and revolution.</p>
               
            <p>When I started this process, I faced two obstacles. First, my graduate training,
                which in 2006 was still the foundation for teaching Romanticism, did not bring
                questions of race or Blackness to bear on Romanticism. Additionally, as a new
                professor, I was anxious to teach Romantic poetry in a way that was legible to
                senior British-literature faculty, especially those who looked askance at my
                decision to include novels in a course they believed should focus only on poetry. I
                was also facing a short tenure clock and an institutional environment hostile to
                faculty of color, realities that left me little time substantially to revise the
                course I was hired to teach. As a result, my first instinct was simply to add more
                texts that explicitly included mentions of Black figures or referred to slavery or
                abolition. This, however, felt like a superficial response to a pedagogical project
                that required nuance not only in texts I might add to the syllabus but also how
                those additions would alter students’ understanding of the Romantic period as a
                whole. To put it simply, would it matter if I added Ottobah Cugoano without thinking
                about how to reframe “The Little Black Boy” or Blake and his contemporaries?</p>
               
            <p>In response to this set of concerns, my initial impulse was to read articles and book
                chapters that focus on how the writers already on the syllabus thought about the
                slave trade, abolition, amelioration, and emancipation. I also experimented in the
                undergraduate classes I regularly taught (“Introduction to Theory”; “Art of
                Fiction”; and “The Novel to 1900”) by introducing new primary texts. I started with
                just a few texts (primarily fiction) and then planned short units that included
                abolitionist literature reflecting the overall themes of the courses. A course on
                women in nineteenth-century literature, for example, included a unit on marriage and
                chattel slavery. I then offered a “special topics” course that explicitly focused on
                abolition and the nineteenth century. By 2014, when my department added a new
                required course, “Writing for the Major,” designed for new English majors, I had the
                materials to plan an entire course that focused on the writers included in my
                Romanticism syllabus and their contemporaries, and this provided an opportunity for
                students to think about race, abolition, and freedom as essential to how we read
                literature, regardless of the time period from which it emerges. My goal was to
                bring this lens to the period not only for special courses but also as a matter of
                course.</p>
           </div>
               
               <div type="section">
            <head>* * *</head>
                   
            <p>My student’s visceral response to “And I am black, but O! my soul is white” (or as I
                came to call it, the “WTF” line) was prompted by a few elements in the poem and gaps
                in their knowledge about its author. The poem begins, “My mother bore me in the
                Southern Wild” (line 1). Students reading poems written in the first-person voice
                often conflate the speaker in the poem with the poem’s author. It is also likely
                that they had not read the biographical information about Blake included in the
                anthology. This meant that they did not know who Blake was and whether or not the
                poem was directly about him. They also did not know if Blake was Black. What follows
                the “WTF” line shocked students who read it as an exceptionally explicit affirmation
                of white supremacy: “White as an angel is the English Child / But I am black as if
                bereaved of light” (lines 4–5). For some students, particularly students of color, a
                Black author writing these lines reflected a self-loathing. Those same students
                struggled with a white author comparing white children to angels while denigrating
                Black skin. Other students read the line as innocuous. They either did not see the
                problem of the racial hierarchy that the poem promoted or saw such beliefs as
                historical relics. These initial responses reflect the dominant racial mythologies
                that held sway in 2006. A diverse group of students in a class on British literature
                taught by a Black professor were prepared to think that racist ideas prevalent in
                the nineteenth century had been eradicated by the Civil Rights Movement.<note place="foot" resp="author"> I am fully
                            aware that some students were surprised because they had not completed
                            the reading for the day. This meant they encountered the poem for the
                            first time in class.</note> Students who assumed that the author of the
                poem was Black because of its title interpreted the statement as a sign of
                    self-loathing. They saw a Black speaker denigrating his skin color and valorizing whiteness as the
                ideal. Other students were willing to allow that attitudes about race in the
                Romantic period were less enlightened than they imagined them to be in the
                twenty-first century; however, they also understood that whatever informed
                nineteenth-century attitudes about race did not mitigate the troubling racial
                hierarchies the line signified. Barack Obama and the backlash to his candidacy had
                not entered their field of vision, and, unlike students who studied abolitionist
                literature with me in subsequent semesters, many of them had not yet been required
                to confront a world that included the deaths of Trayvon Martin, Michael Brown, and
                to process what the protests in Ferguson, Missouri revealed. Donald Trump was not
                yet legible to them as a political threat. As I discuss below, Romanticism’s racism
                felt more contemporary near the end of Obama’s presidency, but in 2006 students
                turned to historical context and information about Blake and his contemporaries to
                interpret the line, and they wanted to understand whether the language in the poem
                signified to eighteenth- and nineteenth-century readers what it meant to them at
                that particular time.</p>
                   
            <p>Students also asked the same question about Blake that critics defensive of their
                chosen authors ask when questions of race and racism arise: If the line is racist,
                should we hold Blake responsible for ideas that were widely, uncritically
                circulating in the 1800s but unacceptable now? They were also, then, intensely
                curious to see how his contemporaries wrote about this—if Blake was in step, out of
                step, or prescient. When I explained that the poem was published at a particularly
                active time in Britain’s abolitionist movement, students wanted to know which “side”
                he was on, leading to what, to my mind, was and remains the most important critical
                point of discussing abolitionist politics. As I explained during that debate and
                continue to emphasize in my teaching, the terms used in the discussion about the
                transatlantic slave trade—abolition, emancipation, amelioration, freedom—do not
                necessarily correlate to notions of antiracism, equality, and equity. It is, I made
                clear, entirely possible for Blake to be opposed to slavery and still cling to
                racial hierarchies.</p>
                   
            <p>David Bindman’s “Blake’s Vision of Slavery Revisited” proved an especially useful
                follow-up to these questions about the poem. Although more recent readings of Blake
                and race have been published, Bindman’s essay offers a compelling, accessible
                history that answers students’ questions about Blake’s understanding of race and how
                consistent it is with the period. Bindman argues that Blake’s poem returns to
                debates about “the relationship of body to soul that, in the seventeenth and
                eighteenth centuries, had divided scientists from theologians in the discussion of
                racial differences,” though he also notes that the “notion that a black body might
                contain a white soul is expressed at least as early as the third century” (374).
                Bindman points us to work by Christopher Miller about how skin color was perceived
                in the Greco-Roman world. Miller cites a third-century C.E. epitaph for an enslaved
                Ethiopian: “Among the living I was very black, darkened by the rays of the sun, but
                my soul, ever blooming with white flowers, won my prudent master’s good will” (as
                cited by Miller, 374). The essay therefore models for students what is required to
                credibly reach the understanding that Bindman offers near the end of his essay, when
                he writes that the texts he discusses do not “cast doubt on the sincerity of Blake’s
                opposition to slavery,” but they do “suggest that Blake was unable to free
                    himself—<hi rend="italic">no more than anyone else at the time</hi>—from the
                complex and often contradictory web of ancient and modern beliefs that had settled
                around Africa and Africans in the late eighteenth century” (382; emphasis added).
                While I might quibble with the aside that I italicize above—and I share my
                disagreement with my students—I nonetheless have found Bindman’s essay exceptionally
                useful in showing students what they might need to think about and the kinds of
                research they might need to do when considering nineteenth-century representations
                of race.</p>
                   
            <p>Bindman’s article has been a mainstay whenever I teach Blake, and I pair it with
                Kwame Anthony Appiah’s “Race”—an essay that succinctly traces how race functions as
                a social construct in the nineteenth century and clearly explains that despite its
                constructedness, it still carries social weight: “For, however mythical the notion
                of race seems to be, we cannot deny the obvious fact that having one set of
                heritable characteristics—dark skin, say—rather than another—blonde hair, for
                example—can have profound psychological, economic, and other social consequences,
                especially in societies where many people are not only racialists but racists”
                (285). Appiah’s assertations here about “heritable characteristics” made some
                students uncomfortable: those who felt implicated by the idea that the
                characteristics they were born with have social capital and those who chafed against
                the idea that their characteristics may not overcome the obstacles they believe can
                be dismantled with education. My students are wary of the idea of “white privilege”
                because they associate it with economic wealth, but Appiah in this moment
                articulates what the “privilege” looks like, quite literally.<note place="foot" resp="author"> For notes on
                            how to talk about white privilege with undergraduates, see my blog post
                            “Afro-Pedagogy: The Poetry of Race and Privilege.”</note>
                Despite their discomfort, students responded well to the accessibility of Appiah’s
                analogies and, as a result, were better prepared to do the more difficult conceptual
                work it takes to understand how he lays out the consequent process of nation
                building and understandings of race: “the dual connection made in eighteenth- and
                nineteenth-century thought between, on the one hand, race and nationality, and, on
                the other, nationality and literature”; thus “the nation is the key middle term in
                understanding the relations between the concept of race and the idea of literature”
                (282).</p>
                   
            <p>Appiah also addresses the impact of the idea of race as a social construction, an
                idea that too many of my students have turned to as a way to dismiss racism. In the
                “Writing for the Major” course, students also watched his interview with the editor
                of <hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi>. His observations in the interview
                prompted open and productive conversations about race and racism in which students’
                curiosity about the history of race and earnest desire to understand how racism work
                overcame some of the defensiveness and anxiety they felt about a topic that became
                increasingly fraught as their understanding of the world as racially just was
                undermined by national events.</p>
                   
            <p>Although the “Writing for the Major” course began with “The Little Black Boy,” and
                other readings included poetry and prose by William Wordsworth, Samuel Taylor
                Coleridge, and Robert Southey, the class was less explicitly about Romanticism as a
                literary period and more about the uses of literary analysis and research to
                understand the relationship between literature and political movements. The goal was
                for students to consider how poets and novelists contribute to and shape national
                debates by paying attention to the rhetoric that abolitionists used to persuade
                their fellow citizens to support abolition, amelioration, or emancipation. I
                organized the course around a set of themes that often overlapped: consumer culture,
                gender, and religious ideology. In addition to reading “The Little Black Boy,” the
                course began with two exercises: a conversation about the various ways that civic
                groups try to effect broad change and a low-stakes free-association exercise about
                the word <hi rend="italic">sugar</hi>. The exercise involving sugar initially struck
                them as odd because the commodity they most associate with slavery is cotton.
                However, in addition to preparing them for the way that the sweetener was integral
                to abolitionist politics, the free-association exercise helped them understand how a
                consumable object morphs into the imaginary and metaphoric. Without fail, each time
                I taught the class the free association began with “honey” and invariably ended with
                students listing songs that mention “Sugar Daddy” in their titles or lyrics. This
                conflation of commodity, commerce, and desire prepared them for a discussion of Mick
                Jagger and Tina Turner’s 1988 performance of “Brown Sugar.” This song, originally
                released on the Rolling Stones’s 1971 album <hi rend="italic">Sticky Fingers,</hi>
                was still familiar to most of them as one they grew up hearing. They may never have
                seen the Turner-Jagger performance, but they recognize the opening chords and know
                the start of the chorus. Students watched the video without the benefit of having
                the lyrics in front of them and then listened to the song again while reading the
                lyrics. The conversation sparked by what the lines reveal was not as angry as the
                debate about Blake, but it was intense:
                
                <lg type="section">
            <l>Gold Coast slave ship bound for cotton fields</l>
            <l>Sold in the market down in New Orleans</l>
            <l>Skydog slaver know he’s doin’ all right</l>
            <l> Hear him whip the women, just around midnight.</l>
                </lg>
                
            I want to be clear here that the point of this exercise was not to hunt for moments
                of popular culture and vet them for their politics. Instead, I wanted to show
                students the long reach of the tropes that they were about to encounter. Still, in
                each class some sort of debate ensued. Some students felt guilty for liking the
                song. In one class, a few of the Black women tried to convince their classmates that
                Jagger is satirizing and mocking English history, while others were unsure of what
                to make of Turner’s full-throated participation in the performance. These early
                class exercises primed students to push past any neat assumptions about race and
                abolition in the Romantic period and in contemporary representations of Black women
                in literature, visual culture, and film. It also prepared them to think along with
                Christina Sharpe when we listened to her response to Kara Walker’s art installation,
                “The Subtlety.” Sharpe not only provided a pointed critique of Walker and her use of
                the Black female form but also offered a model for students about how to ask
                productive questions from the texts they read and see.</p>
                   
            <p>In addition to “The Little Black Boy,” the primary texts in the class included
                Coleridge’s 1795 lecture “On the Slave Trade,” Southey’s six-sonnet sequence “Poems
                on the Slave Trade,” Amelia Opie’s “The Black Man’s Lament; or, How to Make Sugar,”
                Wordsworth’s “The Mad Mother,” and Hannah More and Eaglesfield Smith’s “The Sorrows
                of Yamba,” a poem that students found particularly compelling when they were
                assigned an excerpt from Alan Richardson’s essay about its creation, “‘The Sorrows
                of Yamba,’ by Eaglesfield Smith and Hannah More: Authorship, Ideology, and the
                Fractures of Antislavery Discourse.” The excerpt I used from Richardson’s essay was
                particularly generative. Students read the poem over two class periods. In the first
                class, their work with the poem was a mix of their initial reactions and my lecture
                on motherhood and infanticide. On the second day, I used the excerpt from the essay
                to take students back to the primary text and asked them to identity what in the
                poem supports Richardson’s claim that he “will establish the dual authorship of the
                Cheap Repository ‘Sorrows of Yamba’ on the basis both of external evidence
                (including new evidence that I discovered in the course of preparing a collection of
                British antislavery poems) and internal evidence,” and that “a crucial part of the
                argument—for the priority and relative integrity of Smith’s version of the
                poem—depends almost wholly on internal evidence, but of an unusually persuasive
                kind” (par. 4). This exercise was particularly rewarding for students who had
                completed the reading before class and followed my recommendation to mark passages
                they found intriguing and/or troubling. Those who read the poem carefully reported a
                “feeling” about how it sounded. They couldn’t quite articulate what was happening in
                the poem until we discussed Richardson’s analysis in class. Having Richardson affirm
                their initial thinking about the poem not only rewarded their close reading but also
                opened a dialogue between students and Richardson that didn’t require my
                guidance.</p>
                   
            <p>Richardson’s analysis was also a useful way to show students the limits of thinking
                about our primary texts as infallible historical documents. One risk of a course
                such as this, especially when students start the semester completely unaware of
                England’s connection to the slave trade, is to read the literary as an historical
                account of the experiences of the enslaved. My students tended to forget this, but
                it was especially important for them to think carefully not only about the
                difference between fact and fiction but also about how the idea of specific
                audiences shapes the way information is constructed. For example, as they read
                Olaudah Equiano’s and Mary Prince’s narratives about slavery, I asked them to be
                mindful of the fact that these histories were written for a white audience.</p>
                   
            <p>These opening exercises gave students a set of signposts to look for as they read,
                making it easier for their initial encounters with the assigned texts. This made
                even the most tedious poems, like Opie’s “How to Make Sugar,” manageable, but it
                didn’t help much with Coleridge’s “Lecture on the Slave Trade.” That essay needs a
                great deal of glossing to help students understand the many references to people and
                places they don’t know, and it is written to be heard rather than read. I had to
                develop a rhetorical map to help students understand it. Many of them believed that
                Coleridge’s recitation of pro-slavery arguments that he later dismantles were
                actually his own beliefs and ideas, so we read the lecture as much for the structure
                of his argument as for his thoughts about the slave trade. Students analyzed the
                tonal shifts in the essay—from its bombastic opening, to its almost clinical
                recitation of the arguments for slavery that he is challenging, to its use of
                poetry. I noted that he is a preacher, a parliamentarian, and a poet all in one
                lecture and then asked them to identify which moments in the lecture fit under those
                categories.</p>
                   
            <p>Coleridge provides a useful introduction to Southey’s antislavery sonnet series. In
                the preface to the six sonnets that grow increasingly violent in tone, Southey
                speculates about the necessary conditions for the slave trade to end and points to
                what will happen with sugar specifically. After briefly describing the 1792
                anti-sugar campaigns, he predicts: “There are yet two other methods remaining, by
                which this traffic will probably be abolished. By the introduction of East-Indian or
                Maple Sugar, or by the just and general rebellion of the Negroes; by the vindictive
                justice of the Africans, or by the civilized Christians finding it in their interest
                to be humane” (31). Students read Coleridge and Southey about midway through the
                semester, and Southey’s predictions about the conditions necessary for abolition
                offered a prompt for them to revisit the question of what mechanisms are required
                for meaningful societal change.</p>
                   
            <p>When it came to student work in this course, I aimed to develop a series of
                assignments that reflected how my students imagined their lives after college. When
                I was a new professor, my writing assignments did not offer students enough options.
                But a course titled “Writing for the Major” required me to consider new ways to
                think about what the work of writing does for students and to imagine ways to
                encourage student agency about their education. In his chapter “Anassignment
                Letters,” Fred Moten writes to his students about the inherent contradiction of
                cultivating their intellectual work while imposing institutional structures on them
                in the form of a series of assignments. The nature of assignments, he explains,
                neutralizes whatever revolutionary ideals he might hold, leaving him as “nothing
                other than an overseer even if what [he teaches] appears, at the level of its
                content, to resist the actually existing political-economic order” (229). Moten
                wants to mitigate the tension between the coercive practices he sees himself as
                imposing on his students and his belief that his primary job is to support them as
                they cultivate and refine their intellectual practices. What this has meant for my
                praxis is to think of assignments as preparing students to make a choice about how
                they present their analytical work. Roughly a third of my students have plans to
                teach English, primarily in high school. Working with them to develop a
                research-based lesson plan was a useful, organic way to assess how they took primary
                readings, class discussions, journal articles, and their earlier papers and
                restructured parts of them for their future students. “The Little Black Boy” lesson
                plans, for example, took what in a university classroom ends up being two 30-minute
                class discussions and broke it down into three or four days for younger
                students.</p>
                   
            <p>It was also an instructive glimpse into how my students processed material with an
                eye toward what they needed from me. They tended to be more interested in providing
                the “history” around the poem, and they learned how important it is to spend time
                debunking the myth that historians are simply offering a fixed report of the past.
                Giving students choices about their work also amplified their interest in the course
                readings. They understood that assignments which at first glance felt like busy work
                actually helped them think about their analytical processes for their final project.
                The assignment that required them to read two refereed journal articles made more
                sense to them because it was not simply offering them “context” but also showing
                them how to engage with complex representations and ideologies.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Coleman’s
                            “Conspicuous Consumption” was very popular, especially for students
                            looking for a way to understand what ungirds women’s participation in
                            abolitionist discourse. By far the most popular was Brown’s “Olaudah
                            Equiano and the Sailor’s Telegraph.” Students tend to find Equiano
                            particularly compelling, and Brown’s reading of the memoir points to
                            moments of community and egalitarianism that I suspect appeal to their
                            need for hopeful moments of solidarity in a violent
                        ecosystem.</note></p>
               </div>
               
               <div type="section">
            <head>* * *</head>
                   
            <p>The graduate seminars I teach in my department’s M.A. program are a mix of students
                planning for doctoral studies, teachers seeking the Master of Arts in Teaching, and
                students interested in a graduate-level engagement with literature. The course I
                planned for this group in 2018 provided an opportunity to bring primary texts into
                dialogue with critical race theory, feminist literary criticism, and emergent
                Romanticist critical discourses that reimagine the postcolonial project. Here is the
                full description from the syllabus:
                
            <quote>Students in this course will consider how our understanding of nineteenth-century
                Britain shifts when we take into account how much of the culture that gave us [Percy
                Bysshe] Shelley, [Jane] Austen, and, eventually, the Brontës relied on the
                transatlantic slave trade. Our work will focus on Romantic-era writers who shaped,
                reflected, and contributed to England’s abolitionist movement. We will read
                antislavery writing by canonical poets (Blake, Coleridge, and Wordsworth); consider
                the rhetorical moves in Ottobah Cugoano’s
                <hi rend="italic">Thoughts and Sentiments on the Evils of Slavery </hi>[1791]
                and Olaudah Equiano’s <hi rend="italic">Interesting Narrative</hi> [1789]; and read
                novels and novel fragments that tell the story of mixed-race heroines, including
                <hi rend="italic">The Woman of Colour, A Tale </hi>[1808] and
                    <hi rend="italic">Narrative of Joanna; An Emancipated Slave, of Surinam</hi>
                [1838]. We will also read a few antislavery poems and lectures with an eye towards
                thinking about how representations of people of color are shaped by generic
                conventions. The abolitionist movement is one of the first political events British
                white women organized themselves around, so we will pay special attention to
                nineteenth-century women writers including Jane Austen (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Sanditon</hi> [comp. 1817]), Maria Edgeworth (“The Grateful Negro”), Amelia
                Opie (<hi rend="italic">Adeline Mowbray</hi> [1804]), and Mary Wollstonecraft
                (excerpts from <hi rend="italic">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> [1792]).
                In addition to these primary texts, we will also consider the period’s material and
                visual culture and spend time thinking about how antislavery ideologies are
                reinterpreted in popular culture. We’ll read these primary texts in the context of
                Critical Race Theory, feminist literary criticism, and emergent Romanticist critical
                discourses that reimagine the postcolonial project.</quote>
                   
            In the first few classes, students reacted to this course in a number of ways, almost
                all of which resisted its premise. Some of this was, I suspect, the natural
                performance of skepticism that graduate students bring to courses as they feel their
                way through the dynamics of the class. Some of the resistance was based on how much
                this course differed from how they had been taught Romanticism as undergraduates.
                However much they had read of the period before they took my course, these students
                tended to understand it as a period where there are no Black people or people of
                color, no questions about identity, race, and citizenship, and where the only
                revolutionary activities took place in France. Even students sympathetic to the idea
                of race and representation in the period were skeptical about the seminar, thinking
                that my approach to our reading was a theoretical or temporal sleight of hand. This
                was one of the reasons I didn’t begin this course with Wordsworth’s “To Toussaint
                L’Ouverture.” With its “whistling rustic” and “common wind,” Wordsworth’s sonnet
                reads to students as consistent with Romantic tropes in general and the aesthetics
                of his work. When we did read the poem later in the semester, we followed it with C.
                L. R James’s <hi rend="italic">The Black Jacobins</hi> (1938), which helped reorient
                students to the geographies of slavery and abolition. For students trained in
                African American studies, this class was a revelation that invited them to revisit
                the “trans” in “transatlantic slave trade.” For so many of them the history of the
                transatlantic slave trade has elided England’s role in it and the hollowness of
                “emancipation.”</p>
                   
            <p>The most animated class discussions were sparked by <hi rend="italic">The Woman of
                    Colour, A Tale</hi> (1808). Even though they preferred reading novels to poetry,
                graduate students loved and hated <hi rend="italic">The Woman of Colour</hi> in
                equal measure. The novel, which tells the story of the daughter of an enslaved Black
                woman and a planter with family in England, disrupts their expectations of both the
                “tragic mulatto” narrative and the courtship novel. Many students confessed that
                they wanted the heroine, Olivia Fairfield, to recover from her marriage to a
                bigamist by marrying an early suitor in the novel and wrestled with their own need
                for a happy ending that concludes with nuptials rather than the independence that
                comes with being a wealthy woman who returns with no master—chattel to no man, free
                from her father’s bizarre will requiring her to marry a distant cousin in order to
                inherit, emancipated from the racist strictures of British society—to her home in
                Jamaica. In response to the revelation that Olivia’s supposed husband, August
                Merton, already has a wife, her servant Dido announces that she “<hi rend="italic"
                    >has no</hi> master” after the biracial heroine discovers that her husband is an
                accidental bigamist (141). Dido is not only furious about how her mistress has been
                treated by her husband’s family but is also frustrated to find herself demoted from
                a grand home to a more modest cottage. We thought about the idea of a “master” in
                multiple registers—as the titular head of a wealthy English home and, given that
                Dido is from Jamaica and marked linguistically as other, as a man who bought and
                sold captured African women and men or could claim legal ownership from birth. We
                also thought about Dido’s body and the space she and Olivia occupy materially and
                imaginatively in the novel. The text’s inflections of marriage and/as slavery and
                women and/as chattel underscored our discussions of all the fiction we read. We
                compared Olivia to Wollstonecraft’s description of ideal women in <hi rend="italic"
                    >A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi>.</p>
                   
            <p>Student resistance to the course’s central goal diminished as the semester
                progressed, but it was replaced by an intellectual sentimentalism that I found
                reductive. In my essay on a similar subject (“Jane Austen and the Abolitionist
                Turn”), I talk about the collegial but earnest tug-of-war I have with graduate
                students who want to make the work of reading about race and representation in
                eighteenth- and nineteenth-century Britain into a cause. While I admire the
                intentions behind this idea, I find I am ambivalent about some of the projects that
                emerge from this stance. This is in part a reaction to the way such an approach is
                framed. Projects that work to question our assumptions about Romanticism and its
                entanglements with race and representation make sense. These interrogations tend to
                stay tightly focused, and they rely on the kind of archival thinking that a scholar
                like Rebecca Schneider deploys in her essay “‘He says he is free’: Narrative
                Fragments and Self-Emancipation in West Indian Runaway Advertisements.” I worry
                about an approach that treats these works as ways to “humanize” people of color by
                reading the primary texts (the literary and the historical) as documentaries that
                teach us about the past. They don’t. They show us select representations of the
                past. As Marcus Wood observes in his study of visual representations of slavery,
                “The experiences of millions of individuals who were the victims of slavery is not
                collectable; it is unrecoverable as a set of relics. There can be no archeology of
                the memory of slavery that corresponds to an emotional identification with a lost
                reality” (7). Those representations certainly influence our contemporary notions of
                race, but Britain’s abolitionist project feels too complex to be read as a template
                for what we can and cannot do in the twenty-first century. It is a viewpoint that is
                appealing to students who are less interested in literary analysis and more invested
                in sociological projects. The problem with this approach is that it replicates the
                same problematic assumptions about who we read, so that writers are good or bad
                depending on how they feed into our notions of social justice. As I discuss below by
                way of conclusion, this is different than the connections my undergraduates make
                between abolitionist-era politics and this contemporary moment. Despite reading many
                of the same texts, undergraduates tend to identify structural similarities between
                the two periods, especially the way that British abolitionists construct themselves
                in relationship to the Black figures they claim to support. Graduate students,
                especially women of color and white women, tend to see in the struggles of the past
                their own oppressive experiences.</p>
                   
            <p>One way this is evident is in reactions to Olivia Fairfield in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Woman of Colour</hi>. Whereas, as I note above, graduate students wrestle with
                wanting a traditional, heteronormative ending for Olivia, undergraduates are
                exasperated with her for not confronting the bigotry she encounters. They tend to
                have no interest in the idea of her marrying. They see that legal and social
                contracts have failed her, and their focus tends to stay on that fact. The different
                responses certainly reflect when and how students engage with this material.
                Undergraduates are still developing the analytic skills that graduate students are
                refining on the way to planning longer projects that will make critical
                interventions into existing discourse. Their different reactions also reflect the
                readings that students bring to the class. In the graduate seminar, most of the
                students were very familiar with Regency-era literature and read it by choice. I
                think that for them Olivia Fairfield was a brown version of the white heroines they
                read for pleasure and for escape. Undergraduates encountered her in the context of
                abolitionist debates. As a result, they see her as yet another person of color
                navigating nineteenth-century racism. Generally speaking, perhaps both groups are
                simply projecting their own values onto the text, and I prefer the projection that
                aligns with my own thinking. I get excited when I see my students recognizing
                patterns of structural violence and nervous when they individualize what they read
                in my classes. The latter seems to me more a starting point than the end of an
                intellectual project. This seems a good pedagogical problem to have; in both cases
                students are animated about and engaged with the work of understanding an ecosystem
                that they still see as operating today.</p>
                   
               </div>
               
               <div type="section">
                   
            <head>* * *</head>
                   
                   
            <p>For all that, I want students to see my class discussions—indeed, my class as a
                whole—as a place to work out ideas and a space free from punitive critique and the
                pressure to perform a particular politics. I have been gratified when they make
                connections between our reading and the contemporary political landscape, and I have
                been relieved when they feel they can talk about their political concerns in my
                class. What I admired about the student’s “WTF??!!?” has happened in classes again,
                in more muted but no less intense ways. After the 2016 election, many of the
                students who enrolled in my section of “Writing for the Major” did so because they
                saw it as a space where they could talk about the racist violence they saw in the
                country. The words “Black Lives Matter” were never spoken. But Black students in the
                class were very open about the fear they felt. I will always remember the Black
                woman who said, “I feel like I have to fight the same battles my ancestors already
                won.” The white students around her were visibly shocked by her candor. With no
                prompting from me, students in the class were more likely to choose research
                projects that connected representations of violence in abolitionist culture to
                violence they were reading about in the news. One student, for example, wrote a
                research essay about Equiano’s description of psychological violence and the case of
                Kalief Browder, wrongly imprisoned after police suspected him of stealing a
                backpack. Another student prepared a research presentation that traced depictions of
                Black women’s bodies from Sarah Baartman to the present, revisiting Christina
                Sharpe’s discussion of Kara Walker. Among themselves, students started discussing
                the challenges and risks of confronting racist moments in their lives away from
                school. Ava DuVernay’s documentary <hi rend="italic">13</hi><hi
                    rend="sup">th</hi> was released in October 2016; by 2017 some of
                my students had watched the film, and they brought it up enough in class discussions
                that their peers watched it, too.</p>
                   
            <p>There were difficult debates, as well. Smart, thoughtful students asked earnest
                questions with racist overtones, and I had to walk a fine line. I had to moderate
                those discussions without giving students who were asking troubling questions the
                impression that they were being dismissed, and while also protecting the
                sensibilities of other students who would feel those questions most keenly because
                of their “heritable characteristics.” In those discussions, Coleridge’s lecture was
                quite helpful. He lays out five pro-slavery arguments and then debunks them. In more
                than one class, skeptical students benefitted from our close attention to what
                underscored the pro-slavery debates that Coleridge references.</p>
                   
            <p>In the scant ground of a course reading list, it can be particularly challenging to
                include new authors, especially if one wants to go about the work with care. As
                Miriam Wallace and I noted in our <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles</hi> special
                issue (2008), Annette Kolodny is right when she describes the challenges of changing
                what and how we teach: “Radical breaks are tiring, demanding, uncomfortable, and
                sometimes wholly beyond our comprehension” (12). But I think the outcomes are worth
                the effort, and no one taking on this work is doing so alone. There are so many
                resources available and models to follow. I am thinking especially of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Undisciplining the Victorian Classroom</hi> digital humanities
                project (2020). The site is a repository of peer-reviewed syllabi, recorded
                discussions about teaching, and sample units for faculty use. Similar projects are
                in the works for eighteenth-century studies as well. An abolitionist Romanticism
                course captures most students’ imaginations because they tend to think of slavery
                and abolition as uniquely American. Thinking about race, racism, and slavery in a
                British context gives them space to work out knotty, unnerving questions about these
                complex issues. At the same time, it helps them read contemporary progressive
                movements in more nuanced ways. I have found that in learning about an abolitionist
                Romanticism, students are not only studying historical texts and their connection to
                a movement, they are also learning more about the intricacies of society, protest,
                and revolution.</p>
               </div>
               
               <div type="section">
                   <head>Works Cited</head>
                   
           
            <bibl>Anonymous. <hi rend="italic">The Woman of Colour, A Tale</hi> [1808]. Edited by
                Lyndon J. Dominique. Broadview, 2008.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Appiah, Kwame Anthony. Interview with Gideon Rose of <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                    Affairs</hi>. YouTube, 2014. <ref
                    target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EEOQcVLvnKo"
                    >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EEOQcVLvnKo</ref>.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>———. “Race.” <hi rend="italic">Critical Terms for Literary Studies</hi>, edited by
                Frank Lentricchia and Thomas McLaughlin, 274–87. Univ. of Chicago Press, 1990.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Bindman, David. “Blake’s Vision of Slavery Revisited.” <hi rend="italic">William
                    Blake: Images and Texts</hi>. Special issue, <hi rend="italic">Huntington
                    Library Quarterly</hi> 58, no. 3/4 (1995): 373–82. </bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Blake, William. “The Little Black Boy.” <hi rend="italic">The Longman Anthology of
                    British Literature: The Romantics and Their Contemporaries</hi>. 3rd ed., edited
                by David Damrosch et al., 113–4. Pearson, 2006<hi rend="italic">.</hi></bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Brown, Matthew D. “Olaudah Equiano and the Sailor’s Telegraph: ‘The Interesting
                Narrative’ and the Source of Black Abolitionism.” <hi rend="italic">Callaloo</hi>
                36, no. 1 (2013): 191–201. </bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Coleman, Deirdre. “Conspicuous Consumption: White Abolitionism and English Women’s
                Protest Writing in the 1790s.” <hi rend="italic">ELH</hi> 61, no. 2 (1994):
                341–62.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor. “On the Slave Trade” [1795]. Vol. 1. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lectures, 1795. The Collected Works of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</hi>, edited by
                Lewis Patton and Peter Mann, 231–51. Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1971.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Gerzina, Gretchen. <hi rend="italic">Black London: Life before Emancipation</hi>.
                Rutgers Univ. Press, 1995.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>hooks, bell. <hi rend="italic">Teaching to Transgress: Education as the Practice of
                    Freedom</hi>. Routledge, 1994.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Jagger, Mick. “Brown Sugar.” Rolling Stones, <hi rend="italic">Sticky Fingers</hi>.
                Rolling Stones Records, 1971.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Jagger, Mick, and Tina Turner. Performance of “Brown Sugar,” Tokyo, Japan, Mar., 23,
                1988. YouTube. <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O1xsZ2iE3Zc"
                    >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O1xsZ2iE3Zc</ref>.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Kolodny, Annette. “Dancing through the Minefield: Some Observations on the Theory,
                Practice, and Politics of a Feminist Literary Criticism.” <hi rend="italic">Feminist
                    Studies</hi> 6, no. 1 (1980): 1–25. </bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Makdisi, Saree. “The Political Aesthetic of Blake’s Images.” <hi rend="italic">The
                    Cambridge Companion to William Blake</hi>, edited by Morris Eaves, 110–32.
                Cambridge Univ. Press, 2003.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Matthew, Patricia A. “Academic Freedom: Students and the Problem with Labels.” <hi
                rend="italic">Profession</hi>, Winter 2019. <ref target="https://profession.mla.org/academic-freedom-in-the-classroom-students-and-the-trouble-with-labels/"
                    >https://profession.mla.org/academic-freedom-in-the-classroom-students-and-the-trouble-with-labels/</ref>.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>———. “Afro-Pedagogy: The Poetry of Race and Privilege.” Blog post, Nov., 13, 2013,
                    <ref target="https://patriciamatthew.blog/tag/miley-cyrus/"
                    >https://patriciamatthew.blog/tag/miley-cyrus/</ref>. </bibl>
                   
            <bibl>———. “Jane Austen and the Abolitionist Turn.” <hi rend="italic">Texas Studies in
                    Literature and Language</hi> 61, no. 4 (2019): 345–61.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Matthew, Patricia A., and Miriam L. Wallace, eds. <hi rend="italic">Novel Prospects:
                    Teaching Romantic Fiction</hi>. Special issue, <hi rend="italic">Romantic
                    Circles Pedagogies</hi>, 2008.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Miller, Christopher. <hi rend="italic">Blank Darkness: Africanist Discourse in
                    French.</hi> Univ. of Chicago Press, 1986.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Moten, Fred. “Anassignment Letters.” In
                <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Stolen Life, </hi>227–36. Duke Univ. Press,
                2018.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Newman, Simon P. <hi rend="italic">Freedom Seekers: Escaping from Slavery in
                    Restoration London</hi>. Univ. of Chicago Press, 2021.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Olusoga, David. <hi rend="italic">Black and British: A Forgotten History</hi>.
                Macmillan, 2016.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Richardson, Alan. “‘The Sorrows of Yamba,’ by Eaglesfield Smith and Hannah More:
                Authorship, Ideology, and the Fractures of Antislavery Discourse.” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romanticism on the Net</hi> 28 (2002). <ref
                    target="https://doi.org/10.7202/007209ar"
                >https://doi.org/10.7202/007209ar</ref>.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Schneider, Rebecca. “‘He says he is free’: Narrative Fragments and Self-Emancipation
                in West Indian Runaway Advertisements.” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic
                    Review</hi> 29, no. 4 (2018): 435–47.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Sharpe, Christina. Remarks in “Panel Discussion: Kara Walker: Harper’s Pictorial
                History of the Civil War,” Fleming Museum of Art. Burlington, VT, Oct. 8, 2014.
                    YouTube<hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IhHmHYBssMc"
                    >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IhHmHYBssMc</ref>.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Southey, Robert. “Poems on the Slave Trade.” In <hi rend="italic">Poems.</hi> 2nd
                ed., 29–38. N. Biggs, 1797.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Undisciplining the Victorian Classroom</hi>, 2020, <hi
                    rend="Hyperlink">https://undiscipliningvc.org/index.html</hi>.</bibl>
                   
            <bibl>Wood, Marcus. <hi rend="italic">Blind Memory: Visual Representations of Slavery in
                    England and America, 1780–1865.</hi> Manchester Univ. Press, 2000.</bibl>
               </div>
                    </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
