<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">“Infrastructure and Environment as Archive: On Haitian Revolutionary Romanticism and Voicing Contingent Desolations”</title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Michele Speitz</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-07-9</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2024.contingent.speitz</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">contingent</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Romantic Contingency
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Michele</forename>
                                <surname>Speitz</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/contingent/praxis.2024.contingent.speitz"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/wellbeing/praxis.2024.wellbeing.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Contingency</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-07-09">July 9, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>07.09.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p>
                    This essay studies national narratives at the heart of one of the best-known works of Haitian revolutionary Romanticism. At issue is how these national narratives participate within larger semiotic systems of national infrastructure and nationalized earth. More particularly, the essay foregrounds Haitian places and ruins that bear complicated realities and histories in need of telling. In signature Romantic style, Haitian grounds and built structures have their own stories to tell and speak volumes in Charles Hérard Dumesle’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage dans le nord d'Hayti</hi> (1824). But the voices they sound and the accounts they record are not homogenous, timeless, nor transcendent, as we find in more universalizing iterations of Romantic-era calls for new political orders. Instead these voices and histories are particular, personal, and contingent—proving especially provocative when read in light of key terminology from Haiti’s <hi rend="italic"> Acte de l’Indépendance</hi> (1804). Dumesle’s revolutionary Romantic poetics turn upon the politics of prosopopoeia, intoning counternarratives and correctives to nationally-chauvinistic French colonial politics and aesthetics in part by giving voice to Haitian locales, by giving rise to the human and nonhuman stories they might tell if these places too had tongues or pens. That is, Dumesle drives home the political edge of the aesthetics and poetics of prosopopoeia, a trope that uses the imaginative and metaphorical spaces of narrative to imbue voice to whatever typically is not able to speak, from other animals to the land itself, from built objects to dead subjects. In this sense, Dumesle activates an especially time-sensitive iteration of prosopopoeia in place of more lyric-driven instances of prosopopoeia that might be said to reach for timeless universality. Here Haiti’s natural and built environments speak tales of national heroics and chronicle compressed events of human dispossession and death that cannot be sundered from stories of long-term environmental degradation and desolation.  
                </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="essay">
                <head>“Infrastructure and Environment as Archive: On Haitian Revolutionary Romanticism and Voicing Contingent Desolations"</head><note place="foot" resp="author">I thank Dr. Cherie Maiden for her generous help with many of the translations featured in this essay.</note>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Michele Speitz</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>Furman University</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
           
            <p>“Literature from the growing black geographies canon suggests that black
                infrastructure is not statically ‘set in place,’ but instead a set of revolutionary
                place-making practices with ‘unknowable’ and (im)possible contours.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Symon James-Wilson, “Roads, Routes, And Roots: The (Im)Possible Spatial Mnemonics of Black
                                Infrastructure,” <hi rend="italic">Society and
                                    Space</hi>, 2018. </note></p>
            
            <p>This essay studies national narratives at the heart of one of the best-known works of
                Haitian Revolutionary Romanticism. At issue is how these national narratives
                participate within larger semiotic systems of national infrastructure and
                nationalized earth. What follows is a study of Haitian places and ruins that bear
                complicated realities and histories in need of telling. In signature Romantic style,
                Haitian grounds and built structures have their own stories and speak volumes in
                Charles Hérard Dumesle’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage dans le nord d'Hayti</hi>
                    (1824).<note place="foot" resp="author"> Dumesle, Charles Hérard. <hi
                                rend="italic">Voyage dans le nord
                                d’Hayti.</hi> (Cayes, Haiti: Government Imprint, 1824).</note>
                
                But the voices they sound and the accounts they record are not homogenous, timeless,
                nor transcendent, as we find in more universalizing iterations of Romantic-era calls
                for new political orders. Instead, these cries and histories are particular,
                personal, and contingent—proving especially provocative when read in light of key
                terminology from Haiti’s <hi rend="italic">Acte de l’Indépendance</hi> (1804).<note place="foot"  resp="author"><hi rend="italic" >Acte de l’Indépendance,
                                1804</hi>, “Digithèque de Matériaux
                                Juridique et Politique,” ed by Jean-Pierre Maury,
                            2004–2014.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Dumesle’s poetics of revolution turn upon the politics of prosopopoeia. Dumesle
                drives home the political edge of the aesthetics and poetics of prosopopoeia, a
                trope that uses the imaginative and metaphorical spaces of narrative to imbue voice
                to whatever typically is not able to speak—from other animals to the land itself,
                from built objects to dead subjects. Giving voice to Haitian locales and by giving
                rise to the human and nonhuman stories they might tell if these places too had
                tongues or pens, Dumesle intones counternarratives and correctives to
                nationally-chauvinistic French colonial politics and aesthetics. In keeping with
                Paul de Man’s classic discussions of prosopopoeia, Dumesle relies on the figure of
                prosopopoeia not merely to draft the “fiction of an apostrophe to an absent,
                deceased, or voiceless entity.”<note place="foot" resp="author"><hi> Paul de Man, “Autobiography as De-Facement,” in </hi><hi rend="italic" >The Rhetoric of
                                Romanticism</hi>, 67-81 (New York: Columbia University Press, 1984), 75.
                        </note> In particular, Dumesle activates an especially
                time-sensitive iteration of prosopopoeia in place of more lyric-driven instances of
                prosopopoeia that might be said to reach for timeless universality. Here Haiti’s
                natural and built environments speak tales of national heroics and chronicle
                compressed events of human dispossession and death that cannot be sundered from
                stories of long-term environmental degradation and desolation. Reading
                infrastructure and environment as archive, Dumesle not only anticipates Michel-Rolph
                Trouillot’s landmark work <hi rend="italic">Silencing the Past: Power and the
                    Production of History</hi> (Beacon 1995) but also Rob Nixon’s celebrated text
                <hi rend="italic">Slow Violence: the Environmentalism of the Poor </hi>(Harvard
                    2011).<note place="foot" resp="author"> Michel-Rolph Trouillot, <hi rend="italic" >Silencing the Past: Power and the Production of History </hi>(Boston: Beacon, 1995); Rob Nixon, 
                            <hi rend="italic" >Slow Violence and the
                                Environmentalism of the
                            Poor</hi> (Cambridge, MA. and London: Harvard University Press, 2011). </note> Dumesle’s national narrative foregrounds a refigured
                revolutionary Romanticism, one routed through much more than some fleeting humanist
                spirit of an age, one that is always anchored by deeply rooted contingencies of time
                and place.</p>
                
            <p> Writing after the Haitian Revolution, which spanned a
                bloody thirteen years (1791-1804), and writing in the wake of Haitian independence
                from France (1804), Dumesle has been historicized as one of Haiti’s first epic
                poets. He figures as an early example of an Haitian author participating in a
                nationalized Romanticism specific to Haiti that remained active across the
                nineteenth century and through the early-twentieth century until U.S. occupation in
                    1915.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Jacquelin Dolcé, Gérard Dorval, and Jean Miotel Casthely. <hi rend="italic">Le Romantisme en Haïti: La Vie Intellectuelle, 1804–1915.</hi> (Port-au Prince, Haiti: Éditions Fardin, 1983), 5-9.</note>
                In the Francophone work entitled <hi rend="italic">Le Romantisme en Haïti: La Vie
                    Intellectuelle, 1804–1915</hi> (translating to <hi rend="italic">The Romanticism
                    in Haiti: The Intellectual Life, 1804-1915</hi>), Jacquelin Dolcé, Gérard
                Dorval, and Jean Miotel Casthely identify Haitian art from this period as belonging
                to a Haitian Romanticism where art and politics fed one another, and where art was
                always a provocation to act.<note place="foot" resp="author">Dolcé, Dorval, and Casthely, 3-9.</note>
                Caribbean Studies scholar Marlene L. Daut mounts a compelling case for understanding
                Dumesle’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage </hi>as a pivotal example of
                transnational iterations of revolutionary Romanticism built around tropes of
                justifiable rebellion and rightful vengeance. Daut also distinguishes how <hi
                    rend="italic">Voyage</hi> marks a singular iteration of revolutionary
                Romanticism constitutive of Haiti and its more unique expressions of an
                affect-driven Romanticism predicated upon a condition of becoming sorrowful. Daut
                stresses how “by the mid-nineteenth century the verb <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>
                [to make sorrowful] had become associated with not only the crafting of Haiti’s
                Declaration of Independence, but with the early Haitian literary tradition more
                    broadly.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Marlene L. Daut, “‘Nothing in Nature is Mute’: Reading Revolutionary Romanticism in L’Haïtiade and Hérard Dumesle’s Voyage dans le nord d'Hayti (1824),” <hi
                                rend="italic" >New Literary
                            History</hi> 49, no. 4 (2018): 495.</note>
                Extending Daut’s historical materialist argument, I contend that a poststructuralist
                analysis of <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>, in particular one that takes stock of
                the multiple meanings denoted and connoted by this word, reveals how the condition
                of becoming sorrowful—rather than activating the escapist, accepting, or
                ameliorative energies of elegy—functions with the agency of an aesthetic judgement
                capable of inspiring political action and great change.<note place="foot" resp="author"> On the escapist energies of elegy, especially in relation to environmental political histories, see Greg Garrard, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ecocriticism</hi> (London and New York: Routledge, 2011).</note></p>
                
            <p>As Daut observes, Dumesle “was accused by [the nineteenth-century French grammarian
                Gustave] D’Alaux of having, in his 1824 <hi rend="italic">Voyage dans le nord
                    d’Hayti</hi>, ‘gone into ecstasies’ over” the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >lugubrer</hi>.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Daut, 495.</note> Daut
                foregrounds the term’s etymology, evolving meanings, and politicized reception in a
                long passage:
                
            <quote>The <hi rend="italic">Acte de l’Indépendance</hi> famously contains a phrase that
                allegedly caused the most ardent of French grammarians in the nineteenth century to
                turn up their noses: ‘The name of the French <hi rend="italic">makes sorrowful</hi>
                our land’ [Le nom français <hi rend="italic">lugubre</hi> encore nos contrées].
                Disdain for this phrase derived not solely, it seems, from the uninhibited hatred of
                the French it exhibits, but also from the fact that the adjective <hi rend="italic"
                    >lugubre,</hi> which means “mournful” or “sorrowful,” had been turned into a
                verb, “to make sorrowful.” Although the crassly termed “mulatto verb” [verbe
                mulâtre] has—at least since the publication of Gustave D’Alaux’s 1852 article
                “Yellow Literature” [La Littérature jaune]—been attributed to Dessalines’s most
                prominent secretary, Louis-Félix Boisrond-Tonnerre, the verb <hi rend="italic"
                    >lugubrer</hi> was actually defined a few years before Haitian independence in
                Mercier’s <hi rend="italic">Neologisms: or Dictionary of New words, to Revive, or to
                    Understand in New Ways</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Néologie: ou Vocabulaire de mots
                    nouveaux, à renouveler, ou pris dans des acceptions Nouvelles</hi>] (1801). In
                the dictionary, Mercier, who claimed in the work’s introduction to have “removed
                (with very few exceptions) all words that relate to the [French] revolution,” the
                entry for <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi> reads:
                
                to imprint with sadness. His imagination tends to make sorrowful everything around
                him. To make sorrowful a theatre with dark and sad works, distressing; Make
                sorrowful a group of people with frightening details of an atrocious crime; Make
                children sorrowful with ghost stories.
                
            empreindre la tristesse. Son imagination sombre ne tend qu’à Lugubrer tout ce qui
                l’environne. Lugubrer un théâtre par des pièces tristes et noires, affligeantes;
                Lugubrer une assemblée par les épouvantables détails d’un crime atroce; Lugubrer
                l’esprit des enfans par des contes de revenans.<note
                        place="foot">Daut, 495.</note></quote>
                
            Daut does not linger over this term for much longer in her essay, yet since the
                current purpose of this study is in part to pick up where she left off with <hi
                    rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>, it is first necessary to highlight Daut’s larger
                claim. The aforementioned discussion of <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi> serves as a
                point of departure for Daut’s argument that Haiti’s national founding, replete with
                its history and its literature, “ha[s] a relationship to global Romanticism that has
                been obscured by the tendency of scholars in the US and Western Europe to examine
                this field as primarily literary and aesthetic rather than historical and
                    political.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                           Daut, 497.</note> For Daut,
                “[i]t is precisely the fusion of enlightenment poetics and revolutionary politics
                that we see in the <hi rend="italic">Acte de l’Indépendance</hi>, which allows us to
                understand this document itself (rather than just the moment of independence) as
                axiomatic rather than quixotic, and elemental rather than incidental, for the <hi
                    rend="italic">longue durée</hi> of Romanticism in Haiti.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Daut, 497.</note> To underscore
                her point Daut emphasizes “the direct influence of the <hi rend="italic">Acte de
                    l’Indépendance</hi> on later works of Haitian literature and history,” including
                Dumesle’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage.</hi><note
                        place="foot" resp="author">
                            Daut, 497.</note> Daut rightly
                contends that to responsibly address Haiti’s national literature from this period
                and its relationship to revolutionary Romanticism requires that we recognize the
                contingency of the poetic and the political, the aesthetic and the historical within
                this body of work. For Dumesle’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi> in particular, then,
                is it necessary to grasp the centrality of the <hi rend="italic">Acte de
                    l’Indépendance</hi> as a key allusive, intertextual reference point. It is also
                important to bear in mind what is at stake when Dumesle is characterized as having
                “gone into ecstasies” over the neologism <hi rend="italic">lugubrer,</hi> a highly
                politicized term itself central to the Haitian Declaration of Independence and its
                literary and political legacies.</p>
                
            <p> While the nineteenth-century French grammarian D’Alaux meant to disparage Dumesle
                for being in thrall to the term <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>, when read from
                another perspective, D’Alaux’s phrasing may well have signified a compliment
                attesting to the political power of Dumesle’s words. D’Alaux’s negative aesthetic
                judgement of the word suggests that Dumesle’s writing falls down a peg because of a
                problematic mélange of an implied mindless devotion, hyper-embodiment, and
                irrationality in his allegiance to <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>. The reference to
                his going into “ecstasies” does double duty in conjuring to mind a would-be
                thoughtless state of religious zealousness as well as a sexually-charged state of
                orgasmic release, neither of which suggest a steady hand nor a level head. Neither
                conforms to normative, hyperrational parameters of so-called western enlightenment
                subjects. But when read against the French colonial grain, to go into ecstasy over
                the term <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>, a verb referring to the process of
                becoming sorrowful, suggests arriving at a motivated state of emotional whiplash: a
                frenetic sadness, fevered grieving, heated distress. Here lies vengeance.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Literatures of Saint-Domingue’s formerly enslaved subjects framed vengeance as a mode of countering misrepresentative colonial accounts of the past. As Daut notes, in the case of Vastey’s <hi rend="italic">Le Cri de la conscience </hi>[The Cry of Conscience] (1815), “Vengeance
                                here has become less evidence of African ‘savagery,’ as evoked
                                sometimes even in the laudatory writings of Métral, and closer to
                                what Daina Ramey Berry might call one of the ‘soul values’ of the
                                formerly enslaved peoples of Saint-Domingue. The human soul that
                                lives after death and tells its own story out of revenge for the
                                intractable testimony of the colonists provides Vastey with an
                                archive that not only intimately involves, but was created,
                                contextualized, and preserved by nineteenth-century Haitians
                                themselves” (503).</note> To have gone into ecstasies
                over <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi> becomes the rhetorical equivalent of being half
                in love with sorrow—primarily the half invigorating one to act in the spirit of the
                Haitian Declaration of Independence, as I discuss below.</p>
                
            <p> The term’s reception history hints at how <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi> could
                raise the specter of activating multiple levels of vengeance, applicable not just to
                avenging trespasses against humanity but also against ruined Haitian grounds and
                built structures—against the entire Haitian country in the broadest possible sense.
                As we shall see and confirming anew how Haitian revolutionary literature takes as
                axiomatic a blend of enlightenment aesthetics and revolutionary politics, Dumesle’s
                capacious thinking about the Haitian country, as including not just people but wider
                environs replete with built and natural environments, aligns with evolving meanings
                of the word <hi rend="italic">country</hi> developing in Britain. Anne Janowitz’s
                <hi rend="italic">England’s Ruins: Poetic Purpose and the National Landscape </hi>charts
                this precise historical development. For Britain, 
                
            <quote>The physical situation of cultural ruins within the countryside linked the rhetoric
                of ruin to that of land. This turned out to be fortunate in the creation of British
                nationalism: as assimilated into the later eighteenth-century aesthetic of the
                picturesque, ruins were admired as blending into the countryside, while the sense of
                “country” as rural terrain and “country” as nation also began to melt one into the
                    other.<note place="foot" resp="author">Anne Janowitz, <hi rend="italic">England’s Ruins: Poetic Purpose and the National Landscape </hi>(West Sussex, UK and Hoboken, NJ: Blackwell,
                                1990), 3-4.</note></quote>
            
            To return now to the texts of the <hi rend="italic">Acte de l’Indépendance</hi> and
                Mercier’s <hi rend="italic">Neologisms</hi>, we can see how contingent meanings
                generated by the Francophone term’s usage helps to bring into focus a deep
                relationship between this verb and what we would today call matters of social and
                environmental justice, matters which link the politics of people and place. The use
                of the adjective-turned-verb in the Haitian Declaration of Independence conveys the
                idea of the region of Haiti becoming sorrowful as result of ongoing, still
                continuing colonial processes: “‘The name of the French makes sorrowful our land’
                [Le nom français lugubre encore nos contrées]”.<note
                        place="foot" resp="author">
                            Daut, 495.</note> The phrase
                “lugubre encore nos contrées” [yet makes sorrowful
                <hi rend="italic">our </hi>region], advances the nationalist
                sentiment conveyed by a political document meant to declare Haitian sovereignty over
                a specific population and location (my translation and emphasis). This region and
                country, these Haitian lands, encircling the people residing within it, continue to
                be made sorrowful by “Le nom français,” by trespasses executed there both now and in
                the past and in the name of France and French colonial rule. </p>
                
            <p>The phrase’s possessive pronoun “nos” [our] applies metonymically to a coextensive
                humanity and environment including Haitian people and Haitian ground. This human and
                nonhuman inclusive sweep is likewise suggested by the diction, syntax, and grammar
                adopted in the entry published the same year on the new verb form of the word in
                Mercier’s <hi rend="italic">Neologisms</hi>. The entry’s opening (“empreindre la
                tristesse. Son imagination sombre ne tend qu’à Lugubrer tout ce qui l’environne.”
                [to imprint with sadness. His dark imagination tends to make sorrowful everything
                around him.]) deploys as context a permutation of the French word <hi
                    rend="italic">environner</hi>, a term bearing place-based word histories from the
                    Middle French meaning “to arrange (people or things) in a circle, to travel
                round, circumnavigate (a place)” and the Old French meaning “to wrap around (<hi
                    rend="italic">c</hi>1200), to traverse, to wander about (<hi rend="italic"
                    >c</hi>1230), to surround, encircle (my translation).<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            “environ, v.” <hi
                                rend="italic">OED.</hi></note> While
                    the Anglophone term enivronment would later be derived
                in part from the French <hi rend="italic">environner </hi>, with environment going on to
                    signify the natural world and evoke concepts of nature often exclusive of
                    humanity and its built structures, the same cannot be said for the Francophone
                    future of this term.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            “environment, n.” <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</note> Generating meanings akin to those of the Anglophone term environs, today environner evokes a more wholesale and nonexclusive condition of being surrounded, encircled, enveloped—potentially including people or indeed anything and everything within a constitutive space.</p>  
                
                <p>These wider meanings and political implications are generated not
                    by way of what Paul de Man would call the “paradigmatic structure based on
                substitution, such as metaphor.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Paul de Man, “Semiology and Rhetoric,” <hi rend="italic">Diacritics</hi> 3, no. 3 (1973): 32.</note>
                Rather, language generates political meaning here in alignment with how de Man sees
                metonyms operating in Proust. Instead of relying primarily on the exchange economy
                of metaphor, here the constitutive relations of metonymy predominate. At play in
                this case is “a syntagmatic structure based on contingent association such as
                metonymy … [not] the substitutive totalization by metaphor which is said [by some
                whom de Man would hold suspect] to be more effective than the mere contiguity of
                metonymic association.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> de Man, “Semiology and Rhetoric,” 32,
                                31.</note> Fittingly in this case, meaning is produced
                by constitutive means in <hi >Mercier’s</hi> entry on <hi
                    rend="italic">luguber</hi>. The
                subject, for example, is capable of transforming “everything around him,” everything
                connected to him.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Mercier qtd. in Daut,
                    495.</note>
                At play in Mercier’s defining context is the logic of metonymy and moreover a metonymic “contingent
                habit of proximity.”<note place="foot" resp="author">de Man, “Semiology and Rhetoric,”
                            31.</note> The entry alludes to the way one’s mind
                imagines metaphors (in this case a metaphorical sorrow) differently by way of
                context-driven association. Sometimes, for example, a metaphor can signify all the
                more darkly due to one’s constitutive environs or political context and vice versa.
                The entry’s phrasing foregrounds the contingency of meaning and spotlights the role
                proximity plays in generating associated meanings. That is, the entry’s language
                evokes the way meanings of words such as sorrow or <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>
                can change next to different words, the way one’s sorrow can be transformed by
                another who closes in too close, seemingly encircling and touching with sorrow
                everyone and everything imaginable; “Lugubrer tout ce qui l’environne” [To make
                sorrowful all that surrounds him] (my
                translation). The verbal power and politics of metonymy’s transformative dynamics of proximity are borne out again and again in Mercier’s entry on lugubrer, not least in light of Mercier’s contextualized definition, where the capitalized term “Lugubrer” suggests this particular sort of sorrow-making can be imagined and read as imprinting upon and therefore reformulating affectively and conceptually the entirety of one’s surrounding nature and culture. By extension, here a mind touched and remade by lugubrer is able to see this sorrowful condition and its attendant motivating affective states as legible throughout all reaches of Haitian lived experience.</p>
                
            <p>A stirring scene from Dumesle’s travel narrative, <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi>,
                    captures the full affective arc of the aesthetic politics conveyed by the
                    adjective-turned-verb <hi rend="italic">lugubrer</hi>. Dumesle reads the then-ruinous northern port
                    town of Cap-Haïtien as ripe for revolutionary reversal. For Dumesle, new futures
                    can be scripted here precisely because these environs make legible important
                    correctives to Haiti’s otherwise mistold past. <note place="foot" resp="author"> See, for example, Claude-Pierre-Joseph Le Borgne de Boigne, <hi rend="italic">Nouveau système de colonisation pour Saint-Domingue. </hi>Paris: Dondy Dupré, 1817.</note> For example, the work of French naturalist Michel Etienne Descourtilz, <hi rend="italic">Histoire des désastres de Saint-Domingue</hi>, marks an early yet pivotal 1791 uprising of enslaved peoples living in Le Cap, as the northern port town was then commonly called by Francophone and Francophone-influenced speakers. As the work’s title suggests, the history of Haitian independence beginning to touch off in Cap-Haïtien ranks as the onset of a ruinous disaster.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Michel Étienne Descourtilz, <hi
                                rend="italic">Histoire des désastres de
                                Saint-Domingue</hi> (Paris: Chez Garnery, 1795), 183-84.</note> In this document, to band together as enslaved and relatively-free subjects of color fighting for freedom and fighting against French-colonial subjugation both number as acts of barbaric terror perpetrated against unfortunate French enslavers <hi rend="italic">qua</hi> victims. <note place="foot" resp="author"> Descourtilz,
                                    183-84.</note> Working against written histories such as these, the environs of Cap-Haïtien have a different story to tell. Running counter to hegemonic histories proven primarily by page, print, and pen—narratives originating from Le Cap’s natural and built environment reframe Dumesle’s historical imagination:
                
            <quote>Before-long the city of Cap-Haitian seemed to appear from behind a curtain to present
                before our eyes the panorama of its beautiful edifices and ruins that are spread
                over her; the mountains that encircle her from the direction of the setting sun and
                stretch their arid chain from north to south depict for us her extensive wall. The
                aspect of this city preserves the thoughts of great memories, her ruins reveal the
                events for which she was the stage.<note place="foot" resp="author">Dumesle, 73. All translations from Dumesle are by Cherie Maiden unless otherwise indicated.</note></quote>
                
           For Dumesle, the port town’s overriding affective agencies turn
                    upon a sorrowful yet beautiful aesthetic politics of ruination, seeing as the
                    ruins he surveys there once housed Henry I, King of Haiti, better known as Henri
                    Christophe, who succeeded in throwing off French colonial rule. In this
                    landscape, ruins bear a strain of beauty shared with other, assumedly unruined
                    built structures. “The aspect of this city” holds especial semiotic purchase,
                    “preserv[ing] the thoughts of great memories” of standing up to the French. Its
                    ruins are revelatory, tantamount to a national iconography bearing stories of
                    the Haitian Revolution and histories of its path to independence. Treating the
                    port city’s environs more akin to central characters or narrators than static
                    backdrop or mere setting, Dumesle’s travel narrative imagines an ecological,
                    environmental, nonhuman agency that borders on artistic agency and license. The
                    city “seemed to appear from behind a curtain … the mountains that encircle her
                    from the direction of the setting sun and stretch their arid chain from north to
                    south depict for us her extensive wall.” The city metaphorizes into stage actor.
                    The mountain metaphorizes into the one who depicts. The city is not simply a
                    passive storehouse of memory but also actively “reveal[s] the events for which
                    she was the stage.” Dumesle’s use of active, non-finite verbs affords room for
                    multiple histories and temporalities to appear in synchrony, alongside one
                    another, as the city-as-stage metaphor links the ruins of another time with
                    their stories from the past to Dumesle’s present where “Cap-Haitian seemed
                to appear from behind a curtain to present before our eyes the panorama of its
                beautiful edifices and ruins that are spread over her.” The city and its environs
                surround Dumesle and his fellow travelers with the bounty of a rich infrastructural
                historical archive capable at once of showcasing Haiti’s revolutionary past and
                authorizing decolonized futures not least because the site is capable of carrying
                into the present, and beyond, great memories of the Haitian past.</p>
                
            <p> The longstanding adjectival senses of <hi rend="italic">lugubre</hi> (meaning
                mournful or sorrowful), as well as the reformulated verb form used in the Haitian
                Declaration of Independence (signaling actions or activities rendering the subject
                or object in question sorrowful), accommodate multiple temporalities: past, present,
                future, ongoing processes of becoming. The temporal play afforded by these terms is
                important to consider in relation to the complex temporality of ruins. The kinds of
                time imagined in conjunction with ruins matter not least because temporal dimensions
                signified by ruins underpin “the relation of ruins to history, and of history to
                    ruins.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Sophie Thomas, “Assembling History: Fragments And Ruins.” <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review</hi> 14, no. 2 (2003): 178.</note>
                As Sophie Thomas observes, “[t]here are, clearly, a number of ways in which ruins,
                and fragmentary ruins, speak to, or of, the past. In all cases, it seems ambivalent
                effects are created by the way ruins float between the past and present (the same
                way fragments are suspended between the part and the idea of the whole) but belong
                fully to neither.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Thomas, 181.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>Further enlarging the scope of such temporal play, the ruin’s relationship to past
                and present fosters contingent ideas of futurity. Ann Laura Stoler reminds us how
                “[r]uins hold histories but are less than the sum of the sensibilities of people who
                live in them. Instead we might turn to ruins as epicenters of renewed claims, as
                history in a spirited voice, as sites that animate new possibilities, bids for
                entitlement, and unexpected political projects.”<note
                        place="foot">Ann Laura Stoler, “Imperial Debris: Reflections on Ruins and Ruination.” <hi
                                rend="italic">Cultural Anthropology </hi>23, no. 2 (2008): 197.</note>
                
                How the temporalities of ruins are read produces telling results, not unlike a
                Rorschach test: the temporal aesthetic judgements ruins arouse expose the historical
                politics of their readers. “It is possible, for example, to view the anachronism of
                the ruin as bearing a message from the past, rather than, as Michael Roth suggests
                in <hi rend="italic">Irresistible Decay</hi>, operating as ‘an active site of life
                in the present,’” and, I would add, it goes without saying that ruins could also
                operate as both at once, with ruins bespeaking past and present simultaneously.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Thomas, 181.</note> Then, as Susan Buck-Morss is right to
                suggest, ruins can refer “to the loosened building blocks (both semantic and
                material) out of which a new order can be constructed.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Susan Buck-Morss, <hi rend="italic" >The Dialectics of Seeing:
                                Walter Benjamin and the Arcades
                            Project</hi> Cambridge, MA and London: The MIT Press, 1989), 212.</note>
                All at once, ruins can conjure past and present and augur possible futures. So too
                ruins can activate non-finite and sometimes infinite senses like those at play in
                    <hi rend="italic">lugubre</hi> and lugubrer, and thus can
                    presage a spilling over into futurity in the active and ongoing sense that
                    Dumesle depicts in reference to meanings produced and held by ruins of
                    revolutionary Haiti.</p>
                
            <p> Immediately following the above account of the port town’s
                    mountains, buildings, ruins, Dumesle deploys another signature trope of
                    Romanticism by foregrounding the relationship between nature and
                    imagination:
            <quote>the imagination contemplates [the wider aspect of the city and its ruins] with
                surprise, and occupies itself showing them again detachedly as if it was charged
                with collecting them for history. While questioning the debris of these venerable
                monuments about the great attributes of our revolution, it seeks to discover the
                causes that prepared her and made her course so frightening. Informed by their
                testimonies that injustice and oppression were the motifs for all the disasters
                which have ravaged this land, it remains struck with astonishment and fear by the
                idea of the reign of the usurper who dictated, not so long ago, his banishment
                    decrees.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Dumesle, 73.</note></quote>
                
            Whereas, in lines just previous to these, elements of the built and natural world
                take the stage to assume agential powers of author and artist, the lines quoted here
                foreground the power of an imagination in thrall to the aesthetic force and historic
                significance of revolutionary ruins. The aesthetic force of this landscape first
                sends Dumesle’s imagination reeling—cooling then for a moment in the face of
                resolute purpose: the charge of (re)collecting the scene’s actors, its mountains,
                its monuments, for history. The imagination joins these Haitian environs as central
                players, with Dumesle’s ruins and debris staged here as the imagination’s direct
                interlocuters, ripe as they are for “questioning” and bearing as they do answers
                “about the great attributes of our revolution.” The records these environs disclose
                to the imagination are “testimonies” of “injustice and oppression” that would pave
                the way for “all [of] the disasters which … ravaged this land.” At this point
                Dumesle’s imagination is once again thrown, taken aback, “struck with astonishment
                and fear” not simply by encountering in these ruins the stories of human injustice,
                “the reign of the usurper who dictated,” but also the dialectally enfolding unjust
                desolation of “this land,” as the latter arrives hand-in-hand with human “injustices
                and oppression.” Revealingly, the imagination resides at the center of Dumesle’s
                sentence, with damaged, “ravaged” land on the one side and a damaging, “dictat[ing]”
                humanity on the other. Dumesle’s syntax thematizes a core concept: it grammatically
                yokes together in the space of one sentence the structural link between social
                injustice and environmental injustice. </p>
                
            <p> Just as Dumesle’s narrative foregrounds the structural contingencies of
                environmental and social justice, it also places contingent affective-aesthetic
                forces at the heart of its Romantic revolutionary history. As Dumesle interacts with
                the city, the landscape aesthetics at play in the previous paragraphs that kept the
                Haitian country at arm’s length now give way to an aesthetic of moving engagement—of
                conversant, affective exchange. Now moving within the city, his soul is moved all
                the more, rendered increasingly sensitive to its historical and temporal
                messaging:
                
            <quote>Upon arriving in this city, at one time so flourishing, I feel this movement of the
                soul receptive to receiving the life-saving lessons given by the imposing aspect
                from these precious ruins; I roam its path immediately the day after my arrival, and
                the reflections that each object gives rise in me transport me to the different
                epochs whose traces I rediscovered in all that was surrounding me. I remembered
                [Vincent] Ogé and [Jean-Baptiste] Chavanne, and the time when they appeared on the
                political scene to demand the rights that we hold by nature; the dawning of our
                regeneration preoccupied me deeply.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Dumesle, 73-4.</note></quote>
                
            Not only does he see or read “these precious ruins,” but by roaming “its path” he
                becomes all the more “receptive to receiving the life-saving lessons” that this
                place can impart to him. That is, his immersive multisensory engagement with the
                city—not just gazing at it from a distance but standing upon it, feeling it beneath
                him, being in it and with it—primes him to feel more deeply connected to it; it is
                as if his surrounds or environs become more akin to communicative, speaking subjects
                than mute or reified objects, more akin to historical agents than mere historical
                background for Dumesle as he recounts engaging with the site via multiple sensory
                registers. The ruins conjure experiential histories and lived memories of famed
                Haitian revolutionaries (Vincent Ogé and Jean-Baptiste Chavanne), positioning them
                as key representatives from just one of the “different epochs whose traces [he]
                rediscovered in all that was surrounding [him].” The narrative has Dumesle enswathed
                in Haitian history at the precise moment that he stands within the city’s environs
                and its physical embrace. Feeling there and being there, he is primed to
                conceptualize Haiti’s temporal and historical frameworks in distinctive ways. These
                ruins now speak of lessons that will save lives in futurity as much as they locate
                the lives of Haitian revolutionaries as seeding Haitian “regeneration,” and so
                Dumesle reads Haiti’s revolution and hard-won independence from France as spurring a
                renewed Haiti, cut from French colonial rule but still tethered to longer-standing
                histories lived on and through Haitian grounds. The paragraph fittingly ends with
                contingent figurations of a thoroughly nationalized earth and naturalized political
                imaginary. The aesthetic of these ruins and these Haitian grounds all give rise to
                historical reflections rife with political affect, to deeply preoccupying feelings
                about Haiti as “political scene” and as political stage wherein anticolonial humans
                actors and agents fought to “demand the rights [they] hold by nature.”</p>
                
            <p>Accounting for the multiple meanings generated by Dumesle’s narrative affords an
                important opportunity to revisit revolutionary Romanticism’s figurations of
                prosopopoeitic nature (i.e., representations of a natural environment that speaks)
                and how the trope of a voice-bearing nature often couples with naturalized political
                histories and teleologies. In the figurative sense, to state that revolutionaries
                “appeared on the political scene to demand the rights [they] hold by nature” means
                to suggest that the likes of Ogé and Chavanne fought to recover an inborn political
                sovereignty they already and necessarily possessed. Read in this way any potential
                radicality is all but evacuated as each revolutionary here simply asks with force
                for rights inherently bestowed by way of a citizen-based, nation-granted version of
                sovereignty that would more honestly go by the name of <hi rend="italic">national
                    law</hi> but is naturalized here instead as <hi rend="italic">natural
                law</hi>—granted by the undeniable fact of their existence in Haiti, a place always already
                understood or imagined as “political scene.”</p>
                
            <p>Then when this phrase is read in the literal sense, Dumesle in essence becomes an
                early advocate of environmental justice, an early arbiter of environmental law. In
                this case historical figures such as the revolutionaries Ogé and Chavanne fighting
                on Haitian grounds can be political only after and through nature. These Haitian
                environs and all attendant human rights or political sovereignties can only ever be
                granted or held first by the way of nature, through nature, with nature, never
                without nature. Human beings in this case aren’t automatically or intrinsically
                instilled with political rights at all nor granted any sort of inherent sovereignty.
                Rather nature itself is the foundation. Nature makes politics possible just as Bruno
                Latour will tell us many years later.<note place="foot" resp="author">See Bruno Latour, <hi
                                rend="italic" >Politics of Nature</hi>, Trans. Catherine Porter. Harvard UP,
                                2004.</note> Read literally and not figuratively, here
                nature makes possible any and all human politics, rights, nations, revolutions. Only
                because of the sheer existence not of humanity but of the natural world can Haitian
                rights be possible—they, and by extension anyone and all of us, can only ever become
                able to “demand” or “hold” rights because the natural world makes us and them
                possible, makes possible most anything we think, feel, encounter, or hold to be
                true. The tensions produced between these two readings allow Dumesle’s text to
                simultaneously endorse a transcendental, Enlightenment humanist basis for Haiti’s
                nation-based political sovereignty while also making the case not for transcendental
                nature in the spirit of certain Romantic texts but a metaphysics of rights-based
                politics wherein only the existence of nature could ever begin to serve as the basis
                of politics and any imagined or constructed sovereign rights. This is not simply the
                divine and righteous spirit of nature running throughout all things fueling the just
                revolution, but the physical stuff of nature grounding the revolution, the stuff of
                nature first setting any constructed political scene.</p>
                
            <p>Dumesle’s revolutionary history rehearses and reinvents signature features of
                Romantic aesthetic politics. <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi> tropes upon
                representations of sublime nature and sublime historical temporalities long home to
                teleological narratives of Romantic revolution. Dumesle writes of encounters with an
                otherwise inscrutable nature that transports the narrator to new revelatory heights
                by at last speaking to him only after foregrounding a sublimely rapid Haitian
                national trajectory far outpacing European models of “the progress of civilization”: 
                
            <quote>My reflections embraced the space which separated the origin of our current
                revolution, an immense age, if it is measured according to the progress of
                civilization. What period haven’t the Haitian people traveled since the era of
                independence! And, without having started from a long way, how many centuries
                haven’t the old nations needed, now in existence, to arrive at the point that they
                have reached? All the circumstances which marked the course of this interval
                presented themselves confusedly in my memory; I sought to unravel this chaos, and
                persuaded that nothing is silent in nature for those who know how to consult her, I
                interrogated the places and sights. Then the inspiration from the memories, the
                eloquence of the ruins, and this secret voice that speaks to the soul, spoke to my
                mind, and thus explained to me the events that the imposing remains confirmed.<note place="foot" resp="author">Dumesle, 74.</note></quote>
                
            To unravel the chaos of Haitian national history is to grasp the sublime
                accomplishments not just of revolution and independence but also to acknowledge
                these national achievements as a sublime compression of historical time. While
                accounts of sublime nature routinely recount stories of dizzied spectators whose
                minds cannot approach nature’s profundity and complexity, here Dumesle flips the
                script and then some. To begin to come to grips at all with “[a]ll the circumstances
                which have marked the course of this [national, historical, teleological] interval …
                to unravel this chaos” the narrator must look to sublime Haitian nature replete with
                its speaking ruins. Thinking with nature, listening to nature, engaging with nature
                are all prerequisites to making any sense of Haiti’s national memories, histories,
                and temporalities. Only after accepting the premise that “nothing is silent in
                nature” can the “eloquence of ruins” carry out its sublime work in “speak[ing] to
                the soul … [and] mind” in its “secret voice” to thereby explain “the events that the
                imposing remains confirmed.” In this case, prosopopoeia, as de Man is right to
                observe, once again proves itself to be “the trope of autobiography, by which one’s
                name … is made as intelligible and memorable as a face,” and what is given voice—and
                in so doing granted “face” in this case—is in fact nothing short of the natural
                    world.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            de Man, “Autobiography as De-Facement,”
                                80-81.</note></p>
                
            <p>It is worth emphasizing here that across a short sequence of paragraphs Dumesle
                suggestively advances and intertwines the core arguments of two influential
                scholarly studies: Trouillot’s
                <hi rend="italic">Silencing the Past</hi> and Rob Nixon’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Slow Violence</hi>. Trouillot’s twentieth-century contention that
                Haiti’s ruins and others “provide numerous vantage points from which to examine the
                means and process of historical production” echoes implicit arguments in Dumesle
                whenever his travel narrative stages Haitian monuments and debris as capable both of
                being read and bearing testimony.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                           Trouillot, 44.</note>Daut
                likewise finds parallels between Dumesle’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi> and
                Trouillot’s <hi rend="italic">Silencing the Past</hi>, suggesting that “Dumesle was
                one of the first Haitian writers to try not only to make [Haiti’s] walls speak, but
                to help them tell their own story.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Daut, 499.</note> “In looking
                to the ‘imposing debris’ of Haiti’s revolution to allow it to tell the story of
                Haitian independence,” Daut sees “Dumesle anticipat[ing] Michel-Rolph Trouillot’s
                groundbreaking exploration of the palace at Sans Souci as archive in <hi
                    rend="italic">Silencing the Past</hi>. Trouillot had noted that the historical
                resources for telling the history of Haiti could be found equally in the ‘buildings,
                dead bodies, censuses, [and] monuments,’ as they could be located in ‘diaries [and]
                political boundaries.’”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Daut, 499.</note> Dumesle’s
                narrative already “claimed that stonework, bodies, and national monuments could
                actually speak through him, as if these ‘ruins’ were in fact the primary and most
                important informants and interlocutors of the Haitian past. In arguing that the
                ruins spoke to him … Dumesle puts forward a theory of history based in large part on
                lived memory.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Daut, 499.</note> Beyond this,
                Trouillot follows Dumesle in espousing not just the historical import of lived
                memories actualized through engaging ruins, cities, and larger landscapes that
                figurately speak by way of prosopopoeia. Both Dumesle and Trouillot also model a
                theory of multisensorial history from which lived memories arise. For Trouillot,
                Haiti’s infrastructural and environmental archive “span[s] a material continuum”
                (45). Multisensorial affective histories become legible through various sensory
                modes not reducible to any one avenue of sense perception, be it touch, taste,
                smell, sound, or sight. Instead and in harmony with Dumesle, Trouillot’s Haitian
                ruins are “[c]oncrete reminders that the uneven power of historical production is
                expressed [not simply through immaterial or ideational dimensions of concepts,
                ideas, words, or narratives but] also through the power to touch, to see, and to
                    feel.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Trouillot, 44-5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In addition to anticipating Trouillot’s project in <hi rend="italic">Silencing the
                    Past</hi> of reading of Haitian ruins to recover unacknowledged Haitian pasts,
                    <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi> presages Nixon’s twenty-first century project in
                <hi rend="italic">Slow Violence and the Environmentalism of the Poor. </hi>There,
                Nixon expands running definitions of violence to accommodate the long term and often
                intergenerational damage done to places and peoples through unchecked and often
                unacknowledged abuses of power. Nixon defines “slow violence” as a “violence that
                occurs gradually and out of sight, a violence of delayed destruction that is
                dispersed across time and space, an attritional violence that is not typically
                viewed as violence at all.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Nixon, 2.</note> Thinking with
                nonnormative temporalities proves crucial to this project. “Violence,” he writes,
                “is customarily conceived as an event or action that is immediate in time, explosive
                and spectacular in space, and as erupting into instant visibility. We need … to
                engage a different kind of violence, a violence that is neither spectacular nor
                instantaneous, but rather incremental and accretive, its calamitous repercussions
                playing out across a range of temporal scales.”<note
                        place="foot" resp="author"> Nixon, 2.</note> This change in
                temporal imagination requires new narrative engagements, new narrative modes: “We
                also need to engage the representational, narrative, and strategic challenges posed
                by the relative invisibility of slow violence.”<note
                        place="foot" resp="author">
                            Nixon, 2.</note> Nixon’s call
                to action—his grounding basis for any hope for change or optimism—hinges on framing,
                writing, and thinking—on what he refers to as “rhetorical inventiveness.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Nixon, 6.</note> He places a
                premium on “giv[ing] figurative shape to formless threats,” dismantling silences,
                producing counter histories, exposing misrepresented socioenvironmental
                    catastrophes.<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Nixon, 10, 6, 31.</note>
            </p>
                
            <p>When Dumesle surveys the more recent ruins of the Kingdom of Haiti on display at Cap-Haïtien, reading the earth and infrastructure there to
                access the country’s decades-old revolutionary past, he grapples not only with the
                more explosive events leading to and proceeding from Haitian independence, but
                imagines also an even longer arc of Haiti’s difficult history. As if to allude to
                and to expand the affective force and political resonances of the term <hi
                    >lugubrer</hi> from the Haitian Declaration of Independence, the
                ruins Dumesle consults bear “testimonies that injustice and oppression were the
                motifs for all the disasters which have ravaged this land,” not just those more
                spectacular forms of desolation wrought by “the usurper who dictated, not so long
                    ago.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Dumesle, 73.</note> Already
                working in the spirit of Nixon’s call for inventive narrative models able to mount
                strategic challenges to narrow, normative accounts of epiphanic violence, Dumesle’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi> contains sweeping retrospectives and imagines
                broad futures to give “figurative form to [otherwise] formless threats.” Just as
                Dumesle draws upon lived memory as well as environmental and infrastructural forms
                of historical evidence to “discover the causes that prepared [Haiti] and made her
                course so frightening,” he also leverages such historical recovery work to script
                new contours for what follows as the “dawning of [Haiti’s] regeneration.” Indeed,
                elsewhere in <hi rend="italic">Voyage </hi>dead soldiers buried
                in the Haitian earth end up righting the historical record to forge new futures:
                “Dumesle continues by suggesting that calling forth these names [of buried Haitian
                soldiers] will make them ‘live until the most remote of ages,’ and thus that these
                names alone “will stand as depositions against the fury of the tyrants who have
                desolated this land.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Daut, 502.</note></p>
                
            <p>At risk of romanticizing Dumesle’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage</hi> and its place in
                understanding Haiti’s revolutionary past, Dumesle’s text must not ring more
                universal than it is. Indeed it foregrounds the lived memories and felt histories of
                a politically-motivated, vengeful sorrow borne out by giving voice to Haiti’s
                twinned desolations of place and people during a time of revolution. These
                contingent desolations arrive in light of both French colonial rule and
                revolutionary war, and these contingent desolations continue to endure long after.
                But Dumesle’s text does not and cannot recover a complete history of the Haitian
                revolutionary past. After all, the travel narrative does wear on its sleeve its
                relation to the genre of the epic, making overtly clear its nationalist leanings. As
                Trouillot details, “some former [enslaved people] had refused to submit [not only]
                to the French … some (often the same) contested the new revolutionary hierarchy.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Trouillot, 43.</note> They
                neither wanted to bend to French rule nor that of any others, with many having been
                killed in the process. The important matter to bear in mind is that “[n]ationalist
                narratives … inevitably tell a heroic tale of a benevolent nation-state triumphing
                despite hardship.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Deborah Cowen, “Following the Infrastructures of Empire: Notes on Cities, Settler Colonialism, and Method.” <hi
                                rend="italic" >Urban
                            Geography</hi> 41, no. 4 (2020): 471.</note>
                Deborah Cowen’s work on infrastructures of empire charts how nationalist accounts
                often “enshrine the successes of elites as a common national heritage, even as those
                successes are stories of genocide. These narratives inevitably sideline the violence
                that all this was contingent upon—the dispossession, dehumanization, and
                exploitation. This style of storytelling is high stakes.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                            Cowen, 471-72.</note> So while
                Dumesle’s travel narrative, like the Haitian <hi rend="italic">Acte de
                    l’Indépendance</hi>, gives voice to conjoined sorrows of a Haitian country
                broadly conceived to account for distinct damages done to both place and people,
                that is not to say that they account for all such damage, that is not to say that
                they avoid scripting other desolations, violences, or silences in the process.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="citation">
            <head>Works Cited </head>
           
            <bibl><hi rend="italic">Acte de l’Indépendance, 1804</hi>. “Digithèque de Matériaux
                Juridique et Politique.” Edited by Jean-Pierre Maury, 2004–2014. <ref
                    target="https://mjp.univ-perp.fr/constit/ht1804.htm"
                    >https://mjp.univ-perp.fr/constit/ht1804.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Buck-Morss, Susan. <hi rend="italic">The Dialectics of Seeing: Walter Benjamin and
                    the Arcades Project.</hi> Cambridge, MA and London: The Massachusetts Institute
                of Technology Press, 1989.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cowen, Deborah. “Following the Infrastructures of Empire: Notes on Cities, Settler
                Colonialism, and Method.” <hi rend="italic">Urban Geography</hi> 41, no. 4 (2020):
                469-486. </bibl>
            <bibl>D’Alaux, Gustave. “La Littérature Jaune,” <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux
                    Mondes</hi> Paris: Bureau de la Revue Deux Mondes, 1852.</bibl>
            <bibl>Daut, Marlene L. “‘Nothing in Nature is Mute’: Reading Revolutionary Romanticism in
                L’Haïtiade and Hérard Dumesle’s Voyage dans le nord d'Hayti (1824).” <hi
                    rend="italic">New Literary History</hi> 49, no. 4 (2018): 493-520. </bibl>
            <bibl>de Man, Paul. “Autobiography as De-Facement.” In <hi rend="italic">The Rhetoric of
                    Romanticism</hi>, 67-81. New York: Columbia University Press, 1984.</bibl>
            <bibl> ———. “Semiology and Rhetoric.” <hi rend="italic">Diacritics</hi> 3, no. 3 (1973):
                27-33.</bibl>
            <bibl>Descourtilz, Michel Étienne. <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Désastres de
                    Saint-Domingue</hi>. Paris: Chez Garnery, 1795.</bibl>
            <bibl>Dolcé, Jacquelin, Gérard Dorval, and Jean Miotel Casthely. <hi rend="italic">Le
                    Romantisme en Haïti: La Vie Intellectuelle, 1804–1915.</hi> Port-au Prince,
                Haiti: Éditions Fardin, 1983.</bibl>
            <bibl>Dumesle, Charles Hérard. <hi rend="italic">Voyage dans le nord d’Hayti.</hi> Cayes,
                Haiti: Government Imprint, 1824. </bibl>
            <bibl>“environ, v.” <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. Oxford University Press, December
                2020. Web. 10 December 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl>“environment, n.” <hi rend="italic">OED Online</hi>. Oxford University Press,
                December 2020. Web. 11 December 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl>Garrard, Greg. <hi rend="italic">Ecocriticism</hi>. London and New York: Routledge,
                2011.</bibl>
            <bibl>Janowitz, Anne.
                <hi rend="italic">England’s Ruins: Poetic Purpose and the National Landscape. </hi>West
                Sussex, UK and Hoboken, NJ: Blackwell, 1990.</bibl>
            <bibl>James-Wilson, Symon. “Roads, Routes, And Roots: The (Im)Possible Spatial Mnemonics of
                Black Infrastructure.” <hi rend="italic">Society and Space</hi>, 2018. <ref
                    target="https://www.societyandspace.org/articles/roads-routes-and-roots-the-im-possible-spatial-mnemonics-of-black-infrastructure">Society and Space</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Latour, Bruno. <hi rend="italic">Politics of Nature</hi>. Translated by Catherine
                Porter. Cambridge, MA. and London: Harvard University Press, 2004.</bibl>
           <bibl>Le Borgne de Boigne, Claude-Pierre-Joseph, <hi
                    rend="italic" >Nouveau Système de Solonisation pour
                    Saint-Domingue</hi>. Paris: Dondy Dupré, 1817.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mercier, Louis-Sébastien. <hi rend="italic">Néologie: ou Vocabulaire de Mots
                    Nouveaux, à Renouveler, ou Pris dans des Acceptions Nouvelles.</hi> Paris:
                Moussard, 1801.</bibl>
            <bibl>Nixon, Rob. <hi rend="italic">Slow Violence and the Environmentalism of the
                    Poor.</hi> Cambridge, MA. and London: Harvard University Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl>Stoler, Ann Laura. “Imperial Debris: Reflections on Ruins and Ruination.”
                <hi rend="italic">Cultural Anthropology </hi>23, no. 2 (2008):
                191–219. </bibl>
            <bibl>Thomas, Sophie. “Assembling History: Fragments And Ruins.” <hi rend="italic">European
                    Romantic Review</hi> 14, no. 2 (2003): 177-186.</bibl>
            <bibl>Trouillot, Michel-Rolph. <hi rend="italic">Silencing the Past: Power and the
                    Production of History.</hi> Boston: Beacon, 1995.</bibl>
            <bibl>Vastey, Pompée-Valentin de, <hi rend="italic">Le Cri de la Conscience.</hi>
                Cap-Henry, Haiti: P. Roux, 1815.</bibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
