<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            
            <titleStmt>
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a">Contingency and Method </title>
                
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name>Nathan TeBokkel</name>
                </author>
                
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Praxis Editor</resp>
                    <name>Brian McGrath</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>2024-07-9</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">praxis.2024.contingent.tebokkel</idno> 
                <idno type="resource">contingent</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main">Romantic Contingency
                        </title>
                        <author role="secondary">
                            <persName>
                                <forename>Nathan</forename>
                                <surname>TeBokkel</surname>
                            </persName>
                        </author>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="praxis/contingent/praxis.2024.contingent.tebokkel"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/wellbeing/praxis.2024.wellbeing.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m">Romantic Contingency</title>
                        <title level="s">Praxis</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="2024-07-09">July 9, 2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
            
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:genre.3E on
                        20014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="dcType">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for document type at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E" xml:id="d">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for discplines at http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Ccollex:discipline.3E on 2014-02-27</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                <date>07.09.2024</date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p>This essay explores the quintessential romantic figure of the skylark and disambiguates the overdetermined concept of contingency to reimagine a paradigmatic literary-humanist thought-style and to articulate new lines of inquiry about romantic poetics, romanticist theory and criticism, and academic attitudes about disciplinarity and methodology. Gathering writers from Percy Shelley and Robert Bloomfield to Margaret Masterman and W. V. O. Quine, this essay explicates the systrophic and elliptical figures of idea and matter, fact and fiction, and history and nature at the heart of this paradigmatic thought-style, and argues for these figures’ critical, historical, and contingent (in all its polysemy) repurposing toward an intellectual commons rather than enclosed fields. 
                </p>
                </div>
            
            <div type="essay">
                <head>Contingency and Method</head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>Nathan TeBokkel</docAuthor>
                    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
                </byline>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Working Together</head>
                    <p>Between sentences of this essay, I got my hands
                        greasy fixing the Harvest-Aid and gummy with propolis tending honeybees. I
                        got sunburnt in the strawberry fields and stung while catching swarms; I
                        watched the sunrise over apple saplings and startled killdeer between sandy
                        rows of cantaloupes. I lived all this as a farmer and as a scholar of
                        Romantic literature—in short, as someone keenly aware of how my thoughts and
                        feelings, down to my barest sensations, were mediated by the old poetics of
                        “farming romance,” “written agriculture,” or “book husbandry,” and by the poetics they
                        conditioned, poetics of lyric self-expression, of sensuous experience, of
                        natural and everyday beauty, and so on.<note
                                place="foot" resp="author"> These
                                    three quoted phrases come from, respectively, Anonymous, <hi
                                        rend="italic">A Political Enquiry into the Consequences of
                                        Enclosing Waste Lands, and the Causes of the Present High
                                        Price of Butchers Meat</hi> (Holborn: Davis, 1785), 4;
                                    William Marshall, <hi rend="italic">The Review and Abstract of
                                        the County Reports to the Board of Agriculture</hi>. 5 vols.
                                    (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, and Brown, 1808–17), 1:xx;
                                    Arthur Young, <hi rend="italic">The Farmer’s Letters to the
                                        People of England</hi> (London: Nicoll, 1767),
                                146.</note>My intuition that there’s something dispositionally and historically Romantic
                        about how we farm and how we think and feel about farming prompted my moving
                        to the study of Romantic literature from a BSc in genetics, where I learned
                        the importance of long histories and selection pressures, and from an MA in
                        modernist poetry, where I learned the value of every line, word, letter, and
                        figure.</p>
                    
                    <p> So what are the relationships between farming and
                        Romanticism, then and now? And what’s the best way to talk about them? Like
                        plenty of contemporary research, mine’s wrestling with questions of
                        terminology and methodology has also taken to the mat questions about
                        Romanticism as a field and the literary humanities as a discipline. The
                        causes of this self-reckoning are overdetermined, though, and include the
                        humanities’ perennial introspection about its disciplinary status, economic
                        inequality coupled with the neoliberalization of the university and its
                        STEM-oriented funding, ecological catastrophe, and systemic injustice. My
                        questioning, as a contingent scholar, is contingent on these questionings; I
                        find myself dizzyingly caught up in what historian Andreas Malm calls “an
                        endless cycle of turns—cultural, linguistic, affective, cognitive,
                        performative, material, posthuman, nonhuman.”<note place="foot">
                                    Andreas Malm, <hi rend="italic">The Progress of This Storm:
                                        Nature and Society in a Warming World</hi> (New York: Verso,
                                    2020), 112.</note> Yet regardless of the “turn,” most
                        theories of late ostensibly afford engagements with “interdisciplinarity”
                        and, if more subtly, with “foundationalism.” My essay examines “contingency”
                        as the avatar of both engagements and of our disciplinary self-inquisition
                        in these modes and at these times.</p>
                    
                    <p> What we often mean by “contingency” is something
                        like “systemically dependent,” as in “this event was contingent on those
                        events,” something like “precarious,” as in “contingent faculty,” something
                        like “possible,” as in “contingency plan,” or some combination thereof:
                        fortuitous chance, a butterfly effect, an accident rendered into an act.
                        This meaning of contingency relies on rupture or change rather than
                        continuity, succession rather than sequel, difference rather than
                        similarity. It lends itself well to “theory” in the sense of hypostatizing,
                        systematizing, taxonomizing, and, however each turn may try to duck it,
                        foundationalizing. When we uprooted foundationalism in the
                        1960s, its rhizomes lodged in our collective soil. Every “turn” is a shoot
                        of theory sprouting from a fragmented foundationalism. Anahid
                        Nersessian puts her finger on this when she identifies the “materialisms <hi
                            rend="italic">manqué</hi>—monism, mechanism, physicalism, vitalism,
                        Spinozism, Lucretianism—that have for some time now been presenting
                        themselves as antidotes to the harms wrought” by the polysemy of
                            poststructuralism.<note place="foot"> Anahid
                                    Nersessian, “Literary Agnotology,” <hi rend="italic">English
                                        Literary History</hi>, 84, no. 2 (2017),
                            350–51.</note> Likewise helping us specify Malm’s observation
                        above, Fredric Jameson traces another foundationalism in how literary
                        theorists’ “unconscious” is paradoxically “an
                        <hi rend="italic">enlargement </hi>of consciousness, a
                        widening of the very concept of intention so as to catch these aberrant
                        phenomena also in its net.”<note place="foot"> Fredric Jameson,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Postmodernism, or, the Cultural Logic of
                                        Late Capitalism</hi> (Durham: Duke UP, 1991),
                                214.</note> In response to the aforementioned
                        overdetermined crises and the position of the humanities within them, either seems to seek a new fundament or firmament, a new paradigm, whether
                        it be the material, the unconscious, language, form, objects, ecology, or
                        history, on which everything is contingent, or it gestures toward expertise
                        in other disciplines that may offer some such purchase, whether physics,
                        mathematics, or philosophy. That is, we go in for some kind of
                        foundationalism or interdisciplinarity.</p>
                    
                    <p> Whether these are the right things to do is beside
                        the question of whether these are the only things we can do. There’s at
                        least one other meaning of “contingency,” and it comes from its etymology
                            (<hi rend="italic">con</hi>-, together; <hi rend="italic">-tangěre</hi>,
                        touch): in contact, side by side, touching together. These meanings of
                        “contingency” are themselves contingent in this side-by-side sense, and we
                        can work them together to create something fruitful. I follow Nersessian
                        again, in “Romanticism as Method” (2016), where she writes that
                        “etymologically speaking, method (<hi rend="italic">meta</hi>-, after,
                        beyond, alongside; <hi rend="italic">hodos</hi>-, way) can mean either a
                        travelling-past or else a travelling-alongside.” <note place="foot">
                                    Anahid Nersessian, “Romanticism as Method,” <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Teaching Romanticism and Literary Theory</hi>, ed. Brian
                                    McGrath, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles</hi>,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Pedagogy </hi>(December
                                    2016), 1.</note> There’s a deeper root for “meta”:
                        “with” or “between”; “compare Mycenaen Greek <hi rend="italic">me-ta</hi>,
                        ‘together with,’ which is perhaps the original sense in Greek.”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary Online</hi>, s.v.
                                    “meta-, <hi rend="italic">prefix</hi>,” accessed 4 Mar. 2020.
                                   </note>
                        This root supports Nersessian’s conclusion that methods require
                        “crowd-sourced scholarship” and “multiple forms of knowledge.”<note place="foot"> Nersessian, “Romanticism as Method,” 11.</note> With all this in mind, I offer a close
                        reading of the thinking <hi rend="italic">style</hi> that disguises
                        foundationalism in gestures to interdisciplinarity. I study and repurpose
                        some of its figures, such as <hi rend="italic">systrophe</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">ellipsis</hi>, and some of its motifs, such as cosmic
                        exile and semantic ascent. My essay proceeds by the neglected meaning of
                        contingency, in a side-by-side, nested-example, by-the-way manner, drawing
                        on and examining this thought-style in an array of thinkers with whom I work
                        together metaphors, methodologies, and materials.</p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Parable of the Skylark</head>
                    <p>Before I “ascend” into the heady space of
                        theory—though I would like to recode this movement as a back-and-forth
                        rather than an ascent-and-descent—I situate myself more firmly in the study
                        of Romantic poetry. The relation between understanding Romanticism as a
                        break with its past and understanding it as an “eventuality” of its past is
                            dialectic;<note place="foot" resp="author">Clifford Siskin and William Warner, “If
                                This Is Enlightenment Then What Is Romanticism?”
                                <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review </hi>22,
                                no. 3 (2011), 285.</note> contingency as precarious
                        path-dependence and contingency as codevelopment relate dialectically,
                        though perhaps we’ve given the former somewhat more priority. My argument is
                        that the contingencies within and of these two understandings, their
                        tensions and intersections then and now, are integral to Romanticism, with
                        consequences for what we study and how we do so. There are a lot of ways to
                        make an argument like this, but in “the spirit of the
                        age-of-the-spirit-of-the-age,” I’ve chosen to use the skylark as the “figure
                        of these figures,” to employ some favourite formulae of Romanticists since
                        Paul de Man.<note place="foot" resp="author"> James Chandler,
                                    <hi rend="italic">England in 1819: The Politics of Literary Culture and the Case of Romantic Historicism </hi>(Chicago
                                    UP, 1998), 490.</note> The poems I read (of many
                        options I’ve chosen five) could be paraphrased as being “about” a skylark;
                        they hang together on the rack of this symbol, and how they do so
                        allegorizes Romanticism’s “contingency.” I structure my essay’s movement
                        from poem to poem, then from poetry to theory, then from poetry-and-theory
                        back to my scholarly situation, on the movement of these poetic
                        skylarks.</p>
                    
                    <p>The most famous of these five skylarks is surely
                        Percy Bysshe Shelley’s. Written as an “other poem” in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound </hi>(1820)
                        volume, Shelley’s “To a Skylark” showcases the poet’s formal virtuosity and
                        revolutionary idealism. Opening with praise not for the skylark but for this
                            “blithe spirit! / Bird thou
                        never wert,” the poem figures the skylark not as a bird but as a symbol of
                        Romantic genius, soaring through a systrophe of nested similes,
                        characteristic Romantic images, that reify its power and beauty—it’s like a
                        cloud of fire, an unbodied joy, a star of heaven, an arrow of a silver
                        sphere, the moon raining out its beams, a rain of melody, a poet hidden, a
                        high-born maiden, a glow-worm golden, and a rose embowered—until “heaven is
                        overflowed” with music, light, sympathy, colour, and scent “better than all
                        measures” and “better than all treasures.” Shelley’s skylark is on the one
                        hand a symbol of Romantic symbols and a symbol of Romanticism. It is pure
                        figure, high figure, “scorner of the ground” in his proleptically gestalt
                        terms. But on the other hand, the poet concludes by asking, “Teach us,
                        sprite or bird, / What sweet thoughts are thine” and “What objects are the
                        fountains / Of thy happy strain”; “Teach me half the gladness / That thy
                        brain must know.”<note place="foot">Percy Bysshe
                                    Shelley, “To a Sky-Lark,” in <hi rend="italic">Prometheus
                                        Unbound: A Lyrical Drama in Four Acts, With Other Poems</hi>
                                    (London: Ollier, 1820), pp. 201–06.</note> This skylark
                        is a speculative pedagogy driven by a desire to know what material grounds
                        (objects, brain) facilitate figurative flights of fancy, or conversely a sum
                        of similes whose limit asymptotically approaches “reality.”</p>
                    
                    <p>William Wordsworth’s two “To a Sky-lark” poems
                        likewise figure the bird as an ideal transcending the mundane. The first
                        (1807) is a jaunty, exclamation-mark–ridden ballad in which the poet asks,
                        before Shelley and in a Shelleyan manner, the happy, strong-souled Lark to
                        go “up with me into the clouds” and to “guide me, till I find / That spot
                        which seems so to thy mind.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> William
                                    Wordsworth, “To a Sky-lark,” in <hi rend="italic">Poems, in Two
                                        Volumes</hi>, vol. 1 (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, and
                                    Orme, 1807), pp. 80–82.</note> The second (1827) is
                        three heroic sestets, its lines longer and slower than the first, as if
                        Wordsworth had read Shelley’s poem and sought to revise it and his original
                        (which also appears in the 1827 volume, indeed revised). Instead of singing
                        only of the skylark in the sky, this poem opens by asking if the “Ethereal
                        minstrel” “despise[s] the earth where cares abound” or fixes his heart on
                        “thy nest upon the dewy ground.” However, it moves in a trajectory similar
                        to the former’s, if more earnest and less exuberant, when it encourages the
                        skylark to soar “To the last point of vision, and beyond,” “to sing / All
                        independent of the leafy spring,” and to “Leave to the Nightingale her shady
                        wood,” that it might pour its “rapture more divine” upon the world. Unlike
                        the first poem’s unqualified praise of the skylark in metaphysical flight
                        from the physical, this second poem also refigures the physical <hi
                            rend="italic">as</hi> metaphysical, for the skylark is not merely
                        heavenly but “True to the kindred
                        points of Heaven and Home!”<note place="foot">William
                                    Wordsworth, “To a Sky-lark,” in <hi rend="italic">The Poetical
                                        Works of William Wordsworth</hi>, vol. 2. (London: Longman,
                                    Hurst, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green, 1827), p.
                            165.</note></p>
                    
                    <p> Before Wordsworth’s 1807 poem exclaims about “joy
                        divine,” before Shelley’s 1820 poem proclaims the “rapture so divine,” and
                        before Wordsworth’s 1827 poem revises this into a “rapture more divine,”
                        farmer’s-boy-cum-London-cobbler and Aeolian harp maker Robert Bloomfield
                        wrote of a skylark in his wildly popular
                        <hi rend="italic">Farmer’s Boy </hi>(1800). This
                        georgic, which sold more copies than Wordsworth’s and Shelley’s volumes
                        combined, precociously criticizes the skylark of these Romantics’ Romantics
                        in a passage worth quoting entirely:
                   
                        <lg type="stanza">
                    
                  <l>But what can unassisted vision do?</l>
                   <l>What, but recoil where most it would pursue;</l>
                   <l>His patient gaze but finish with a sigh, </l>
                   <l>When music waking speaks the <hi rend="italic"
                            >sky-lark</hi> nigh.</l>
                   <l>Just starting from the corn she cheerly sings,</l>
                  <l> And trusts with conscious pride her downy
                        wings;</l>
                  <l> Still louder breathes, and in the face of day</l>
                  <l> Mounts up, and calls on <hi rend="italic"
                            >Giles</hi> to mark her way.</l>
                   <l>Close to his eyes his hat he instant bends,</l>
                   <l>And forms a friendly telescope, that lends</l>
                   <l>Just aid enough to dull the glaring light,</l>
                   <l>And place the wand’ring bird before his sight;</l>
                   <l>Yet oft beneath a cloud she sweeps along,</l>
                   <l>Lost for awhile, yet pours her varied song:</l>
                   <l>He views the spot, and as the cloud moves by,</l>
                  <l>Again she stretches up the clear blue sky;</l>
                   <l>Her form, her motion, undistinguish’d quite,</l>
                  <l>Save when she wheels direct from shade to
                        light:</l>
                   <l>The flutt’ring songstress a mere speck became,</l>
                   <l>Like fancy’s floating bubbles in a dream;</l>
                   <l>He sees her yet, but yielding to repose,</l>
                  <l>Unwittingly his jaded eyelids close.</l>
                   <l>Delicious sleep! From sleep who could forbear,</l>
                   <l>With no more guilt than <hi rend="italic"
                            >Giles</hi>, and no more care?</l><note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    Robert Bloomfield, “Summer,” in <hi rend="italic">The Farmer’s
                                        Boy; A Rural Poem</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: Vernor and Hood),
                                    lines 85–108.</note>
                        </lg>
                    
                  
                   Bloomfield prefigures several of the images used by
                        Wordsworth and Shelley. The skylark “pours” its song out, soars so high it’s
                        almost lost to sight, and is compared to fancy and dream. But Giles,
                        watching it, falls asleep. There is no rapture and no divinity, just a
                        farmhand observing an animal. Accustomed as I was to the Romantic skylark, I
                        missed the implicit criticisms of the passage when I first encountered this
                        poem, but Giles’s visceral sleep, in contrast to their cerebral dreams,
                        turned me back again. This skylark passage opens with a question about the
                        limits of vision, then emphasizes how Giles sees the bird—his hat shades the
                        “glaring light” (resonantly opposed to the “glorious light” of the later
                        poets), the bird flies beneath the clouds (as opposed to above them), and it
                        wheels from shade to light. Crucially, the passage concludes with Giles’s
                        earthly cares overcoming him.</p>
                    
                    <p>John Clare, another agricultural-labourer-and-poet,
                        was almost certainly responding to his predecessors in his “Skylark” (1835).
                        In Clare’s poem, hurrying schoolboys startle the skylark out of “her
                        half-formed nest.” She “Winnows the air […] / Then hangs a dust spot in the
                        sunny skies” before dropping back to her nest unbeknownst to the boys, on
                        whom the poem meditates:
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>they unheeded passed—not dreaming then</l>
                    <l>That birds, which flew so high, would drop
                        again</l>
                    <l>To nests upon the ground, which any thing</l>
                    <l>May come at to destroy. Had they the wing</l>
                    <l>Like such a bird, themselves would be too
                        proud,</l>
                    <l>And build on nothing but a passing cloud!</l>
                    <l>As free from danger, as the heavens are free</l>
                    <l>From pain and toil, there would they build, and be. <note place="foot" resp="author"> John Clare, “The Skylark,” in <hi rend="italic">The Rural Muse</hi> (London: Whittaker, 1835),
                                    lines 13–20.</note></l>
                   
                            </lg> 
                    Opening with a terrified hare among corn “sprouting its spiry points of tender green,” the poem closes with the skylark lying “safely, with the leveret, in the corn.” As
                        Bloomfield’s skylark, also nesting in corn, offered momentary reprieve from
                        farm labour for Giles, so Clare’s is part of the agricultural
                        landscape—although it too is constituted by agriculture, “winnowing” the air
                        and hanging like threshing dust. But Clare extends Bloomfield’s critique.
                        Whereas Bloomfield describes how the skylark is visible to Giles, Clare
                        explains that the boys’ ignorance makes the skylark invisible to them, then
                        contrasts what he imagines to be their proud, ignorance-inspired fancies
                        “buil[t] on nothing but a passing cloud” and thereby free of danger, pain,
                        and toil, with the skylark’s vulnerable “nests upon the ground.” <note place="foot" resp="author"> Clare, “Skylark, lines 2, 10, 18, 25.</note> If Wordsworth and Shelley, and the kind of
                        Romanticism I’m using them as a synecdoche for, give us a metaphysical
                        skylark from which we’ve scarcely looked back, Bloomfield and Clare give us
                        a physical skylark to which we ought to look back. A “physical” skylark only
                        loosely, of course, for we are still reading poems, and a figured skylark
                        nevertheless. </p>
                    
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Language of Nature </head>
                    
                    <p> So far, it may seem like I’ve set up a standard
                        dichotomy within Romanticism, two canonical poets against two less canonical
                        poets, majoritarian center and minoritarian margin. This rupture in the
                        Romantic era along class lines (<hi rend="italic">ca</hi>. 1820) continues
                        in Romanticist scholarship along methodological and disciplinary lines (<hi
                            rend="italic">ca</hi>. 1835–2020). These ruptures and the language used
                        to describe them, including mine above, depend on and make it all too easy
                        to fall back into a singular and hypostatic understanding of “contingency.”
                        But in simply touching these poems together so they overlap and
                        intersect—Bloomfield’s earthly cares, Shelley’s systrophe, Wordsworth’s
                        transfiguration, Clare’s critique of imagination—I hope to unsettle and
                        reimagine this singular account, to show not only that are the ruptures
                        complicated but that their intertwinings and continuities are as vital as
                        their fractures and tensions to what Romanticism is. I want to contrast the
                        recognized-as-Romantic skylark with the as-yet-unrecognized but no less
                        Romantic skylark in order to revive Romantics’ latent understanding of and
                        participation in their late Georgian age as Enlightenment eventuality, as
                        improved improvement, ruptures and continuities and all.</p>
                    
                    <p>Before I get there, and as a step on the way to
                        “theory,” I examine Romanticism’s “semantic ascent.” This is W.V.O. Quine’s
                        phrase for shifting from a material to a formal mode of talking. One example
                        is the shift from “talk of miles to talk of ‘mile.’” Quine does not intend
                        it to be positivistic disinterpretation into a logical vocabulary that
                        attempts to, but cannot, neglect pragmatic considerations, but to be a way
                        to “carr[y] the discussion into a domain where both parties are better
                        agreed on the objects (<hi rend="italic">viz</hi>., words) and on the main
                        terms concerning them.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Willard Van Orman
                                    Quine, <hi rend="italic">Word and Object</hi>, New ed.
                                    (Cambridge: MIT P, 2013), 249–54.</note>The trouble
                        with semantic ascent is that it creates a high-low dichotomy, privileges the
                        high over the low, and then neglects the low. When I wrote that the skylark
                        of the two quintessentially Romantic poets was a “figure of a figure,” I
                        meant semantic ascent, or Celeste Langan’s “reduction and abstraction.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Celeste Langan, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Vagrancy: Wordsworth and the Simulation of
                                        Freedom</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995),
                                16–29.</note> This is one of the central figures of the
                        Romantic movement, and it’s how these poets figured language itself. Famously, Wordsworth writes in the Preface to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads </hi>(1802) that
                        poets must use “a plainer and more emphatic language,” “the very language of
                        men,” and “the real language of nature” by judiciously choosing “incidents
                        and situations from common life,” particularly from “low and rustic life”
                        and “rural occupations” that the poet must “make [. . .] interesting.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> William Wordsworth, “Preface to the <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi> (1802),” in <hi
                                        rend="italic">Wordsworth’s Poetry and Prose</hi>, ed.
                                    Nicholas Halmi (New York: Norton, 2014), 78–89.</note>
                        Shelley echoes these decrees in the preface to
                        <hi rend="italic">The Cenci </hi>(1819), where he
                        claims that “in order to move men to sympathy we must use the familiar
                        language of men,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Percy Bysshe
                                    Shelley, <hi rend="italic">The Cenci</hi>,
                                    in<hi rend="italic"> Shelley’s Poetry and Prose</hi>,
                                    2nd ed., ed. Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat (New York:
                                    Norton, 2002), p. 142.</note> and in the preface to
                        <hi rend="italic">Hellas </hi>(1821) he writes that
                        “[I] must trespass on the forgiveness of my readers for the display of
                        newspaper erudition to which I have been reduced.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Percy Bysshe Shelley, <hi rend="italic">Hellas</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s
                                        Poetry and Prose</hi>, 2nd ed., ed. Donald H. Reiman and
                                    Neil Fraistat (New York: Norton, 2002), p. 431.</note>
                        Their decrees are like their skylarks, singing and soaring about knowledge
                        rather than stooping to know—as has been much acknowledged about
                        Wordsworth’s so-called “real language,” starting with Coleridge’s
                        observation that nobody talked the way Wordsworth wrote. <note place="foot" resp="author"> Samuel Taylor Coleridge, <hi rend="italic">Biographia Literaria; or, Biographical Sketches of my Literary life and Opinions </hi>(New York: Leavitt, 1834), 194–206.</note> Shelley and
                        Wordsworth claim that poetry must be written in a pastoral “real language,”
                        though neither mean any particular dialect; rather, by “real” they mean what
                        they theorized, what their improvement milieu told them, language should
                            be.<note place="foot" resp="author"> I engage with these ideas extensively in Nathan TeBokkel, “Pastoral Authority,” <hi rend="italic">New Literary
                                        History</hi> 54, no. 4 (2024), 1637–63.</note></p>
                        
                    <p>Bloomfield’s vicious oscillation in <hi
                            rend="italic">The Farmer’s Boy</hi> between scenes of cliché pastoral
                        bliss and of inevitable anti-pastoral brutality offers a glimpse at what he
                        made of this idealization of “low and rustic life”—if through another sort
                        of idealization. For instance, we read of “tufted barley yellow with the
                        sun,” a “fav’rite morsel with the Rook and Crow,” who are so “Familiariz’d”
                        with Giles’s scarecrows that he must resort to a grim method:
                        
                        <lg type="stanza">
                    <l>Let then your birds lie prostrate on the earth,</l>
                    <l>In dying posture, and with wings stretch’d
                        forth;</l>
                    <l>Shift them at eve or morn from place to place,</l>
                    <l>And death shall terrify the pilfering race.<note place="foot" resp="author"> 
                        Bloomfield, “Spring,” lines 98–120.</note></l>
                            </lg>
                        
                        
                    Similarly, the poet moves from cows’ yielding
                        bountiful milk to impossibly hard cheese,<note
                                place="foot">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> 237-67.</note> from an
                        anthology of flowers to enclosure’s fences,
                                <note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> 269-320.</note> from the
                        playing of companion lambs to “their fleeces drench’d in gore” by a
                        “murd’ring Butcher,”<note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> 321–52.</note>from a
                        beautiful maiden’s golden hair to horsetails clipped too short to fend off
                            flies,<note place="foot" resp="author"> Bloomfield,
                                    “Summer,” lines 169–224.</note> from harvest feasts to
                        tyranny’s scarcity,<note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> 283–346.</note> and from
                        maids looking for love to one “Crazy Poll” sleeping in pig-sties.<note place="foot" resp="author">Bloomfield, “Autumn,” lines 101–12.</note> Bloomfield’s skylark section makes these
                        moves, too, as does Clare’s, in which the scared, vulnerable, toiling bird
                        is contrasted with the flights of fancy of the ignorant boys. These poets
                        defamiliarize a metaphor and its metaphysics by familiarizing contingent
                        ecological and economic histories. Their language was not less or more
                        “real” because they were grounded on some foundation or looking down from
                        some firmament. My turn to Bloomfield and Clare is therefore not a turn to
                        authors who wrote in some mythical, monolithic “real language,” but a turn
                        to authors who knowingly wrote in what the others, following the
                        long-standing capitalist naturalization of labour and labourers, considered
                        as such—<hi rend="italic">viz</hi>., Wordsworth’s “lower classes,” Shelley’s
                        apology for “erudition,” Capel Lofft’s correcting Bloomfield’s “Jiles” to
                        “Giles,” and John Taylor’s redacting Clare’s solecisms.</p>
                    
                    <p>If the “real language of men” is a fantasy, as
                        Bloomfield and Clare remind us, their languages are nonetheless real, and we
                        ought to renegotiate what we mean by “real” and “fantasy” and how they are
                        contingent. This needs to be applied to Shelley and Wordsworth. If consensus
                        frees these canonical skylarks from the vicissitudes of contingencies but
                        insists on them with respect to the non-canonical skylarks, then for
                        symmetry’s sake and contingency’s sake we might insist on them with respect
                        to both. If there’s no one “real language,” there might be languages more or
                        less “real” given a certain situation; there might be languages that
                        accomplish different purposes in different contexts, along different
                        figural-historical axes. If it’s easy, as above, to conclude that Bloomfield
                        and Clare’s languages, as their skylarks, come from their contingency with
                        farming and labouring, then it should be just as easy to conclude that
                        Shelley and Wordsworth’s language, as their skylarks, comes from contingency
                        with philosophy and poetry—Shakespeare, for instance, writes a lark
                        “arising” to sing at “heaven’s gate,”<note
                                place="foot" resp="author">
                                    William Shakespeare, “Sonnet XXIX,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Shakespeare’s Sonnets</hi> (Boston: Ticknor and Fields,
                                    1865), lines 11–12. </note> and Gray writes a skylark
                        who “melts into air and liquid light.”<note
                                place="foot" resp="author"> Thomas
                                    Gray, “Ode on the Pleasure Arising from Vicissitude,” in <hi
                                        rend="italic">The Poems of Mr. Gray</hi>, 2nd ed., ed.
                                    William Mason (London: Hughs, 1775), lines
                            13–20.</note></p>
                    
                    <p>However, we can also observe that it is Wordsworth
                        and Shelley who insist on the contingency of the skylark’s ability to sing
                        while soaring, and it is Clare and Bloomfield who insist on the contingency
                        of people’s perceptions, experiences, and descriptions of the skylarks—both,
                        indeed, responding to the poetic tradition of using the skylark as a figure.
                        Both are as informed by ornithology as by mythology, by material history as
                        by poetic convention, by fact as by fiction. The ways these languages are
                        already contingent <hi rend="italic">on</hi> their own histories complicate
                        the ways they become contingent <hi rend="italic">with</hi> each other.
                        Approaches to these tangled figural histories can only benefit from
                        contingent methods. To anticipate my turn to Meillassoux, the problem with
                        this thought-style isn’t metaphysics or figuration, but, having
                        metaphysicalized and figured, a neglect to also return to the physics and
                        the ground—pithily, perhaps, theory without method. Calls to do so are loud
                        in these skylark poems: Shelley’s conclusion, rife with questions, begs for
                        that return, that recontextualization, as does Wordsworth’s uneasy opening
                        and aporetic conclusion. But they’re also audible in Bloomfield’s skylark
                        calling on Giles to “mark her way” and in Clare’s wistfulness for heavenly
                        imagination.</p>
                    
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>A Whole Cloud of Philosophy</head>
                    
                    <p>Quentin Meillassoux’s <hi rend="italic"> After Finitude: An Essay on the Necessity of Contingency</hi>
                        (2008) is another synecdoche of the thought-style I’m complicating. In
                        particular, Meillassoux’s metaphysical project, including his <hi
                            rend="italic">antirrhesis</hi> that his project is not metaphysical, is
                        quintessentially Romantic(ist) in that it reduplicates what Walter Benjamin
                        calls “the striving on the part of the Romantic aestheticians after a
                        resplendent but ultimately noncommittal knowledge of an absolute.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Walter Benjamin, <hi rend="italic">The Origin of German Tragic Drama</hi>, trans. John Osborne
                                    (New York: Verso, 1998), 159.</note> It is the
                        surreptitious foundationalism I’ve pointed at above. Meillassoux’s project
                        is Romantic not only in this transcendental, sublime, imaginative sense, but
                        in a close-to-science sense, for much of the force propelling his argument
                        comes from compressed mathematical metaphors—think of Coleridge attending
                        Humphry Davy’s chemistry lectures to “renew his stock of metaphors.”<note place="foot" resp="author">Richard Holmes, <hi rend="italic">Coleridge: Early Visions</hi> (New York: Harper Collins,
                                    1989), 312.</note> After my reading, I hope this
                        project will be Romantic in a new contingent sense. Here I submit to closer
                        scrutiny two of Meillassoux’s “grammatical figures,”<note place="foot" resp="author">Jonathan Culler, <hi rend="italic">Structuralist Poetics: Structuralism, Linguistics, and the
                                        Study of Literature</hi> (London: Routledge, 2002),
                                    80–86.</note> his “metaphors that hold the
                            metaphysics”:<note place="foot" resp="author"> Gayatri
                                    Chakravorty Spivak,
                                    <hi rend="italic">A Critique of Postcolonial Reason: Toward a History of the Vanishing Present. </hi>(Cambridge:
                                    Harvard UP, 1999), 53.</note> systrophe and ellipsis.
                        If, as Wittgenstein writes, “a whole cloud of philosophy condenses into a
                        drop of grammar,”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Ludwig
                                    Wittgenstein, “Philosophy of Psychology—A Fragment,” in <hi
                                        rend="italic">Philosophical Investigations</hi>, trans. G.
                                    E. M. Anscombe, P. M. S. Hacker, and Joachim Schulte, 4th ed.
                                    (Hoboken: Wiley, 2009), sec. 315.</note> then we might
                        analyze this drop to better know the cloud—Meillassoux’s figures to better
                        know the thought-style.</p>
                    
                    <p>The way I close-read Meillassoux is the way
                        cognitive linguist Margaret Masterman, in 1965, close-read Thomas Kuhn’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Structure of Scientific Revolutions </hi>(1962)—and
                        for similar reasons. Kuhn’s book presented the notion of the “paradigm,” the
                        relatively closed, model-based framework of beliefs, values, and practices
                        held in common in a given “normal science.” Paradigms “shift” when the
                        anomalies inexplicable within a paradigm accrue and effect new
                        extra-paradigmatic research. Thinking about a natural science or even all
                        knowledge in terms of “paradigms” became its own paradigmatic thought-style,
                        like thinking in “contingency” is now. Both are akin to what Raymond
                        Williams called the “epochal analysis” of history as disconnected stages and
                        static types with “categorical rigidity.”<note
                                place="foot" resp="author"> Raymond Williams, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Marxism and Literature</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
                                    University Press, 1977): 67, 121.</note> Both
                        prioritize rupture, discreteness, and the unprecedented over continuity and
                        the known; both bury inconsistencies and alternatives. From her hospital bed
                        in Norwich, Masterman showed that there are twenty-one distinct senses of
                        “paradigm” in Kuhn’s theory, that they fall into three
                        categories—metaphysical, sociological, and artefact—of which the former is
                        grounded on the latter two, and that at their heart is a concrete,
                        analogy-drawing sequence of words (a figure) that focuses a research field,
                        that is constructed and extended
                        “<hi rend="italic">by using speech, </hi>with or
                        without the help of mechanical apparatus or of mathematics,” and that
                        collapses when it’s pushed too far.<note
                                place="foot" resp="author">
                                    Margaret Masterman, “The Nature of a Paradigm,” in <hi
                                        rend="italic">Criticism and the Growth of Knowledge:
                                        Proceedings of the International Colloquium in the
                                        Philosophy of Science, London 1965</hi>, ed. Imre Lakatos
                                    and Andrew Musgrave (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1970),
                                73–84.</note> If a paradigm has a figure at its heart, then
                        it has a figural history—a history of being rhetorically figured, a history
                        it in turn figures. To analyze a paradigm’s figural history is also a way to
                        analyze the paradigm-shift–paradigm’s figural history, and a model for
                        analyzing “contingency.”</p>
                    
                    <p> Though Masterman’s disambiguation is frequently
                        cited by Kuhn’s critics, Kuhn himself incorporated her revisions.<note place="foot" resp="author"> Thomas Kuhn, <hi rend="italic">The
                                        Road Since Structure: Philosophical Essays, 1970–1993, with
                                        an Autobiographical Interview</hi> (Chicago: Chicago UP,
                                    2000), 299–300; Thomas Kuhn, “Reflections on My Critics,” in <hi
                                        rend="italic">Criticism and the Growth of Knowledge:
                                        Proceedings of the International Colloquium in the
                                        Philosophy of Science, London 1965</hi>, ed. Imre Lakatos
                                    and Andrew Musgrave (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1970),
                                231–78.</note> In this spirit, I use Masterman’s method to
                        deconstruct Meillassoux’s metaphorics, not to refute him and what he
                        represents so much as refigure it, repurpose it, pragmatize metaphysical
                        absolutes and ground transhistorical universals. In <hi rend="italic">After
                            Finitude</hi>, there are at least 35 senses of “contingency,” listed
                        here in order of appearance, with page references:
                        
                    <list rend="numbered">
                        <item>opposite of inevitability (34)</item>
                        <item>opposite of essentiality (36–37)</item>
                        <item>indifference of physical laws to entities
                                (39)</item>
                        <item>“knowing that worldly things could be
                                otherwise” (39, 53–54)</item>
                        <item>opposite of necessity (40, 65,
                            67)</item>
                        <item>variability of entities (40)</item>
                        <item>opposite of facticity (53–54)</item>
                        <item>the absolute “capacity-to-be-other” of the
                                given (54, 117)</item>
                        <item>knowledge that there is no reason for
                                entities’ perishability or variability (62)</item>
                        <item>necessary (62, 80)</item>
                        <item>“pure possibility” (62–63)</item>
                        <item>perishability (62)</item>
                        <item>eternal (65)</item>
                        <item>conformity to certain conditions
                            (66)</item>
                        <item>determined or externally guided by chaos
                                (68, 70)</item>
                        <item>becoming of alterity (69)</item>
                        <item>chaos (71)</item>
                        <item>possibility of actualities to exist or not
                                (73–75)</item>
                        <item>possibility of propensities, eventualities,
                                or negative and positive facts to exist or not (75)</item>
                        <item>possibility of existence to exist or not
                                (75–76)</item>
                        <item>unreason (77)</item>
                        <item>possibility of worlds or universes to
                                become other than what they are now (78, 92)</item>
                        <item>conceivability of possibility of worlds or
                                universes to become other than what they are now (78)</item>
                        <item>conformity to speculative criteria
                                (78)</item>
                        <item>conceivability violated by real
                                contradiction and inconsistency (79)</item>
                        <item>background of the cosmos, that from which
                                necessity, an absolute, or a whole emerge (80)</item>
                        <item>possibility of physical laws themselves to
                                become other than what they are now (83)</item>
                        <item>acausality (92)</item>
                        <item>a priori (95–96)</item>
                        <item>opposite of chance (101)</item>
                        <item>inaccessible to reason (101)</item>
                        <item>determinate or precise condition of chaos
                                or of the stability of chaos (101)</item>
                        <item>transfinity (101, 110)</item>
                        <item>“something that finally happens”
                            (108)</item>
                        <item>independence of thought or humans (116,
                                117).</item>
                    </list>
                        
                    These thirty-five senses fall into six categories.
                        “Contingency” is something about:
                    <list rend="numbered">
                        <item>entities (6, 34)</item>
                        <item>laws (3, 27)</item>
                        <item>knowledge (4, 8, 9, 14, 23–25, 31, 33)</item>
                        <item>the sum total of entities, laws, and knowledge, perhaps “existence”
                            (8, 11, 12, 20, 22, 29) </item>
                        <item>the negative background from which [IV] emerges (15–19, 21, 26, 28,
                            32, 35) </item>
                        <item>a quality of any or all of the preceding (1, 2, 5, 7, 10, 13,
                            30).</item>
                    </list>
                        
                    “Contingency” is a systrophe, a “turning together,”
                        the figure of listing many qualities without explicit definition.<note place="foot" resp="author">See Gideon O. Burton, “Silva
                                    Rhetoricae,” Brigham Young University, 2016. <ref
                                        target="http://rhetoric.byu.edu/">rhetoric.byu.edu/</ref>.
                                    Accessed 6 Mar. 2020.</note> Systrophe is the figure at
                        the heart of Meillassoux’s paradigm, but one he doesn’t embrace. The reader
                        is instead encouraged to smooth these complications into a definition:
                        “contingency” is the possible emergence of existence from, or the
                        capacity-to-be-other of, a necessary chaos. Meillassoux hypostatizes, from
                        observable entities within the universe, a chaos behind the multiverse, from
                        [I] to [V]. The centerpiece of this argument is Chapter 4, “Hume’s Problem,”
                        which refutes consensus probabilistic arguments for the truth of causal
                        necessity (the reason the same effects always follow from the same causes is
                        that the universe in which the physical laws governing causality always
                        emerges from the set of all possible universes, “given a sufficiently
                        gigantic number of attempts”) with a Badiouan take on Cantor’s theorem (the
                        set of all possible universes cannot be totalized and so does not exist), in
                        order to turn our usual order of operations on its head and attempt to
                        explain causal necessity given that it must be contingent.<note place="foot" resp="author">Quentin Meillassoux, <hi rend="italic">After Finitude: An Essay on the Necessity of
                                        Contingency</hi>, trans. Ray Brassier (London: Continuum,
                                    2008), 87–105.</note></p>
                        
                    <p>This catachresis of mathematical metaphors (or, per
                        Meillassoux, “anhypothetical principles” and “axiomatics”) has more than a
                        family resemblance to the humanistic theories of the past half-century. It’s
                        a variation in a metaphysical key on a common motif, from paradigm shifts to
                        contingency and between foundationalism and interdisciplinarity. Meillassoux
                        does something Romantic in figuring contingency via a series of
                        expropriations that free various kinds of contingency or contingent things
                        from their social contexts, figural histories, and material referents, and
                        then by attempting to fuse them into an organic whole, to use Langan’s
                        analysis of the process of “reduction and abstraction” in Wordsworth’s
                        poetry. And in Wordsworth’s own words, Meillassoux “might’st seem, proud
                        privilege! to sing / All independent of the leafy spring.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Wordsworth, “To a Sky-lark” (1827), lines 11–12.</note> But since one of my purposes here
                        is to get back to the leafy spring, to de-hypostatize Meillassoux’s
                        conclusions, I develop the systrophe elided in his theory. I want to restore
                        systrophe from this thought-style’s reifying use of “semantic ascent” to
                        humanistic methods in general and Romanticism in particular. It’s one drop
                        of grammar—a useful one—in this cloud of philosophy.</p>
                        
                    <p>Another figure at the heart of Meillassoux’s contingency is ellipsis—not just of his integral systrophe, but also with respect to the verb “think.” Instead of common, idiomatic verb phrases like “think about <hi
                            rend="italic">x</hi>or “think of <hi
                            rend="italic">x</hi>,” “think over <hi
                            rend="italic">x</hi>" or “think through <hi >x</hi>" Meillassoux uses “think <hi
                            rend="italic">x</hi>." As far as my French allows me to read, this isn’t an effect of Ray Brassier’s translation but is also true in the French original, <hi rend="italic">Après la Finitude </hi>(2006), which uses neither the idiomatic and most common “penser à <hi
                            rend="italic">x</hi>," nor the idiomatic but less common “penser de <hi
                            rend="italic">x</hi>,”
                            “penser
                        <hi rend="italic">z</hi>” (where <hi rend="italic">z </hi> is an infinitive), or “penser que <hi
                            rend="italic">x</hi>,”
                            but opts instead for “penser
                        <hi rend="italic">x</hi>.” I don’t mean Meillassoux (or Brassier) simply elides “that,” which is idiomatic and which he sometimes does. I mean that he deploys a grammatical figure. Excluding adjective or noun uses of “thinking,” “think <hi rend="italic">x</hi>" appears 100 times in <hi
                            rend="italic">After Finitude</hi>, almost always when Meillassoux presents his own
                            argument, whereas idiomatic uses of “think” (with a preposition or an
                            elided “that”) occur only 32 times, almost always when Meillassoux
                            presents arguments to refute or characters discussing his
                            arguments.</p>
                        
                    <p>This ellipsis is no inexplicable quirk, and regardless of whether it has precedents in Pascal or Descartes, it’s nevertheless that from which a little of this contingency’s philosophical <hi rend="italic">je ne sais quoi</hi> derives. Witness it in examples of senses (20),
                            (22), and (35) above:
                            <lg type="stanza">
                   <l> “I can think the contingency of this existing thing” (75) </l>
                    <l>“I cannot think the contingency of <hi rend="italic">existence </hi> as such” (75) </l>
                    <l>“I am perfectly incapable of thinking the abolition of existence”
                        (76)</l>
                    <l>“it becomes possible to think a plurality of contradictory worlds”
                        (78) </l>
                    <l>“thought has become able to think a world [. . .] unaffected by whether or
                            not anyone thinks it” (116)</l>
                                </lg>
                          
                    A reduction and abstraction complementary to that from a congeries of senses to one definition occurs in this ellipsis of “thinking <hi rend="italic">about </hi>a world” into “thinking a world”: the former merely conjures a representation in the mind of a world that has mind-independent existence, whereas the latter either produces a world in the mind or calls it into existence from the unthought void, and as such it is not mind-independent (contrary to Meillassoux’s larger “post-Kantian” project). But we don’t say “I think a skylark”; we say “I’m thinking <hi rend="italic">about</hi> a skylark.” There is a tantalizing intimation of agency, being, or power in the way the preposition-less “think” works. Yet, when prepositions are re-inserted, “contingency” re-systrophized, made contingent, this cloud of philosophy condenses into a drop of grammar, static theory into dynamic methods.</p>
                        
                    <p>Prepositionalizing in this way has its own figural
                        history. Wittgenstein does it in his celebrated complication of “seeing”
                        into “seeing-as,” in which he postulates the ineluctable conditioning of
                        perception by precognition, habit, and experience <note place="foot" resp="author"> Wittgenstein, “Philosophy of Psychology,” secs. 203–40.</note>—not unlike Clare and
                        Bloomfield do. Philippa Foot does it in her elegant reconceptualization of
                        Aristotelian necessity “all things considered” (a.t.c.) into necessities
                        “relevant to certain considerations” such as species’ habitats, patterns of
                        life, and repertoires of working things out <note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    Philippa Foot, <hi rend="italic">Natural Goodness</hi> (Oxford:
                                    Clarendon, 2001), 15, 57.</note>—not unlike Shelley and
                        Wordsworth do. Contingencies-as, contingencies-for: these are more fruitful
                        than Contingency a.t.c. This Contingency is a foundation on which a given
                        thing, event, even world “could have been otherwise”—a conditional perfect
                        tense that enjoins a wistful imaginary to wring its hands while
                        transmogrifying “could” into “would” and “should”—and, moreover, it
                        conflates concepts we already have handy phrases for, such as
                        “path-dependent” or “systemically caused” or, in a pinch, “socially
                            constructed.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Cf. Joel Mokyr,
                                    “King Kong and Cold Fusion: Counterfactual Analysis and the
                                    History of Technology,” in <hi rend="italic">Unmaking the West:
                                        “What-if?” Scenarios that Rewrite World History</hi>, ed.
                                    Philip E. Tetlock, Richard Ned Lebow, and Geoffrey Parker (Ann
                                    Arbor: U of Michigan P, 2006), 277–322; Stephen Jay Gould, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Wonderful Life: The Burgess Shale and the
                                        Nature of History</hi> (New York: Norton, 1989), 51,
                                    283–91.</note> Refiguring it does not trivialize it,
                        merely repurposes it, for to mistake de-metaphysicalizing for trivializing
                        is only the contrapositive of hypostases in the thought-style represented by
                        Meillassoux. The grammars and the figures are the vital parts—they’re parts
                        of how we organize our forms of life.</p>
                        
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Cosmic Exile</head>
                    
                    <p>If we hew only to this Contingency that affords a
                        semantic ascent away from the everyday, a streamlining of systrophic mess,
                        we end up with the kinds of foundationalizing, totalizing, and teleologizing
                        that “contingency” is meant to resist. Quine calls this move “cosmic exile”
                        in the final paragraph of
                        <hi rend="italic">Word and Object </hi>(1960), which
                        concludes his discussion of semantic ascent:
                        
                    <quote>"'The philosopher’s task differs from the others’,
                        then, in detail; but in no such drastic way as those suppose who imagine for
                        the philosopher a vantage point outside the conceptual scheme that he [<hi
                            rend="italic">sic</hi>] takes in charge. There is no such <hi
                            rend="italic">cosmic exile</hi>. He cannot study and revise the
                        fundamental conceptual scheme of science and common sense without having
                        some conceptual scheme, whether the same or another no less in need of
                        philosophical scrutiny, in which to work."<note
                                place="foot" resp="author"> Quine,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Word and Object</hi>, 254, emphasis
                                    added.</note></quote>
                        
                   That is, fruitfulness comes from working conceptual
                        schemes together, making them contingent in the side-by-side sense, from
                        moving back-and-forth between them, not from ascending out of them all.
                        Without returning systrophe to the heart of Meillassoux’s paradigm, without
                        adding prepositions back to his ellipses,
                        <hi rend="italic">After Finitude </hi>performs two
                        kinds of cosmic exile. The first is Quine’s: this thought-style <hi
                            rend="italic">exiles itself into the cosmos</hi>. It takes an outside
                        vantage, allowing philosophers (and literary theorists) to see “themselves
                        as presiding over a tribunal of pure reason,” as legislating disciplinary
                        bounds, as handling the really R/real.<note
                                place="foot" resp="author">
                                    Richard Rorty, <hi rend="italic">Philosophy and the Mirror of
                                        Nature</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1979),
                            139.</note> The second is one Quine might not have foreseen:
                        this thought-style <hi rend="italic">exiles the cosmos itself</hi>. With
                        pure reason allegedly encroached by math and physics, theory can reclaim its
                        prestige by presiding over a tribunal of pure <hi rend="italic"
                            >unreason</hi>, from which reason emerges and on which it is contingent
                            (<hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. Meillassoux, also François Laruelle and
                        “non-philosophy”). This is the regressive and foundationalist move we make
                        when, for example, we state or imply that, yet elide how, poetry is about or
                        even <hi rend="italic">is</hi> ecology, ontology, affect, history, or
                        otherwise, though plenty of tough questions call to us from the “is” that
                        brings these fields together, if it’s more than “the fantastic
                        interdisciplinary nothingness of metaphor.”
                                <note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    Alan Liu, “The Power of Formalism: The New Historicism,” <hi
                                        rend="italic">English Literary History</hi> 56, no. 4,
                                    (1989), 743.</note> This is also the move we make when
                        we both substitute an authoritative gesture at a field for authority in that
                        field <hi rend="italic">and</hi> disavow authority in general or authorities
                        outside our fields—Benjamin’s “noncommittal knowledge” or Liu’s “detached
                            immanence”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Alan Liu, “Local
                                    Transcendence: Cultural Criticism, Postmodernism, and the
                                    Romanticism of Detail,” in
                                    <hi rend="italic">Local Transcendence: Essays on Postmodern Historicism and the Database </hi>(Chicago: U of Chicago P, 2008), 113.</note>—though plenty of
                        problems ask us to bring such fields together.</p>
                    
                    <p>Instead of cosmic exile, I want to explore the
                        borderless free flow of ideas between cosmoi, disciplinary fields as an
                        open-field commons, before the enclosure that transformed the Georgian era
                        set off a series of enclosures (of knowledge, culture, biology, <hi
                            rend="italic">etc.</hi>) amid which we still find ourselves. There’s no
                        one contingency, but all kinds, visibly so in farming, which is another one
                        of my systrophe of examples. I was writing this paper in spring, the season
                        in which every decision—who will clean the germination greenhouse, when to
                        prepare the beehives for spring growth and pollination, what old blueberry
                        growth needs to be pruned—has effects amplified a hundredfold some months
                        from now, even more so because that season these
                        sensitively dependent decisions were made during the manifold uncertainties
                        of a pandemic. This is the Lorenz attractor, butterfly effect,
                        path-dependency kind of “contingency” with which we Romanticists are most
                        familiar, not least because of Meillassoux.
                               <note place="foot" resp="author">
                                    Cf. Christina Lupton, “Literature and Contingency,” <hi
                                        rend="italic">Textual Practice</hi> 32, no. 3 (2018),
                                    375–79; Gillian White, “Poetics of Contingency,” <hi
                                        rend="italic">Textual Practice</hi> 32, no. 3 (2018),
                                    529–50.</note> It also shows up in the way farmers rely
                        on their previous decisions, review their past seasons, and stick with what
                        worked as much as possible—a reliance on tradition that might raise the
                        hackles of the critical Romanticist, but one that such a Romanticist shares,
                        at the very least in continuing to consult two-hundred-year-old poetry.</p>
                    
                    <p>At least one other kind of contingency is
                        contingent with this kind, though. This contingency is what farmers have to
                        know and do in dozens of fields and communities at once, an overlapping Venn
                        diagram and exploded-view drawing, and a concern, as
                        contemporary-and-Romantic farmer-and-poet Wendell Berry says, “for the way
                        that things are joined together.”<note
                                place="foot" resp="author">
                                    Gregory McNamee and James R. Hepworth, “The Art of Living Right:
                                    An Interview with Wendell Berry,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Conversations with Wendell Berry</hi>, ed. Morris Allen
                                    Grubbs (Jackson: Mississippi UP, 2007), 19–26.</note>
                        Farmers have to know ecology, botany, animal biology, soil science,
                        chemistry, climatology, machinery, carpentry, fieldwork techniques, worker
                        management, legislation, they have to know people who know these things
                        better than they do, and they have to know how these fields interact. If
                        they are experts in one field, sometimes literally, their expertise
                        diffracts against,<note place="foot" resp="author"> Karen Barad, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Meeting the Universe Halfway: Quantum Physics
                                        and the Entanglement of Matter and Meaning</hi> (Durham:
                                    Duke UP, 2007), 71.</note> interferes with, relies on,
                        builds with numerous others’. This is, I would submit, what the literary
                        humanities have been at their best, too. Conditioned by a Romanticist’s
                        reflexivity, Meillassoux’s systrophe is the figure
                        <hi rend="italic">sine qua non </hi>for grappling with
                        this contingency in all its movement, mess, and “mangle of practice,”<note place="foot" resp="author">Andrew Pickering, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >The Mangle of Practice: Time, Agency, and Science</hi>
                                    (Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1995), 1.</note> for it’s
                        neither a smooth synthesis nor a total definition, but centers versatile,
                        accommodating methods.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Semantic Descent and Open Cosmoi</head>
                    
                    <p>To the extent that I’ve soared, it has been with a
                        view of nesting back in the corn. If doing metaphysics or being
                        foundationalist is useful, then its use comes in its recontextualization,
                        pragmatization, pluralization—in its vulnerabilities, persistences, and
                        responses to difference and difficulty, like Clare’s skylark. We can recover
                        a <hi rend="italic">semantic descent</hi> from Contingency to a systrophe of
                        contingencies with various non-elided prepositions such as Wittgensteinian
                            “contingencies-<hi rend="italic">as</hi>” or “contingencies-<hi
                            rend="italic">of</hi>” or “contingencies-<hi rend="italic">with</hi>,”
                        and from Necessity to various Footian “necessities-<hi rend="italic"
                            >for</hi>.” In other words, from a Romantic “real language” to many real
                        languages. We can replace cosmic exile with open cosmoi, forming
                        “contingencies” in the “side by side” or “touching together” sense of common
                        fields and of a farmer’s knowledge, the glorious, glaring light of
                        metaphysics helping us, by a bent-hat shade, to carefully scrutinize a
                        penumbrae of practices. These contingencies form and are formed by
                        intersections, path-dependencies, and historical figurations that must be
                        stated and debated—and crucially, they are formed by purposes that must be
                        aired, too. They are less tidy ideas that appear on one or the other side of
                        paradigm shifts, epistemic breaks, Contingency, and incommensurabilities,
                        more messy notions that criss-cross in deep shifts, slow breaks, long
                        contingencies, and commensurabilities. As I’ve tried to demonstrate
                        throughout this essay, this is where Romanticists can use our methodological
                        reflexivity, in retooling the many methods of the post-Feyerabendian “almost
                        anything goes” that results from such contingency; this is where we can use
                        our formalism, in analyzing what Stephen Jay Gould calls “the complex events
                        of narrative” rather than “the simple consequences of natural law” (or, for
                        that matter, of a Meillasouxian supernatural unlaw and of what we think of
                        as simple, as consequence, as natural, as law);<note place="foot"> Gould, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Wonderful Life</hi>, 278.</note> and this is where
                        we can use our historicism, in generalizing the lessons of the conditional
                        perfect to the revolutionary reimagination of what Emily Rohrbach calls the
                        future anterior, of what will have been. <note place="foot" resp="author"> Emily Rohrbach,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Modernity’s Mist: British Romanticism and
                                        the Poetics of Anticipation</hi> (New York: Fordham UP,
                                    2016), 1–2.</note></p>
                        
                    <p>I’m only beginning my foray into the worlds of
                        Romanticists and farmers. But I hope the contingencies of my fields have
                        been and will be fruitful. After Spivak’s assessment of the state of
                        comparative literature in
                        <hi rend="italic">Death of a Discipline </hi>(2003),
                        and despite my disagreement with her that “‘fieldwork’ belongs to the social
                            sciences,”<note place="foot" resp="author">Gayatri
                                    Chakravorty Spivak, <hi rend="italic">Death of a Discipline</hi>
                                    (New York: Columbia UP, 2003), 9, 37.</note> I think we
                        Romanticists can train ourselves and our students
                        <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to be Scholars, Theorists,
                        or Philosophers, whose field of choice lies cosmically exiled beneath or
                        behind or beyond all other fields, whether it be because language is
                        everything or mathematics is or affect is or agency is or matter is or form
                        is, <hi rend="italic">etc.</hi>, but to be a contingent of scholars-and-…,
                        theorists-and-. . ., philosophers-and-…, whose fields lie beside and between
                        other fields, because language, mathematics, affect, matter, or form belongs
                        to most things in some way. This means decolonizing, remembering,
                        demarginalizing, building specializations and expertise in anything but
                        silos—but building them nonetheless, and lending, borrowing, and helping
                        others build. For me, this also means a systrophe of Romanticist-and-farmer,
                            “sideshadowed”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Gary Saul Morson,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Narrative and Freedom: The Shadows of
                                        Time</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1994), 117.</note>
                        by historian and philosopher of science, genetics student, would-be writer.
                        This is, per the parable of the skylark, consistent with a renewed
                        post–Romantic-ideology sense of Romanticism as a vulnerable nest in a
                        certain field from which we can both soar and return to care, Romanticism
                        done by paper-cut, plough-cramped hands. We can make the sophistications of
                        Romanticism complement others, supplement others, “yoking the humanities,
                        however distantly, with however few guarantees, to a just world.”<note place="foot" resp="author"> Spivak, <hi rend="italic">Death of a
                                        Discipline</hi>, 100–02.</note></p>
                        
                    <p>We might take the lessons learned in our semantic
                        ascent and return from the clouds with them to nestle in fields around,
                        refreshing the purpose of the university within and without it, outside,
                        around, all the time. Berry puts it succinctly in “Unspecializing Poetry”
                        (1983): this semantic descent
                        
                    <quote>calls for a different kind of mind and a different
                        kind of university, in which the motions of intelligence would not follow
                        radii ever outward from the center, each discipline dividing farther from
                        the others the farther outward it goes, but would move in a dance pattern of
                        exchanges and returns. Literary scholars might then begin to teach biology,
                        history, philosophy, science, etc., not to be versatile, but to be
                        pertinent. Writers would begin to feel the judgment of engineers, farmers,
                        and doctors.<note place="foot"> Wendell Berry,
                                    “Notes: Unspecializing Poetry,” in <hi rend="italic">Standing By
                                        Words</hi> (Albany: North Point, 1983),
                        84.</note></quote>
                        
                    I’ve recontextualized, poetically and politically,
                        Berry’s farmer-poetics as one of my guides to try to show how I might do
                        this—repurpose and ramify, not refute or reify. Insofar as Romanticist
                        approaches to contingency in particular depend on the thought-style I’ve
                        sketched, I hope I have made progress toward repurposing that dependency.
                        And insofar as Romanticist methods in general tend to recreate its cosmic
                        exile and semantic ascent, I hope I have made progress toward reimagining
                        that tendency. As rapturous as it is to soar, the corn needs care
                        too.</p>
                        
                </div>
                <div type="citation">
                    
                    <head>Works Cited</head>
                    
                    <bibl>Anonymous. <hi rend="italic">A Political Enquiry
                            into the Consequences of Enclosing Waste Lands, and the Causes of the
                            Present High Price of Butchers Meat</hi>. Holborn: Davis, 1785.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barad, Karen. <hi
                            rend="italic">Meeting the Universe Halfway: Quantum Physics and the
                            Entanglement of Matter and Meaning</hi>. Durham: Duke University Press,
                        2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Benjamin, Walter. <hi
                            rend="italic">The Origin of German Tragic Drama</hi>. Translated by John
                        Osborne. New York: Verso, 1998.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Berry, Wendell. “Notes: Unspecializing Poetry.”
                           In <hi rend="italic">Standing By
                            Words</hi>. Albany: North Point, 1983. pp. 80–91.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bloomfield, Robert. <hi rend="italic">The Farmer’s
                            Boy; A Rural Poem.</hi> 2nd ed. London: Vernor and Hood, 1800.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Burton, Gideon O. “Silva Rhetoricae.” Brigham Young
                        University, 2016. <ref target="http://rhetoric.byu.edu/">rhetoric.byu.edu/</ref>. Accessed 6 Mar. 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chandler, James.
                        <hi rend="italic">England in 1819: The Politics of Literary Culture and the Case of Romantic Historicism. </hi>Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1998.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clare, John. “The
                        Skylark.” In <hi rend="italic">The Rural Muse, </hi>85.
                        London: Whittaker, 1835. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Cobbett, William.
                        <hi rend="italic">The Woodlands. </hi>London: Cobbett,
                        1825.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coleridge, Samuel
                        Taylor.
                        <hi rend="italic">Biographia Literaria; or, Biographical Sketches of my Literary Life and Opinions. </hi>New
                        York: Leavitt, 1834.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Culler, Jonathan. <hi
                            rend="italic">Structuralist Poetics: Structuralism, Linguistics, and the
                            Study of Literature</hi>. London: Routledge, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Foot, Philippa. <hi rend="italic">Natural
                            Goodness</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gould, Stephen Jay. <hi rend="italic">Wonderful
                            Life: The Burgess Shale and the Nature of History</hi>. New York:
                        Norton, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gray, Thomas. “Ode on
                        the Pleasure Arising from Vicissitude.” In <hi rend="italic">The Poems of
                            Mr. Gray</hi>. 2nd edition, edited by William Mason, 78-82. London:
                        Hughs, 1775. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Holmes, Richard. <hi rend="italic">Coleridge: Early
                            Visions</hi>. New York: Harper Collins, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jameson, Fredric. <hi rend="italic">Postmodernism,
                            or, the Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism</hi>. Durham: Duke University
                        Press, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kuhn, Thomas S. <hi rend="italic">The Structure of
                            Scientific Revolutions</hi>. 4th ed. Chicago: University of Chicago
                        Press, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Reflections on My Critics.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Criticism and the Growth of Knowledge: Proceedings of the
                            International Colloquium in the Philosophy of Science, London 1965</hi>,
                        edited by Imre Lakatos and Andrew Musgrave, 231–78. Cambridge: Cambridge
                        University Press, 1970.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi
                            rend="italic">The Road Since Structure: Philosophical Essays, 1970–1993,
                            with an Autobiographical Interview</hi>. Chicago: University of Chicago
                        Press, 2000.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Langan, Celeste. <hi rend="italic">Romantic
                            Vagrancy: Wordsworth and the Simulation of Freedom</hi>. Cambridge:
                        Cambridge University Press, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Liu, Alan. “The Power
                        of Formalism: The New Historicism.” <hi rend="italic">English Literary
                            History</hi> 56, no. 4, (1989): 721–71.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Local
                        Transcendence: Cultural Criticism, Postmodernism, and the Romanticism of
                        Detail.” In <hi rend="italic">Local Transcendence:
                            Essays on Postmodern Historicism and the Database</hi>110-54.
                        Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Lupton, Christina.
                        “Literature and Contingency.” <hi rend="italic">Textual Practice</hi> 32,
                        no. 3 (2018): 375–79.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Malm, Andreas. <hi rend="italic">The Progress of
                            This Storm: Nature and Society in a Warming World</hi>. New York: Verso,
                        2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marshall, William. <hi rend="italic">The Review and
                            Abstract of the County Reports to the Board of Agriculture</hi>. 5 vols.
                        York: Thomas Wilson,
                            1808–17.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Masterman, Margaret. “The Nature of a Paradigm.” In
                            <hi rend="italic">Criticism and the Growth of Knowledge: Proceedings of
                            the International Colloquium in the Philosophy of Science, London
                            1965</hi>, edited by Imre Lakatos and Andrew Musgrave, 59–89. Cambridge:
                        Cambridge University Press, 1970.</bibl>
                    <bibl>McNamee, Gregory and
                        James R. Hepworth. “The Art of Living Right: An Interview with Wendell
                        Berry.” In <hi rend="italic">Conversations with Wendell Berry</hi>, edited
                        by Morris Allen Grubbs, 19–26. Jackson: University Press of Mississippi,
                        2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Meillassoux, Quentin. <hi rend="italic">Après la
                            Finitude: Essai sur la Nécessité de la Contingence</hi>. Paris: Éditions
                        du Seuil, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi
                            rend="italic">After Finitude: An Essay on the Necessity of
                            Contingency</hi>. Translated by Ray Brassier. London: Continuum,
                        2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mokyr, Joel. “King
                        Kong and Cold Fusion: Counterfactual Analysis and the History of
                        Technology.” In <hi rend="italic">Unmaking the West: “What-if?” Scenarios
                            that Rewrite World History</hi>, edited by Philip E. Tetlock, Richard
                        Ned Lebow, and Geoffrey Parker, 277–322. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan
                        Press, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Morson, Gary Saul. <hi rend="italic">Narrative and
                            Freedom: The Shadows of Time</hi>. New Haven: Yale University Press,
                        1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nersessian, Anahid. “Romanticism as Method.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Teaching Romanticism and Literary Theory</hi>, edited by
                        Brian McGrath, Pedagogies Volume, <hi rend="italic">Romantic Circles</hi>
                        (December 2016) <ref target="https://romantic-circles.org/bibledagogies/commons/teaching_romanticism/bibledagogies.commons.2016.teaching_romanticism.nersessian.html">Romantic Circles</ref> .
                        Accessed 4 Mar. 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Literary Agnotology.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >English Literary History</hi> 84, no. 2 (2017): 339–60.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic"
                            >Oxford English Dictionary Online</hi>, s.v. “meta-, prefix.” Accessed 4
                        Mar. 2020.
                        <ref target="https://www.oed.com/view/Entry/117150?rskey=kBsi4V&amp;result=4#eid.">Oxford English Dictionary</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pickering, Andrew.
                        <hi rend="italic">The Mangle of Practice: Time, Agency, and Science. </hi>Chicago:
                        University of Chicago Press, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Quine, Willard Van
                        Orman.
                        <hi rend="italic">Word and Object. </hi>Cambridge:
                        Massachusetts Institute of Technology Press, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rohrbach, Emily. <hi rend="italic">Modernity’s
                            Mist: British Romanticism and the Poetics of Anticipation</hi>. New
                        York: Fordham UP, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rorty, Richard. <hi rend="italic">Philosophy and
                            the Mirror of Nature</hi>. Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                        1979.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shakespeare, William. “Sonnet XXIX.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Shakespeare’s Sonnets</hi>. Boston: Ticknor and Fields, 1865. p. 35.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shelley, Percy Bysshe. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Cenci</hi>.
                        In<hi rend="italic"> Shelley’s Poetry and Prose. </hi>2nd
                        ed. Edited by Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat, 138–202. New York: Norton,
                        2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “To a Sky-Lark,” <hi rend="italic">Prometheus
                            Unbound: A Lyrical Drama in Four Acts, With Other Poems</hi>. London:
                        Ollier, 1820. 201–06.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi
                            rend="italic">Hellas</hi>. In <hi rend="italic">Shelley’s Poetry and
                            Prose</hi>. 2nd ed. Edited by Donald H. Reiman and Neil Fraistat,
                        427–62. New York: Norton, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Siskin, Clifford, and
                        William Warner. “If This Is Enlightenment Then What Is Romanticism?”
                        <hi rend="italic">European Romantic Review </hi>22, no.
                        3 (2011): 281–91.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Spivak, Gayatri Chakravorty.
                        <hi rend="italic">A Critique of Postcolonial Reason: Toward a History of the Vanishing Present. </hi>Cambridge:
                        Harvard UP, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Death of a Discipline</hi>.
                        New York: Columbia University Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>TeBokkel, Nathan. “Pastoral Authority,” <hi
                            rend="italic">New Literary History</hi> 54, no. 4 (2024), 1637–63.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Virgil,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Aeneid. </hi>Translated by John
                        Dryden. Internet Classics Archive, 2000.</bibl>
                    <bibl>White, Gillian. “Poetics of Contingency.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Textual Practice</hi> 32, no. 3 (2018): 529–50.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Williams, Raymond.
                            <hi rend="italic">Marxism and Literature</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University
                        Press, 1977. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Wittgenstein, Ludwig. “Philosophy of Psychology—A
                        Fragment.” In <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Investigations</hi>,
                        translated by G. E. M. Anscombe, P. M. S. Hacker, and Joachim Schulte,
                        182–243. 4th ed. Hoboken: Wiley, 2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wordsworth, William. “Nutting.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Wordsworth’s Poetry and Prose</hi>, edited by Nicholas
                        Halmi, 130–31. New York: Norton, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Preface to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads </hi>(1802).” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Wordsworth’s Poetry and Prose</hi>, edited by Nicholas
                        Halmi, 76–96. New York: Norton, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “To a Sky-lark.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">Poems, in Two Volumes</hi>, vol. 1. London: Longman,
                        Hurst, Rees, and Orme, 1807. 80–82.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “To a Sky-lark.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">The Poetical Works of William Wordsworth</hi>, vol. 2.
                        London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green, 1827. 165.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Young, Arthur. <hi rend="italic">The Farmer’s Letters to the People of England. </hi>London:
                        Nicoll, 1767.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
