<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.partFiveIntro</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4499</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or
            disseminated in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism,
            comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act
            of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are
            copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use
            provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
            redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent
            from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for
            authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior
              written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their
              current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on
            their own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled
            subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and
            additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current
            text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of
            course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of
            use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <author>
              <name>Lynda Pratt</name>
            </author>
            <title>Introduction, Part V</title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.partFiveIntro" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.partFiveIntro.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 4p. . Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New
          Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London &amp; New York, 1965), II, pp. 192&#8211;194.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian
          Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank
          the Beinecke Rare Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of
          English and American Literature, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden
          Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the British Library; Boston Public
          Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the Fitzwilliam
          Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania;
          the Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library,
          Harvard University; the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research
          Library, University of Kansas; Luton Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts
          Historical Society; McGill University Library; the National Library of Scotland; the
          Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer Collections); the
          Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury St
          Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the
          Society of Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library,
          Stafford, the Wisbech and Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did
          support from the English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and '
            for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
            keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact
            rendering of their length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the
            content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded
            in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
            http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E
            on 2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g5 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David
        Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="PartFiveIntro">
        <head>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Five</head>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Introduction</hi>
        </p>
        <p>
          <title>Part Five</title> collects, in one place for the first time, the surviving letters written by Robert Southey between 1816 and
               1818. It follows the editorial conventions described in About this Edition and contains newly transcribed, fully annotated texts of 537
               letters drawn from archives in the United Kingdom, Europe and North America. Of these, 341 are published for the first time, with a
               further 51 published here in full for the first time. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The letters brought together in this edition begin on 2 January 1816 with an account of Southey&#8217;s latest task as Poet
               Laureate (the composition of a New Year&#8217;s Ode) and his progress on a topical new poem, <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>
               (Letter 2690). They conclude on New Year&#8217;s Eve 1818 with a letter that combines news of Southey&#8217;s family and friends in the Lake
               District with a description of his labours for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> (Letter 3227). The letters in between contain
               reflections on a massive variety of subjects &#8211; literary and non-literary, public and private, local and global. They make available a
               great deal of new information about Southey&#8217;s views on literature, politics, religion and society; his work as Poet Laureate and
               engagement in public life and public controversy; his relationships with his contemporaries; his domestic life in Keswick; his extended
               family and social networks; his extensive reading; his working practices; his prolific output of poetry and prose; and his interactions
               with publishers and negotiation of the literary marketplace. They reveal Southey&#8217;s agonised response to the death of his son in April
               1816: &#8216;how large a part of my hopes &amp; happiness will be laid in the grave with Herbert&#8217; (Letter 2757). They show how the
               announcement, in autumn 1818, of Edith Southey&#8217;s eighth, and final, pregnancy only confirmed Southey in his conviction that his loss
               was &#8216;irreparable&#8217; and the new baby could not replace &#8216;that incomparable boy&#8217; (Letters 3203). They demonstrate how Southey used his
               influence to assist the careers of others, recruiting William Wilberforce&#8217;s help in an attempt to gain a consulship at Maranh&#227;o,
               Brazil, for Henry Koster (Letter 3168), for example, and providing &#163;10 from his own purse and raising money from Samuel Rogers and Earl
               Spencer to fund the impoverished young poet Herbert Knowles&#8217;s studies at Cambridge University (Letters 2855, 2858, 2866, 2879 and
               2887). The letters also touch on other matters of interest and concern to Southey, including tea drinking (Letter 3030); cats (Letter
               3031); the impact of the 1815 eruption of Mount Tambora on the world&#8217;s climate, fauna and flora (Letter 3056); the outbreak of typhus
               in the town of Keswick (Letter 3115); the discovery, by one of the Southey daughters, of an ancient bronze spear head on the slopes of
               Skiddaw (Letter 3117); the offer of the post of Librarian at the Society of Advocates, which Southey refused (Letter 3148); the chaotic
               relationship between William Wilberforce and his servants (Letter 3204); and the increasing rarity of bitterns in the Lake District, a
               scarcity not helped by the actions of a visiting Cambridge undergraduate, who shot, killed and ate one (Letter 3033). </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The 537 letters published here are proof that Southey remained a vigorous and indefatigable correspondent in mid life,
               even though the demands on his time were increasing apace. <title>Part Five</title> sees the continuation of established
               correspondences with friends and colleagues, including Mary Barker, Grosvenor Bedford, Andrew Bell, Joseph Cottle, John Wilson Croker,
               James Montgomery, John Murray, John Rickman, William Wilberforce, William Wordsworth and Charles Wynn. It provides compelling evidence
               of how the number and range of networks in which Southey was involved continued to expand in tandem with his personal and professional
               commitments. In 1817, for example, he wrote to the Prime Minister, Lord Liverpool (Letter 2947). Other new correspondents in this
               period include the ambitious young writers Caroline Bowles, Herbert Knowles and Chauncey Hare Townshend; the churchman John Jebb; the
               antiquarian Dawson Turner; the American inventor Horatio Gates Spafford; and, last but not least, Samuel Rogers and Helen Maria
               Williams, both established figures in the literary world. Moreover, although 537 letters by Southey survive from this period, letter
               fragments and references within surviving letters to ones that are now lost are reminders of the selective nature of any edition such
               as this and of the contingencies of literary history. What we have here are the remains of a much larger output. Southey&#8217;s letters to
               Coleridge, Peter Elmsley, Charles Lamb, Sharon Turner and William Wordsworth exist only in part, while other correspondences have been
               lost entirely and can now only be glimpsed in letters sent to others. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">In January 1816 Southey was forty-one years old and an established, though controversial, writer. He had been married
               since 1795 and fathered seven children, five of whom were still living &#8211; Edith May, Herbert, Bertha, Kate and Isabel. He had been
               resident at Greta Hall, on the outskirts of the market town of Keswick, since autumn 1803, though he had made occasional forays from
               home, touring the continent, for example, in autumn 1815. This pattern of Lake District residence punctuated by periods of travel was
               to continue throughout the later 1810s. His longest and most ambitious tour of the period took place in May&#8211;August 1817, when Southey
               journeyed through France, Switzerland, Italy, Germany and the Low Countries, accompanied by his friends, the artist Edward Nash and the
               landowner Humphrey Senhouse. Southey&#8217;s life was not, however, as &#8216;regular&#8217; and &#8216;monotonous&#8217; an existence as this might suggest (Letter
               3088). His 1817 continental tour, though a private undertaking, generated public controversy over what Southey had seen &#8211; or not seen &#8211;
               written in the visitors&#8217; book at Montanvert, and the resulting row over the so-called &#8216;Atheist&#8217; inscription inflamed his already
               antagonistic relationship with Percy Shelley (Letter 3004). Moreover, family tragedy and economic changes were to make Southey&#8217;s
               residence at Greta Hall less than secure. The death of his nine-year-old son in April 1816 made Southey long to escape from a house and
               landscape haunted by the child&#8217;s presence: the &#8216;wound will never close while I remain&#8217; in &#8216;this country&#8217; (Letter 2757). Although he
               eventually decided to stay put, the bankruptcy of his landlord in 1817 and uncertainty over the future ownership of the property
               threatened Southey&#8217;s continued tenancy of his home (Letter 2961). </p>
        <p rend="indent1">In 1816&#8211;1818 Southey was concerned &#8211; as he had been earlier in his career &#8211; with the local, national and international.
               His travels, documented in long letters to family and friends and in a journal, opened up new places, led to meetings with, amongst
               others, the writer and expert on Latin America Alexander Humboldt, and the educational reformer Johann Pestalozzi, and supplied fresh
               gossip about Princess Caroline, estranged wife of the Prince Regent, whose &#8216;infamous&#8217; conduct bore comparison &#8216;in history with
               Messalina and Joan of Naples&#8217; (Letter 3003). Foreign journeys also allowed Southey to indulge his book-buying habit and to enrich
               further the shelves of his substantial library. His letters anxiously track the progress of the volumes purchased on his 1817 tour and
               reveal that Southey enlisted the help of the London banker Nathan Meyer Rothschild to ensure they were safely conveyed back to Britain
               (Letter 3003). Moreover, even when he was at home in Keswick and hard at work, Southey was not cut off from the wider world. His
               voracious and wide reading in multiple languages, and his writing on a huge range of topics (from the history of Brazil to poems for
               his children) brought the world within the walls of his study. In the hours not spent at his desk, he socialised with prominent Keswick
               families, such as the Speddings of Mirehouse, and with local magnates such as the Earl of Lonsdale. In addition, Southey&#8217;s professional
               reputation brought an increasing stream of visitors, national and international, welcome and unwelcome, to his door. Between 1816 and
               1818 these included the publishers John Murray and William Blackwood, who arrived together in Murray&#8217;s carriage. Southey could not
               afford such a vehicle and he commented waspishly on this as yet another indication of &#8216;Maximus Murray&#8217;s&#8217; increasingly grand manner
               (Letter 3187). It also, of course, said much about the publisher&#8217;s financial standing and professional success. Overseas visitors
               included Samuel Heinrich Spiker, Librarian to the King of Prussia. Spiker, in his account of the meeting, marvelled at Southey&#8217;s
               library of &#8216;between 3 and 4000 volumes of the most select works in the Spanish and Portuguese languages, in the departments of history,
               statistics, and voyages, and travels&#8217; and described &#8216;the pleasant evening I passed in Mr. Southey&#8217;s family, as one of the most happy
               sections&#8217; of his tour of the United Kingdom.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Heinrich Spiker (1786&#8211;1858), <title>Travels
                     in England, Wales, and Scotland in the Year 1816</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, pp. 270, 272.</note> Other welcome guests
               included, in 1817, the factory owner and social reformer Robert Owen, &#8216;a very interesting personage &#8230; full of plans for the poor&#8217;, and
               the Harvard professor Edward Everett, the &#8216;most interesting person whom we have as yet seen this summer&#8217; (Letters 2859, 2908, 3191).
               Southey&#8217;s letters do more than just describe these occasions and individuals. Many of the links he forged with his visitors had been
               initiated, and were to be sustained in the future, via letter writing. His letters are thus evidence of the central role played by
               correspondence in Romantic period social networking. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Southey often expressed relief when the &#8216;succession of company&#8217; was over, when he could settle, as he explained in
               November 1817: </p>
        <quote>&#8230; to my winters work, with the probability of as few interruptions from without, as Bruin has when he rolls himself up in his cave,
               &amp; trusts to his paws till the spring. (Letter 3034)</quote>
        <p>As his letters reveal, Southey was as busy as ever in 1816&#8211;1818. His literary output continued to be prolific and diverse, covering
               domestic and international subjects, current affairs and the recent and the distant past. He contributed regularly to the
                  <title>Quarterly Review</title> and laboured on the <title>History of Brazil</title>, the second volume of which appeared in 1817.
               He produced an edition of Malory&#8217;s <title>Morte d&#8217; Arthur</title>, entitled <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title>
               (1817), and brought out fresh editions of his long poems <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> and <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                  Goths</title>. He continued to compose new poems, including the annual odes required of him as Poet Laureate and topical longer
               pieces such as <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> and <title>The Lay of the Laureate</title>, both published in 1816.
               Southey also accepted occasional commissions to write poems, including, in 1818, an epitaph for Ralph Broome, the nephew of his old
               friend James Burney and the novelist Fanny Burney (Letter 3070). He refused, however, numerous uninvited solicitations for verses.
               These included one of 1817 from an individual identified only as &#8216;N.T.P.&#8217;, who had importuned Southey to </p>
        <quote>&#8230; compose an acrostic for the writer to express his passion for Rebecca, a rival having lately got a head of him in consequence of
               having addressed some verses to the object of their affections &#8230; (Letter 3016)</quote>
        <p>&#8216;N.T.P.&#8217;s request was accompanied by 20 shillings, which Southey gave to charity. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">A high profile figure since the mid 1790s, Southey retained his appetite for controversy and, in his writings, engaged
               with acutely topical and contentious issues, including the need for effective censorship of the radical press, which attracted the
               opprobrium and ridicule of contemporaries such as Leigh Hunt and William Hazlitt. His letters reflect and provide new information about
               the disputes in which he was embroiled. They make it possible, for example, to track in detail Southey&#8217;s reaction to the <title>Wat
                  Tyler</title> furore, including his attempt to seek restitution by recourse to the law. They also refine current understanding of
               Southey&#8217;s reaction to being confronted, publicly, with the ghost of his radical youth. It has long been assumed that in spring 1817
               Southey responded to the <title>Wat Tyler</title> affair by publishing a letter in the <title>Courier</title> on 17 March 1817.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This belief almost certainly arose because of Cuthbert Southey&#8217;s handling of the letter to the
                  Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, which he misdated 17 March 1817 (see Letter 2946 of our edition). Cuthbert published this in
                  the main run of letters dealing with the furore over <title>Wat Tyler</title> and while he did not explicitly indicate the letter
                  had appeared in the <title>Courier</title>, he did not say it had not. See <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 252&#8211;255. </note> He did in fact write two letters for the newspaper: one addressed to William
               Smith, the radical MP who had used parliamentary privilege to attack Southey in a speech delivered in the House of Commons on 14 March
               1817 (Letter 2943), and a second letter addressed to the <title>Courier&#8217;s</title> editor (Letter 2946). They were sent by Southey to
               Charles Wynn, on 17 and 19 March respectively, with instructions to forward them to the <title>Courier</title> (Letters 2944 and 2948).
               However, as revealed here for the first time, Wynn was away and did not receive the letters and Southey&#8217;s instructions until his
               return. By then public interest had moved on and the moment for publishing either or both in a newspaper had passed. Neither letter
               appeared in the <title>Courier</title>. Instead, Southey reworked both into his pamphlet <title>A Letter to William Smith</title>,
               which appeared at the end of April 1817. New light, too, is cast here on the controversial memorandum sent by Southey to Lord Liverpool
               (dated 19 March 1817), which advocated the suppression of the radical press. It has hitherto never been published in full and we
               restore here a final paragraph omitted in the previously published version (Letter 2947). This reveals that Southey urged the Prime
               Minister both to censor the press, and to implement Robert Owen&#8217;s plans to tackle unemployment. It thus complicates understanding of
               Southey&#8217;s mid-life politics, suggesting that he was far from being a straightforward reactionary, however much he proclaimed his
               detestation of radicals and Whigs. By shedding fresh light on these and other controversies, the letters we publish here demonstrate
               that although the years 1816&#8211;1818 were important ones in Southey&#8217;s career and impacted on his longer-term reputation, they are yet to
               be fully documented or completely understood. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">While writing to the moment &#8211; be it to the Prime Minister, to newspapers or in the pages of the <title>Quarterly
                  Review</title> &#8211; remained important to Southey, he also had an eye ever on posterity. In an unpublished draft of <title>A Letter to
                  William Smith</title>, he described himself in the third person and predicted how generations to come would perceive him as one who
               &#8216;in an age of personality &#8230; abstained from satire&#8217; (Letter 2966). Many of his contemporaries would have disagreed. Yet confidence in
               his posthumous fame led Southey to plan for the future. In 1816&#8211;1818 he continued work on earlier uncompleted writings such as a
               sequence of inscriptions on the Peninsular War, and the longer poems <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title>, and &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;. He also
               laid the foundations for a series of major projects that he believed would underpin his reputation. These included a biography of John
               Wesley, which emerged out of an 1817 essay for the short-lived conservative journal the <title>Correspondent</title>; a full-scale
                  <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, for which Southey both sought out and was offered the papers of a series of eminent
               participants; and a project, inspired by Boethius, that mixed verse and &#8216;prose &#8230; in colloquy between Sir T More &amp; Meipsum&#8217;, and
               which eventually became <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829) (Letter 3042).
               The quest for fame sometimes took a wrong turn. Other projects planned in this period &#8211; notably a &#8216;desultory poem in blank verse&#8217;
               occasioned by the death of his son &#8211; were never finished (Letter 2969). The letters published here provide fresh evidence on how these
               and other writings did or did not come about and the reasons for this. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Key to Southey&#8217;s career in 1816&#8211;1818 was the importance that he placed upon his role as a writer and on the capacity of
               his poetry and prose to influence public life for the better, as he thought, both in the present and the future. This belief had been
               given fresh impetus by his appointment in 1813 as Poet Laureate and his determination to revitalise the post. The Laureateship had
               precipitated Southey&#8217;s return not just to poetry but to verses that engaged explicitly (rather than, as previously, in a coded fashion)
               with current affairs. This impacted on obviously topical pieces such as <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> and <title>The
                  Lay of the Laureate</title> (written to celebrate the marriage of the Princess Charlotte). It also inflected his other writings. As
               he explained, the &#8216;main object&#8217; of his Boethian-inspired, poetry-prose hybrid was &#8216;to show that we are rapidly approaching a <hi rend="ital">crisis</hi> in society&#8217; (Letter 3042). His prose, too, was galvanised and shaped by a similar preoccupation. He was, he
               explained, in writing on issues of current public concern for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, &#8216;giving my whole time and thought to
               these great subjects&#8217; in order to &#8216;take the lead in preparing &amp; informing the public&#8217; (Letter 3066). </p>
        <p rend="indent1">However, Southey did not have things his own way and contemporaries did not always agree with the information he wished
               to put before them. His ambitions for the Poet Laureateship were consistently thwarted by attacks from all sides and by the compromises
               forced on him. These included being obliged to continue producing annual odes, though he had taken the post in the belief that this
               custom had been abolished. His hatred of the task and growing overall discontent with the Poet Laureateship was encapsulated in the
               description of his New Year&#8217;s Ode for January 1819, on the death of Queen Charlotte, as &#8216;fitter to be bum-fiddled&#8217; (Letter 3221). Such
               relative powerlessness was also reflected in the titles given to Southey&#8217;s published works. In 1815&#8211;1816 he wanted to use
               &#8216;Belle-Alliance&#8217;, &#8216;anything but Waterloo&#8217;, in the title of his new, battlefield-visit poem in an attempt to expose the self-serving
               actions of the Duke of Wellington, who had given &#8216;the name of Waterloo &#8230; to the battle &#8230; in a spirit of the lowest &amp; vilest
               jealousy&#8217;. <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Thomas Southey, 17 December 1815, <title>The Collected Letters of
                     Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2684.</note> Politically well-connected friends and acquaintances cautioned against
               this, concerned that using the Prussian name for the battle would offend Wellington and lead to trouble. Southey eventually, not
               without considerable protest, caved in and the volume duly appeared in 1816 as <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Southey made a great deal of noise in his correspondence about wishing to publicly expose and humiliate individuals,
               such as William Smith, Henry Brougham, Leigh Hunt, Francis Jeffrey and the Duke of Wellington, whom he detested. Yet, in practice, his
               polemics were often moderated. William Gifford, for example, censored many of Southey&#8217;s contributions to the <title>Quarterly
                  Review</title>, a practice Southey loathed, railed against and was powerless to do anything about. Friends, whose advice Southey
               often asked, accepted and acted on, also impacted on his writing, though Southey tended to take their interventions with a grace not
               reserved for Gifford and his ilk. &#8216;I would&#8217;, he informed one of his oldest friends, Charles Wynn</p>
        <quote>&#8230; take reproof from you as a dog does blows from his master; &#8211; which same dog if he were struck by a stranger would make his teeth
               meet in the calf of his leg. (Letter 2976)</quote>
        <p>It was friends who, in 1817, urged him to remove any reference to duelling from <title>A Letter to William Smith</title>, on the
               grounds that Smith might be provoked to challenge the Poet Laureate (e.g. Letter 2976). Southey acted on their advice. The following
               year he began work on a public letter, a &#8216;Tender epistle&#8217;, prompted by Henry Brougham&#8217;s attack from the hustings on both himself and
               Wordsworth. Southey&#8217;s plan was to chastise publicly &#8216;a man who has &#8230; slandered me in the face of my neighbours&#8217; and to expose him &#8216;as
               he deserves to be exposed&#8217; (Letter 3167). Friends again dissuaded him. The &#8216;epistle&#8217; was abandoned and remained unpublished until 1821
               when sections &#8211; with Brougham&#8217;s name removed &#8211; appeared in the second edition of the Laureate ode <title>Carmen
                  Triumphale</title>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey, <title>Carmen Triumphale, For the Commencement of the Year
                     1814</title>, 2nd edn (London, 1821), pp. 45&#8211;53.</note> Southey&#8217;s letters thus reveal a significant difference between what he
               proclaimed he would do and what he actually ended up publishing. In so doing, they show how even the most combative of writers had to
               negotiate the transition of their writings into a hostile, potentially fatal, public sphere. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The letters we publish here make available important new information about Southey&#8217;s writing life and his intersections
               with contemporaries drawn from many different walks of life, including literature, politics and religion. They show his career in
               progress, reveal that it was more complex than has previously been thought, and provide compelling evidence about how his works were
               shaped and reshaped by external pressures that he could not always control or defeat. They thus refine our understanding both of
               Southey and of the ways in which individual writers came to terms with the complex and contentious culture of the late 1810s.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>