<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3223</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4494</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3223. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 22 December 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3223" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3223.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                  48123D. ALS; 3p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 323&#8211;325 [in part; misdated 30 November 1818].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3223" type="letter">
        <head>3223. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1818-12-22">22 December 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                  48123D. ALS; 3p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 323&#8211;325 [in part; misdated 30 November 1818].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-12-22"> 22 Dec. 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was truly glad to hear of your daughters recovery.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had a growing family of five daughters:
                  Charlotte (1807&#8211;1869); Mary (1808&#8211;1869); Harriet (1812&#8211;1878); Emma (1814&#8211;1824) and
                  Sidney (1818&#8211;1867); and one son, Watkin (1816&#8211;1832). His final child was Charles
                  (1822&#8211;1896).</note> I have been in a storm at sea in a Spanish vessel,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to Southey&#8217;s journey to Spain
                  in 1795; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 29 January [1796],
                     <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter
                  146.</note> &#8211; &amp; the feeling when the weather had so sensibly abated that the
               danger was over, is the only one I can compare to that which is felt in a case like
               yours upon the first assurance <del>x</del> that the disease is giving way. Those
               writers who speak of childhood, or even of youth, as the happiest season of life seem
               to me to speak with little reason. There is indeed an exemption from the cares of the
               world, &amp; from those anxieties which shake us to the very centre. But as far as my
               own experience goes, when we are exempt from trials of this <del>kind</del> {nature},
               our happiness as we grow older is more in quantity &amp; <del>x</del> higher in
               degree as well as in kind. What hopes we have are no longer accompanied with
               uneasiness, or restless desires; &#8211; the way before us is no longer uncertain, &#8211; we see
               to the end of our journey; the acquisition of knowledge becomes more &amp; more
               delightful, &amp; the appetite for it may truly be said to grow with what it feeds
               on. And as we set our thoughts &amp; hearts in order for another world, the prospect
               of that world becomes a source of deeper <del>xxxxxxxx</del> delight than any thing
               which this <del>world</del> could administer to an immortal spirit. On the other hand
               we are vulnerable out of our-selves &#8211; &amp; you &amp; I are reaching that time of
               life in which the losses which we have to endure will be so many amputations, &#8211; the
               wound may heal but the mutilation will always be felt. Not to speak of more vital
               afflictions, the loss of a familiar friend casts a shade over the remembrance of
               every thing in which he was associated. &#8211; You &amp; I my dear Wynn are less to each
               other than we were in old times, &#8211; years pass away without our meeting, nor is it at
               all likely that we shall ever again see as much of each other in this world, as we
               used to do in the course of one short term at Oxford. And yet he who is to be the
               survivor will one day feel how much we are to each other even now, &#8211; when all those
               recollections which he now loves to invite &amp; dwell upon will come to him like
               spectres.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> However I hope that both you &amp; I may be permitted to do something
               more before we are removed. And I cannot but hope that you will take upon yourself a
               conspicuous part in that reformation of the criminal laws, which cannot much longer
               be delayed, &amp; which will be infinitely better in your hands than in
                  Romilly&#8217;s.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Samuel Romilly
                  (1757&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), legal reformer and MP for Horsham 1807&#8211;1808,
                  Wareham 1808&#8211;1812, Arundel 1812&#8211;1818 and Westminster June&#8211;November 1818. He had
                  been Solicitor-General 1806&#8211;1807. Romilly committed suicide on 2 November
                  1818.</note> Nor do I know any one (setting all personal feelings aside) by whom
               it could so fitly be taken up. I thought very unfavourably of Sir S. Romilly &amp; of
               his projects; &#8211; that speech of Franklands<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">On 29 March 1811 the MP for Thirsk 1801&#8211;1815, William Frankland (1761&#8211;1815),
                  had spoken against a bill proposed by Samuel Romilly, who, amongst other things,
                  wished to restrict the number of crimes punishable by the death penalty.
                  Frankland&#8217;s speech had been reported approvingly by Southey in the
                     <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 151&#8211;162.</note>
               was perfectly conclusive to my mind. But that alterations are necessary is certain,
               &amp; the late trials for forgery show that they must be made, &#8211; even now with a bad
               grace, &#8211; but with a worse <del>than</del> the longer they are delayed. &#8211; To me it has
               long appeared a safe <del>xxx</del> proposition that the punishment of death is
               misapplied whenever the general feeling that it excites is that of compassion for the
               criminal. &#8211; A man &amp; woman were executed for coining at the same time with Patch;
               &#8211; now what an offence was this to the common sense of justice!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The suspension of cash payments in 1797 led the
                  Bank of England, in an attempt to increase confidence in its paper banknotes, to
                  prosecute 870 people for forgery over the next twenty years, over 300 of whom were
                  hanged. On 5 December and 7 December 1818 four men accused of forgery were
                  acquitted, leading to charges that the law was out of step with popular feeling on
                  the matter, e.g. <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 10 December 1818. The notorious
                  case to which Southey refers is that of 8 April 1806, when, at Horsemonger Lane
                  jail in Southwark, the husband and wife, Benjamin and Sarah Herring, were hanged,
                  alongside the notorious murderer Richard Patch (c. 1770&#8211;1806, <title>DNB</title>),
                  although their crime was forging small denomination coins. </note> There is
               undoubtedly at this time a settled purpose among the Revolutionists to bring the laws
               into contempt &amp; hatred. &#8211; &amp; to a very great degree it has succeeded. The more
               reason therefore that where they are <del>shown as</del> plainly objectionable they
               should be revised. &#8211; But for the principle of making the sentence in all cases
               proportionate to the crime, &amp; the execution certain, &#8211; nothing, in my judgement
               can be more impracticable, &amp; I am sure nothing could lead to greater injustice
               than an attempt to effect it. The sentence must be sufficient for the <del>worst
                  state</del> {highest degree} of the crime, &amp; a discretionary power
                  <del>given</del> allowed for tempering it to the level of the lowest. &#8211; You would
               take up the matter with a due sense of its difficulty, &amp; with every possible
               advantage of character both in the House &amp; in the country, &#8211; &amp; moreover the
               disposition of the Ministers ought to be, &amp; I really should suppose would be in
               your favour. If the business be suffered to fall into the hands of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>, you know what mischief
               might be apprehended, &#8211; <del>xx</del> he would embark in any thing for the sake of
                  <del>un</del>popularity, &amp; in nothing is he more likely to embark as this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There were some wretched verses in the Courier the other day<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A poem entitled &#8216;The Visit&#8217;, by &#8216;O&#8217;, had
                  appeared in the <title>Courier</title>, 14 December 1818. It was a satire on the
                  leaders of the opposition and included the lines &#8216;For too little the spokesman is
                  W&#8211;nn for our ends,/ And too little the gentleman Br&#8211;m&#8217;.</note> saying that you
               were not spokesman enough to become leader of the opposition,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn was the leader in the House of Commons of the Grenvillite
                  opposition group, who had decided to split away from the Whigs in July 1817; he
                  was well aware of his own deficiencies as a speaker, which were not helped by his
                  high, piping voice. Brougham was not the official leader of the Whigs, but he was
                  one of their most forceful figures in the House of Commons. He was a member of a
                  long-established landed dynasty, based at Brougham Hall, near Penrith, which
                  claimed to have been established in the area since the 11th century. But Brougham
                  was often perceived to be too ambitious and combative to be considered a
                  gentleman.</note> &amp; that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> was not gentleman enough. You would be pleased to see that they
               could say nothing worse of you. <del>I was xxxxx with</del> No doubt you have seen
               the Winchester pamphlett, &#8211; &amp; the statement concerning the Croydon charity.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham had been campaigning since 1816
                  against the abuse of funds by charities and in 1818 the Charity Commission was set
                  up, initially to examine those charities providing for the education of the poor.
                  Brougham vehemently objected to its limited powers and scope in his <title>Letter
                     to Samuel Romilly, M.P. from Henry Brougham, Esq. M.P., F.R.S. Upon the Abuse
                     of Charities</title> (1818). This pamphlet (pp. 51&#8211;53) contained some stinging
                  criticism that Winchester College, founded in 1382 to educate the &#8216;poor and
                  indigent&#8217;, was attended in the main by the sons of by rich men. Liscombe Clarke
                  (d. 1841) defended the College in <title>A Letter to H. Brougham Esq. &#8230;: in Reply
                     to the Strictures on Winchester College Contained in his Letter to Sir Samuel
                     Romilly M.P.</title> (1818); and William Lisle Bowles did the same in
                     <title>Vindiciae Wykehamicae; or, a Vindication of Winchester College, in a
                     Letter to H. Brougham Esq., Occasioned by his Letter to Sir S. Romilly, on
                     Charitable Abuses</title> (1818). Brougham&#8217;s pamphlet (e.g. pp. 16, 28) also
                  had much to say on the abuse of charities in Croydon, including the Whitgift
                  Foundation. Defences of their conduct included John Ireland (1761&#8211;1842;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Letter to Henry Brougham, Esq. M.P.</title>
                  (1818). Southey (correctly) perceived Brougham&#8217;s actions as an attack on the
                  Church of England and an attempt to remove some of its endowments for use in state
                  education.</note> A commission with such powers as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> required &amp; with
               himself at the head of it would have been a more intolerable <del>xxx</del>
                  {<del>xx</del> evil} than any thing which has existed in this country since the
               Committee of Sequestration.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1643,
                  during the Civil War, the Sequestration Committee was created by parliament as a
                  means of confiscating the estates of royalists.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written upon the Copy right question,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 196&#8211;213. Southey argued for an increase in
                  the period of copyright and against the requirement to donate a copy of a new
                  publication to eleven university and other libraries.</note> &#8211; &amp; had you been
               in town &#8211; the proofs should have been submitted to you. They have however been shown
               to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> for his
               approbation &amp; correction. I got a little angry, &amp; could not help expending a
               little whipcord upon <del>that</del> Mr Professor Christian, who ought to be sent to
               his relations upon Pitcairns Island.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Christian (1758&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), Downing Professor of the
                  Laws of England at Cambridge University, published a <title>Vindication of the
                     Right of the Universities of the United Kingdom to a Copy of Every New
                     Publication</title> (1818) &#8211; it was one of the items savaged by Southey in his
                  article &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217; (especially at 200&#8211;206). Christian&#8217;s
                  brother was Fletcher Christian (1764&#8211;1793; <title>DNB</title>), mutineer on
                     HMS<title> Bounty</title> who had, it was discovered in 1812, founded a colony
                  of mutineers and native people on Pitcairn Island. </note> At the end of the
               article I have said something upon the exceeding justice of the law which has taken
               from us the perpetual copy right of our own works. Upon this no man has more cause to
               speak feelingly.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey argued that
                  authors had a perpetual copyright in their works under the common law, until a
                  legal decision by the House of Lords in 1774, in his &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright
                  Act&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 199. This point had been
                  much disputed for the previous thirty years. At the end of his article Southey
                  pleaded for the &#8216;common and natural right&#8217; to perpetual copyright to be restored
                  (213).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you my dear Wynn</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>