<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3207</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4478</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3207. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 10 November 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3207.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3207" type="letter">
        <head>3207. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1818-11-10">10 November 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
                  Postmark: E/ 13 NO 13/ 1818<lb /> Endorsements: 10 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1818;
                  10 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1818<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The lowering of the pulse which led me to drink your honours health
               in a glass of gin was not produced by green tea, which, as you know I never take at
               breakfast, nor tea of any kind, if there be any thing else to be had. It came on
               without any assignable cause, &amp; went off upon the application of the honest dram.
               Green tea has had this effect upon some half a score times in my life, more
               particularly when I have taken it in a morning. It is indeed, between ourselves, a
               matter of surprize {to me} that this bodily machine of mine should have continued its
               operations with so few derangements, <del>considering</del> knowing, as I well do,
               its excessive susceptibility to many deranging causes. The nitrous oxyd approached
               nearer to the notion of a <hi rend="ital">neurometer</hi> than any thing which
                  <del>xxxxxx</del> perhaps could be desired, &amp; I was acted upon by a far
               smaller dose than any person <del>xx</del> upon whom it had ever been tried, when I
               was in the habit of taking it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey took
                  nitrous oxide at the Pneumatic Institution in Bristol in 1799 under the
                  supervision of Humphry Davy. For Southey&#8217;s ecstatic response to his first dose,
                  see Southey to Thomas Southey, 12 July 1799, <title>The Collected Letters of
                     Robert Southey. Part 2</title>, Letter 421.</note> &#8211; If I did not vary my
               pursuits &amp; carry on many works of a totally different kind at once, I should soon
               be incapable of <del>xxxx</del> proceeding with any, so surely does it disturb my
               sleep, &amp; affect my dreams, if I dwell upon one with any continuous attention. The
               truth is that tho some persons whose knowledge of me is scarcely skin-deep suppose I
               have no nerves because I have great self controul as far as regards the surface, &#8211; if
               it were not for great self management, &amp; what may be called a strict intellectual
               regimen, I should very soon be in a deplorable state of what is called nervous
               disease, &amp; this would have been the case any time during the last twenty
               years.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank God I am well at present, &#8211; &amp; well employed: <del>as
                  far</del> Brazil &amp; Wesley both in the press,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The last volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810&#8211;1819) and his <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of
                     Methodism</title> (1820). </note> &#8211; a paper for the QR in hand,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">One of three articles for the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title> on which Southey worked in late 1818 (probably the first): a
                  review, published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549&#8211;591, of
                  Haydon&#8217;s <title>New Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they
                     Offer for the Encouragement of Painting</title> (1818); an article on the
                  &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217;, published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21
                  (January 1819), 196&#8211;219; and an article &#8216;Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris&#8217; which
                  appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819),<title />359&#8211;398. </note> &amp; Oliver Newman now seriously resumed,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s New England epic poem, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;. It
                  remained unfinished and a fragment was published posthumously in 1845; see
                     <title>Oliver Newman: a New England Tale (Unfinished): with Other Poetical
                     Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;92.</note> &#8211; while for light reading I am
               going thro Souths Sermons,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert South
                  (1634&#8211;1716; <title>DNB</title>), controversial Hugh Church clergyman. His
                     <title>Twelve Sermons Preached upon Several Occasions</title> (1692) was much
                  reprinted and expanded.</note> &amp; the whole British &amp; Irish part of the
               Acta Sanctorum.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Acta
                     Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), a massive, 53&#8211;volume, compendium of
                  hagiographies, which Southey had bought in Brussels in 1817, had reached Keswick
                  in August 1818. It was no. 207 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
               I am quite persuaded however <del>xx</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn"> Murraymagne</ref> may boast of his
               liberal payment, that my time might be more profitably employed than in working for
               him, &amp; so I have told him for his comfort.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had received &#163;150 (and advice from Murray on how to plan his articles)
                  for his review of <title>Memoirs, Illustrative of the Life and Writings of John
                     Evelyn</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 1&#8211;54,
                  and his essay &#8216;On the Means of Improving the People&#8217;, which also appeared in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 79&#8211;118 (published 26
                  September 1818). Southey had made his displeasure known in a letter to John
                  Murray, 7 October 1818, Letter 3201.</note> When first this <del>mighty</del>
                  Maecenas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Cilnius Maecenas (68&#8211;8 BC),
                  Roman patron of the arts.</note> proffered me twenty guineas a sheet instead of
                  ten,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">When Southey reviewed various
                  biographies of the naval hero, Horatio Nelson (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262.</note> I told him
               such consideration could make no possible difference in my writing, for I always
               wrote as well as I could. By what he afterwards said I really gave him credit for
               understanding me &amp; for believing me, &#8211; but were you to see his letters, you would
               marvel at my patience. However it would be ridiculous to be offended by such
               egregious vanity, &#8211; especially as I believe he respects me as much as he is capable
               of respecting anybody. He had grace enough to confess when he was here that his first
               number would have failed had it not been for me.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had contributed an &#8216;Account of the Baptist Missionary
                  Society&#8217; to <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 1 (February 1809), 193&#8211;226.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Reviewing is the only work which I flag over: &#8211; it is like going to
               an exercise, &#8211; mere task work, &amp; therefore it takes up twice or thrice the time
               that any composition would do in which my heart was engaged. If I had no reviewing I
               could in twelve months begin &amp; finish a long poem, &#8211; from laying down the first
               timber to the fair launch of the vessel, &#8211; &amp; yet go on with my historical works.
               The time which four articles require would finish D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Daniel
                  Dove,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The book of comic materials that
                  Southey had, since their schooldays, dreamed of writing with Bedford. The
                  collaboration never bore fruit in a jointly-authored book but did lead to
                  Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor</title> (1834&#8211;1847).</note> &amp; judge you whether it
               would not be more worthily employed, &amp; with a chance of much greater emolument.
               But enough of this. This quarter &amp; the next I must work for Maecenas, &#8211; but
               afterwards I will do no more for him than just to keep <del>xxxx</del> a place in the
               Review for my own convenience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the MSS. of Wesley which passed thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> hands while you were absent
               there was a chapter<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 9, <title>The
                     Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London,
                  1820), I, pp. 305&#8211;336.</note> which I wished you to have seen, because both in
               matter &amp; manner it is among the best things I have written. It contained a view
               of our religious history down to the accession of the present family, &#8211; not the facts
               but the spirit of the history. You will be pleased {to see} how I have relieved &amp;
               diversified this book, which will be as elaborate as a Dutchmans work &amp; as
               entertaining as a Frenchmans, bearing withall in its fidelity &amp; perfect freedom
               the true stamp of R.S. But of that person &amp; his concerns <hi rend="ital">sat.
                  superque</hi>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Enough and more than
                  enough&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So you are to have another Westminster Election.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The Westminster constituency had been hotly-contested
                  at the general election of 1818, with the poll only concluding after 15 days of
                  voting. One of the two elected MPs, the Whig lawyer, Sir Samuel Romilly
                  (1757&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), killed himself on 2 November 1818, so
                  necessitating a by-election. Brougham, who sat for the small, corrupt, borough of
                  Winchelsea, had been defeated in his attempt to win a prestigious county seat in
                  Westmorland in 1818. However, he did not contest Westminster in the ensuing
                  by-election.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> I dare say will
               offer himself. I wonder <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>
               did not propose to me to review his letter to Sir S Romilly,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham&#8217;s <title>A Letter to Sir Samuel Romilly, M.P. from Henry
                     Brougham, Esq. M.P., F.R.S. upon the Abuse of Charities</title> (1818).</note>
               &#8211; a service indeed for which I should have offered myself if <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Townsend</ref> had not been here
               to occupy the very time that <del>ought</del> would have been required for it.
               Romilly seems clearly a case of brain fever.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Romilly became ill after the death of his wife, Anne (1773&#8211;1818), on 29 October
                  1818, and cut his throat.</note> But it is remarkable that he &amp; Whitbread
               &amp; Paul should all have laid violent hands upon themselves.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), the
                  leading Whig politician, also cut his throat, on 6 July 1815, after a period of
                  declining health. James Paull (1770&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), briefly MP for
                  Newtown, Isle of Wight 1805&#8211;1806, was best known for his criticisms of Marquess
                  Wellesley&#8217;s conduct as Governor-General of India 1798&#8211;1805. He, too, cut his
                  throat, on 15 April 1808, after gambling losses and increasing signs of
                  derangement.</note> If one or two {more} of the leading Anarchists were to follow
               the example it would look very much like a Judicial dispensation. The state has lost
               nothing.</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8211;&#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I did my best about Beresford, &amp; should have served him if
               earnestness in the application could have done it.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been attempting to find a post in the civil service for
                  an old Westminster schoolfellow Charles Griffis Beresford (dates unknown).</note>
               But <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">R.</ref> had nothing in his power.
               Poor fellow, it is a dismal thing to be cast upon the world at his time of life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your trouble about the promissory note.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been induced by the Ballantynes, and by
                  their silent partner Walter Scott, to take a 1/12th financial share (valued at
                  &#163;209) in the publication to which they invited him to contribute &#8211; the
                     <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. Southey wrote the historical sections
                  in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808&#8211;1811</title> (1810&#8211;1813). But he
                  received none of the profits from these editions, was not paid for his final
                  contribution, to the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813),
                  and feared his share in the <title>Register</title> had become worthless. However,
                  unexpectedly, the Ballantynes had repaid Southey&#8217;s investment.</note> If it be
               duly paid, as I have no reason to doubt, it will have been a very unexpected
               recovery. I want now to provide against that inability which may any day &#8211; or any
               moment overtake me. &#8211; You are not mistaken in thinking that the last three years have
               considerably changed me &#8211; the outside remains pretty much the same, but it is far
               otherwise within. If hitherto the day has been sufficient for the labour, as well as
               the labour for the day, I now feel that it cannot always, &amp; possibly may not long
               be so. Were I dead there would be a provision for my family, which tho not such as I
               yet hope to make it, would yet be a respectable one. But if I were unable to work,
               half my ways &amp; means would instantly be cut off,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">If Southey could not work, he would lose the prospect of future
                  earnings from writing for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> and future works of
                  prose and poetry. But he would still have his government pension of &#163;200 p.a., his
                  salary as Poet Laureate of &#163;100 p.a. and any income from new editions of his
                  published works.</note> &#8211; &amp; the whole of them are needed. Such thoughts did
               not use to visit me. My spirits retain their strength, &#8211; but they have lost their
               buoyancy, &amp; that for ever. I should be the better for travelling, but that is not
               in my power. At present the press fetters me, &amp; if it did not, I could not afford
               to be spending money when I ought to be earning it. But I shall work the harder to
               enable me so to do</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-11-10">10 Nov. 1818</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>