<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2999</idno><idno type="nines">rce4270</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2999. Robert Southey to Edith
                  Southey, 28 May 1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2999.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>.  Previously  published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                  6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 264–267 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2999" type="letter"><head>2999. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith
                  Southey</ref>, <date when="1817-05-28">28 May 1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: Angleterre/ To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland<lb/> Stamped: [illegible]/
                  ONPARLIER; SS; PP<lb/> Postmarks: FPO/ JU 7/ 1817; [partial] JU/ 7 <lb/> MS:
                  British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 264–267 [in part].</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName>Neufchatel.</placeName></address><date when="1817-05-28"> Wednesday. 28 May. 1817.</date></dateline><salute> My dear Edith</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Yesterday we entered Switzerland, &amp; reached this place after a
               weeks journey from Paris without let, hindrance accident, or inconvenience of any
               kind.</p><p rend="indent1"> We left Paris at six o clock on the <del>Tuesday</del> Wednesday, not
               having been able to see the Thulleries on Tuesday as we had proposed. Tuesday
               therefore we dined with <ref type="m" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">Kenyon</ref>, whose wife<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Susan Kenyon (d. 1818), Kenyon’s first wife,
                  who died in Naples during their prolonged continental tour.</note> is not a
               prepossessing personage. I shall hurry over our route, not to repeat here what is
               minutely related in my journal. <del>Tuesday</del> {Wednesday} to Fontainbleau,
                  <del>Tuesday</del> Thursday to Joigny Friday to Rouering, Saturday to Dijon,
               Sunday to Besançon, Monday to Pontarlier &amp; Tuesday to this city, – where we have
               opened our portmanteaus, consigned our unclean wardrobe to the Blanchisseuses, are
               taking a days rest. The season is unusually backward &amp; cold. On the way to Paris
               we found the country in great want of rain, &amp; since we left Paris it has been
               equally in want of sunshine, yet our weather has been so far favourable that we have
               lost nothing in consequence of the occasional showers. Here there is not the
               appearance of a leaf upon the vines; in other respects the country is in full beauty,
               the trees having their richest verdure. Tomorrow we go to Yverdon &amp; see
                  Pestalozzi.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Swiss educational
                  reformer, Johann Heinrich Pestalozzi (1746–1827). The ‘Pestalozzi Method’ argued
                  that children should learn through activity and through things, rather than words.
                  As part of this, children should be free to pursue their own interests and draw
                  their own conclusions.</note> Friday to Lausanne where I shall find M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S. Canning<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Stratford
                  Canning, 1st Viscount Stratford de Redcliffe (1786–1880; <title>DNB</title>),
                  diplomat. At this time he was Envoy Extraordinary and Minister-Plenipotentiary to
                  Switzerland 1814–1820.</note> the Embassador to whom I have a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T. Ackland</ref>, &amp; near Lausanne is Miss Bigg with her
               sister M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Awdrey<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  Awdry family were John Awdry (1766–1844), solicitor in Reybridge and his wife
                  Jane, née Bigg-Wither (1770–1845), sister of Herbert Hill’s wife, Catherine. ‘Miss
                  Bigg’ was a third, unmarried sister, Alethea Bigg (1777–1847). Southey visited
                  them at Echichens on 1–3 June and 29 June-3 July.</note> &amp; her family, – your
               acquaintance Alethea for whom you may remember <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Marquis
                  Bruin</ref> paid you the <del>xxxx</del> compliment of mistaking
               you. I shall be glad to meet her at this distance from England. – In the police book
               here, I find the names of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General Peachy</ref>, Sotheby,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">William Sotheby (1757–1833;
                     <title>DNB</title>), poet and translator.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T Ackland</ref>, – &amp; only a fortnight before us,
                  Haygarth.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Haygarth (1784–1825),
                  poet and travel writer, son of the physician, John Haygarth (1740–1827;
                     <title>DNB</title>).</note> From Lausanne to Geneva &amp; thence by Chamberry
               &amp; the Mount Cenis<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A mountain pass
                  between France and Italy, the traversal of which had been eased by a road
                  constructed between 1803 and 1810.</note> pass into Italy. Probably my next letter
               will be from Turin, – we return by the Simplon<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Simplon pass, in the Swiss Alps, between Brig and Domodossola in Italy.
               </note> to Geneva where I shall expect to find a letter from you, you will well know
               how anxiously.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is with the greatest difficulty that I find time to keep a
               journal. We rise at five, &amp; have travelled from ten to twelve hours every day,
               going about twenty miles before breakfast. Hunger would hardly permit us to do any
               thing in the way of writing before dinner, if there were not always something to see
               while dinner is preparing; – &amp; after dinner it requires an effort of heroic
               virtue to resist the pleasures of wine &amp; conversation, &amp; it becomes almost
               impossible upon taking the pen in hand to resist sleep. This morning we lay in bed
               till seven, that we might have the full enjoyment of a whole holyday. I remember at
               Westminster <del>this was</del> the chief gratification which a whole holyday or a
               Sunday afforded, was that of lying abed till breakfast was ready at nine o clock.</p><p rend="indent1"> Our windows are within a stones throw of the Lake, &amp; we see the
               Alps across it. The Lake is like a sea in its colour, its waves, &amp; its voice, –
               of which we are of course within hearing. The Alps of which we have the whole extent
               in view, cannot be less than fifty miles distant in the nearest point, directly
               across the Lake, &amp; Mont Blanc, which is at the extremity on the right, about
               fourscore. If our horizon at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> were wide enough I
               could sometimes show you the Alps in the clouds. They have precisely the appearance
               of white cumulated clouds at the verge of the sky, resting upon the earth, &amp;
               silvered with sunshine; &amp; from such clouds they are only to be distinguished by
               their definite outline &amp; permanent forms. It is idle to compare this country with
               our own, – or rather it would be worse than idle to form any comparison for the
               purpose of depreciating either. Part of our yesterdays journey was so like
               Cumberland, that I could have fancied myself within an hours walk of home; &amp; this
               forced upon me such a sense of time, distance &amp; separation, that the tears were
               more than once ready to break loose. The mountains through which we passed from
               Pontarlier to this place, rise behind the town, &amp; in that direction the view, as
                  <del>for xx</del> {to its} natural objects might be English. A huge harbour, or
               still better an arm of the sea, with such a sky as I have described will give you a
               full idea of the rest.</p><p rend="indent1"> We hear dismal stories of famine &amp; distress, – but the scene
               continually recedes as we approach it, nor have we seen any indication of it
               whatever. From all that I can collect, the bad harvest of last year has acted here as
               it does in England &amp; must every where, it presses severely upon that class of
               persons who stood in need of economy before, &amp; who with economy had a little to
               spare for others. There are plenty of beggars throughout France, &amp; much squalid
               poverty, but the children of the peasantry are as hale, &amp; apparently as well fed,
               as far as all appearances of flesh &amp; blood may be trusted, as those in our own
               country. – What I have seen of France, – about 500 miles, from Calais to Pontarlier,
               is on the whole, less <del>xx</del> interesting than an equal distance in G Britain
               would appear to a foreign traveller, I mean that he would meet with a country more
               generally beautiful, finer parts, &amp; better towns. But there have been very fine
               parts upon this journey, with a character &amp; beauty of their own. In Switzerland
               every step must be interesting, &amp; go in what direction you will, it is impossible
               to go wrong.</p><p rend="indent1"> Nothing surprised me more in France than that there should be no
               middleaged women among the peasantry; they appear to pass at once from youth to
               hagged old age, &amp; it is no exaggeration to say that they look like so many living
               &amp; moving mummies. Fond as they are of finery in youth <del>&amp; xxxxx xxx</del>
               for they are then tricked out in all the colours of the rainbow, in old age their
               dress is as wretched &amp; squalid as their appearance. I see nothing among them of
               the gaiety of which we have heard so much in former times. Not a single party have we
               seen dancing throughout the whole journey, – the weather indeed has been unusually
               cold, but certainly not such as would check the propensities of a light-heeled
               generation, if they <del>xxx</del> were as fond of a dance as their light hearted
               progenitors. I must say to their credit that we have uniformly met with civility, –
               not the slightest insult or incivility of any kind has been offered to us, &amp; if
               some extortion has been practised rather generally at the Hotels, it is no more than
               what is done every where, &amp; perhaps more in England than any where else.</p><p rend="indent1"> But I must conclude. It is now three o clock &amp; I have been
               closely employed since breakfast in bringing up my journal &amp; in writing only this
               letter, – which however you must remember in any common handwriting would make two or
               three respectable epistles. My wolf is in great force &amp; devours every thing which
               is set before him. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> performs tolerably well, &amp;
               as for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> he eats five eggs at breakfast.</p><p rend="indent1"> God bless you give my love to all.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2">yr</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>