<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3038</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4309</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3038. Robert Southey to [John Kenyon], 17 November 1817 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3038" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3038.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.231. AL; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 75&#8211;78. Note on MS:
                  The manuscript is a fragment: the final paragraph and closing signature are missing. This missing text is here supplied from
                  Warter.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3038" type="letter">
        <head>3038. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">John Kenyon</ref>], <date when="1817-11-17">17 November 1817 </date>
          </head><p>Stamped: [partial] WICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: [partial, illegible]<lb /> Endorsement:
                     N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1.<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.231. AL; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 75&#8211;78.<lb /> Note on MS:
                  The manuscript is a fragment: the final paragraph and closing signature are missing. This missing text is here supplied from
                  Warter.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-11-17"> 17 Nov. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am truly obliged to you for the trouble you have taken in procuring for me my old friend Martin Dobrizhoffer,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae
                     Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> of whom I have been ten years vainly in
               search. It will come in excellent time, just when I shall be composing a chapter<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 38 of
                     <title>History of Brazil</title> (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 374&#8211;441.</note> upon the equestrian tribes, the chief <del>of
                  which</del> materials for which are taken from this Jesuit, the most entertaining &amp; most interesting of all the missionary
               writers. The last volume of my history is now in the press, &amp; from this time forward it will form part of every days business till
               I shall have compleated the laborious work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our journey was prosperous in all points, without any accident of any kind, or any unpleasant delay. In the Val de
                  Triens<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">This incident occurred when Southey&#8217;s party breakfasted at Trient in the Valais,
                  Switzerland on 25 June 1817.</note> I found your name written in pencil on the wainscot of the little cabin in which travellers are
               entertained, &#8211; immediately under it I pencilled my own &amp; those of my companions, &#8211; &amp; if any person finds as much pleasure in
               seeing this memorial, as I did in seeing yours, it may be reckoned among my succesful writings. We entered Switzerland by Pontarlier
               &amp; Neufchatel, from thence to Lausanne, finding it too early to cross S Gothard;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The St
                  Gotthard Pass connects the northern, German-speaking area of Switzerland with the southern, Italian-speaking part, and opens the
                  route to Italy.</note> then to Geneva, &amp; turning aside from Chamberry to visit the Chartreuse<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Head monastery of the Carthusian order, founded 1084; located high in an Alpine valley north of Grenoble.</note> (one
               of the finest objects in our route) proceeded by Mount Cenis<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A mountain pass between France and
                  Italy.</note> to Turin &amp; Milan. This was our farthest point. We were three days at Como, &#8211; but went no higher than the fork of
               the lake at Bellaggio, which must certainly be the finest of all Lake stations. Yet as a Lake Lugano may perhaps be preferred to Como,
               &#8211; &amp; the Maggiore where we<del>r</del> crost from Laveno is equal to either. We returned into Switzerland by the Simplon,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Simplon pass, in the Swiss Alps, between Brig and Domodossola in Italy.</note>
          <del>which</del> magnificent as it is {it} impressed me on the whole not so much as the pass of Mount Cenis, which nobody speaks of &#8211;
               Chamounix we took from Martigny, going &amp; returning by the Tete Noir. The Col de Balm was not passable, &#8211; &amp; as we returned to
               Martigny because we were bound to Echichens, near Morges, where I had some friends<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry
                  (1766&#8211;1844), solicitor in Reybridge and husband of Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife, Catherine.
                  Southey&#8217;s party visited them at Echichens, Switzerland on 1&#8211;3 June 1817 and returned again for the visit Southey mentions on 30
                  June&#8211;3 July.</note> to visit. We halted with t[MS torn] three days, &#8211; a very pleasant resting place: Then made for Berne, &amp;
               sen[MS torn] our carriage from that city to Zurich struck into the Oberland, where at Unterseen Hans Roth<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Earlier in the year Hans Roth (dates unknown) had acted as a guide to Southey, Senhouse and Nash for about ten days
                  on their walking tour in central Switzerland.</note> was added to our company. On our way home we went a step out of the road to see
               the Danube at Donauschingen, then thro the Black Forest to Friburg, looked at Strasburg &amp; returned the same day to Kohl,
                  <del>saw</del> went into the dungeons of the Secret Tribunal at Baden-Baden,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  Vehmgericht, or Secret Tribunal, was a court that met in Westphalia from the fourteenth to the sixteenth centuries to suppress major
                  crimes, especially heresy and witchcraft. It featured prominently in German and British Gothic novels and plays.</note> &amp;
               shuddered at seeing the doors of solid stone a foot in thickness; &#8211; Rastadt Carlsruhe, Heidelberg, Manheim Frankfurt, Mentz &#8211; Cologne &#8211;
               &amp; so by Brussels &amp; Lisle to Calais.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In Hans&#8217;s book wherein my doggrel was written,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had composed a poem in
                  Hans Roth&#8217;s honour in his book of testimonials. It was seen by another traveller, who sent a copy to <title>The Times</title>, where
                  it was published on 31 October 1817.</note> were some Latin verses which deserved to be copied. <del>M</del> Very probably they came
               from Bloomfield,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Valentine Blomfield (1788&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), classical scholar
                  and Fellow of Emmanuel College, Cambridge. He contracted a fever on his tour of Switzerland and died in Cambridge on 9 October
                  1816.</note> &#8211; whose name was among his testimonials, tho not written in the same hand: certainly they are of English growth, &#8211; as
               you will perceive</p>
        <p rend="indent5">Hans Loquitur.</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Sum Rothius, parv&#230; dux optimus Untersen&#230;.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Quaque lacus inter surgunt mapalia binos.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Seu te findentem scopuloso vertice nubes</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Gotthardum peragrare placet, seu florea mavis</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Regna Rigi, aut fractam pileato culmine montem,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Omnia lustrabis Graii cognominis Alpes</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Auspicio ductuque meo: fert sive dolores</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Dira &#948;&#953;&#940;&#961;&#961;&#959;&#953;&#945;, aut fessis &#973;&#960;&#959; &#960;&#959;&#963;&#963;&#953;
                  &#967;&#953;&#956;&#949;&#964;&#955;&#945;,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Non ignarus ero; novi qu&#230; rupibus altis,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Qu&#230;que in secretis crescunt convallibus herb&#230;.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Hans speaks.// I am Roth, the
                     best leader of small Unterseen,/ Where between two lakes chalets rise up./ Whether it is pleasing that you traverse/ Gotthard
                     which cleaves the clouds with its craggy summit,/ Or you prefer the flowery/ Kingdoms of Rigi or the broken mountain with its
                     be-capped top,/ You will survey in every way the Alps of Grecian surname/ By my guidance and conducting: or if dread diarrhoea/
                     Or chilblains under your tired feet bring pains,/ I shall not be unmindful; I know which herbs grow on high cliffs,/ And which in
                     remote valleys.&#8217;</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent5">&amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Present my compliments to your friend Mr. Ritchie,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Ritchie (c.
                  1788&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>), surgeon, explorer and naturalist who died during an expedition to find the course of the
                  Niger.</note> for the letter which he forwarded to Geneva for me. The ladies below stairs have desired me not to forget their
               remembrances. Here is Ormathwaite<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Ormathwaite Hall, at the foot of Skiddaw; formerly rented by
                  Lieutenant John Ponsonby (dates unknown), of the Royal Navy.</note> to be let, and Barrow,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Barrow House on Derwentwater, designed and built by Joseph Pocklington (1736&#8211;1817).</note> and the house which in your time was
               called Mr. Marshalls:<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a house rented by John Marshall (1765&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>),
                  Leeds mill-owner.</note> I will risk the one which you may like best to remain vacant till you have finished your travels. Let me
               hear from you sometimes, and fail not to say where a letter may find you upon your road. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General</ref> is on the Island, enjoying all the advantages of solitude and retirement, and I
               daresay just now heartily disposed to join in the complaint of the lover against space and time, in reference to the limits of his
               island, and the length of the day. God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Yours most truly,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Present my compliments &#8230; Robert Southey: final
                     paragraph and signature are missing from the manuscript and the text is here taken from the version published in
                  Warter.</note>
          </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry it should be reported, (tho no person who knows either me or my manner of writing <del>x</del> can
                  believe the report,) that I am the reviewer of Lady Morgans book.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of Lady Morgan
                     (bap. 1783&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), <title>France</title> (1817) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 17 (April
                     1817), 260&#8211;286, published 8 September 1817, was by John Wilson Croker and William Gifford.</note> Her opinions are bad enough,
                  but I would rather have cut off my right hand than have written any thing so unmanly &amp; disgraceful as that criticism.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>