<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2832</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4103</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2832. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 25 August 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2832" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2832.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 195&#8211;197 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2832" type="letter">
        <head>2832. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>, <date when="1816-08-25">25 August 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 25 Augt. 1816<lb /> MS:
                  Huntington Library, RS 290. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 195&#8211;197 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1816-08-25">25 Aug. 1816. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been long in your debt; &#8211; my summers are more like those of
               the grasshopper than of the Ant.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In Aesop&#8217;s
                  (c. 620&#8211; c. 560 BC) <title>Fables</title> the story of the &#8216;Ant and the
                  Grasshopper&#8217; is used to illustrate the virtues of hard work &#8211; the grasshopper
                  sings all summer, while the ant stores up food for the winter.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> was here nearly a week, &#8211; &amp; when
               he departed I rejoined him with my guest <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lowtherestate">Lowther</ref>; &#8211; a great house serving the
               purpose of a good inn, from whence I could show <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> a
               part of the country which would not have been easily accessible from any other point.
               This, &amp; a round home by way of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>
               employed a week, &amp; what with the King of Prussias Librarian,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Heinrich Spiker (1786&#8211;1858). An English
                  translation of his account of his experiences in Britain was later published as
                     <title>Travels through England, Wales, &amp; Scotland, in the Year 1816</title>, 2 vols
                  (London, 1820). His meeting with Southey was described on I, pp. 269&#8211;272. Naturally,
                  Spiker was most interested in Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; the two Secretaries of
               the Bible-Society,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Secretaries of the
                  British and Foreign Bible Society (founded 1804): John Owen (1766&#8211;1822;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Curate of Fulham 1795&#8211;1813; and Joseph Hughes (1769&#8211;1833;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Baptist Minister who held various posts at Bristol&#8217;s
                  Broadmead Baptist Church 1791&#8211;1796, where he met Southey.</note> &amp; other such
               out of the way personages who come to me by a sort of instinct, &#8211; <del>at</del> I
               have had little time &amp; less leisure since my return.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The last odd personage who<del>se</del> made his appearance was Owen
               of Lanark,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen (1771&#8211;1858;
                     <title>DNB</title>), manager and owner of the mills and model community at New
                  Lanark in Scotland 1799&#8211;1825.</note> &#8211; who is neither more nor less than such a
               Pantisocrat as I was in the days of my youth. He is as ardent now as I was then; &#8211;
               &amp; will soon be cried down as a visionary. Certainly he proposes to do more than I
               can believe practicable in this generation after the way in which he would introduce
               it &#8211; but I will go to Lanark &amp; see what he has done.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey paid a brief visit to New Lanark on 28 September 1819,
                  whilst returning from his tour of Scotland; see <title>Journal of a Tour in
                     Scotland in 1819</title>, ed. Charles Harold Herford (London, 1929), pp.
                  259&#8211;266.</note> I conversed with him for about an hour, &#8211; &amp; not knowing any
               thing about him good part of the time elapsed before I could comprehend his views, &#8211;
               so little probable did it appear that any person should come to me with a levelling
               system of society &amp; tell me that he had been to the Archbishop of Canterbury<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Manners-Sutton (1755&#8211;1828;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Archbishop of Canterbury 1805&#8211;1828. He chaired a committee
                  set up in 1816 by the Association for the Relief of the Manufacturing and
                  Labouring Poor to look into ways of relieving distress. Owen was invited to become
                  a member.</note> &#8211; the Ministers &amp;c. But he will be here again in a day or
               two, &amp; meantime have read a pamphlett, which is much more injudicious than his
               conversation, &amp; will very probably frustrate the good which he might by
               possibility have produced.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen&#8217;s
                     <title>An Address delivered to the Inhabitants of New Lanark ... at the opening
                     of the New Institution Established for the Formation of Character</title>
                  (1816).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To this system, he says, we must come <hi rend="ital">speedily</hi>,
               &#8211; I think we shall come to it at last, &#8211; but that we are far from it.
                  <del>However</del> What he says of the manufacturing system has much weight in it,
               &#8211; the machinery which enabled us to manufacture for half the world, has found its way
               into other countries, &#8211; every market is glutted, &#8211; more goods are produced than can
               be consumed, &#8211; &amp; every improvement in mechanism that <del>renders fewer</del>
               performs the work of hands &#8211; throws so many mouths upon the public, &#8211; a growing evil
               which has been increased by the premature employment of children, bringing them
                  <del>also</del> into competition with the grown workmen &#8211; when they should have
               been at school or at play. Great eventual good, thus produces great immediate
               distress. He wants Government to settle its paupers &amp; supernumerary hands in
               villages upon waste lands, to live in community:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Owen embodied these ideas in his <title>Report to the Committee
                     of the Association for the Relief of the Manufacturing and Labouring
                     Poor</title> (1817).</note> urging that we must go to the root of the evil at
               once: he talks of what he has done at Lanark (&amp; this indeed has been much talked
               of by others) but his Address to his people there has in it <del>some</del> much that
               is misplaced, injudicious, &amp; reprehensible. &#8211; Did you see him in London? Had we
               met twenty years ago the meeting might have influenced both his life &amp; mine in no
               slight degree: during those years he has been a practical man, &amp; I have been a
               student, &#8211; we do not differ in the main point, &#8211; but my mind has ripened more than
               his.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have well answered my query respecting Bedford &amp;
                  Herefordshire.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">For this query, see
                  Southey to Rickman, 9 June [1816], Letter 2809. Southey had been studying a
                  &#8216;Comparative View of the Area, Fertility and Agricultural Population, of Several
                  Counties of England and Wales&#8217;, <title>The Literary Panorama and National
                     Register</title>, 7 (June 1816), 447&#8211;448.</note> I see clearly the infinite
               applicability of your columns:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Census
                  which Rickman had organised in 1801 and 1811.</note> &#8211; &amp; the necessity of
               local knowledge to extract the most from them. There are two branches of industry
               which I should have thought would have added much to the agricultural produce of
               Bedfordshire (if I am right in classing them under that head) &#8211; basket making, &amp;
               straw plaiting, the latter wholly &amp; the former in great part (osier peeling)
               performed by the females of the agricultural families.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You talk of brain-transfusion, &#8211; &amp; placing one mans memory upon
               another mans shoulders &#8211; that same melancholy feeling must thro the mind of every man
               who labours hard in acquiring knowledge; for communicate what we can, &amp; labour as
               assiduously as we may how much must needs die with us! This reflection makes me
               sometimes regret (as far as is allowable) the time which I employ in doing what
               others might do as well, or what might as well be left undone. The Quarterly might go
               on without me, &amp; should do so if I could go on without it, &#8211; but what would
               become of my Portugueze acquirements &amp; of yonder heap of materials which none but
               myself can put in order, &#8211; if I were to be removed by death!<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey never completed his planned &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217; and
                  his collection of rare books and manuscripts was auctioned and split up in 1844,
                  after his death.</note> I had 50 &#163; from the last Quarterly for a sketch of the La
               Vendee war, &amp; 100 &#163; for a paper upon the Poor, which might have been good if I
               could have {freely} pursued some of the topic this touched upon <del>it</del>. &#8211;
               these two sums are <del>more as</del> more than the second volume of Brazil will give
                  me.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 1&#8211;69, a series of memoirs of
                  the French Revolutionary wars and wrote an article &#8216;On the Poor&#8217;, 15 (April 1816),
                  187&#8211;235. The second volume of Southey&#8217;s three&#8211;volume <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> was published in 1817.</note> Two chapters more will conclude
               the volume, &#8211; one of the general history, &#8211; the other miscellaneous upon the state of
               the country at that time, &#8211; &amp; its manners, &#8211; this will be rich in Catholic<hi rend="ital">ana</hi>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, pp. 588&#8211;692,
                  constituting Chapters 29&#8211;30. Chapter 30 included several sections on &#8216;the
                  extravagances to which Catholic superstition was carried in Brazil&#8217; (p.
                  689).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have seen no other Canal reports than those with the maps of the
               intended roads &#8211; &amp; of the canal itself<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Rickman had been, since 1803, the Secretary to both the Commissioners for
                  the Making and Maintaining of the Caledonian Canal and the Commissioners for Roads
                  and Bridges in the Highlands. On 22 July 1816 Rickman had written to Southey
                  mentioning that his Annual Reports on the Caledonian Canal, from 1804 onwards,
                  constituted the first detailed history of the building of a canal, Orlo Williams,
                     <title>Lamb&#8217;s Friend the Census-Taker. Life and Letters of John Rickman</title>
                  (Boston and New York, 1912), p. 181. The Commissioners for Roads and Bridges
                  issued their first Report, which contained detailed maps, in 1804 but subsequent
                  Reports appeared irregularly.</note> &#8211; For the {two} voted monuments I want one
               durable one which should ultimately pay itself, &#8211; a pyramid not smaller than the
               largest in Egypt, &#8211; the inside of which should serve London for catacombs, &#8211; some
               such provision is grievously wanted for so huge a capital.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The House of Commons had voted on 29 June 1815 to erect a
                  monument to commemorate the Battle of Waterloo (18 June 1815) and on 5 February
                  1816 also agreed to a monument to the Battle of Trafalgar (21 October 1805).
                  Designs were drawn up and debated extensively, but neither monument was built.
                  Southey&#8217;s idea was ingenious as London was desperately short of space for burials,
                  though no solution was found until the construction of large private cemeteries in
                  the suburbs from 1832 onwards.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>