<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3067</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4338</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3067. Robert Southey to Thomas Southey, 13 January
                  1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3067" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3067.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Princeton University Library, Robert H. Taylor Collection, Box 17, Folder 27. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3067" type="letter">
        <head>3067. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Thomas Southey</ref>, <date when="1818-01-13">13 January
                  1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Southey. RN./ Warcop/ near/ Brough<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: Princeton University Library, Robert H. Taylor Collection, Box 17, Folder 27. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Tom</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here is a note showing that Phipps&#8217;s course for the wreck was no new thought.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The information was for Tom Southey&#8217;s on-going work on the West Indies. In 1683 Captain William Phips (1651&#8211;1695;
                     <title>DNB</title>) made an unsuccessful attempt to locate the wreck of a Spanish galleon off the Bermuda Banks. Acting on advice
                  provided by an &#8216;old Spaniard&#8217; he searched &#8216;a few leagues to the northwards of Puerta de la Plata&#8217;. Another attempt in 1687 succeeded
                  in locating the wreck on a &#8216;shoal called The Boilers&#8217;, near Puerta de la Plata. Phips received a knighthood and &#163;11,000 (his share
                  of the &#163;250,000 salvaged cargo). The story was told in Tom Southey, <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title>, 3 vols
                  (London, 1827), II, pp. 127, 142&#8211;143.</note> In a political squib entitled an honest account of the Receipts &amp; Disbursements
               expended by the Committee of Safety upon the emergent occasions of the nation. 1660. is the following item. &#8220;Paid to a Projector,
               towards a design which he had to look into the middle of the Western Ocean for a great Spanish galleon that was sunk with the weight of
               the gold that she carried, some thirty years ago, two thousand five hundred pounds.&#8221; Harleian Miscellany. 8vo edition. Vol. 7. p.
                  154.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Harleian Miscellany; or, A Collection of Scarce, Curious, and Entertaining
                     Pamphlets and Tracts, As Well in Manuscript as in Print, Found in the Late Earl of Oxford&#8217;s Library, Interspersed with
                     Historical, Political, and Critical Notes</title>, 10 vols (London, 1808&#8211;1813), VII, p. 154. Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 1282 in the
                  sale catalogue of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At last I have compleated the Morte Arthur for you: first there was neither introduction nor notes, &amp; when I wrote
               for these the introduction came without the notes, &#8211; these last <del>xxx</del> arrived yesterday. The sheets will now go to be put in
               such half binding as we can get here, &#8211; which is to serve the purpose of boards, <del>being</del> having the advantage of being
               stronger, &amp; the leaves of course not being cut; &#8211; &amp; when <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEliza">Eliza</ref> passes by
               Thomas Tinklers<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Tinkler (c. 1754&#8211;1824), of Brough; landlord of the Wheatsheaf Inn,
                  Warcop, where deliveries for Thomas Southey could be left because the mail coach stopped there.</note> which she probably will do on
               Tuesday week next, she will leave <del>them</del> it there. The price of the book is eight guineas, so you may reckon it among your
               rarities &amp; valuables.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A presentation copy of <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title>, published in two volumes by
                  Longman in 1817.</note> &#8211; The story of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEliza">Elizas</ref> correspondence with Sarah
                  Castle<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey&#8217;s wife, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>, whose
                  maiden name was Castle. </note> is comical enough. She was to have halted at Brough in her way back, to have taken up a scholar;
               &amp; in that case she would have got to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Warcop">Warcop</ref>, &#8211; but a letter has arrived today which
               alters this arrangement, so that she goes straight forward.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My books from Milan<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Books purchased during Southey&#8217;s time in Milan in 1817 on
                  his continental tour.</note> have reached London, &amp; are now I trust on the road to Cumberland. Ramusio halts at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> for a new jacket, his other one having been worn out in the course of two hundred
               years wear.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Giovanni Battista Ramusio (1485&#8211;1557), <title>Navigationi e Viaggi</title>, 3 vols
                  (1556&#8211;1588), no. 2382 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> The only book which concerns you in this cargo is a volume
               entitled Soirees Bermudeens, &#8211; but relating I believe chiefly, if not wholly to S. Domingo, &amp; written at the Bermudas by a planter
               who <del>hav</del> escaped there from the horrors of the negro insurrection.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-F&#233;lix Carteau
                  (dates unknown), <title>Soir&#233;es Bermudiennes, Ou Entretiens Sur Les &#201;v&#232;nemens Qui Ont Op&#233;r&#233; La Ruine De La Partie Fran&#231;aise De l&#8217;&#206;le
                     Saint-Domingue, Ouvrage O&#249; L&#8217;on Expose les Causes de ces &#201;v&#232;nemens, les Moyens Employ&#233;s pour Renverser cette Colonie</title>
                  (1802). The &#8216;negro insurrection&#8217; was the slave uprising in Haiti (formerly known as St Domingue), which began in 1791.</note> &#8211; Jan
               de Laet<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Joannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649), <title>Historie ofte Iaerlijck Verhael van de Verrichtingen
                     der Geoctroyeerde West-Indische Compagnie</title> (1644), no. 1671 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> which is
               the book wherein I suppose there will be most to your purpose is in the Brussels party, &amp; of this I have no intelligence as
                  yet.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Books bought by Southey in Brussels in 1817; their delayed arrival caused him anxiety
                  and annoyance.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is among the Milanese volumes a very curious account of the Milicia de las Indias &#8211; which I had read in <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Hebers</ref> copy, it was written in the Nuevo Reyno, &amp; much of it cannot be
               applicable to the Islands, &#8211; even the larger ones; &#8211; still there must be something. It is one of the most curious books respecting the
               Indies, &amp; I look upon it as one of my most valuable acquisitions.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Bernardo de Vargas
                  Machuca (1557&#8211;1622), <title>Milicia y Descripci&#243;n de las Indias</title> (1599); when it arrived, Southey wrote a long note in his
                  copy signalling its importance; see no. 3758 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; I had forgotten also an Italian Essay
               concerning the birthplace of Columbus.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Gianfrancesco Napione (1748&#8211;1830), <title>Delia Patria
                     di Cristoforo Colombo</title> (1808), no. 730 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> The Milan Cargo consists of 114
               volumes. Of these 17 remain in London to be hided: &#8211; the rest will make a joyful arrival, &#8211; &amp; there will be a second joy when the
               fellows in their new coats come after them. A good many indeed still belong to the ragged regiment, &#8211; tho not to be placed in Duck
                  Row.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The part of Greta Hall where Southey kept less valuable books.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Today I attacked your sage cheese which proves laudable &amp; good. The toasters have been of unequal merit, some
               pretty good, &amp; one very bad. Do you know the old recipe of Thomas Tusser for improving cheese by putting a certain proportion of
               ewes milk with it?<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Tusser (c. 1524&#8211;1580; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Five Hundred Good
                     Points of Good Husbandry</title> (London, 1812), p. 150, no. 2923 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> It must have
               been the usual practise in his days.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEliza">Eliza</ref> will now return by way of Kendal &amp; Leeds, as the surest way of hitting
               the cross stage which is to carry her to York. So your Morte Arthur<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">A presentation copy of
                     <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur ... With an introduction and notes by Robert Southey. (Printed from Caxton&#8217;s
                     edition, 1485)</title>, published in two volumes by Longman in 1817.</note> must go by the carrier. Daniel Crossthwaite<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;D. Crosthwaite&#8217; was listed as a bookseller in Keswick in various commercial directories. He
                  might have been Daniel Crosthwaite (c. 1776&#8211;1847), a portrait painter and proprietor of the museum in Keswick. Whatever his
                  identity, he was providing a cover for Tom Southey&#8217;s copy of <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title> (1817).</note>
               will probably have done his part the end of this week, &#8211; it will be sent in that case to the carrier on Monday, directed to the Wheat
               Sheaf, &#8211; after which time you will know how to enquire for it, &#8211; but it is a sadly uncertain road for packages, which is always the
               case where carriers are to be changed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In consequence of this news from the North Pole<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Reports of events in the Arctic
                  were widespread in British newspapers and suggested a dramatic decline in the ice fields around Greenland.</note> the North West
               passage is to be attempted this year, &#8211; with more prospect than ever of effecting it.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Newspaper
                  accounts (e.g. <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 22 November 1817) reported that the Royal Society was pressing the government to
                  mount an expedition to search for the North West passage and offering fishermen a bounty to explore the area. Two Royal Navy
                  expeditions were made. In April 1818 one commanded by David Buchan (1780&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>) and John Franklin (1786&#8211;1847;
                     <title>DNB</title>) explored the Arctic sea around Spitsbergen; another commanded by John Ross (1777&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>)
                  sought a North West passage around Baffin Island. Neither was successful.</note> I am very curious to know the result, especially if
               the pole itself should be accessible. This dislocation of the ice is by much the most interesting physical fact that has occurred
               within my recollection.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#WatsonRichardBishopLlandaff">Daffs</ref> memoirs have been published, &amp;
               appear by the newspaper extracts to be just what might have been predicted from the character of the man, &#8211; a worldly minded man, with
               just knowledge enough for a respectable college tutor, bloated with self-conceit, &amp; cankered with discontent.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Anecdotes of the Life of Richard Watson, Bishop of Llandaff; Written by Himself at Different
                     Intervals, and Revised in 1814</title> (1817). Watson&#8217;s unusual position as a Bishop and a Whig made him especially disliked by
                  the government&#8217;s supporters.</note> The Times<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Times</title> published a series of
                  extracts from the <title>Anecdotes</title>, 24 December 1817&#8211;5 February 1818.</note> &amp; the M Chronicle<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 2 January 1818, stoutly defended Watson: &#8216;the character for virtue and purity
                  of conduct, for incorruptible patriotism, and for extraordinary learning and talents of Bishop WATSON is so well established in this
                  country, that even Courtly sycophancy will not dare openly to insult his memory.&#8217;</note> are trying to make him a Saint &amp; a
               Patriot, but all this exaggeration is like putting a filthy little hexaped into a solar microscope, &#8211; the stronger the light in which
               it is exhibited, the uglier it looks. (If Sir Kreeper has more legs than six I beg his pardon.) The Courier takes the much easier part
               of showing what the man was by his own account of his own actions &amp; motives.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                     <title>Courier</title> had published extracts from and highly critical comments on Watson&#8217;s <title>Memoirs</title> on 3, 5 and 10
                  January 1818, accusing Watson of, amongst other things, &#8216;disgusting and ridiculous intellectual arrogance&#8217; (5 January 1818). It
                  resumed its attack on 26 January 1818. <title>The Times</title> (5 February 1818) protested at the &#8216;ribaldry&#8217; of the
                     <title>Courier</title>&#8217;s treatment of Watson. The <title>Courier</title>&#8217;s criticisms were, nevertheless, expanded into <title>A
                     Critical Examination of the Bishop of Llandaff&#8217;s Posthumous Volume, entitled &#8220;Anecdotes of his Life&#8221;</title> (1818).</note> It is
               not a little amusing to me when I find the Opposition thus stoutly extolling him, for I happen to know how heartily he was despised by
                  <del>some of</del> the leaders of that party, &amp; that no conceivable change in administration would have gratified his desire of
               promotion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very busy with Brazil<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">The third and final volume of the <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &#8211; &amp; the Poor Laws.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Rickman&#8217;s article
                  (mainly written by the latter) appeared as &#8216;On the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>&#184;18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308, published
                  9 June 1818.</note> &#8211; The weather is peeling the front of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall"> the house</ref>, &amp; God
               know who is to re-case it. &#8211; The inspection of windows draws upon me a heavy additional tax &#8211; the whole house is to be charged as one.
                  -<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was filling out his tax form for assessed taxes and feared an increase in the
                  window tax he would have to pay, as this depended on the number of windows in the house. Possibly, he had only been paying tax on
                  the number of windows in the part of the house he had originally rented in 1803.</note> I have great hopes about the Poor
                  Rates.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey, as the householder at Greta Hall, would be assessed by his parish to
                  determine his liability for poor rates, to support the local poor. Presumably he hoped that the economic situation was improving and
                  thus the amount required in poor rates would decline.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> is
               gone as tutor to some little boys near Ulverston,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Coleridge lived with the Hopwood
                  family, well-connected Lancashire landowners, at Summerhill, near Ulverston 1817&#8211;1819. Robert Gregge Hopwood (1773&#8211;1854) had married
                  in 1805 Cecilia Elizabeth Byng (1770&#8211;1854), daughter of John Byng, 5th Viscount Torrington (1743&#8211;1813). However she was a first
                  cousin, rather than a sister, of Georgiana Byng (1768&#8211;1801), first wife of Lord John Russell, later the 6th Duke of Bedford
                  (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>). Lady Russell had lived in Lisbon for two years for her health and was known to Herbert Hill and,
                  possibly, John May. Derwent Coleridge was tutor to the Hopwoods&#8217; sons: Edward (1807&#8211;1891); Frank (1810&#8211;1890); and Hervey
                  (1811&#8211;1881).</note> where if he stays two years he is to have 35 guineas for the first &amp; 40 for the second &#8211; he will then have
               earned something to help himself with at College,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Coleridge entered St John&#8217;s College,
                  Cambridge in 1820.</note> &#8211; which may induce others to help him: &#8211; but it is becoming easier now to provide for girls than for boys,
               &#8211; for the expences of a mans education amount to what would be independence in frugality for a woman, &#8211; &amp; after his education, a
               man has his bread to seek with a very great chance of not finding it. Were I young &amp; single I should certainly emigrate.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>. &#8211; God bless you.</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1818-01-13"> Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 13. 1818. </date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>