<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3107</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4378</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3107. Robert Southey to Edward Nash, 29 March
                  1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3107" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3107.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Newnham College, Cambridge, Harold Young Papers 382b. ALS;
                  4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3107" type="letter">
        <head>3107. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#NashEdward">Edward Nash</ref>, <date when="1818-03-29">29 March
                  1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Edward Nash Esq<hi rend="sup">re.</hi>/ 6. George Street/ Hanover
                  Square/ London <lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: [partial] E/ [illegible]/ 1818<lb /> Watermark: H.E. &amp; S. BATH
                  1814<lb /> Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb /> MS: Newnham College, Cambridge, Harold Young Papers 382b. ALS;
                  4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-03-29">29 March 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Nash</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> This has been a week of great events. &#8211; no less in magnitude, &amp; no fewer in number, than the arrival of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw&#8217;s</ref> box on one day, that of the frames on the next, &amp; of a parcel of
               books the third.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Framed pictures that Nash had painted on his visit to Keswick; and a parcel of
                  books that Southey had bought in Milan in June 1817 on his continental tour.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> First let me thank you for the Caviare; &#8211; the paper with which the jar was covered had an odour truly detestable, as
               tho it had been dipt in rancid train oil,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Oil derived from the blubber of whales.</note> or some
               thing worse, if aught worse there be. But the Wolf you know is a Wolf of approved valour, &#8211; &amp; moreover I was perfectly sure that
               the taste of the Caviare could not possibly resemble this perfume a la diable. And as I expected excellent I found it, &#8211; excellente,
               excellentissime, superbe, magnifique.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Excellent, most excellent, superb, magnificent&#8217;.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> agrees with me, &amp; so does <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref>, but as for <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my Governess</ref>
                  &amp;<ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah"> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref>, they belong to the multitude<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Caviare to the multitude&#8217; was a commonplace meaning &#8216;good things that are unappreciated by the
                  masses&#8217;. It derives from a misquotation of <title>Hamlet</title>, Act 2, scene 2, line 437, &#8216;caviary to the general&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The frames fit perfectly, &amp; are in very good taste. They came safe, to the no small merit of the packer. Their
               Ladyships Racket &amp; Riot<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Two of Southey&#8217;s daughters, possibly <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="eople.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>.</note> were full of
               joy at the arrival, &amp; if I were to repeat all the thanks which they wish to send, or half the things which they desire to say,
               there would be no room for any thing else in this sheet of paper.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The books came in excellent order, &amp; nothing missing except the four volumes of Ebel,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Gottfried Ebel (1764&#8211;1830), author of the first comprehensive guidebook to Switzerland. The missing books
                  possibly arrived, because a complete edition of Ebel&#8217;s <title>Manuel du Voyageur en Suisse</title> (1810) was no. 887 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> which I conclude were left out at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> by mistake, &amp; therefore have written about them. It was a rich cargo &amp; some fellows who were in ragged
               attire when they came into my service at Milan, having now their new liveries on, were worthy of promotion to the best ranks in the
               room. Then I had to enter them in a list which I began to keep at the commencement of this year, of all the books which <del>are</del>
               may be added to my stores. Right glad should I be to hear that the more important collection from Van Beast<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Volumes Southey bought in Brussels in 1817 from the bookseller Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1849).</note> were
               safely on the road to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>: &#8211; their arrival will be a great event indeed; &#8211; for I
               cannot help having some apprehension that they may have been sent off in the autumn, &amp; have missed their way. Yet I think Van Beast
               perfectly understood my directions, &amp; would have written, as he was instructed, to advise Mr Rothschild<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The banker Nathan Mayer von Rothschild (1777&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), whom Southey had enlisted to help ease the
                  transportation of his books.</note> when they were sent off.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> dined here yesterday, &#8211; in good health &amp; spirits. He sets out for
               London in about a month. The retouching his plates has failed in three or four of them. if the fault be not in working them off at
               Carlisle; &#8211; &amp; this makes him fear that they must be published after all as coloured prints, &#8211; for which I shall be sorry, because
               (as far as I am capable of judging) some of them are fine works of art in their kind, better than any thing of that kind which has yet
               been produced.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to either Westall&#8217;s collection of engravings, <title>Views of the
                     Caves near Ingleton in Yorkshire</title> (London, 1818), which combined several engraving techniques to create effects of light
                  and shade; or to Westall&#8217;s <title>Views of the Lake and of the Vale of Keswick</title> (1820), a book of coloured aquatints that
                  represented a great step forward in the reproduction of the Lake District landscape.</note> This however seems to be the immediate
               motive for his journey to town &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> is still in <ref type="m" target="places.html#RosthwaitePlace">Borrodale</ref>, &amp; has been there ever since you left us! </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General Peachy</ref> the other day, who is now at
                  N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 39. George Street. Portman Square. Can you tell me whether <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> is at Bath, for if he were there, I would write to him &amp; entrust Miss
                  Wood<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Anne Wood (1782&#8211;1860), Senhouse&#8217;s cousin.</note> with a commission which I think
               she would like to execute, &#8211; that of visiting &amp; giving me an account of <del>an</del> a sort of female College near Bath.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Ladies Association was created by the philanthropist Lady Isabella Lettice King (1772&#8211;1845;
                     <title>DNB</title>) with the aim of improving the lot of impoverished gentlewomen by providing them with &#8216;conventual&#8217;
                  communities. Its first establishment opened at Bailbrook House, near Bath, in June 1816. This moved to Cornwallis House, Clifton,
                  near Bristol, in 1821. The Association was suspended in 1832 and Cornwallis House sold in 1837, with the remaining funds devoted to
                  local charitable causes. Southey was a supporter of King and she wrote to him in the hope that he might influence others to take up
                  her cause.</note> I am about ere long to write a paper upon the great advantage of establishing institutions of this kind,
                  <del>where</del> by which the untold misery to which <del>female</del> women who are left without friends or fortune are now
               inevitably exposed.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey promoted this idea, specifically praising the Ladies Association,
                  in his article on &#8216;British Monachism&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 22 (July 1819), 59&#8211;102 (at 90&#8211;102).</note> And this will
               lead me to give as full an account of the Beguines<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Lay Catholic communities of women. Medieval
                  in origin, they could still be found in the Low Countries. Southey&#8217;s interest in them dated back to the late 1790s; see Robert
                  Southey to John Rickman, 9 January 1800, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 476. </note> as I
               can collect from my books.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Vardon</ref>,&#8211; to whom I shall
               write ere long. All here are well (except poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L.</ref>) &#8211; &amp;
               all join in the kindest remembrances.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear Nash &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>