<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3135</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4406</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3135. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 15 May 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3135.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 167. ALS; 4p..  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3135" type="letter">
        <head>3135. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>,<date when="1818-05-15"> 15 May 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert
                  Hill/ Worting/ near/ Basingstoke <lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 18
                  MY 18/ 1818<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 167. ALS; 4p.<title>
              <lb />
            </title>Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ArrowsmithAaron">Arrowsmith</ref> marks in his
                  map,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Outlines of the Physical
                     and Political Divisions of South America: Delineated by A. Arrowsmith Partly
                     from Scarce and Original Documents</title> (1811) was the basis of the map of
                  Brazil and Paraguay that Arrowsmith had been commissioned to make for the second
                  volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819). The diamond
                  demarcation was a special area under direct government control since 1772 because
                  of the mineral wealth it contained &#8211; it is indeed in Minas Gerais. Cuiaba in Mato
                  Grosso was founded in 1719 as the result of a gold rush, but there were no
                  diamonds in the area.</note> &amp; in mine, a Diamond Demarcation in Cuyaba, &amp;
               omits to mark that in Minas Geraes. The omission we know to be an error, &#8211; but are
               there two such Demarcations, or not? Among the Documenta printed with the Latin
               translation to Charlevoix,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre
                  Francois-Xavier de Charlevoix (1682&#8211;1761), <title>Historia Paraguajensis</title>
                  (1779), no. 691 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey was using this
                  work to aid his researches for the third volume of his <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &amp; belonging to the supplement which
               makes this translation of more worth than the original, is an account of Cuyaba in
               which it is said that Diamonds are found in one of the <hi rend="ital">lavaderos de
                  oro; mas en estos a&#241;os antecedentes, porque los diamontes no perdiesen su
                  estimacion, se prohibio por el Rey de Portugal sacarlos de Cuyaba</hi>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The passage translates as: &#8216;the gold-panning
                  sites; but, in the last few years, the King of Portugal prohibited taking the
                  diamonds out of Cuyaba, so that they would not lose their value&#8217;. Southey&#8217;s source
                  was Jose Quiroga (1707&#8211;1784), &#8216;Summa Itinerarii adverso Paraguai ad Xauruum&#8217;
                  (1753), Charlevoix, <title>Historia Paraguajensis</title> (Venice, 1779), pp.
                  514&#8211;521 (at p. 518). </note> This paper is dated 1753. On the other hand there is
               a tolerably full account of Matto Grosso in the Patriota,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>O Patriota, Jornal Litterario, Politico, Mercantil
                     &amp;c do Rio de Janeiro</title> (1813&#8211;1814), no. 3641 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library. A long geographical description of the captaincy of Mato Grosso
                  featured in the issues for July, August, November and December 1813 and January
                  and February 1814. </note> &amp; no mention is made of diamonds or of any such
               Demarcation. It is indeed possible that there may be a continuation of this paper in
               the subsequent number of that publication; &amp; as <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> has undertaken to have them enquired
               for at the Rio,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. v&#8211;vi, Southey thanked John
                  May for procuring the third volume of <title>O Patriota</title> for him, &#8216;when it
                  was not to be obtained at Lisbon&#8217;.</note> I hope soon to receive them. &#8211; I find no
               mention of any diamonds among all your papers except those of the Serro do Frio.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A diamond-bearing area in Minas
                  Gerais.</note> But <ref type="m" target="people.html#ArrowsmithAaron">Arrowsmith</ref>, I think, must have had <del>xxx</del> authority for his map in
               those mss maps which were entrusted to him. &#8211; Mawe evidently knows nothing of any
               Cuyaba diamonds,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Mawe (1764&#8211;1829;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Interior of Brazil, particularly in
                     the Gold and Diamond Districts of that Country, including a Voyage to the Rio
                     de la Plata</title> (1812), no. 1864 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> &amp; I know not of whom to make enquiry with any chance of
               success in England. At Pernambuco the question may perhaps be answered, but only to
               appear in the notes, as information obtained after it was wanted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have printed 24 sheets,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Of the third volume of the <title>History of Brazil
                  </title>(1810&#8211;1819).</note> &amp; the QR<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Quarterly Review</title>. The issue containing Southey and
                  Rickman&#8217;s article &#8216;On the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January
                  1818), 259&#8211;308, had still not appeared and did not do so until 9 June 1818.</note>
               has given me so long a holyday that I am far ahead of the press, both with this work
               &amp; with the Life of Wesley.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism
                  </title>(1820).</note> The War<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (London,
                  1823&#8211;1832).</note> I shall probably keep back till Brazil is finished, the end
               being now in view. Dobrizhoffer came in excellent time for a second perusal when I
               knew every thing which I should want in it.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri,
                     Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue
                  of Southey&#8217;s library. In 1809 Southey had made extensive transcriptions from a
                  copy that Walter Scott had borrowed from the Advocates Library, Edinburgh. </note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoxeWilliam">Coxe</ref> when he wrote to
               me for some books about Pombal<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebasti&#227;o
                  Jos&#233; de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Marquess of Pombal (1699&#8211;1782), effectively the Prime
                  Minister of Portugal 1750&#8211;1777.</note> told me he had a ms. about the Jesuits in S
               America, &amp; that I may lose nothing for want of enquiry, I have now written to ask
               him for it.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to William Coxe,
                  25 April 1818, Letter 3126. In<title> History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. vi&#8211;vii, Southey thanked Coxe for the communication of
                  diplomatic correspondence.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have got a new correspondent in <ref type="m" target="people.html#CraufurdCharlesGeneral">General Craufurd</ref>,
               husband of the Dutchess of Newcastle, &amp; brother to that General C. who was killed
               at Ciudad Rodrigo.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant-General
                  Sir Charles Gregan Craufurd married in 1800 Anna Maria Stanhope (1760&#8211;1834), whose
                  first husband had been Thomas Pelham-Clinton, 3rd Duke of Newcastle (1752&#8211;1795).
                  Craufurd did not serve in the Peninsular War, but his brother was Major-General
                  Robert Craufurd (1764&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), commander of the Light Division
                  1809&#8211;1812. Craufurd led his troops into one of the breaches in the walls at the
                  siege of Ciudad Rodrigo on 19 January 1812, but was mortally wounded by musket
                  fire, dying on 23 January 1812. </note> His brothers papers were all lost after
               his death, but he has sent me what he remembers of his remarks upon the course of his
               war, &amp; some remarks of his own, which will be useful, as he is a thorough-bred
               soldier &amp; an able man. I happened to have among my Inscriptions an Epitaph for
               his brother, which of course I sent him, as soon as I understood the
                  relationship.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;For the Walls of
                  Ciudad Rodrigo&#8217;; it was not published until it appeared in Southey&#8217;s<title>
                     Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), III, p.
               150&#8211;151.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Geographical Description of Matto Grosso was written in 1797 by
               Sargenti Mor of Engineers, Ricardo Francesco de Almeida Serra.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Ricardo Franco de Almeida Serra (1748&#8211;1809), a
                  sergeant-major of engineers in the Portuguese Army, had authored a long
                  geographical description of his jouneys in the 1780s in the captaincy of Mato
                  Grosso, which appeared in <title>O Patriota, Jornal Litterario, Politico,
                     Mercantil &amp;c do Rio de Janeiro</title>, July, August, November and December
                  1813 and January and February 1814. </note> &#8211; It is an important paper to me &#8211;
                  Goyaz<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Now the state of Goi&#225;s in the
                  centre of Brazil. Southey described it in <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                  (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 305&#8211;308. It was made a separate captaincy general in
                  1744.</note> is now the only Captaincy of which I shall be able to say nothing
               more (except indeed the time of its foundation) than what may be learnt from the map.
               But on the whole I think there will be more reason to wonder at the information which
               is collected into these volumes than to <del>blame the</del> condemn the compiler for
               their unavoidable defects. Can you learn when Rio Negro was made a Captaincy?<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The captaincy of S&#227;o Jos&#233; de Rio Negro was
                  established in 1755.</note> &#8211; The Engineer seems to demonstrate that Para is the
               natural port of Mato Grosso; &#8211; but probably the establishment of the Court at the Rio
               or S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paulo (if that report be true)<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese court in exile remained at Rio de Janeiro from
                  1808 to 1821.</note> will tend to keep the trade in its present channel</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It would be a great pleasure to me if you were near enough to talk
               over such things while the information is fresh in my mind. My head is like one of
               these Kaleidoscopes,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The kaleidoscope,
                  newly invented by Sir David Brewster (1781&#8211;1868; <title>DNB</title>), was marketed
                  from 1817. Hundreds of thousands were sold in the first year.</note> full of all
               sorts of fancies &amp; notions belonging to them, &#8211; when I sit down to any one
               subject, &#8211; it is like turning the glass. Off flies <del>the</del> one set, &amp; the
               other <del>xxxxxxxxx</del> arranges itself instantly in regular form.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Think of your floods at Brixton &amp; Kennington!<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">There had been major floods in these areas on 8
                  May 1818, leading to fatalities.</note> I should as soon have expected one upon
               Salisbury plain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my
                  Aunt</ref> &amp; as many of the young ones as are with you. Tell
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> when you see
               him next that I do not fail to <del>inquire</del> think of him often, &amp; to
               enquire how he goes on with his Latin.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you all</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-05-15"> 15 May. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>