<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2945</idno><idno type="nines">rce4216</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2945. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 18 March 1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2945.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2945" type="letter"><head>2945. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1817-03-18">18 March 1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham
                  Gate/ <title>London</title><lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmark: E/ 21 MR 21/ 1817<lb/> Endorsements: 18 March 1817; 18 March
                  1817<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p.<lb/> Unpublished.</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1817-03-18">18 March. 1817</date></dateline><salute> My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> As soon as I had seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smiths</ref> speech in the
                  Courier,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Courier</title>, 15 March 1817. Smith had denounced Southey in the House
                  of Commons on 14 March 1817 in the debate on the Seditious Meetings Bill, condemning ‘the settled, determined malignity of a
                  renegado’ and comparing Southey’s arguments against radical views in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 227
                  with those expressed in <title>Wat Tyler</title> (1817), Act 2, lines 103–112.</note> I threw off a tolerably warm letter to the
               honourable &amp; presbyterian member<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey here refers to Smith as a ‘presbyterian’ as the
                  latter was a prominent Dissenter and member of the Octagon Chapel in Norwich, whose congregation, though historically Presbyterian,
                  was by this stage mainly Unitarian.</note> &amp; inclosed it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>,
               desiring him unless he disapproved its contents to forward it to the Courier.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to
                  Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, of 17 March 1817 (Letter 2944), which enclosed Southey to William Smith, 17 March 1817 (Letter 2943).
                  The latter (Letter 2943) was not sent to the <title>Courier</title> for publication because Wynn’s absence from home meant there was
                  a delay in his receiving it. By the time he did so, the public debate had moved on and Southey therefore decided to incorporate the
                  letter into his pamphlet <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (1817). </note><ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> I think will not quarrel with its warmth after such gross provocation. More
               might have been said but I did not like to lose the post, – &amp; the Quarterly gives me fair opportunity to comment upon the practice
               introduced by such men as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> of slandering &amp; insulting
               individuals in the H of Commons &amp; then skulking under the privilege of Parliament from personal responsibility.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey may be referring to Brougham’s speech in the House of Commons on 24 February 1817, when he
                  contrasted the unwillingness of the government to prosecute Southey’s early radical play, <title>Wat Tyler</title>, for sedition,
                  with its eagerness to pursue radical publications.</note> The manner in which these fellows assail me is good proof that I have not
               written without effect.</p><p rend="indent1"> It is for the consideration of the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> whether the
               accession of notoriety which has been forced upon me, like honour upon poor Malvolio,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Twelfth Night</title>, Act 2, scene 5, lines 145–146: ‘some have greatness thrust upon them’.</note> be not a good reason
               for embodying in a regular form the papers which have provoked <del>xxxxxxxx</del> {this} malignant &amp; cowardly mode of attack,
               &amp; laying before the public in full my views of the state of society, its whole danger, its real evils, &amp; the means of
               mitigating &amp; ultimately as far as may be possible <del>xx</del> of removing them.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  was considering whether to use his <title>Quarterly Review</title> articles as the basis for a book on the ‘State of the
                  Nation’.</note> On the other hand very desirable as it is that this should be done, I cannot do it at present, because I have
               engaged to start with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> (&amp; I hope <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>) for the continent from London, on, or as near as can be, to the first of May. I cannot
               doubt but that the Book would have weight in the world, – for it <del>x</del> is pretty clear that on both sides the house they are
               disposed to think me a personage of more importance than I have the slightest desire to be in the political line.</p><p rend="indent1"> Somebody defends me with a very inaccurate statement in the Courier,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A defence
                  of Southey by Coleridge, entitled ‘Mr. Southey and Wat Tyler’, appeared in the <title>Courier</title> on 17 March 1817.</note> –
               &amp; with no very skilful hand. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> I see made a reply to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith </ref><del>xxxx</del> {but} by the manner in which it was reported {it} seems not have been very distinctly heard.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had spoken in reply to Smith in the House of Commons on 14 March, immediately after Smith’s attack.</note> – I
               hope he will send my letter to the newspapers, &amp; half regret that I did not send it there myself without delay, or asking any
               persons advice. – It is strange that I should not have yet heard what is doing about the injunction, – or why nothing is doing, since
               the second affadavit arrived in London, which it must have done on Tuesday last, – this day week.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1794 Southey sent James Ridgway (1755–1838) and Henry Symonds (1741–1816), radical booksellers, then in Newgate
                  prison, a copy of his Jacobin drama <title>Wat Tyler</title>; see Robert Southey to Edith Fricker, [c. 12 January 1795], <title>The
                     Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part One</title>, Letter 123. Ridgway and Symonds did not publish it and it remained in
                  manuscript until a pirated publication, designed to embarrass the now anti-Jacobin Southey, appeared in 1817. Having taken advice
                  from <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> and
                     <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, Southey launched a suit in Chancery so as to gain an injunction
                  suppressing the publication. His case was not heard until 18–19 March 1817. To support his case, Southey had sworn an affidavit on 8
                  March 1817.</note> – My ignorance upon this point prevented me from alluding to it in the letter. Whatever may have {been} done I
               beseech you pay <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> the costs as soon as he can tell you what they are. – And
               this mention of money matters reminds me of requesting that you will pay, or come to be paid for me into <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Rogers’s</ref><note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Rogers, a banker and partner in Rogers,
                  Olding &amp; Rogers, as well as a poet, was co-ordinating an appeal to relieve the poverty of Bloomfield, who was ill and who had
                  lost his royalty income owing to the bankruptcy of his publishers; see Southey to [Samuel Tillbrook], 22 December 1816, Letter
                  2883.</note> bank (Rogers, Olding &amp; Rogers is the form if I read it rightly) five pounds towards a subscription for poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Robert Bloomfield</ref>. </p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> sans doubt will be well pleased to see his
               glorious Review referred to in the H. of Commons. To me I confess it is one of the ominous symptoms of the time that public journals
               should have this kind of consequence imparted to them.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>