<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3062</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4333</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3062. Robert Southey to John May, 3 January 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3062.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                  University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John
                     May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 162&#8211;164.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3062" type="letter">
        <head>3062. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1818-01-03">3 January 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>&#8211;/ Richmond/ Surry<lb /> Stamped:
                  KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: E/ 6 JA 6/ 1818; 10 o&#8217;Clock/ JA. 6/ 1818 F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb /> Watermark: Hagar &amp; Co/
                  1815<lb /> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 197 1818/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> January/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb /> Seal: [partial] black wax, with &#8216;S&#8217;, &#8216;In Labore Quies&#8217; motto below<lb /> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                  University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John
                     May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 162&#8211;164.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I want a piece of information which <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> perhaps
               will <del>xxx</del> be kind enough to obtain for me: it is whether Samuel, the father of John Wesley, was a <hi rend="ital">Servitor</hi> at Exeter College, (as I suppose he must have been) where he entered about the year 1678.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Wesley (1662&#8211;1735; <title>DNB</title>), father of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>), was indeed a
                  servitor at Exeter College (a poor scholar who earned his keep at Oxford by waiting on wealthy students), though he did not
                  matriculate until 1684. John Coleridge was a Fellow of Exeter College 1812&#8211;1818 and so had access to the College&#8217;s registers.
                  Southey included this information in a footnote to his <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2
                  vols (London, 1820), I, pp. 7&#8211;8, thanking &#8216;a fellow of Exeter College, through the means of a common friend&#8217; for their help.</note>
               By way of self indulgence I am writing in truant hours a very diligent life of Wesley, &#8211; which will form two {or perhaps three} such
               volumes as the life of <del>xxxx</del> {Nelson};<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Life of Nelson</title> was
                  published in two volumes in 1813.</note> &#8211; it includes the life of Whitefield,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George
                  Whitefield (1714&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), an evangelical preacher and ally of John Wesley in spreading Methodism in Britain and
                  America. His life is recounted in <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820),
                  I, pp. 48&#8211;56, 136&#8211;154.</note> &amp; a full account of the Moravians,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">This proselytising
                  Protestant sect, having arrived in Britain from Saxony in the 1730s, was influential on John Wesley&#8217;s early career and thought; see
                     <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, pp. 77&#8211;81, 175&#8211;208.</note> &#8211;
               &amp; if I do not deceive myself it will be a <del>very</del> curious &amp; substantial book. The history of Methodism which it
               involves is a subject of great &amp; growing importance, &#8211; &amp; indeed my views embrace little less than {the religious history of
               England for the last hundred years}</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps you can procure for me from the Rio as many numbers of the Patriota as may have been published since the year
                  1813.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>O Patriota, Jornal Litterario, Politico, Mercantil &amp;c do Rio de
                     Janeiro</title> (1813&#8211;1814), no. 3641 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. In <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                  (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. v&#8211;vi, Southey thanked John May for procuring the third volume of <title>O Patriota</title> for him,
                  &#8216;when it was not to be obtained at Lisbon&#8217;.</note> The two first volumes I have, but the remainder were not to be had at Lisbon,
               &amp; the publication is now discontinued. It is abominably dear &amp; nine parts of it are the veryest rubbish, &#8211; but what information
               it does contain is of that nature that I would purchase at any price. I am working on steadily with my third volume, which is in the
                  press.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> To day I have begun upon a
               manuscript which that unhappy man Joam Ribeiro found in the Madre de Deos library at Pernambuco, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> made a copy of it from his transcript for my use.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Joam Ribeiro Pessoa de Melo Montenegro (1766&#8211;1817), a priest who was a member of the provisional government set up by
                  the revolutionaries in Pernambuco, 8 March&#8211;18 May 1817. He committed suicide in the town of Paulista after the defeat of the
                  revolutionary forces and the fall of Recife, the provincial capital. Ribeiro had found the manuscript in question in the Cathedral
                  Library in Recife. It is no. 3840 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, where it is described as &#8216;Guerra Civil ou Sedissoens
                  de Pernambuco Exemplo Memoravel aos vindouros 1710&#8217;. The document recounts the Mascate War (or &#8216;War of the Peddlers&#8217;) in Pernambuco
                  in 1710&#8211;1711.</note> During the last month I have kept very close to this work, which must be my main business till it is
               compleated. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have received Robert Walpoles Memoirs relative to Turkey<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Walpole
                  (1781&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs Relating to European and Asiatic Turkey</title> (1817), no. 3098 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; a note from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> informing me
               that it was sent by his desire. When you inform me of his address I will write to thank him for it, &#8211; I thought he had been in orders,
               but the title page leaves me in doubt whether he be or be not, &#8211; in the one case I should have looked for his Reverendship &#8211; in the
               other for the Esquireship; &#8211; set me right upon this point, that I may not make an awkward blunder in the direction.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Walpole was in holy orders: he was Rector of Tivetshall, Norfolk 1815&#8211;1828. However, the title page of
                  his <title>Memoirs</title> merely described him as &#8216;Robert Walpole, M. A.&#8217;.</note> As soon as I have finished my final paper upon
               the state of the Poor, (the first portion of which goes off by this post for the next Review)<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of the Report of the House of Commons Select Committee to consider the Poor Laws (1817) in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308, was mainly written by John Rickman.</note> I shall take up the Memoir of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpole in its place, as one of my daily employments, &amp; make of it the best I can, &#8211; in the almost total want
               of materials for the main subject.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Here Southey refers to a proposed memoir of Robert Walpole
                  (1736&#8211;1810), father of the Robert Walpole who wrote <title>Memoirs Relating to European and Asiatic Turkey</title> (1817). The
                  senior Robert Walpole was the British envoy to Portugal 1771&#8211;1800.</note> There is a great deal of curious matter among his papers,
               which is important to me in many ways, &#8211; but very little that relates to his own transactions. One point however is clear as daylight
               that he was very ill treated by the Ministry when he applied for an increase of his appointments;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had made this point before to May; see Robert Southey to John May, 22 August 1814, <title>The Collected
                     Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2473. </note> &#8211; that story indeed ought to have been told in Parliament when
               the debate concerning the allowance to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> &amp; Sydenham took place.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">George Canning was the British Ambassador to Portugal 1814&#8211;1815; Thomas Sydenham (1780&#8211;1816) was
                  the Minister Plenipotentiary at Lisbon 1814&#8211;1816. The opposition had moved a vote of censure on 6 May 1817 concerning the costs of
                  these posts. Canning mounted a robust defence and the opposition&#8217;s motion was lost 270&#8211;96.</note> If I had wanted anything to make
               me dislike the cold, unfeeling, ungenerous temper of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenville</ref> it would be
               his conduct towards M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpole on this occasion. &#8211; My next letter (&amp; the interval will not be so long as has
               occurred since the last) I shall report progress in the Memoir. I am very long in brooding upon the subjects which I execute, &amp;
               they sometime lie by me long in an unfinished state, &#8211; yet they are ripening the while; so that when they are taken up in earnest, it
               is with full power to go <del>with</del> thro with them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As yet I have received no intelligence of the books from Brussels, <del>xxx</del> where your consignment is. If they
               are not discovered in London, enquiry will be made concerning them forthwith of the Brussels bookseller,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1849), well-known Brussels book-dealer, from whom Southey had bought many books in his
                  continental journeys of 1815 and 1817.</note> &#8211; but I am in hopes that they will be heard of as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> would have means of asking about them this week. When they come <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> will take out yours at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>. The box from Milan is arrived in town, &#8211; when I had begun to despair of it, &#8211; it
               is a rich cargo, &amp; contains some many books which will tempt me in my horae otiosiores<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Leisure hours&#8217;.</note> to put together some supplementary notices to my journal: &#8211; from which said journal by the bye, there is a
               packet of your <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">god-daughters</ref> transcriptions to send you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Till this day no snow had fallen in the valley, &#8211; hitherto indeed the winter has been the most beautiful I ever
               remember. &#8211; I caught cold at church on Christmas day, &amp; have in consequence been laid up two days this week on the sofa, with a
               bilious attack which it induced; &#8211; it has past off &amp; left me nothing the worse. Since <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> left me I have been very steadily at work, &#8211; a long paper upon Lope de
               Vega, somewhat uncivilly shoved aside in the last Quarterly<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The article, a review of Lord
                  Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817) appeared
                  in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 1&#8211;46.</note> to make room for matters which deserved no such preference, is
               one proof: &#8211; &amp; good progress in the Brazilian history is another.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History
                     of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> Neither has the Peninsular war<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                     <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> stood still, tho it is now waiting for a book from Paris,
               announced for October last which will contain precisely the information I want for compleating the introductory chapter, &#8211; an account
               of the system of education introduced by Buonaparte throughout his empire;<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Baptist Germain
                  Fabry (1770&#8211;1821), <title>Le Ge&#769;nie de la Re&#769;volution Conside&#769;re&#769; dans l&#8217;Education ou Me&#769;moires pour Servir a l&#8217;Histoire de
                     l&#8217;Instruction Publique, Depuis 1789 jusqu&#8217;a&#768; Nos Jours</title>, 3 vols (1817&#8211;1818) contained an account of the educational
                  reforms introduced by Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; First Consul 1799&#8211;1804, Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note> &#8211; this I
               want to compleat the moral &amp; military view of France under his tyranny. I have written also a good deal of Wesley, &#8211; so much indeed
               that it will probably soon go to press, &#8211; perhaps as soon as I shall have settled with <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> the form of publication.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise
                     and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> In verse I have done very little &#8211; only about a hundred lines of the Tale of
                  Paraguay,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s verse romance <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was not completed and
                  published until 1825.</note> &#8211; &amp; my peppercorn rent for the Laureateship.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey refers
                  to the composition of the annual New Year&#8217;s Ode he was required to produce as Poet Laureate. &#8216;Funeral Song for the Princess
                  Charlotte&#8217; was not published until it appeared in <title>Friendship&#8217;s Offering: A Literary Album and Christmas and New Year&#8217;s
                     Present, for 1828</title> (London, 1828), pp. 1&#8211;6.</note> Two or three days whenever I can so bestow them, will finish the first
               canto of the Paraguay, &amp; as soon as it is finished I shall transcribe it &amp; send it you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Greek Epigram, which I had not before heard of.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.
                  Southey had been the subject of the anonymous &#8216;On Mr. Robert Southey&#8217;s Letter to W. Smith, Esq. M.P.&#8217;, written in the style of a
                  Greek epigram. It appeared in, amongst other places, the <title>Monthly Repository</title>, 12 (June 1817), 371: &#8216;Thus the veer&#8217;d
                  Laureate of our time,/ So juicy ripe for royal rhyme,/ His lofty praise rehearses,/ &#8220;What&#8217;s the good friend of Liberty,/ The
                  Patriot, Senator, to me?/ Great <hi rend="ital">I</hi> have written verses!&#8221;&#8217;</note> I live indeed in a happy state of ignorance
               &amp; indifference of all that is said about me. These are very civil lines, &amp; perhaps it is the first time that a man was ever
               called a drone by way of compliment. Apiarists however now know that the poor drones are in reality as active &amp; as useful as any
               other inhabitants of the hive. As for my sting, &#8211; perhaps <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  William Smith</ref>
          <note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> was an attack on
                  Smith. It had been published by Murray at the end of April 1817.</note> might not exactly agree with the friendly epigrammatist.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present, thank God, we are all well. Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; take our best wishes for many &amp; happy years to come. believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-01-03">3 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>