<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3072</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4343</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3072. Robert Southey to Mary
                  Barker, [29 January 1818] </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3072" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3072.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>.  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3072" type="letter">
        <head>3072. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Mary
                  Barker</ref>, <date when="1818-01-29">[29 January 1818] </date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Barker<lb /> MS:
                  MS untraced; text is taken from Robert Galloway Kirkpatrick, &#8216;The Letters of
                  Robert Southey to Mary Barker From 1800 to 1826&#8217; (unpublished PhD, Harvard, 1967),
                  pp. 447&#8211;448 [dated January 1818].<lb /> Unpublished.<lb /> Dating note: This letter
                  was written on a Thursday before Candlemas (i.e. 2 February 1818) and whilst
                  Southey was still in hope that the books that he had bought in Milan in 1817 might
                  arrive imminently. The only date that meets all these criteria is 29 January
                  1818.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> Dear Senhora</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Because you have not law enough upon your hands, I send you a case
               upon which I shall be much obliged to you to ask the advice of your nonpareil Lawyer
               Mr Edmunds.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Edmunds (d. 1826), an
                  Ambleside attorney. He was a well-known Whig and supporter of Brougham&#8217;s
                  parliamentary candidacy in 1818, hence Southey&#8217;s comment. Mary Barker&#8217;s financial
                  difficulties arising from the construction of her house at Rosthwaite, Borrowdale
                  were no doubt providing Edmunds with plenty of work.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Betty (whose law name is Elizabeth Thompson)<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Thompson (c. 1777&#8211;1862), the Southeys&#8217; long-standing
                  servant. She was buried in the Southey family grave.</note> has thirty pounds
               owing to her by George Ellis<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George Ellis
                  (dates unknown) was possibly a stuff weaver of this name from Ambleside.</note> of
               <ref type="m" target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref>, a worthless fellow, who by virtue of the
               Insolvent Act (alias the Rogues Jubilee-Bill) is just come out of Carlisle
                  Castle.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Insolvent Debtors (England)
                  Act (1813) provided for the release of people incarcerated for debt if they came
                  to an agreement with their creditors. Carlisle Castle was the jail for the County
                  of Cumberland.</note> The money was lent in two sums by her father; <hi rend="ital">his</hi> father<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly
                  Joseph or Thomas Ellis (dates unknown), masons at Ambleside.</note> is bound for
               the one of &#163;10, &amp; this she supposes to be safe, he being reckoned a substantial
               man. His wifes father John Seward of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Ambleside">Ambleside</ref> was
               bound for the other &#163;20; this John Seward is dead, &amp; James his son is his
                  Executor.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John and James Seward are
                  unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> &#8211; Do you understand me? as
               Dryander said to Dr Willich when he told him &#8211; Dr Veeleec, &#8211; Sir Joseph says you are
               not to come here any more.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Jonas Carlsson
                  Dryander (1748&#8211;1810) was a Swedish botanist and the librarian of the scientist and
                  President of the Royal Society, Sir Joseph Banks (1743&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>).
                  The &#8216;Dr Willich&#8217; refused access was probably the German physician and writer,
                  Anthony Florian Madinger Willich (d. 1804). Willich was well-known in literary
                  circles and had taught Walter Scott to speak German in Edinburgh in 1792.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ellis has been here since he was hatched from Jail. he says he has
               nothing to do with the business himself, &#8211; which is true enough, &#8211; the more&#8217;s the
               pity: &amp; he wants her to wait for the &#163;20 from John Sewards estate till the
                  Candlemas<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Feast of the Presentation
                  of Jesus at the Temple, held on 2 February.</note> of <hi rend="ital">next</hi>
               year, instead of receiving it next Candlemas, because he says they have a great deal
               to do; &amp; it will be more convenient that the payment be delayed. To this she has
               no objection whatever, if there is reason to think that she may wait safely. Mr
               Edmunds, living on the spot, may probably know the state of this John Sewards
               affairs, &amp; will perhaps have the knowledge to say in what manner she had better
               act, &#8211; whether to wait patiently, or make her demand at once, lest if there be a
               scramble she lose all by coming in too late. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Nuns of the Desert indeed,&#8221;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Alethea Lewis (1749&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Nuns of the Desert: or,
                     the Woodland Witches</title> (1805). Alethea Lewis lived at Penkridge,
                  Staffordshire and so was probably known to Mary Barker.</note> &#8211; &amp; a male
               visitor who talks of kissing! &#8211; Pray of what order may the Nuns be? &#8211; I like your old
               man much.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A note on the manuscript in
                  Barker&#8217;s hand explains the news to which Southey was alluding: &#8216;A very curious old
                  man was here last week. On going away I asked him to come and see me again &#8211;
                  &#8220;Then,&#8221; said the old man, &#8220;if I am to come and see you again let us have a kiss
                  before we part&#8221;.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> went
               yesterday for Sedburgh,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall married,
                  in 1820, Ann Sedgwick (1789&#8211;1862) of Dent, near Sedbergh, about forty miles
                  southeast of Keswick.</note> &amp; we are going tomorrow evening to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrothersMrs">Mrs Crothers&#8217;</ref>. I am very busy, &#8211; &amp; there is a <hi rend="ital">possibility</hi> that my box from Milan may arrive today.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been waiting since the autumn of 1817 for the
                  delivery of books he had bought in Milan. They had arrived in London at the end of
                  the year and were being held at the Customs House. </note> All as usual except
               that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs C.</ref> has a trunk in her head,
               &#8211; which as you may well suppose must be a very uncomfortable thing. This trunk which
               is at the same time in her head &amp; on the road to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref>
          <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent
                  Coleridge lived with the Hopwood family, well-connected Lancashire landowners, at
                  Summerhill, near Ulverston 1817&#8211;1819. Robert Gregge Hopwood (1773&#8211;1854) had
                  married in 1805 Cecilia Elizabeth Byng (1770&#8211;1854), daughter of John Byng, 5th
                  Viscount Torrington (1743&#8211;1813); Derwent was tutor to the Hopwoods&#8217; sons: Edward
                  (1807&#8211;1891); Frank (1810&#8211;1890); and Hervey (1811&#8211;1881).</note> (being like
                  Kehama<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">One of the powers of the central
                  protagonist of Southey&#8217;s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> in more
               places than one at once,) is to catch a rheumatic fever on the way, &amp; communicate
               it to Derwent. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">So farewell</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1818-01-29">Thursday morning.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>