<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3021</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4292</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3021. Robert Southey to John Murray, 4 September 1817 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3021.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS;
                  4p.  .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York,
                  1965), II, pp. 171&#8211;172.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3021" type="letter">
        <head>3021. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1817-09-04">4 September 1817 </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 8 SE 8/ 1817 <lb /> Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb /> Watermark: R E
                  &amp; S BATH 1814<lb /> Endorsement: R Southey 4 Sept/ <del>4 Oct</del> 1817<lb /> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42551. ALS;
                  4p. <lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York,
                  1965), II, pp. 171&#8211;172.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-09-04">4 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Of course I postponed the paper upon East Africa, in consequence of your first note: &#8211; &amp; perhaps I was not sorry
               {that I should only have} to furnish <del>only</del> an article upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord
                  Hollands</ref> book for your next number,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October
                  1817), 1&#8211;46, Southey reviewed Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen
                     de Castro</title> (1817). His article on East Africa was not written.</note> having at present a strong appetite toward my
               greater undertakings. It will not be long before I send you the first chapter of the History of the War,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 3&#8211;62.</note> &#8211; &amp; when
               that chapter is dispatched, the whole will go smoothly on till it is compleated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There can be no better subject for a good &amp; efficient paper than <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> volumes will afford, &#8211; after <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitts</ref> review of them shall have appeared;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Hazlitt reviewed Coleridge&#8217;s <title>Biographia Literaria</title> (1817) in the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 28 (August 1817),
                  488&#8211;515. Southey did not review Coleridge&#8217;s book in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note>
          <del>xxx</del> I am very ready to undertake it, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">omnibus viribus</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;With
                  all my powers&#8217;.</note> &#8211; beginning very quietly, proceeding clearly &amp; discretely <del>xx</del> so as to make the readers on our
               side, &amp; lastly laying it on with a willing hand &amp; a cat &amp; nine tails.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The reign <del>of George 3</del>, &#8211; or more properly as I should <del>xx</del> call it the Age of George 3, is as you
               know one of those subjects which I propose to myself one day to treat at full length, in a manner commensurate with the importance of
               the argument.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this book on the times of George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of
                  Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), or write a review article on the subject.</note> What I may do for the review will
               bear the same relation to this work {in some respects} as the reviewal of Nelson did to the life,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review article on the life of Horatio Nelson (1758&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 3 (February 1810), 218&#8211;262, laid the basis for his full-scale <title>Life of Nelson</title> (1813).</note> &#8211; but
               the arrangement would be very different, because the book would contain in the briefest form of philosophical summary the contemporary
               history of Europe &amp; the world, &#8211; &amp; the reviewal must of necessity limit its range. Let the first paper include every thing
               anterior to the American war,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The American War of Independence 1775&#8211;1783.</note> &#8211; that war must
               be treated separately, &#8211; being indeed a fine subject for a detached history of that kind which deals more in causes &amp; consequences
               than in detail, yet selects from the detail whatever is most striking. &#8211; You have sent me <ref type="m" target="people.html#AikinJohn">Aikins</ref> Annals<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Aikin, <title>Annals of the Reign of King George III
                  </title>(1816), no. 20 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; let me have whatever other histories of the reign have
               been written &#8211; I recollect Macfarlanes (this I think is the name &#8211; the author was run over by a carriage in <ref type="m" target="people.html#Burdett">Burdetts</ref> mob, &amp; killed)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert MacFarlan (1734&#8211;1804;
                     <title>DNB</title>) wrote the first and fourth books of the 4-volume <title>History of the Reign of George III</title>
                  (1770&#8211;1796), no. 1774 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. He fell under a carriage at Hammersmith in 1804 during the
                  Middlesex election campaign of Sir Francis Burdett.</note> &#8211; Adolphus&#8217;s,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Adolphus
                  (1768&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of England, from the Accession of George III, to the Conclusion of Peace in the Year
                     of One Thousand Seven Hundred and Eighty-Three</title> (1802). This book was regularly updated and the 4th edition of 1817 was
                  no. 20 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; &amp; T. Campbells<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas
                  Campbell (1777&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Annals of Great Britain, from the Ascension of George III, to the Peace of
                     Amiens</title> (1807), no. 532 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; neither of which have I ever seen. Let me
               have also Woodfalls Junius,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The printer and journalist Henry Sampson Woodfall (1739&#8211;1805;
                     <title>DNB</title>) published <title>The Letters of Junius</title> (1771), no. 1540 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> &amp; the two publications of Walkers Letters<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Walker (d. 1817)
                  published editions of <title>The Letters of Junius</title> (1806) and (1807).</note>: the Anecdotes of Lord Chatham,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John Almon (1737&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>) produced <title>Anecdotes of the Life of the Right Hon.
                     William Pitt, Earl of Chatham</title> (1792). A 7th edition of 1810 was no. 580 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> &#8211; &amp; that I may lay the foundations of my own knowledge well, &#8211; the lives of Sir Robert Walpole, &amp; of his
               brother Lord Walpole.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Walpole, 1st Earl of Orford (1676&#8211;1745; <title>DNB</title>), Prime
                  Minister 1721&#8211;1742 and his brother Horatio Walpole, 1st Baron Walpole (1678&#8211;1757; <title>DNB</title>). The books Southey sought were
                  William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Administration of Sir Robert Walpole</title> (1798) and <title>Memoirs of Horatio, Lord
                     Walpole</title> (1802). Second editions of these works, from 1800 and 1808 respectively, were nos 752 and 754 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. </note> The last paper should relate to the progress of science arts &amp; literature &#8211; the moral
               &amp; intellectual picture of our Georgian Age, &#8211; a name which by that time we shall be strong enough to affix to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let me review the book about New Zealand,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not review a book about
                  New Zealand in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. The book Murray had suggested was probably John Liddiard Nicholas (1784&#8211;1868),
                     <title>Narrative of a Voyage to New Zealand, Performed in the Years 1814 and 1815, in Company with the Rev. Samuel
                     Marsden</title> (1817), no. 2037 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &amp; send me with it Savages book,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John Savage (1770&#8211;1838), <title>Some Account of New Zealand: Particularly the Bay Islands, and
                     Surrounding Country; with a Description of the Religion and Government &amp;c.</title> (1807). Murray was the publisher.</note> &#8211;
               &amp; Sir Richard Hoares Ancient Wiltshire,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Richard Colt Hoare (1758&#8211;1838;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Ancient History of North and South Wiltshire</title> (1812&#8211;1819).</note> which will bear both upon N
               Zealand &amp; the <hi rend="ital">Catacombs</hi>:<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review article &#8216;Cemeteries and
                  Catacombs of Paris&#8217; appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359&#8211;398. </note> for I believe there are some
               striking points of similarities between the N Zealanders &amp; our British ancestors. And in your next parcel let me have half a dozen
               copies of my tender Epistle to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith</ref>,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The pamphlet Southey published with Murray, <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title>.
                  (1817). A copy with &#8216;<hi rend="ital">red morocco, gilt leaves</hi>&#8217; was no. 2695 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; I
               should like to have one in handsome binding.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I never have sketched the whole of any thing before it went to the press. Particular parts are written twice or thrice
               over, &#8211; &amp; indeed every part which does not consist of mere narrative is rough written before it is transcribed, &#8211; but the first
               draught suffices for narration. When indeed many &amp; various authorities are to be consulted the case is different, &#8211; if ever I
               should have the satisfaction of seeing you here, I will show you the first MS. of my Hist. of Brazil,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &amp; you will then understand how truly laborious a
               writer I am, when patient &amp; persevering labour is necessary. But for the reign of George 3 it is sufficient if the division be
               clearly marked out in my own mind. I think what has already been done in the Life of Wellington<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s reviews of a series of books on the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Duke of Wellington</ref>
                  were given the running title of &#8216;Life of Wellington&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 215&#8211;275, and
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448&#8211;526. </note> &amp; by some other person in the Life of Pitt<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">John Gifford (1758&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A History of the Political Life of the Right
                     Honourable William Pitt; Including Some Account of the Times in which he Lived</title> (1809), reviewed by Robert Grant
                  (1780&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>) and George Canning in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 4 (August 1810), 207&#8211;271.</note> might excuse
               the necessity of including the time from the beginning of the French Revolution. This however is for after consideration.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall be very civil to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Ld Holland</ref>, who deserves every kind
               of civility from men of letters, &amp; is so delightful a man, that I heartily wish he had been bred on a better school of taste,
               morals, politics &amp; philosophy. I heartily wish that I had the collected edition of Lope de Vega,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio de Sancha (1720&#8211;1790), <title>Colecci&#243;n de las Obras Sueltas, Assi en Prosa, Como en Verso, de D. Frey Lope
                     Felix de Vega Carpio</title> (1776&#8211;1779), a collected edition of the works of F&#233;lix Arturo Lope de Vega y Carpio (1562&#8211;1635).</note> &#8211; I
               have a good many of his works separately, in the original editions, &#8211; but it would be much more satisfactory to possess the whole. The
               one which I suspect would be of most use to me is El Peregrino en su Patria.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Lope de Vega,
                     <title>El Peregrino en su Patria</title> (1604). Southey later acquired editions of 1618 (no. 3672 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library) and 1733 (no. 3762 in the sale catalogue of his library).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>