<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2875</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4146</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2875. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [started before and
               continued on] 8 December [1816]</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2875.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 227&#8211;229 [in part; dated 7&#8211;8 December
               1816]</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2875" type="letter">
        <head>2875. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, [started before and
               continued on] <date when="1816-12-08">8 December [1816]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ <del>Xxxxxxx</del>/ <del>Wrexham</del>/ {Llangedwyn/ Oswestry}<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS:
                  National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 227&#8211;229 [in part; dated 7&#8211;8 December
               1816]</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonJohn">Wilson</ref>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wilson lived at Elleray, on Lake
                  Windermere. He published the <title>Isle of Palms, and Other Poems</title> (1812), followed by <title>The City of the Plague</title> (1816), set
                  during the Great Plague of London in 1665.</note> is a man of such sensitive feelings that he suffers no poultry to be kept about
               his house, because he could not bear to eat creatures which should have fed in his sight, &#8211; &amp; he is &#8211; the greatest cockfighter in
               the country. He is a man of great genius who delights in blackguard company, &amp; has more than once in his fits of drunken insanity
               very nearly come to an untimely end. Withall he has some good qualities of which I believe generosity is the best. I disapprove his
               mode of life so much that I have shunned his society. And partly for this reason, partly because I did not chuse to review his Isle of
               Palms in compliance with a request which, very improperly, was made to me, with his knowledge he I believe bears me a respectful sort
               of dislike.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> With a great deal of genius his former volume is one continued string of plagiarisms of the worst kind, &#8211; chiefly from
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, whom he is constantly caricaturing by the most injudicious
               imitation. The great fault of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is regarding all things too much in
               one strain of mind, &amp; regarding the great &amp; the little with equal force of passion, &amp; equal effort of thought. And this
               fault is carried to a tenfold degree by <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonJohn">Wilson</ref> in that volume which alone I have
               seen; &#8211; with little or no strength of thought to support him. His friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#DeQuinceyThomas">De
                  Quincey</ref> tells me the plagiarism is quite as great in this. But my dear Wynn is there not something monstrous in taking such a
               subject as the Plague in a great city &#8211; Surely it is out-Germanizing the Germans. It is <del>xx</del> bringing racks wheels &amp; red
               hot pincers upon the stage to excite pathos. No doubt but a very pathetic tragedy might be written upon &#8220;the Chamber of the Amputation&#8221;
               &#8211; <del>xx xx</del> cutting for the stone, or the Caesarean operation. <del>There is something</del> but these actual &amp; tangible
               horrors do not belong to poetry &#8211; We do not <del>xxx</del> exhibit G Barnwell upon the ladder {<del>xxx</del>}, to affect the gallery
               {now} as was originally done,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George Lillo (1691&#8211;1739; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The London
                     Merchant</title> (1731), was an enormously popular play that told the story of George Barnwell, executed for murdering his uncle.
                  It was based on a seventeenth century ballad about a murder in Shropshire.</note> &#8211; &amp; the best picture of Apollo fleaing
                  Marsyas,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek legend, the satyr Marsyas was flayed alive by Apollo after challenging the
                  god to a music contest and losing. There are a number of famous paintings of the incident, including Titian (c. 1488&#8211;1576), &#8216;The
                  Flaying of Marsyas&#8217; (c. 1570&#8211;1576).</note> or of the martyrdom of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bartholemew<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Saint Bartholomew (1st century AD), one of the Apostles, was, in later tradition, executed by being flayed alive. He
                  was often depicted in art holding his flayed skin as in Michelangelo (1475&#8211;1564) &#8216;The Last Judgement&#8217; (1536&#8211;1541).</note> would be
               regarded as <del>xxx</del> more disgusting than one of a slaughter house, or of a dissecting room.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What news tomorrow may bring of Mondays riots<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spa Fields Riots of 2 December
                  1816. Most of a crowd of about 20,000 had assembled at Spa Fields, Islington to hear the radical speaker Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt
                  (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>). But a small group of revolutionaries broke away from the crowd and attempted to storm the Tower of
                  London, looting a gun shop on the way. They were dispersed by troops at the Royal Exchange. The government responded with a new
                  Treason Act and a new Seditious Meetings Act in 1817.</note> God knows &#8211; the loss of some lives I <del>xxx</del> expect, &amp; this
               I am sure of that if Government refrain much longer from exerting those means which are intrusted <del>it</del> to it for the
               preservation of public security, the alternative will be ere long between revolution &amp; a military system.</p>
        <p rend="center"> __</p>
        <p rend="indent0">
          <date when="1816-12-08"> 8 Dec.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am more sorry than surprized to see so many sailors in the mob. It has always been the custom to disband as many men
               as possible at the conclusion of a war, &#8211; but there has been often a great cruelty in this, &amp; in the present instance a great &amp;
               glaring impolicy. The immediate cause of that distress which was felt in the beginning of the year was an enormous diminution of
               national expenditure &#8211; the War, a customer of 50 millions, being taken out of the market; &amp; consequently a great number of hands
               put out of employ. Now surely <del>xx xxxx Irish way to remedy the</del> to spend less, &amp; to turn off more hands, &#8211; is but an Irish
               way of remedying this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You who know how much my thoughts have been led toward the subject will not be surprized to hear that I am writing
               Observations upon the Moral &amp; Political state of England.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been asked to edit a
                  pro-government journal, but declined. Instead he proposed to write a pamphlet, or book, with this title. This project was not
                  realised and instead Southey wrote on &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 225&#8211;278, and the
                  &#8216;Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511&#8211;552.</note> What I have at
               different times written in the Quarterly has sometimes been mutilated, &amp; always written under a certain degree of restraint to
               prevent mutilation. But I have heard of these things from many quarters, &amp; seen that when the author was not suspected, they have
               produced an impression. And I am disposed to think <del>that</del> it not unlikely that I may do some present good, &amp; almost
               certain that if this hope be disappointed for the present it must sooner or later take effect. There is plenty of zeal in the country,
               &amp; abundance of good intentions, which if they were well directed might be of infinite service: there are great &amp; sore evils
               which may certainly be alleviated if not removed, &#8211; &amp; there are dangers which we ought to look fairly in the face. &#8211; I have nothing
               to hope or fear for myself, &amp; the sole personal consideration that can influence me is the desire of acquitting myself at least of
               the sin of omission. Better that the candle should be blown out, than that it should be a bushel.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Neither do men light a candle, and put it under a bushel, but on a candlestick&#8217;, <title>Matthew</title> 5:
                  15.</note> &#8211; Whether I am ripe in judgement must be for others to determine: this I know that I am grown old at heart, I bore up
               under the freshness of my loss<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The death of Southey&#8217;s son <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> on 17 April 1816.</note> with surprising strength, &amp; still carry a serene
               front; &#8211; but it has changed me more than years or bodily disease could <del>ever</del> have done, &#8211; &amp; time enough has now elapsed
               to show how very little <del>time can</del> {it will ever} effect in <del>xxx</del> restoring my former nature. It is a relief &amp; a
               comfort to employ myself usefully, or at least <del>xxx</del> in endeavouring to be useful</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Wynn</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>