<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3027</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4298</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3027. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 6 October
                  1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3027.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and
                  Art Gallery, WC 160. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3027" type="letter">
        <head>3027. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1817-10-06">6 October
                  1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmark: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ OC 9/ 1817 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb /> Seal: red wax, design illegible<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and
                  Art Gallery, WC 160. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1"> The manuscript<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A section of the second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819). The publication of this volume had been announced in May 1817, see, for example, <title>Morning
                     Chronicle</title>, 28 May 1817, but had been delayed because this part of the manuscript had been mislaid.</note> no doubt will
               be found at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>, they having told me that they had laid it aside, not
               thinking it worth while to put it to press before my journey to the continent. I have written to remind them of this. If it be lost I
               shall be angry, &amp; with good reason, &#8211; but the original is at hand &amp; it is only the time required for transcription that would
               be wasted. &#8211; How is it that the last portion should have reached you unfranked &#8211; if it had been properly forwarded from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>, the original frank would have carried it any where.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have read Llorentes <del>xxx</del> history<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Antonio Llorente (1756&#8211;1823),
                     <title>Histoire Critique de l&#8217;Inquisition d&#8217;Espagne</title> (1817&#8211;1818). Murray had sought advice on whether an English
                  translation was advisable, but did not take up the option and no English version appeared until 1826. The French translation was no.
                  1738 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; in the Spanish. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>
               sent me the manuscript. There is much curious matter in it, tho I do not remember that any light was thrown upon the affair of Antonio
                  Perez.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio P&#233;rez (1540&#8211;1611), a senior Spanish civil servant, fled into exile in 1591
                  after being accused of murder and heresy by the Spanish Inquisition.</note> A history of the troubles in Aragon which grew out of
               that business written by Lupercio Leonardo de Argensola was printed during the liberty of the press in Spain.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Lupercio Leonardo de Argensola (1559&#8211;1613), <title>Informaci&#243;n de los Sucesos del Reino de Aragon en los a&#241;os de 1590
                     y 1591</title> (1808), no. 3172 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The book was a presentation copy from its editor,
                  Manuel Abella. Perez had attempted to escape the charges against him by fleeing to Aragon and claiming the right to be charged under
                  Aragonese judicial processes. This led to a prolonged constitutional crisis in Spain during 1590&#8211;1591.</note> Of this I have a copy.
               &#8211; If Llorente has not extracted all the important matter of his papers for his own work, he has not acted fairly as an historian; &#8211; if
               he has he is not acting fairly in setting such a price upon them. And it is very clear that he has not come by these papers honestly;
               but must (to use a gentle term) have taken advantage of his official situation to abstract them.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Llorente was Secretary-General to the Inquisition at Madrid 1789&#8211;1794, but supported the French-backed regime of 1808&#8211;1813 and was
                  given control of the Inquisition&#8217;s archive.</note> The papers of the Inquisition ought upon its dissolution to have been deposited
               among the archives of the Government, &#8211; &amp; certainly could not have been left to take their chance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Farther accounts have arrived from <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">H. Koster</ref>, compleating the
               story of the insurrection in Pernambuco. P. Joam Ribeiro, it seems, destroyed himself.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joam
                  Ribeiro Pessoa de Melo Montenegro (1766&#8211;1817), a priest who was a member of the provisional government set up by a group of
                  revolutionaries in Pernambuco, 8 March&#8211;18 May 1817. He committed suicide in the town of Paulista after the defeat of the
                  revolutionary forces and the fall of Recife, the provincial capital.</note> &#8211; This unhappy man had promised me, unsolicited, a
               manuscript concerning the last trouble in that captaincy, containing the popular side of the story, in opposition to one which <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> brought over;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Guerra Civil ou
                  Sedissoens de Pernambuco Exemplo Memoravel aos vindouros 1710&#8217;, no. 3840 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was an
                  account of the Mascate War (or &#8216;War of the Peddlers&#8217;) in Pernambuco, Brazil in 1710&#8211;1711, between landowners based around Olinda and
                  merchants in Recife (backed by the colonial government). The landowners&#8217; leaders were the first to call for Brazil to become an
                  independent Republic. Koster&#8217;s manuscript was decidedly favourable to the colonial government &#8211; he had sent it to Southey in
                  1815.</note> &#8211; &amp; at my desire, he was to have given me in detail his reasons for believing that the suppression of the Jesuits
               was a politic measure, as far as it concerned Brazil.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Society of Jesus was expelled from
                  Brazil in 1759.</note> He understood English &amp; was much interested in the progress of my work. I sent him the first volume about
               two years ago, &amp; the second was on the way to him, when he came to this miserable end.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  first two volumes of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> I am sorry to see from the list of persons
               implicated that <del>the xxxx</del> many of the great landed proprietors, took part with the revolutionists, &#8211; the Albuquerques in
               particular are involved.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Various branches of the Albuquerque dynasty, among the most powerful
                  and largest landowners in northern Brazil, featured prominently in the 1817 revolt in Pernambuco.</note> If my wishes were any way
               doubtful respecting the struggle in Spanish America, the state of Brazil would now decide them. I heartily wish to see the authority of
               the mother country reestablished, because it will secure the tranquillity of the Portugueze possessions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HolroydJohnBaker">Lord Sheffield</ref> has sent me the whole details of the recovery of Lerida,
               Mequincaza &amp; Monzon by Baron d&#8217;Eroles<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Joaqu&#237;n Ib&#225;&#241;ez Cuevas y de Valonga, Baron de Eroles
                  (1784&#8211;1825), one of the key leaders of the Army of Catalonia in the Peninsular War. The French garrisons of Lerida, Mequincaza and
                  Monzon were tricked into surrendering in February 1814 by forged documents that claimed the war was over.</note> toward the
               conclusion of the war. &#8211; I have been working at my first chapter,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the
                     Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 3&#8211;62.</note> &amp; shall stick to it tooth &amp; nail as soon as I
               have done with the review; &#8211; for which I am employed upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Hollands</ref> Lope
               de Vega.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of
                     Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817) was published in<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October
                  1817), 1&#8211;46.</note> &#8211; My review I suspect will have cost me more reading than <del>xxx</del> was thought sufficient for his volume,
               I have very nearly read thro the Arcadia<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">F&#233;lix Arturo Lope de Vega y Carpio (1562&#8211;1635),
                     <title>Arcadia</title> (1598), a pastoral novel.</note> to day (which I had not patience to do twenty years ago. You will
               perceive that I have made out some things respecting his private history which had escaped all his biographers, &#8211; &amp; that I have
                  <del>xxx</del> subjected the account of his writings to the best of arithmetic &#8211; which they had all neglected to do, <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord H.</ref> as well as the rest.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 11&#8211;12, Southey demonstrated that Lope de Vega could not have written 1800 plays, 400 sacred
                  dramas and over 21 million verses, as was often claimed.</note> &#8211; Do you happen to know who is the author of the satirical poem in
               the Fenis Renaseida, &#8211; Jornada que Diogo Camacho Fez as Cortes do Parnaso?<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Diogo de Sousa
                  (16th&#8211;17th centuries), <title>Jornada &#225;s cortes do Parnaso de Diogo Camacho</title>, a satirical journey to Parnassus probably
                  written 1614&#8211;1621. It was first published in <title>A Fenix Renascida</title> (Lisbon, 1716&#8211;1728). Southey possessed a 1746 edition
                  of this work, no. 3647 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; I have occasion to quote it in this paper:<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 32&#8211;33, contained a lengthy translation of the
                     <title>Jornada as cortes do Parnaso</title> from <title>A Fenix Renascinda ou Obras Poeticas dos Melhores Eugenhos
                     Portuguezes</title>, 5 vols (Lisbon, 1746), V, pp. 13&#8211;14. Southey correctly identified the author as Diogo de Sousa.</note>
               perhaps it may be found in your <del>xxx</del> compendium of Barbosa.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Diogo Barbosa Machado
                  (1682&#8211;1772), <title>Bibliotheca Lusitana</title> (1741&#8211;1759). This was the first major reference work of Portuguese
                  publications.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> has been here, <del>xxxx</del> I hope he will learn some
               tidings of my books now that he is returned to London.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The books that Southey had purchased in
                  Milan and Brussels on his continental journey in 1817.</note> I have been very idle since my return &amp; now that I am settled to
               my desk it is not a pleasant thing to perceive how much better motion agrees with me than rest. &#8211; We have had a smart influenza thro
               the family, &#8211; but it is past away. Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the Orsini &#8211; <note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The Hills&#8217; children.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-10-06">6 Oct. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>