<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3131</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4402</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3131. Robert Southey to John May,
                  8 May 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3131.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                  University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Ramos
                  (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838
                  (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 166&#8211;168.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3131" type="letter">
        <head>3131. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,
                  <date when="1818-05-08">8 May 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks:
                  [partial] E; 10 o&#8217;Clock/ MY.11/ 1818 F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb /> Watermark: B.
                  E. &amp; S. Bath 1814 <lb /> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 199 1818/ Robert
                  Southey/ Keswick 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July<lb /> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center,
                  University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Ramos
                  (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title>
                  (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 166&#8211;168.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-05-08">8 May. 1818.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope very shortly to give you some good tidings of your books from
               Brussels, having ascertained that they were shipt at Antwerp on the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> April. In all likelihood they are at this time in the Custom House, but
               the enquiry there &amp; the removal from thence depend upon the convenience &amp;
               leisure of no less a personage than Rothschild,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathan Mayer von Rothschild (1777&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>),
                  Jewish banker and founder in 1811 of N. M. Rothschild and Sons, a leading firm in
                  the City of London and central to the world-wide trade in gold bullion and
                  government bonds. Southey may have been put in touch with Rothschild by John
                  Charles Herries, the former Commissary-in-Chief, who worked closely with
                  Rothschild to ensure the transfer of funds to pay British troops during the
                  Peninsular War. Rothschild&#8217;s key role in the financial aspect of the British war
                  effort no doubt made Southey well-disposed towards him; and Rothschild&#8217;s network
                  of agents, shippers and couriers made him ideally-placed to expedite the books
                  Southey had bought in Brussels in 1817 through British customs. Southey had also
                  bought some books for John May.</note> with whom I have no acquaintance
               whatsoever, &amp; who if he were not one of the best-natured of all possible Jews,
               would certainly not bestow a minutes thought or trouble upon such an affair, from his
               weighty concerns in the three &amp; a halfs &amp;c.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The government&#8217;s new issue of 3&#189; per cent stock was not selling
                  well and was declining in value; among the major subscribers was Rothschild&#8217;s
                  firm, which had reportedly invested &#163;2 million; see the <title>Morning
                     Chronicle</title>, 20 April 1818.</note> For unless report wrongs him greatly
               he is one of those sweet like Mosaic Cherubs who sit up aloft, &amp; sway the scales
               of finance as Jupiter<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Biblical
                  prophet Moses was commanded by God to construct two golden cherubs to place on
                  top of the gold slab covering the Ark of the Covenant, <title>Exodus</title> 25:
                  18&#8211;20; Southey compares this image to Jupiter, the supreme Roman god, who was
                  sometimes portrayed as holding the scales of fate.</note> is represented holding
               the scales of fate. &#8211; As soon as the cases are safely lodged in <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">the Row</ref>, I will take
               care that your books shall be looked out &amp; sent to <ref type="m" target="places.html#TavistockStreet">Tavistock Street</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For myself I hardly expect to see this cargo for three months. Some
               little repairs from the bookbinders will be desirable while they are in London, &amp;
               they will then have to wait for one of <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Vardons</ref> ships to Newcastle whither he gives them
               a passage. They fill three cases, the Acta Sanctorum being fifty two volumes of large
               &amp; full folios.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had bought in
                  Brussels the massive, 53&#8211;volume, compendium of hagiographies entitled <title>Acta
                     Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library.</note> Of this book without which it is not possible to write the early
               history of any part of Christendom as it ought to be written, there was no copy in
               England, till the British Museum sent for one, upon Gibbon&#8217;s<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), author of a
                     <title>History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title>
                  (1776&#8211;1788).</note> applying for it there, <del>xx xxx</del>. So at least I have
               heard, tho I cannot call to mind upon what authority. I shall find it of
               indispensable use in the History of Portugal,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> &#8211; to the publication of
               which I now begin to look on with more impatience, as the time draws nearer.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Quarterly Review by its long delay,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Quarterly Review</title> was running considerably in
                  arrears: volume 18 (January 1818) did not appear until 9 June 1818. It contained
                  Southey and Rickman&#8217;s article, &#8216;On the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                  Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308; Southey placed the remaining material
                  in his &#8216;On the Means of Improving the People&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19
                  (April 1818), 79&#8211;118.</note> &amp; by the exertions which I made not to be the
               cause of delaying it three months ago, has given me a good holyday, &amp; I have made
               good use of it in getting on with Brazil.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> Two &amp; twenty
               sheets are printed &amp; I am two chapters ahead of the press, &#8211; speaking of what is
               fairly transcribed, &amp; in the printers hands, or ready to send off. The most
               laborious part &#8211; that which related to the Mines, &amp; for which the materials were
               wholly manuscript &amp; of the most disjointed nature, &#8211; is compleated;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapters 32&#8211;33, <title>History of Brazil</title>,
                  3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 40&#8211;161, on the development of mining in
                  inland Brazil.</note> indeed the operose part of the work is accomplished. If I
               judge rightly this last volume will rather exceed the preceding ones in interest than
               fall short of them. &#8211; The first proof of the Life of Wesley reached me on Monday
               last; &#8211; this will extend to two full sized octavos.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of
                     Methodism</title> (1820).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">God
                  daughter</ref> has found a curious piece of antiquity, a copper
               spear-head, perfectly enamelled with verdigrease. It was lying among the crags of one
               of our mountains on the surface of the ground, &amp; there it must have lain from the
               time when spears were used in this part of the country, &amp; copper supplied the
               place of iron. There are copper mines near us. It is very well made, well shaped
               &amp; just a span in length.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> An electioneering fever is raging in the neighbouring county with the
               utmost virulence,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A general election was
                  imminent, though the House of Commons was not dissolved until 10 June 1818. It was
                  already clear, though, that there would be a contest in Westmorland, which was
                  dominated by the Lowther family, who were supporters of the government &#8211; the two
                  sitting MPs were the brothers Henry Lowther (1790&#8211;1867), MP for Westmorland
                  1812&#8211;1867 and William, Viscount Lowther (1787&#8211;1872), later 2nd Earl of Lonsdale
                  and MP for Cockermouth 1808&#8211;1813, MP for Westmorland 1813&#8211;1831 and 1832&#8211;1841. So
                  complete was the Lowthers&#8217; dominance that the last contested election in
                  Westmorland was in 1774. However, in January 1818, a committee of Whigs and
                  smaller landowners had brought forward Henry Brougham to challenge the Lowthers &#8211;
                  Brougham&#8217;s family home was Brougham Hall near Penrith and he could plausibly be
                  presented as a local candidate.</note> &#8211; we are luckily not in the sphere of its
               influence. Whatever may be the issue of the contest, it will leave a great deal of
               ill-blood behind it, more I believe than ever was known in these parts. I myself
               rather incline to think that Parliament will not be dissolved this year,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A general election was called on 10 June
                  1818.</note> &#8211; the chance of the Kings death in the course of the next twelve
                  months<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of
                  Great Britain and Ireland 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) died on 29 January 1820;
                  this event automatically triggered the dissolution of parliament on 29 February
                  1820.</note> is surely to be <del>xxx</del> placed among probable contingencies,
               &amp; General Elections are not such public blessings that any Ministry should desire
               to have one upon the heels of another. Now that there is nothing of importance at
               stake, one may look upon politics as upon a game in which we have no interest. Both
               parties go blundering on, &#8211; a great stir is made about things of little consequence,
               &amp; some good is done, tho very seldom in the way it ought to be. &#8211; Meantime the
               longer peace endures on the continent, the longer it is likely to endure. &#8211;
               Sovereigns are sick of war, &amp; every day is lessening the number of those persons
               who can live in no other element.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think Spain will recover her colonies if America does not take part
               in the war,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Spain sent an expeditionary
                  force of 10,500 men to South America in 1815 to bolster local royalist forces and
                  enjoyed considerable success in New Granada and Chile. The United States did not
                  intervene directly in the conflict.</note> the Americans are likely enough to do
               so, for I do not believe that a more thoroughly ambitious &amp; unprincipled
               government has existed, since the time of the Roman Republic. But even in that case
               the event would be very doubtful; &#8211; for even the Americans would feel little appetite
               for such warfare as is there carried on when once they had tasted it, &amp; the
               Spaniards are a people <del>whom</del> who in no instance, have ever given up any one
               object {in} which they had heartily engaged. I was more sorry for Mina when I heard
               of his departure for Mexico, than I was for his death,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Javier Mina y Larrea (1789&#8211;1817), Spanish guerilla
                  leader, exiled after an unsuccessful rising in 1814 against royal absolutism. He
                  joined the Mexican independence movement in 1816 and was executed by royalist
                  forces on 11 November 1817.</note> &#8211; for death is better than to find {himself}
               engaged in such a war, not by any dreadful necessity, but by his own act &amp; deed,
               fatally deceived as to its nature &amp; its possibility of success.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are at present God be thanked, all well. Remember us most kindly
               to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               May</ref>. Remember me also to your two eldest daughters &amp; tell
               Charlotte that I hope she continues to look at the Lamb &amp; the Lark.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">May&#8217;s daughters, Mary Charlotte (b. 1804),
                  Susanna Louisa (1805&#8211;1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812). The &#8216;Lamb and the Lark&#8217;
                  may refer to a children&#8217;s book, possibly Lindley Murray (1745&#8211;1826;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Introduction to the English Reader: or, A Selection
                     of Pieces, in Prose and Poetry; Calculated to Improve the Younger Classes of
                     Learners in Reading; and to Imbue their Minds with the Love of Virtue</title>
                  (1811).</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>