<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2949</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4220</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2949. Robert Southey to Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 21 March 1817 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2949.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Collection of Professor Paul
                  Betz; a photocopy is British Library, RP 9236. ALS; 4p. (c). .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2949" type="letter">
        <head>2949. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>, <date when="1817-03-21">21 March 1817 </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ S. T. Coleridge Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ at Mr Gillmans/ Highgate<lb />
                  Stamped: TwoPyPost/ Xxxxchester<lb /> Postmark: 4 o&#8217;Clock/ Mxxxx/ 1817<lb /> Endorsement: 1817 <lb /> MS: Collection of Professor Paul
                  Betz; a photocopy is British Library, RP 9236. ALS; 4p. (c).<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1817-03-21">21 March 1817. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Coleridge, I have no reason to regret the apparition of my Uncle Wat,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                  Jacobin drama <title>Wat Tyler</title>, which he had written in 1794 and sent to James Ridgway (1755&#8211;1838) and Henry Symonds
                  (1741&#8211;1816), radical booksellers, for publication; see Robert Southey to Edith Fricker, [c. 12 January 1795], <title>The Collected
                     Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 123. Ridgway and Symonds did not publish it and it remained in manuscript
                  until a pirated publication, designed to embarrass the now anti-Jacobin Southey, appeared in 1817. Southey used the term &#8216;Uncle Wat&#8217;
                  for the play because of his Tyler family connections &#8211; he had three uncles with the surname Tyler.</note> since with the
               recollection of old times, it has brought back some of their feelings also.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will know the result of my appeal to Chancery sooner than I shall. This step was taken by <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynns</ref> judgement, as the measure best becoming me.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Having taken advice from Wynn and Turner, Southey launched a suit in Chancery before John Scott, 1st Earl of Eldon (1751&#8211;1838;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1801&#8211;1806, 1807&#8211;1827 so as to gain an injunction suppressing the publication of <title>Wat
                     Tyler</title>, on the grounds that it breached his copyright. The case was heard on 18&#8211;19 March 1817 and Southey&#8217;s application
                  for an injunction was rejected on the grounds that copyright in <title>Wat Tyler</title> was disputed and would have to be
                  determined in a common law court.</note> The ground of defence which <ref type="m" target="people.html#MontaguBasil">Basil
                  Montagu</ref> has taken is such, that if the Chancellor admits it, it exposes them immediately to a prosecution from the Attorney
               General, if he chuses.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Basil Montagu, one of the two defence lawyers, argued that, according to
                  precedent, there could be no copyright in the work because of its &#8216;libellous tendency&#8217;. Southey suggests that if the Court accepted
                  this view, then the publishers could be prosecuted for seditious libel, on the authority of Sir William Garrow (1760&#8211;1840;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Attorney-General 1813&#8211;1817.</note> And if he should so chuse what a happy instance would it be of a
                  <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> rogue being caught in his own snares. I learn also that they have procured a man to perjure himself, &amp;
               swear that I made a free gift of the manuscript. Who this may be I have not heard, nor is it possible for me to guess, &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MontaguBasil">Basil the Benevolent</ref> has doubtless many such &#8220;damned souls&#8217; at his command.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have addressed two letters to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                  Smith</ref>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith had denounced Southey in the House of Commons on 14 March 1817 during the
                  debate on the Seditious Meetings Bill, condemning &#8216;the settled, determined malignity of a renegado&#8217; and comparing Southey&#8217;s
                  arguments against radical views in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 227 with those expressed in <title>Wat
                     Tyler</title> (1817), Act 2, lines 103&#8211;112. In reply, Southey wrote two letters which he originally hoped to publish in the
                     <title>Courier</title>: Southey to William Smith, 17 March 1817 (Letter 2943) and Southey to the Editor of the
                     <title>Courier</title> [19 March 1817] (Letter 2946). These two letters were sent to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, on 17 and 19
                  March 1817 (Letters 2944 and 2948), for him to forward to the newspaper. In the event, Wynn&#8217;s absence from home led to a delay in
                  his receiving the letters. By the time he did so, the public debate had moved on and Southey therefore decided to incorporate them
                  into his pamphlet <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (1817). </note> &#8211; perhaps <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> thro whom I sent them to the Courier may withold the first, &#8211; the second is the best &#8211;
               but a better than either might have been made from both. However they will do, &amp; perhaps the less premeditation in such things the
               better. This is the only direct notice I shall take, unless a plan should be carried into effect concerning which I am at issue with
               the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> &amp; some of his privy Council. I want to methodize my political
               papers which have appeared in the Quarterly,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Southey had
                  been considering for some time a plan to expand some of his articles in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> into a book on the
                  &#8216;State of the Nation&#8217;; this project was not realised.</note> &amp; with much alteration &amp; addition, if the restoration of such
               things as were too strong <del>xxxx xxxxx</del> to be administered in that form, reprint them in one volume, in the hope of producing
               an effect something like what was brought about by Pasley in our military policy.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles
                  William Pasley (1780&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British
                     Empire</title> (1810), calling for a determined offensive against France, a co-ordinated global strategy and a policy of
                  annexations (including the whole of Italy). The book won him considerable public acclaim and Southey&#8217;s admiration, but it was not a
                  major influence on British strategy.</note> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> vows &amp; protests
               that I act with far greater advantage thro his darling review, &#8211; where the circulation is already prepaid to an enormous extent (10,000
               are sold) &amp; where the readers are prepared also to receive &amp; assent. There is some truth in this, &#8211; but I should press my
               opinion upon his with more earnestness if my time &amp; attention were not very much divided by other subjects, this being one to which
               God knows I have no inclination but in these times the danger &amp; the duty are too plain to be mistaken. Meantime however I carry on
               the war in the Review, which is unquestionably a strong post.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was writing the &#8216;Rise and
                  Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511&#8211;552.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunts</ref> personal hatred to me arises from a letter which I administered to him some
               years ago thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gooch</ref>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey to Robert Gooch, 14 April 1813, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>,
                  Letter 2247.</note> &amp; which if he had not been wrong at heart, would have produced a directly opposite effect. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> told me that I shook him to his very marrow. The occasion was this, &#8211; he complained
               thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> who was then attending him in prison of some allusions which he took
               to himself in my first paper upon the Poor &amp; the Jacobin Press; &#8211; but which in reality was not intended for him,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Hunt served two years (1813&#8211;1815) in prison for libelling the Prince Regent. Southey here refers to his
                  &#8216;Inquiry into the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356, especially 346&#8211;347, which stated &#8216;To
                  slander public and private characters has become a regular trade in England; and miscreants of one description take to it just as
                  miscreants of another to the more dangerous, but not more nefarious, practice of thieving and robbing; they begin upon players and
                  they end upon princes&#8217;; and his &#8216;Lives of the French Revolutionists&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 7 (June 1812), 412&#8211;438,
                  especially 437&#8211;438, which attacked British journalists who were, in Southey&#8217;s view, abusing the liberty of the press and thus
                  provoking the possibility of revolution. He compared them to the journalists and revolutionaries Jacques H&#233;bert (1757&#8211;1794),
                  Jean-Paul Marat (1743&#8211;1793) and the radical politician Pierre Gaspard Chaumette (1763&#8211;1794). All three had met violent ends.
                  Southey&#8217;s article did not mention Hunt by name, but it did draw clear parallels between revolutionary France and contemporary
                  Britain.</note> &#8211; &amp; he talked of being hurt the more because they came from one whom he so much respected &amp;c. There happened
               at the same time to arrive here a chance paper of the Examiner, directed to poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#DanversCharles">Danvers</ref>, &#8211; &amp; in this paper was a most scandalous attack upon you.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a
                  reference to the <title>Examiner</title>, 9 (21 June 1812), 387: &#8216;A love of drinking, especially if it has any gift of talking to
                  work upon, will make a man exceedingly didactic: &#8230; he will sometimes deceive his very self into a notion that he is a worthy person,
                  and attribute his bad habits to a vague sort of destiny that besets him, and renders him more to be pitied than blamed. The most
                  didactic and talkative person of the day appears to be one of this description, and wants nothing but his supply of brandy and water
                  to be set a-doling about the &#8220;moral feeling&#8221; from morning to night.&#8217;</note> So I wrote to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> demanding what right <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hunt</ref> could have to complain of any personalities (had any such been intended) &#8211; &amp; least of all, with what
               conscience could he address his complaint to any person in <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">
            <hi rend="ital">this
                  house</hi>
          </ref> where <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">your wife</ref> &amp; children were residing &#8211; And I then
               read him a lecture upon the course he was pursuing, pointing out the stages thro which he would pass (unless he retrod his steps in
               time) till from being at first sincere tho mistaken &#8211; he would end at last in a rascal &amp; a traitor, &#8211; a prediction which he {has}
               most fully verified. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> has no doubt preserved the letter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Sir Tarquin of the Round Table</ref>
          <note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Hazlitt had republished a number of his essays for the<title> Examiner </title>in a book with the Arthurian title,
                     <title>The Round Table </title>(1817). In Arthurian legend, Sir Tarquin was a treacherous knight who fought against his former
                  friends. Southey and Coleridge considered themselves betrayed by Hazlitt, having hosted him at Greta Hall in 1803 and assisted him
                  in escaping from the anger of the townsfolk after he caused a furore in a Keswick inn following an incident with a local
                  woman.</note> if he did not wish to cut my throat, there would be no truth in the old proverb.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Save a thief from the gallows, and he&#8217;ll be the first shall cut your throat&#8217;.</note> Little do these dogs know how
               little all their yelping is able to disturb me!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not heard who was the Resurrection-Man<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A grave-robber who provided
                  corpses to anatomy classes for medical students.</note> in Uncle Wats affair, it will come out in due time, &amp; may very possibly
               be traced to the Old Serpents coterie where in addition to other offences my knowledge of the farce of Phaedra &amp; Hippolytus
               entitles me to all proper abhorrence. <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Old Serpent&#8217; is the Devil, as in
                     <title>Revelation</title>, 12: 9 and 20: 2. This is most probably a reference to the circle of writers around Leigh Hunt. Southey
                  imagines himself abhorred by this circle because he knows its scandalous secret &#8211; that Hunt and his sister-in-law Elizabeth Kent
                  (1790&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>) were in love with each other and that Kent had, in consequence, tried to drown herself in Hampstead
                  ponds in February 1817. In Euripides (c. 480&#8211;406 BC), <title>Hippolytus</title> (428 BC), Phaedra kills herself, consumed by an
                  incestuous passion for her stepson, Hippolytus.</note> &#8211; We may as well deny the effect of <hi rend="ital">blood</hi> in dogs &amp;
               horses as in the human species. I never knew but one man who was the son of a whore &amp; <del>xx xxxxxxxx</del> an Atheist,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Basil Montagu. He was the son of John Montagu, 4th Earl of Sandwich (1718&#8211;1792;
                     <title>DNB</title>), who was a member in his youth of the Hell-Fire Club, which reportedly practiced devil-worship; and of
                  Sandwich&#8217;s mistress, the opera singer Martha Ray (1742&#8211;1779; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; this <hi rend="ital">tertium
                  quid</hi>
          <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Third thing&#8217;; i.e. the product of the combination of the first two
                  elements.</note> proved to be a hypocrite &amp; a rascal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And so wishing him a due share of Ernulphus&#8217;s maledictions<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The famous curse of
                  Ernulf (1040&#8211;1124), Bishop of Rochester 1114&#8211;1124. A part-translation from the Latin original appears in Laurence Sterne (1713&#8211;1768;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</title> (London, 1759&#8211;1767), Book 3, chapter 11:
                  &#8216;May he be cursed in living, in dying. May he be cursed in eating and drinking, in being hungry, in being thirsty, in fasting, in
                  sleeping, in slumbering, in walking, in standing, in sitting, in lying, in working, in resting, in pissing, in shitting, and in
                  bloodletting!// May he be cursed in all the faculties of his body! May he be cursed inwardly and outwardly! May he be cursed in the
                  hair of his head! May he be cursed in his brains, and in his vertex, in his temples, in his forehead, in his ears, in his eyebrows,
                  in his cheeks, in his jaw-bones, in his nostrils, in his fore-teeth and grinders, in his lips, in his throat, in his shoulders, in
                  his wrists, in his arms, in his hands, in his fingers! May he be damn&#8217;d in his mouth, in his breast, in his heart and purtenance,
                  down to the very stomach! May he be cursed in his reins, and in his groin, in his thighs, in his genitals, in his hips, and in his
                  knees, his legs, and feet, and toe-nails!&#8217;</note> in this world, &amp; consigning them to the Bottomless Pit in the next, till
                  <del>xxxx xxxx xxx</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam"> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Hazlitt</ref> shall be able to determine the exact proportion
               which the time they have past there bears to Eternity I leave this unworthy subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In all this you would see nothing very different from the R.S. of former times. But he is greatly changed. That
               joyousness of nature which seemed to suspend the effect of time is gone, never to return, &#8211; &amp; I was better able twelve months ago
               to bear the sight of the coffin &amp; the grave than I am <del>xx xx</del> now to endure the daily &amp; hourly circumstances which
               bring to recollection what I have lost.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s son <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> died on 17 April 1816. </note>
          <del>Xxx</del> I am not deficient in self controul, but this would avail me little were it not <del>for the xxxxxxxx xxxxxxxx</del>
               that the way before me cannot be very long, &#8211; &amp; there is the Gate of Heaven at the end of it. &#8211; Neither of my parents got beyond
               fifty. &#8211; I am in my forty third year, &amp; have unequivocal <del>xxxxxxx</del> indications that my bodily powers are on the decline &#8211;
               that is that without having any disease I feel myself growing old.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for political affairs, &#8211; your opinions cannot possibly differ from mine &#8211; I will only say that I have done my
               utmost, &#8211; &amp; it is not my fault if efficaceous means are not taken to save us from a Jacquerie. Unless the press be checked every
               thing else is foolery. What I have endeavoured to <del>press upon them</del> show is that transportation should be the punishment for
               seditious libel: fines &amp; imprisonment are worse than nugatory. The Courier should act in this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall be in town about the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of next month, on my way to the continent, with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>, &#8211; who was with
               me in the Netherlands, &amp; at whose lodgings if you are so disposed (6 George Street, Hanover Square), &#8211; you may see a beautiful
               portrait of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">your daughter</ref>. We mean to see as much of Switzerland as
               that time will allow, &amp; return by way of the Rhine. On my return I go to press with the history of the Peninsular War.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are in fear of some inconvenience about this property &#8211; our Landlord is a miserable rogue, playing bo peep with the
               bailiffs, &#8211; he cannot continue this game long,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall had suffered from the complicated
                  financial and legal entanglements of its owner, Samuel Tolson Jnr (dates unknown), who was in Carlisle jail for debt by April 1817.
               </note> &amp; if the property be sold as I think it must be, there is great danger that we shall be built out of all comfort for Clark
               is a bankrupt, &amp; there will be the nursery garden to cut up.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Clark (dates unknown)
                  rented some of the land next to Greta Hall, which was part of the same estate. He was a nurseryman and had been declared bankrupt on
                  11 March 1817.</note> &#8211; I should be very loth to move, &#8211; having my heart in <del>xxxxxx</del> yonder church yard. &#8211; All here send
               their remembrances. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C</ref> has hurt her arm in a fall, so as
               to impede the use of it in certain actions; &#8211; but time will set all to rights.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just learnt that my appeal for an Injunction is refused. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref> having perjured himself,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Winterbottom&#8217;s affidavit of 15 March 1817,
                  National Archives C31/372 Pt. 2. He claimed Southey had given him the manuscript and copyright of <title>Wat Tyler</title>.</note>
               &amp; sworn that I gave the work to him &amp; <hi rend="ital">D. I. Eaton</hi>
          <note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel Isaac
                  Eaton (1753&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), a radical author and publisher.</note> &#8211; whom I never saw. &#8211; I pray you call now upon the
               Attorney General to prosecute the publishers.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge further defended Southey and condemned
                  the publication of <title>Wat Tyler</title> in the articles &#8216;Mr Southey and Wat Tyler. III: Rejected Articles&#8217;,
                     <title>Courier</title>, 27 March 1817, and &#8216;Mr Southey and Wat Tyler. IV: Apostacy and Renegadoism&#8217;, <title>Courier</title>, 2
                  April 1817. But Coleridge retained doubts about the wisdom of Southey&#8217;s actions and he did not explicitly call for the publishers of
                     <title>Wat Tyler</title> to be prosecuted.</note> I think this letter is not going upon a forlorn hope &#8211; but that I shall hear
               from you &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">Your parcel is this moment arrived.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>