<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3144</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4415</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3144. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 1 June 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3144" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3144.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3144" type="letter">
        <head>3144. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1818-06-01">1 June 1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9 Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb /> Stamped:
                  KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: [illegible]<lb /> Endorsements: 1 June 1818; 1 June
                  1818<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Hyde &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>
               are the only claimants upon my property in your hands,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey wished Bedford to pay from his stipend as Poet Laureate
                  the bill of his London tailor, Hyde (d. 1820) and to reimburse Nash for the
                  purchase of picture frames. Southey had already paid for a carpet he had asked
                  Henry Herbert Southey to order.</note> &#8211; the carpet is paid for. For the tea, I
               pray you take into your consideration that we are all this while <hi rend="ital">being poisoned</hi>; &#8211; for tho I, <del>xxx</del> who always drunk hyson, have
               some little of Twinings left, the stock of souchong from that quarter is exhausted,
               &amp; what we get here to supply it is plainly the precious composition which Dauncey
               described on the trial; as appears by the shape of the few leaves which have not been
               carefully chopt to elude this mode of detection.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford was occasionally commissioned by Southey to buy tea
                  from Twinings in The Strand. <title>The Times</title> of 18 May 1818 reported the
                  trial of Edward Palmer (dates unknown), a grocer of Red Lion Street, Whitechapel,
                  for making counterfeit and poisonous tea. The prosecuting counsel, Southey&#8217;s
                  acquaintance Philip Dauncey (1759&#8211;1819), told the jury that &#8216;It would appear that
                  a regular manufactory was established in Goldstone Street. The parties by whom the
                  manufactory was conducted &#8230; engaged others to furnish them with leaves, which,
                  after undergoing a certain process, were sold to and drank by the public as tea.
                  The leaves, in order to be converted into an article resembling black tea, were
                  first boiled, then baked upon an iron plate; and, when dry, rubbed with the hand,
                  in order to produce that curl which the genuine tea had. This was the most
                  wholesome part of the operation; for the colour, which was yet to be given to it,
                  was produced by logwood. The green tea was manufactured in a manner more
                  destructive to the constitution of those by whom it was drank. The leaves, being
                  pressed and dried, were laid upon sheets of copper, where they received their
                  colour from an article known by the name of Dutch pink. The article used in
                  producing the appearance of the fine green bloom, observable on the China tea,
                  was, however, decidedly a deadly poison! He alluded to verdigris, which was added
                  to Dutch pink in order to complete the operation.&#8217; Palmer was convicted and fined
                  &#163;840.</note> In my conscience I believe that the trading part of this nation are,
               for the most part, as great rogues at this time as the Chinese themselves, &amp; this
               is not said lightly upon the mere evidence of the tea &amp; coffee trials. A man who
               was employed in a druggists business, the greatest in Bristol {once} told me that not
               a single article in that business was unadulterated which was capable of
               adulteration. And I knew a person who was about to engage in a mustard mill or
               manufactory (or whatever it may be called) till he found, upon enquiring into the
               business, that it was carried on upon <del>xx</del> a system in which no man of
               integrity could be concerned.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The subjects
                  of both of these stories are unidentified.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think you will get rid of the aureoles if you wash your eyes with
               an infusion of <hi rend="ital">Ki-an</hi> pepper,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Cayenne pepper.</note> just strong enough to make them smart
               well. It is made merely by pouring {a little} boiling water upon about as much pepper
               as you would put upon your plate with salmon, &amp; no nicety is required in the
               proportion or process.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> will leave at the
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Dockstors</ref> for you the number of the S.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had sent Southey &#8216;Mr M&#8217;Kerrell and Mr Brougham&#8217;,
                     <title>The Satirist; or, Monthly Meteor</title>, 11 (September 1812), 208&#8211;227.
                  Robert M&#8217;Kerrell (1761&#8211;1841), a textile merchant and manufacturer in Paisley, had
                  on 28 May 1812, given evidence to the House of Commons committee enquiring into
                  the Orders in Council system, which enforced a trade blockade on territories
                  controlled by France. The Whig opposition were campaigning for its repeal, on the
                  grounds that it harmed British manufacturing. Brougham denounced M&#8217;Kerrell (though
                  not by name) in the House of Commons on 16 June 1812, claiming he had told the
                  committee that textile workers were overpaid and &#8216;oatmeal and water were good
                  enough for Englishmen.&#8217; M&#8217;Kerrell denied he had said this and published an
                  acrimonious exchange of letters between himself and Brougham in <title>The
                     Times</title> of 20 July 1812. Southey had been collecting material that could
                  be used against Brougham in his election campaign in Westmorland.</note> which you
               borrowed, &amp; a farther portion of <del>xxxx</del> the Life of Wesley.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise
                     and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> This work <del>xxxx xxxxx
                  advances &amp;</del> takes a wider range <del>xxxxxx</del> as it advances, &amp;
               comprehends much interesting &amp; diversified matter <del>with xxxxxx</del> {of}
               fact, more conducive to a knowledge of the human mind, than all the metaphysical
               treatises which ever have been written upon that subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211;&#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just received yours of the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. I do not
               want the translation of Dobrizhoffer.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Writing to Grosvenor Charles Bedford on 23 May 1818 (Letter 3138), Southey
                  had requested Bedford to examine some manuscripts that had been put up for sale as
                  part of a large collection of Spanish texts. Bedford had reported that a
                  manuscript on the Abipone tribe of South America was not an original work but a
                  translation into Spanish of a book he already owned &#8211; an account of the Jesuit
                  missions in Paraguay by Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de
                     Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 843
                  in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> And <del>concerning</del> {for}
               Oviedo we must wait the result of the enquiry concerning the other volumes.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had asked Bedford to see if one of
                  the advertised works for sale was a complete edition of a multi-volume work &#8211;
                  Gonzalo Fern&#225;ndez de Oviedo y Vald&#233;s (1478&#8211;1557), <title>Historia General y
                     Natural de las Indias</title>. The first part of this work was published in
                  1535, the rest not until 1851&#8211;1855.</note>
          <del>If thexx</del> For the three volumes I would gladly give ten guineas. The old
               Lady should send her catalogue to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Lord Holland</ref>, &amp; to Sir Charles Stuart (our Emb: at
                  Paris)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles Stuart, later 1st
                  Baron Stuart de Rothesay (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), Envoy Extraordinary to
                  Portugal 1810&#8211;1814 and 1825&#8211;1826; and Ambassador to France 1815&#8211;1824 and
                  1828&#8211;1831.</note> &#8211; the two persons who are most likely to purchase the whole
               collection. She however is very likely to over-rate its collective value.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This post (<hi rend="ital">inter nos</hi>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Between us&#8217;.</note>) has brought me the offer of being
               librarian to the Advocates Library at Edinburgh, with 400 &#163; a year, &amp; the duty of
               making a Catalogue Raisonn&#233;e attached to it.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Advocates Library, founded in 1689, is the library of the Faculty of
                  Advocates (the Scottish equivalent of barristers) in Edinburgh and was at this
                  time a copyright library. Alexander Manners (dates unknown), the incumbent, had
                  tendered his resignation as Librarian on 10 April 1818. His successor, David
                  Irving (1778&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), was not appointed until 1820.</note> I have
               no hesitation in refusing it, &amp; remaining free in all my motions. Were <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> from ill health to give
               up the management of the Review,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Gifford did not give up its editorship on
                  health grounds until 1824.</note> an offer to undertake that office, might draw me
               near London, &#8211; to Hampstead, Highgate, or Richmond, perhaps, &#8211; because there are
                  <del>only xxxx</del> other magnets which would draw me strongly in that
                  direction,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John May lived at
                  Richmond. Hampstead and Highgate were relatively healthy areas with good access to
                  open country.</note> &amp; my method &amp; management would leave me a good long
               sea-side holyday every summer. But let Edinburgh keep its good things for hungrier
               men. I am far enough from my friends already, &amp; better employed than in making
               catalogues, &#8211; tho <del>xxxx xxxx</del> {it} would be no uninteresting employment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This return of your Uncle<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> seems to show that the old system of spring physicking
               might have been useful to you. &#8211; I have my summer cold as usual, &amp; had an upper
               lip yesterday big as Goliaths<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">A giant
                  warrior in 1 <title>Samuel</title> 17.</note> in consequence. Our weather is,
               &amp; has been for the last 16 days, the finest possible.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I long to hear that the books are actually lodged with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Patres Nostri</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> has directions concerning
               them, &amp; he will know whether <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Vardon</ref> can give them a passage to Newcastle. If not,
               they must come in that direction by some of the regular traders, as soon as the
               bookbinder has performed his part.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                  consignment of books Southey had bought in Brussels in 1817 had finally, after
                  much anxiety concerning its whereabouts, been located. </note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1818-06-01">June 1. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>