<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2707</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3978</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2707. Robert Southey to John Rickman, 3 February
                  1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2707" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2707.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. ALS; 2p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2707" type="letter">
        <head>2707. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1816-02-03">3 February
                  1816</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens
                  Court/ New Palace Yard/ Westminster<lb /> Postmark: FREE/ 6 DE 6/ 1816<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. ALS; 2p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-02-03">3 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has sent me a book upon the Catacombs of Paris, which I shall probably
               digest into a paper for the Quarterly.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis-Etienne-Fran&#231;ois, Vicomte H&#233;ricart de Thury
                  (1776&#8211;1854), <title>Description des Catacombes de Paris, pr&#233;c&#233;d&#233;e d&#8217;un Pr&#233;cis Historique sur les Catacombes de tous les Peuples de
                     l&#8217;Ancien et du Nouveau Continent</title> (1815); reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819),
                  359&#8211;358.</note> By a sort of Irish <del>xxxxxx</del> {contrivance} the French <del>xxxx for</del> ever since the beginning of this
               city have been quarrying below as they built above, &#8211; &amp; if the danger had not been discovered in time the people of Paris would
               like Korah Dathan &amp; Abiram have gone down alive into the pit.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Numbers</title> 16, details how they were swallowed up by the earth as divine punishment for their rebellion against
                  Moses.</note> Engineers were then appointed to <hi rend="ital">prop the city</hi> &amp; take care of the quarries, &amp; they are
               now converted to Catacombs, &#8211; in which process the French have displayed a great deal of good sense &amp; not a little of what may be
               called <hi rend="ital">Frenchness</hi> for want of a fitter name. At present Paris is the only city in the world that is properly
               provided with a receptacle for its dead.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have lately received some good documents for the peninsular war: <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir
                  Hew Dalrymple</ref> has sent me some thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, &#8211; of no great value to me,
               &amp; of none to himself, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">his</hi> purpose being obvious enough.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his first
                  article on the &#8216;Life of Wellington&#8217;, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815), 215&#8211;275, especially at 242&#8211;243, Southey
                  had criticised the conduct of Dalrymple when, arriving in Portugal as commanding officer, he had, at the Convention of Cintra,
                  signed 30 August 1808, allowed a defeated French army free passage out of the country with its weapons and supplies intact.
                  Dalrymple responded by sending Southey papers giving his version of events; see Robert Southey to Hew Dalrymple, 6 March 1816,
                  Letter 2732.</note> I gather from them one fact, that Morla&#8217;s<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Tomas de Morla y Pacheco
                  (1748&#8211;1812), Spanish General and Governor of Cadiz 1800&#8211;1808. He opposed the French invasion in 1808, but was disgraced after
                  negotiating the surrender of Madrid. Southey mentioned Dalrymple&#8217;s distrust of Morla in <title>History of the Peninsular
                  War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, p. 29.</note> dislike toward the English was seen at the beginning of the Revolution, &#8211;
               Sir Hew <del>x</del> remarks it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Sir A Wellesley</ref>, &amp; I know
                  <del>xxxx</del> {that} <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> always suspected him. &#8211; I have a good account
               of the Douro campaign in a letter from an officer who fell at Talavera,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of the Douro
                  occurred on 12 May 1809 when British and Portuguese troops under Wellington defeated French troops and took the city of Porto. The
                  Battle of Talavera took place on 27&#8211;28 July 1809 as Wellington&#8217;s British and a Spanish army met the French on the road from Portugal
                  to Madrid. Southey discusses these battles in <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp.
                  289&#8211;313, 410&#8211;418, but the identity of the officer who wrote the account of the Battle of the Douro is not revealed.</note> &#8211; &amp;
               the correspondence of the Portuguese committee<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> The papers Southey had received concerned the
                  &#163;100,000 parliament had voted in 1811 to relieve the sufferings of the Portuguese people following the French invasion. The money
                  was distributed by Commissioners, whose report was placed before the House of Commons on 6 July 1814.</note> has been sent me &#8211; that
               is the offical accounts which they received from Portugal of the conduct of the French under Massena<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Andre Massena (1758&#8211;1817), commander of the invasion of Portugal in 1810&#8211;1811.</note> &amp; the state of the
               country. <hi rend="ital">Ni fallor</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;if I err not&#8217;.</note> the history of that campaign
               will for some generations secure the people of Europe from another such: the infamy which will be attached to Massena &amp; his army
               operating henceforth <hi rend="ital">in terrorem</hi>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;In [order to] frighten&#8217;, i.e. a
                  warning.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>