<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3005</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4276</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3005. Robert Southey to John May,
                  1 August 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3005.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert
                     Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 156&#8211;159;
                  Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 271&#8211;276 [in
               part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3005" type="letter">
        <head>3005. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,
                  <date when="1817-08-01">1 August 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: England/ To/ John May
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb /> Stamped: DOORNIK/ FRANCO<lb />
                  Postmarks: [partial] FPO/ AU11/ 1817; 4o&#8217;Clock/ AU.11/ 1817 EV<lb /> Watermark: H
                  Renoz<lb /> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 194 1817/ Robert Southey/ Brussels
                     1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> August/<lb /> rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. personally<lb /> MS:
                  Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS;
                  4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert
                     Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 156&#8211;159;
                  Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 271&#8211;276 [in
               part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Brussels.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-08-01">1 Aug. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2"> I wrote to you a long letter from Geneva<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The letter appears not to have survived.</note> on our way to Italy
               &amp; since that time have written twice to London so that I conclude you would hear
               by roundabout means that I had reached Milan; &amp; afterwards that we had safely
               returned into Switzerland. From Geneva we made for Mount Cenis<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A mountain pass between France and Italy, the
                  traversal of which had been eased by a road constructed by the French government
                  (1803&#8211;1810).</note> &amp; turned aside from Chamberry to visit the Grand
                  Chartreuse,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Head monastery of the
                  Carthusian order, founded in 1084. It is located high in an Alpine valley north of
                  Grenoble.</note> which after all that we have since seen, remains impressed upon
               our minds as one of the finest imaginable scenes. The hot weather did not begin till
               the first of June when we left Lausanne, &#8211; we had too much of it in going up the
                  Maurienne,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Alpine valley near Mont
                  Cenis.</note> &amp; suffered severely from the dust &amp; the sun. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> in consequence had a smart
               bilious attack at Turin which detained us there two days instead of one: this has
               been the only unpleasant circumstance during the whole journey, &#8211; &amp; this lasted
               so short a time &amp; was so little serious while it lasted that it can scarcely be
               called such. At Milan I purchased some books <del>but xx</del> {but} this was not the
               place for executing your commission. Thence to Como where I found <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> &amp; we remained three days.
               Bellaggio, twenty miles from Como upon the fork of the Lake, is the finest single
               spot that I have ever seen, commanding three distant lake views, each of the grandest
               character. Lugano was our next stage, &amp; somewhere here it is that if climate
               &amp; scenery alone were to be consulted I should like to pitch my tent, &#8211; perhaps at
               Laveno upon the Lago Maggiore. The Isola Bella upon that Lake is of all extravagant
               follies the most absurd.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The island of Isola
                  Bella on Lake Maggiore. It is entirely occupied by the enormous
                  seventeenth-century Palazzo Borromeo and its gardens. The palace was built by
                  various members of the Borromeo family, whose coronet and family motto,
                  &#8216;Humilitas&#8217; (humility), is much in evidence.</note> Having crost the Lake we
               entered upon the Simplon road,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Simplon
                  pass, in the Swiss Alps, between Brig in Switzerland and Domodossola in Italy.
                  Southey was able to cross using the carriage road constructed by the French
                  government (1801&#8211;1805). </note> which on the whole I do not think so fine as the
               passage of Mount Cenis; &#8211; but it is foolish to compare things which are in so many
               respects essentially different. In the Maurienne &amp; indeed when you begin to
               descend into Piedmont the world seems tumbling to pieces about your ears, of such
               perishable materials are the mountains made. In the Simplon you have generally rocks
               of granite. A glorious Alpine descent brought us into the Valais, &#8211; which even more
               than the Maurienne is the land of goitres &amp; cretins, &#8211; both more numerous &amp;
               more shocking to behold than I could have believed possible. At Martigny we halted
               &amp; crost to Chamounix by the Tete Noir.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                  peak in the Valais region of Switzerland.</note> In the Album at the M.
                  Auvert<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Montanvert was a common name in the
                  eighteenth century for a summit near the glacier known as the Mer de Glace. The
                  spectacular views it afforded of the Vale of Chamonix and the surrounding
                  mountains made it a popular tourist destination. At its top was a small building
                  for travellers to take shelter, known as the hospice. It contained an album in
                  which visitors could write their names and comments.</note> I found <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridges</ref> adventures in going
               to the Garden<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Travellers based in Chamonix
                  could undertake a hazardous expedition to the Glacier du Tal&#232;fre, where they could
                  see &#8216;the Garden&#8217;, a raised, flattened rock that was covered with grass in summer.
                  The recommended route included an overnight stay in the hospice on Montanvert
                  before tackling the Glacier du Tal&#232;fre. John Taylor Coleridge visited in 1814 on
                  his European tour paid for by John May.</note> as it is called, &#8211; unluckily the
               ink with which he wrote has made them <del>almost</del> {in part} illegible. I found
               also a more curious record. You may have heard me speak of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The two men had met in
                  Keswick in 1811&#8211;1812.</note> who left <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyHarriet">his wife</ref> (to drown herself) &amp; lived
               with two of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">Godwins</ref> daughters
               in Switzerland.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Godwin Shelley
                  (1797&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), Godwin&#8217;s daughter with Mary Wollstonecraft; Clara
                  Mary Jane Clairmont (1798&#8211;1879; <title>DNB</title>), daughter of Godwin&#8217;s second
                  wife Mary Jane Clairmont Godwin (1766&#8211;1841) and Sir John Lethbridge (1746&#8211;1815).
                  Shelley had left his wife in 1814 for Mary Godwin and travelled to Switzerland
                  with her and her step-sister (who could speak French). The three of them returned
                  in the summer of 1816 and visited Montanvert in July.</note> &#8211; Many persons who
               visit the Mer de Glace have expressed some religious feeling in the Album: &#8211; this
               party had written their names &amp; designation thus</p>
        <table rows="3" cols="2" width="740">
          <row>
            <cell width="300">
              <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Percy Bysshe Shelley</ref>
            </cell>
            <cell width="50"> }</cell>
            <cell width="390" />
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="300">Madame son epouse<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;His
                        wife&#8217;; i.e. Mary Godwin Shelley. </note>
            </cell>
            <cell width="50">}</cell>
            <cell width="390"> &#949;&#954;&#945;&#962;&#959;&#943;
                        &#945;&#952;&#949;&#959;&#943;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8217;Atheists one and all&#8217;. </note>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell width="300">Pheoffteigyne la s&#339;ur<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a French version of the Greek for &#8216;hater of God&#8217;; followed by &#8216;her
                        sister&#8217;, i.e. Clara Clairmont.</note>
            </cell>
            <cell width="50"> }</cell>
            <cell width="390" />
          </row>
        </table>
        <p> after their Greek words, another hand had added, &#954;&#945;&#953; &#949;&#953;
               &#964;&#959;&#965;&#964;&#959; &#945;&#955;&#951;&#952;&#949;&#962;
               &#949;&#963;&#964;&#953;&#957;, &#949;&#954;&#945;&#963;&#964;&#959;&#953;
               &#956;&#969;&#961;&#959;&#953; &#949;&#953;&#963;&#953;, &#954;&#945;&#953;
               &#948;&#965;&#963;&#964;&#965;&#967;&#959;&#953;,
               &#948;&#959;&#958;&#945;&#950;&#959;&#957;&#964;&#949;&#962; &#949;&#957;
               &#964;&#8131; &#945;&#966;&#961;&#959;&#963;&#965;&#957;&#8131;
               &#945;&#965;&#964;&#969;&#957;. &#949;&#953; &#948;&#949;
               &#964;&#959;&#965;&#964;&#959; &#959;&#965;&#954; &#949;&#963;&#964;&#953;&#957;
               &#945;&#955;&#951;&#952;&#949;&#962;, &#949;&#954;&#945;&#963;&#964;&#959;&#953;
               &#968; &#949;&#965;&#963;&#964;&#945;&#953;.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The addendum translates as: &#8216;if that is true they are all fools and unfortunates,
                  believing it in their stupidity. But if it is not true, they are all
                  liars&#8217;.</note> This was probably written by <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref>.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1811 Copleston, having received a copy of <title>The Necessity
                     of Atheism</title>, which Shelley wrote while an Oxford undergraduate, reported
                  Shelley to the Master and Fellows of his college, resulting in his expulsion from
                  the university. He visited Switzerland in August-September 1816, shortly after
                  Shelley&#8217;s party.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We returned by the Tete Noir as we came. the Col de Baume<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">A mountain pass near Chamonix.</note> being still
               covered in great part with snow &amp; proceeding by Vevay &amp; Lausanne: returned to
                  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Audrys at Echichens,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry (1766&#8211;1844), solicitor in Reybridge and husband of Jane,
                  n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife, Catherine.</note>
               where we rested three days. Just four weeks had elapsed since we left that place,
               &amp; it was a high enjoyment to find ourselves again among friends &#8211; I found one
               letter from home &amp; by that learnt the news of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> household, for which I must
               else have waited till this time.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry
                  Herbert Southey&#8217;s first child, Robert Southey, was born on 1 June 1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Proceeding to Berne, we sent our carriage to Zurich &amp; struck into
               the Oberland where we travelled ten days by land &amp; by water on horseback, or on
               foot, sometimes in cars &amp; sometimes in carts. The snows rendered it impossible to
               cross the Grimsale<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The Grimsel pass connects
                  the valley of the Rhone in the canton of Valais and the upper valley of the Aar
                  river.</note> without more risque than it would have been justifiable to incur. We
               slept on the Righi<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">A massif in central
                  Switzerland.</note> &amp; had a scene there which was not a little curious in such
               a place. At Zurich a days halt was necessary for the love of the washerwoman, we then
               set off homeward in good earnest, thro the Black forest. I was unfortunate enough to
               miss Osterwald,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Jean Frederic
                  Ostervald (1773&#8211;1850), a Swiss surveyor, cartographer and publisher, whom Southey
                  had met in Portugal in 1796.</note> whom I found when I got to Manheim was gone to
               Heidelberg &#8211; a place which we had left in the afternoon. He lives with a sister<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &amp; frequently comes to
               the Hotel at which we lodged, <hi rend="ital">to talk English</hi> with the Landlord.
               I wrote a letter to him communicating all the news I could recollect concerning his
               old friends &amp; requested to hear from him at Brussels. We then made for Frankfort
               &amp; Mentz, &amp; down the left bank of the Rhine to Cologne, where we <hi rend="ital">saw</hi> the Three Kings &amp; a very considerable number of the
               Eleven Thousand Virgins, &#8211; certainly some thousands of them, &#8211; a sight more curious
               than any {of its kind} in Portugal or Spain.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">A reliquary in Cologne cathedral supposedly contains the bones of the Three Wise
                  Men who visited the infant Christ in Bethlehem, described in
                     <title>Matthew</title> 2: 1&#8211;12. The church of St Ursula in Cologne contains an
                  enormous reliquary in which supposedly lie the bones of this fourth-century
                  British saint who, according to legend, was killed, with her eleven thousand
                  virginal handmaids, on a pilgrimage to Cologne, by the Huns besieging the city.
                  The reliquary is extraordinary because, in addition to its size, it displays the
                  bones arranged in patterns and so as to form letters and words.</note> Here we
               arrived last night, &#8211; &amp; here to my bitter disappointment I find no letter from
               home. I know that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has
               written &#8211; &amp; that she would never be weak enough to conceal ill tidings from me,
               therefore I am not unnecessarily anxious, &#8211; but anxious I needs must be having no
               intelligence later than the tenth of June. A few lines from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> was all that I found
               here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Very unwillingly my return is protracted one day that we may escort
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Vardon</ref>
               across the channel. We hope to reach Calais on Wednesday, &#8211; perhaps to arrive in
               England that night.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have found three of the Books here of which you gave me the
               memorandum, &amp; they are the most important. Helyot Durand &amp; Martens &amp; the
               anonymous book upon the Monastic Orders.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Hippolyte Helyot (1660&#8211;1716), <title>Histoire des Ordres Religieux et
                     Militaires</title> (1792); Edmond Mart&#232;ne (1654&#8211;1739) and Ursin Durand
                  (1682&#8211;1771), <title>Voyage Litteraire de Deux Religieux Benedictins de la
                     Congregation de Saint Maur</title> (1717); and an unidentified work. Uncut
                  copies of the first two of these works were advertised in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library (nos 1183 and 1701) after his death, so it is possible that the
                  purchases never reached May.</note> You have them exceedingly cheap &#8211; as they will
               escape duty in my great package. Helyot 50 franks, &amp; the other two, if I
               recollect rightly, only 23. &#8211; I have made large purchases which with the Acta
               Sanctorum, now at last compleated, will fill three chests. Verbiest has promised to
               dispatch them immediately.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had bought
                  the massive compendium of hagiographies entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, 53
                  vols (1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library. Jean-Baptiste Ver
                  Beyst (1770&#8211;1849) was a famous bookseller in Brussels.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You may well imagine how anxious I am to hear from home, &amp; how
               desirous to get there. As for news we have lived so long without it, that the
               appetite seems almost extinguished. In Italy we had now and then the Lugano
                  Gazette,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Gazzetta di Lugano</title>
                  (1814&#8211;1822), a weekly Swiss paper of liberal views.</note> at Echichens Galignanis
               English Paris paper,<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Galignani&#8217;s
                     Messenger</title>, a daily newspaper in English, printed in Paris from 1814 by
                  Giovanni Antonio Galignani (1757&#8211;1821).</note> &#8211; &amp; in Germany I picked out
               London news from the Rastadt Carlsruhe &amp; Frankfort papers. By mere chance I got
               at Zurich a German account of Massenas campaign in Portugal written by a Physician of
               his army,<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Der Feldzug von Portugall,
                     in den Jahren 1811 and 1812, in Historischer und Medizinischer-Hinsicht
                     Beschrieben, von einem Arzte der Franzosischen Armee von Portugall</title>
                  (1816). This work does not appear in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, but
                  it is listed among the sources used for <title>History of the Peninsular
                     War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), III, p. 936.</note> &#8211; my knowledge of
               the subject assisted me greatly in making out the meaning &amp; I have found in it
               some curious matter. As far as I can learn this is the only original document
               concerning the war, which has yet been published in Germany.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been perfectly well during the whole journey, &amp; the
               knowledge which it has given me amply repays the expence both of money &amp; of time.
               It has been with great difficulty that I could keep up my journal so fully has every
               day &amp; every hour been occupied, from five &amp; frequently four in the morning &#8211;
               I have however kept it up. My spirits have been equal to any demand which outside
               circumstances might make upon them: &#8211; but to live always out of oneself is not
               possible, &amp; in those intervals which frequently occur amid the excitement &amp;
               exhilaration of such a journey, my <del>thoughts</del> {lonely feelings} have perhaps
               been more poignant [MS torn] would have been amid the even tenour of domestic
                  life.<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was still grieving for his
                  son <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, who had died
                  on 17 April 1816.</note> But I have learnt to give them their proper direction.
                  <del>Xxxx</del> When I am once more at home I shall feel the benefit of having
               travelled.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear friend. Perhaps I shall be in England as soon
               as this letter. On Friday I hope to reach <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Queen Anne Street</ref>. ten days must be the
               utmost of my stay in London. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; believe
               me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">most truly &amp; affectionately yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>