<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3015</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4286</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3015. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 23 August 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3015.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 276&#8211;278 [in
                  part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3015" type="letter">
        <head>3015. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1817-08-23">23 August 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Llangedwin/ Oswestry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 276&#8211;278 [in
                  part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-08-23">23 Aug. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2"> After getting thro the packets of letters pertinent &amp; impertinent
               which were waiting my return, &#8211; this is the first which I write ex propria motu,
                  &#8211;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A Latin legal term, meaning &#8216;of one&#8217;s own
                  accord&#8217;.</note> on the first evening that I am left to myself &amp; my wonted
               occupations.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> During the thirteen weeks which I past upon the continent I saw no
               English newspapers, except at Paris when dining at Mackenzies.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Colin Alexander Mackenzie (?1778&#8211;1851), a wealthy Scot
                  who was employed on a number of delicate diplomatic missions and may well have
                  been a government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of the Commissioners of
                  Liquidation, Arbitration and Deposit, who adjudicated on claims by British
                  citizens for loss of property against the French government. Southey had dined
                  with him on 17 May 1817.</note> In Switzerland while halting on my return for
               three days at the house of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my
                  Uncles</ref> brother-in-law<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry
                  (1766&#8211;1844), solicitor in Reybridge and wife of Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1855),
                  sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife, Catherine. Southey stayed with the family in
                  Echichens, Switzerland twice on his journey.</note> I found Galignanis paper<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Galignani&#8217;s Messenger</title>, a daily
                  newspaper in English, printed in Paris from 1814 by Giovanni Antonio Galignani
                  (1757&#8211;1821).</note> &amp; in it an abstract of the debate upon the choice of a
                  speaker.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had stood for the post of The
                  Speaker on 2 June 1817 but was heavily defeated by 312 votes to 151 by Charles
                  Manners-Sutton (1780&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), the government candidate, who
                  served as The Speaker 1817&#8211;1835.</note> There were so many valid reasons why the
               result ought to have been different that I was disappointed to find <del>xxxx</del>
               how it had terminated; &#8211; yet the whole manner of the debate was exceedingly
               gratifying, &amp; the more so to me, from the Westminster feeling which was brought
               forward. It seems impossible that you should not succeed in case of another vacancy;
               &#8211; if ever such an event occurs I will go up to London on purpose to see you in your
               proper costume, &amp; dine with you on the banks of the Thames.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They tell me both here &amp; in town that travelling has fattened me.
               Certainly it agreed with my bodily health most admirably, <del>xx</del> whether
                  <del>that</del> {it} be attributable to early rising, continual change of air, or
               copious libations of good wine, or to all these. The early rising is unluckily the
               only practice which it would be possible to continue here. As for the wine, when I
               think of the red wines of Savoy (the Montmelian<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">At this time the most highly-prized red wines of Savoy came from
                  the area around Montmelian, especially the light-coloured claret.</note> in
               particular), &amp; the white wines of the Rhine &amp; the Moselle, I feel something
               as the children of Israel did when they remembered the flesh pots of Egypt.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Exodus</title> 16: 3.</note> Were I to
               settle anywhere upon the continent, Switzerland should be the country, &amp;,
               probably Lausanne the place. There are lovelier places in the Oberland of Berne,
               &amp; the adjacent small cantons, &#8211; but Lausanne has <del>those</del> {all those}
               comforts which are desirable &amp; there is as good society in the canton de Vaud as
               need be desired. We could not gain admittance into Gibbons garden, tho his house
                  <del>xxxx xxxx</del> {belongs} <del>xxxx by</del> {to} the Banker on whom we had
                  bills;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794;
                     <title>DNB</title>) famously finished his <title>History of the Decline and
                     Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776&#8211;1788) in the summerhouse in the garden
                  of his home, La Grotte, in Lausanne (he lived in the city 1783&#8211;1793). By 1817 the
                  occupants were increasingly annoyed by the stream of tourists, including Southey,
                  who visited the house. </note> &#8211; the assigned reason for refusing was, that the
               way lay thro a chamber which was then occupied by an invalid. I confess that I
               doubted this, &amp; could not believe that the only way into the garden should be
               thro a bed chamber. This was a mortifying disappointment: as some compensation
               however, our own apartments were not more than 100 yards off, &amp; opened upon a
               terrace which commanded exactly the same view of the lake &amp; mountains, with no
               other difference of foreground than a hundred yards would make in looking over
               gardens &amp; groves of fruit trees.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our route was from Paris by Dijon, Besan&#231;on &amp; Pontarlier to
               Neuchatel. We meant to have proceeded immediately to the pass of S Gothard &amp; have
               returned by the Simplon, but it was too early in the season, &amp; this pass is not
               at any time practicable for a carriage without taking it to pieces, &#8211; which involves
               a heavy expence at all times, so we proceeded to Lausanne &amp; Geneva &amp; entered
               Italy by the pass of M. Cenis, making an excursion on the way to the Chartreuse. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> told me I should
               see nothing finer than this in Switzerland, &amp; he was perfectly right.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth had visited the Chartreuse monastery in
                  1790.</note> Turin &amp; Milan were the farthest points which we reached, then to
               Como, Lugano, across the Lago Maggiore, &amp; back over the Simplon. From Martigny
               (in the Valais) we went to Chamounix, &amp; would also have gone to the S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bernards if the weather had not been unfavourable, &#8211; then to our
               friends near Morges with whom we rested three days.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry and his family; Echichens is in the Swiss district of
                  Morges. Southey visited the Awdrys for a second time 29 June &#8211; 3 July 1817.</note>
               Thro Friburg to Berne was our next move, from this latter city we sent our carriage
               to Zurich, struck into the Alps &#8211; going by way of Thuin, Interlaken, Linterbrunn,
               Grindlewald, Meyringhem &amp; Sarnen to Lucerne, then to Altof, Schweitz, Arth &amp;
               Zug to Zurich. From Schaffhausen we went to the source of the Danube, then thro the
               Black Forest to Freyburg, crost the Rhine to Strasburg, &amp; returned the same night
               to Kehl, &#8211; Baden &#8211; Rastadt &#8211; Carlsruhe &#8211; Heidelburg &#8211; Manheim &#8211; Frankfurt &#8211; Mentz so
               to Cologne Brussels &amp; home by way of Lisle &amp; S Omers.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I kept a full journal &#8211; this was a great effort, weary as we always
               were at night. However I persevered, &amp; if it were tolerably printed it would fill
               a reasonable octavo volume; but if drawn out for publication the extent would be
               doubled. I have no such intention, in as much as my time may be much more worthily
               employed, &#8211; &amp; that portion of it which is given [MS torn] more profitably <del>x
                  xxxx xxxxxx Scotland xxx Highland xxxxxxxxx xxxxxxxxx xxx xxxxxxxxx xxxxxx xx
                  xxxxxxx xxxx </del>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">In several places I saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsleys</ref> name &amp; met several Englishmen
               who had become acquainted with him in Italy. He was last [MS obscured] at the
               Ambrosian Library.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Biblioteca Ambrosiana, a
                  Library in Milan opened in 1609 and containing a huge number of medieval
                  manuscripts.</note> I bought a box of books at Milan, &amp; thrice as many at
               Brussels, &#8211; picking up others on the way. At Lugano I purchased three volumes by an
               Italian poet,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Filippo Pananti (1776&#8211;1837),
                     <title>Avventure o Osservazioni di Filippo Pananti sopra le Coste di
                     Barberia</title>, 5 vols (Milan, 1817), I, p. 107; no. 3075 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> whom W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Spencer<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">William Robert Spencer (1769&#8211;1834;
                     <title>DNB</title>), English poet and junior member of the family of the Dukes
                  of Marlborough.</note> had patronised in England &#8211; I forget his name, &#8211; but when
               the book arrives I will transcribe for your amusement a choice passage from it
               respecting Madoc.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s epic poem,
                     <title>Madoc</title> (1805).</note> In the same shop I found a volume of Polish
               Chronicles in Latin printed at Cracow, a book such I suppose to be exceedingly
                  rare.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Maciej Miechowita (1457&#8211;1523),
                     <title>Chronica Polonorum</title> (1521), no. 3335 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Ramusio is among my purchases<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Giovanni Battista Ramusio (1485&#8211;1557), <title>Navigationi e
                     Viaggi</title>, 3 vols (1556&#8211;1588), no. 2382 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> &amp; the Gesta Dei.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacques Bongars (1554&#8211;1612), <title>Gesta Dei per Francos</title> (1611), no.
                  1193 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> And I have seen &amp; paid
               for my set of the Acta Sanctorum.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">A complete
                  set of the <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, 53 vols (1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey had bought an abridged version in 1815,
                  much to his disappointment.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Does this country you will ask appear flat &amp; unprofitable after
               Alpine scenery? Certainly not. It has lost very little by the comparison, &#8211; &amp;
               that little will soon be regained. <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">
                  Skiddaw</ref> is by much the most imposing mountain for its height that I have yet
               seen, &#8211; many mountains which are actually as high again from their base do not appear
               to more advantage. I find here, as <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> had told me I should,
               the charm of proportion, &amp; would not exchange Derwentwater for the Lake of
               Geneva, &#8211; tho I would gladly enrich it with the fruit trees &amp; the luxuriant
               beauties of a Swiss summer. Their waterfalls indeed reduce ours to insignificance: &#8211;
               on the other hand all their streams &amp; rivers are hideously discoloured &#8211; so that
               that which should be one of the greatest charms of the landscape is in reality a
               disgusting part of it: the best colour which you see is that of clean soap suds, &#8211;
               the more common one that of <del>dirty</del> the same mixture when dirty. But the
               rivers have a power might &amp; majesty which it is scarcely possible to describe,
               especially the Ares which comes down the Maurienne from M Cenis. Indeed I should
               consider my journey as well repaid if it was only for the images which I treasured up
               in ascending this part of Savoy. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I found all well at home. We had been outbidden at the sale of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall"> our house</ref>, for which as it seems
               likely that we shall not be molested by our new Landlord<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall had been put up for sale in June 1817 and was bought by
                  Isaac Fisher (c. 1773&#8211;1819), a member of a Borrowdale farming family and a gold
                  and silversmith in Cockspur Street, London.</note> I am not sorry, being in no
               condition to purchase estates. My worldly affairs however are on the whole
               prosperous, &amp; as far as relates to these things I have no care for the morrow.
               But there is a world of work before me. I expect by every post the first proof of my
               third volume of Brazil,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &amp; am about to
               visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxHenryRichard">Ld Hollands</ref> Lope de
                  Vega<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed Lord Holland,
                     <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and
                     Guillen de Castro</title> (1817) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18
                  (October 1817), 1&#8211;46.</note> for the ways &amp; means of the quarter. I hope also
               to finish my Tale of Paraguay<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale
                     of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> during the winter.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Wynn &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>