<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3149</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4420</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3149. Robert Southey to John
                  Murray, 9 June 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3149.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Scotland, MS
                  42551. ALS; 4p.  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3149" type="letter">
        <head>3149. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John
                  Murray</ref>,<date when="1818-06-09"> 9 June 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
                  Postmark: E/ 13 JU 13/ 1818 <lb /> Watermark: R E &amp; S BATH 1814<lb />
                  Endorsement: 1818 June 9 Southey, R<lb /> MS: National Library of Scotland, MS
                  42551. ALS; 4p. <lb /> Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-06-09">9 June. 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your letter &amp; its inclosures. &#8211; Evelyn in a few
                  days.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Memoirs,
                     Illustrative of the Life and Writings of John Evelyn</title> (1818),
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 1&#8211;54.</note> &#8211; Dobrizhoffer
               has been published far too long to be reviewed as an original work: (1784) there is a
               German translation, &#8211; &amp; a Spanish one is among some manuscripts now upon sale in
               Parliament Street.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">On 23 May 1818 (Letter
                  3138), Southey had asked Bedford to examine some manuscripts for sale as part of a
                  large collection of Spanish texts. Bedford had reported that a manuscript on the
                  Abipone tribe of South America was not an original work but a translation into
                  Spanish of a book Southey already owned &#8211; an account of the Jesuit missions in
                  Paraguay by Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri,
                  Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library. A translation into German was produced by Anton Kreil (d. 1833),
                  <title>Geschichte der Abiponer, Einer Berittenen und Kriegerischen Nation in Paraquay</title>
                  (Vienna, 1783&#8211;1784). A Spanish translation was not published and the first English
                  translation was finally made, at Southey&#8217;s suggestion, by Sara Coleridge, <title>An
                  Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822).</note> I should
               think it remarkable that no English translation should have been made, if it were not
               the case with so many of the very best books of travels, &#8211; for instance Chardin,
               Pietro della Valle, Tavernier, &amp; Niebuhr, have only been translated in fragments,
               or miserably abridged,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Partial or abridged
                  translations of these travel writers into English include: Jean Chardin
                  (1643&#8211;1713), <title>The Travels of Sir John Chardin into Persia and the East
                     Indies. The First Volume, Containing The Author&#8217;s Voyage from Paris to
                     Ispahan</title> (1686); Pietro della Valle (1586&#8211;1652), <title>Travels into
                     East-India and Arabia Deserta</title> (1665) (no. 2894 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library); Jean-Baptiste Tavernier (1605&#8211;1689), <title>The Six Voyages of
                     John Baptista Tavernier, Baron of Aubonne</title> (1677); Carsten Niebuhr
                  (1733&#8211;1815), <title>Travels through Arabia and Other Countries in the East</title>
                  (1792).</note> &amp; it would be easy to name many more of inferior celebrity but
               of great intrinsic worth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A narrative poem in eight-lined verse has been sent me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">a Lady</ref> who is not in
               circumstances to incur the risque of publishing it. The story has few models &amp; is
               deeply tragical, &#8211; there is a great deal of womanly feeling in it, with sweetness of
               thought &amp; of expression, &#8211; &amp; a very striking conclusion. The length about
               2500 lines, &#8211; it would be the better for curtailment, &amp; has <del>xxx</del> sundry
               incorrectnesses which require weeding. The authoress is an entire stranger to me, but
               I have been so much interested by her letter &amp; her poem, that if you think it
               worth looking at, I will take some trouble in advising her how to correct it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles to Robert Southey, 25 April
                  1818, enclosing her poem, &#8216;Ellen FitzArthur&#8217;; see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and
                  London, 1881), pp. [1]&#8211;4.</note> Give me a line in reply to this, I intreat you,
               at your earliest convenience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a good many subjects in preparation for you out of the common
               route. The Jesuits in particular will be well timed.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on the Jesuits for the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>.</note> &#8211; I have just received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> concerning the Copyright
                  Committee:<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The House of Commons Select
                  Committee examining the workings of the Copyright Act (1814) reported in
                  1818.</note> he thinks an article upon that rascally subject in the Christmas
               number, would be of great consequence towards enabling our friends to take the field
               with effect in the ensuing session &amp; this I am very willing to undertake, &#8211; a
               clear, plain, pointed matter of fact statement is what is wanted, &#8211;
                  <del>something</del> which without using one harsh word or uncourteous phrase
               toward the opposite part should make every unconcerned person regard the case as it
                  <del>xx</del> really is, &#8211; something which differs only from a common robbery in
               this point, &#8211; that the robbers <del>have influence enough to take our property by
                  {stand up} acts of parliament</del> make us deliver <del>xxx</del> our
                  <del>goods</del> {property} by acts of parliament.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article on the &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217; appeared
                  in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 196&#8211;213. Southey (and
                  Murray) particularly disliked the legal requirement that copies of all works
                  should be given to the 11 copyright libraries.</note> For Heavens sake do not
               suffer <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref> to interfere
               in this matter, &#8211; he is on the side of the thieves.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <del>The Monastic</del> &#8216;British Monachism&#8217; is an admirable text.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed Thomas Dudley Fosbrooke (1770&#8211;1842;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>British Monachism; or, Manners and Customs of the
                     Monks and Nuns of England</title> (1817) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 22
                  (July 1819), 59&#8211;102.</note> Many years ago I began to collect materials for a
               History of the Monastic Orders, &#8211; a vaster subject than I shall ever live to compleat
               according to my original plan, &#8211; but in a more popular form I could <del>make a
                  xx</del> put together some most extraordinary Sketches of Monastic History.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this book.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>