<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3059</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4330</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3059. Robert Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 27 December 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3059" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3059.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Art Library,
                  London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 30. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 286&#8211;289 [in part; misdated 17 December
                  1817].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3059" type="letter">
        <head>3059. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1817-12-27">27 December 1817</date>
          </head><p>Address: [deletion and readdress in
                  another hand] To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Como/
                     <del>Italy</del>/ {Como} <lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; ANGLETERRE; COMO<lb />
                  Postmarks: PAID/ 31 DE 31/ 1817; [partial] MIL<lb /> MS: National Art Library,
                  London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 30. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 286&#8211;289 [in part; misdated 17 December
                  1817].</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was just about to send you the names of the Ship &amp; Captain,
               when your second letter arrived; &amp; I was also going to make enquiry concerning a
               box <del>from</del> of books from Milan,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The books Southey had sent Landor earlier in the year had now reached him,
                  obviating the need to make further enquiry after them; the books that Southey had
                  purchased in Milan on his continental tour of 1817 had now arrived in
                  Britain.</note> when tidings came that they were safely lodged in London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This evening I have received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorRobertEyres">your brother</ref> about the Latin poems, &amp; have in
               consequence written to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to know if he will
               undertake the publication; in that case the impression will be forwarded to him
               without delay. So you may strike out the Oxford printers from the black list.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had asked Longman if they would be
                  prepared to publish Landor&#8217;s <title>Idyllia Nova Quinque Heroum atque
                     Heroidum</title> (1815), as Landor was deeply unhappy with Joseph Munday (c.
                  1773&#8211;1844), the Oxford bookseller, printer and publisher, and the edition he had
                  produced in 1815. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps the Lugano Gazette<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Gazzetta di Lugano</title> (1814&#8211;1821), a weekly liberal newspaper,
                  widely read in Switzerland and northern Italy.</note> may not have given you the
               great news from the North which excites much more interest in me than any thing which
               is going on at present in the political world. The Greenlandmen last season got as
               far as 84, &amp; saw no ice in any direction; &#8211; they were of opinion that if they
               could have ventured to make the experiment, they might have reached the pole without
               any obstruction of this kind.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Reports of
                  events in the Arctic were widespread in British newspapers, e.g. <title>Morning
                     Chronicle</title>, 22 November 1817, which coincides closely with Southey&#8217;s
                  information.</note> The coast of East Greenland, which had been blocked up for
               four or five centuries was open. It is believed that some great convulsion of nature
               has broken up the continent of ice which has during those centuries been
               accumulating; &amp; it is certain that the unnatural cold winds which were
               experienced throughout the whole of May last from the S. &amp; S.W. were occasioned
               by this ice floating into warmer latitudes. This effect is more likely to have been
               produced by volcanic eruptions than by earthquakes alone, &#8211; because for the last two
               years the fish have forsaken the Kamtschatkan<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">British newspapers had recently carried a number of extracts from Hamburg
                  papers, e.g. <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 8 December 1817. One of the
                  extracts reported that in the Kamchatka peninsula &#8216;in the course of last winter an
                  incredible number of bears have left the woods, frequently entered the houses of
                  the Kamtschdales; in many places have attacked and devoured the inhabitants; nay
                  traces have even been found of their having killed and devoured each other; at the
                  end of the winter many bears were found who had perished of hunger. In several
                  settlements they have killed from two to three hundred bears, the oldest
                  Kamtschadales do not remember ever to have seen so many bears so savage and
                  blood-thirsty. The cause of this savageness and of their hunger is, that for these
                  two years past there has been an entire want of fish in the Kamschatka sea, and
                  fish, as is well known, are the chief food of the bears, which being usually so
                  abundant in those waters, they easily contrive to catch. A couple of shocks of an
                  earthquake have been lately felt in the Peninsula.&#8217;</note> coast, so that the
               Bears (<del>xxxx</del>
          <hi rend="ital"> &#953;&#967;&#952;&#965;&#959;&#966;&#945;&#958;&#959;&#953;</hi>
          <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Fish eaters&#8217;</note>) <del>tho at xxxx
                  xxxxxxx</del>) have been carrying on a civil war among themselves, &amp; a war
               plus quam civile<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;More than civil&#8217;.</note>
               with the Russians. Earthquakes would not discompose their fish much, but they have a
               great objection to marine volcanoes. We are fitting out four ships for a voyage to
               the pole, &amp; the N West passage.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Newspaper accounts (e.g. <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 22 November 1817)
                  reported that the Royal Society was pressing the government to mount an expedition
                  to search for the North West passage and offering fishermen a bounty to explore
                  the area. Two Royal Navy expeditions were made. In April 1818 one commanded by
                  David Buchan (1780&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>) and John Franklin (1786&#8211;1847;
                     <title>DNB</title>) explored the Arctic sea around Spitsbergen; another
                  commanded by John Ross (1777&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>) sought a North West passage
                  around Baffin Island. Neither was successful.</note> We shall have some curious
               facts about the needle, &#8211; possibly even our climate may be improved, &#8211; &amp; trees
               will grow large enough for walking sticks in Iceland.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Amusements of Como<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor had given Southey a rather confused account of the scandal concerning
                  another expatriate resident of Como, the estranged wife of the Prince Regent,
                  Caroline of Brunswick-Wolfenb&#252;ttel (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), detailing the
                  insolent behaviour of Bartolomeo Pergami (1783/4&#8211;1842), her major domo, with whom
                  Caroline was rumoured to be having an affair. The Princess&#8217;s behaviour was the
                  subject of much gossip and in 1820 the government unsuccessfully introduced a Bill
                  of Pains and Penalties to dissolve her marriage.</note> may very probably become
               the amusement of England ere long. &#8211; in that case the Knight will have a plenary
               absolution for all those offences which in old times were punished with
                  brimstone;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Genesis</title>
                  19: 24, Sodom and Gomorrah were destroyed by God with &#8216;fire and brimstone&#8217; for the
                  sinfulness of their inhabitants. The sin primarily associated with Sodom in
                  Christian traditions was homosexuality, so Southey is implying that one of
                  Caroline&#8217;s attendants was homosexual. Again, this information is merely local
                  gossip and it is not possible to identify this member of Caroline&#8217;s
                  household.</note> &#8211; the assassin will be as popular among our Liberals as
                  Buonaparte<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;assassin&#8217; and the
                  &#8216;other worthy&#8217; were members of Princess Caroline&#8217;s household, but Landor&#8217;s account
                  is too jumbled to identify them with certainty. Southey suggests they would become
                  radical heroes as associates of Princess Caroline, who was popular with the
                  opposition as an antagonist of the Prince Regent. Thus they would join Napoleon
                  Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815), another radical
                  hero.</note> &#8211; (why not?) &amp; the other worthy will be a red letter Saint in the
               Morning Chronicle.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning
                     Chronicle</title> (1769&#8211;1862) was a Whig daily newspaper opposed to the
                  government. In medieval Catholic liturgical books the days sacred to important
                  saints were printed in red letters.</note> &#8211; This I think a likely consequence
               from the death of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WalesCharlottePrincess">the P.
                  Charlotte</ref>.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Princess Charlotte died in childbirth, after 18 months of marriage, on 6
                  November 1817. Popular grief (and dislike of the Prince Regent) was increased by
                  the belief that she had been ill-treated by her father in the past, and that news
                  of her death had been kept by him from her mother, Princess Caroline.</note> In
               the lamentation upon this subject there has been a great deal of fulsome canting,
               &amp; not a little faction; &#8211; still among the better part &amp; the better classes of
               society, there was a much deeper &amp; more general grief than could have been
               expected or would easily be believed. Two or three persons have told me that in most
               houses which they entered in London the women were in tears</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Tis not the public loss which hath imprest</l>
          <l rend="indent3">This general grief upon the multitude</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And made its way at once to every breast</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The old, the young, the gentle &amp; the rude; &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Tis not that in the hour which might have crown&#8217;d</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The prayers preferrd by every honest tongue,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The very hour which should have sent around</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Tidings where with all churches would have rung</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And all our echoing streets have pealed with gladness,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And all our cities blazed with festal fire,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">That then we saw the high-raised hope expire</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And Englands expectation quenched in sadness.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">This surely might have forced a sudden tear</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Yet had we then thought only of the State,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Tomorrows sun which would have risen as fair,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Had seen upon our brows no cloud of care.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">It is to think of what thou wert so late,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">O thou who liest clay cold upon thy bier!</l>
          <l rend="indent3">So young, &amp; so beloved, so richly blest</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Beyond the common lot of royalty, &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The object of thy worthy choice possest, &#8211;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The many thousand souls that prayed for thee</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Hoping in thine a nations happiness,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And in thy youth, &amp; in thy wedded bliss,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And in the genial bed, &#8211; the cradle drest,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Hope standing by, &amp; Joy a bidden guest, </l>
          <l rend="indent3">Tis this that from the heart of private life</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Makes unsophisticated sorrows flow,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">We mourn thee as a daughter &amp; a wife</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And in our human natures feel the blow.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">These &#8216;Lines Written Upon the Death of the Princess
                     Charlotte&#8217; were not published until they appeared in <title>The Amulet, or
                        Christian and Literary Remembrancer</title> (London, 1829), pp. 91&#8211;92.
                  </note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="center"> ____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you succeeded in getting sight of the <hi rend="ital">aspide</hi>?<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Vipera asperis, a
                  venomous species of viper, found in Italy.</note> In Cyprus they stand in such
               dread of this serpent that the reapers have bells fixed to their sides &amp; their
               sickles, <hi rend="ital">&#954;&#959;&#965;&#966;&#953;</hi>
          <note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Deaf&#8217;.</note> they call it there, &#8211; one
               traveller names it the asp, &amp; another asks an veterum aspis?<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Is this the ancient asp?&#8217; The former traveller
                  is Alexander Drummond (1698&#8211;1769; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels through the
                     Different Countries of Germany, Italy, Greece, and Parts of Asia, as Far as the
                     Euphrates, with an Account of what is Remarkable in their Present State and
                     their Monuments of Antiquity</title> (London, 1754), p. 143; the latter is the
                  botanist, John Sibthorp (1758&#8211;1796; <title>DNB</title>), extracts from whose
                  journal of his tour in Cyprus in 1787 were published in Robert Walpole
                  (1781&#8211;1856), <title>Memoirs Relating to European and Asiatic Turkey</title>, 2
                     vols (London, 1817&#8211;1820), I, p. 285; no. 3098 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. These are probably references to the Blunt-nosed
                  viper, Macrovipera Lebetina, though, rather than Vipera asperis.</note> so I
               suppose it to be your neighbour. I do not know if <del>your</del> the venom of your
               serpent produces death (as some others do) by paralysing the heart, but it may be
               worth knowing that in that case the remedy is to take spirit of hartshorn<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Ammonium carbonate, originally derived from
                  shavings of the horns of red deer. It was much used as smelling salts to revive
                  people who were feeling faint.</note> in large doses, repeating them as long as
               the narcotic effect is perceived. A surgeon in India<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr John Macrae (dates unknown), a Surgeon of the East India
                  Company at Chittagong, who reported he had cured himself of the effects of a cobra
                  bite by this method on 12 May 1809; see <title>Asiatick Researches; or,
                     Transactions of the Society Instituted in Bengal, for Inquiring into the
                     History and Antiquities, the Arts, Sciences, and Literature, of Asia</title>,
                  11 (1810), 309&#8211;317; no. 77 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
          <del>xx</del> saved himself in this manner by taking much larger doses than he could
               have prescribed to any other person, &#8211; because he understood his own sensations &amp;
               proportioned the remedy accordingly. He took a tea spoonfull of the Spiritus Ammoni&#230;
                  compositus<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Compound of spirit of
                  ammonia, or hartshorn. </note> in a Madeira glass-full of water, every five
               minutes for half an hour, &amp; seven other such doses at longer intervals,
               (according to the symptoms) before he considered himself out of danger, &#8211; in the
               whole a wine glass full of the medicine. This is a very valuable fact, the medicine
               having lost its repute in such cases because it was always administered in
               insufficient doses. And so may S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Abondio<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Saint Abundius (d. 469), Bishop of Como c. 448&#8211;469 and patron
                  saint of the town.</note> bless the prescription. I owe that saint a good turn for
               the delicious shelter that he afforded me in a hot-day.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had visited the 11th century Basilica of
                  Sant&#8217;Abbondio, Como on 19 June 1817, when he was staying in the town to visit
                  Landor. Saint Abondius&#8217;s relics are preserved in the church.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1817-12-27"> 27. Dec. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>