<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3018</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4289</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3018. Robert Southey to Henry Koster, 26 August
                  1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3018.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro, Rio de Janeiro; text taken from
                  Sousa-Lea&#771;o .  Previously  published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de
                  1804 a 1819&#8217;, Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro, 178 (1943), 50&#8211;53.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3018" type="letter">
        <head>3018. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref>, <date when="1817-08-26">26 August
                  1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro, Rio de Janeiro; text taken from
                  Sousa-Lea&#771;o<lb /> Previously published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e Henry Koster, anos de
                  1804 a 1819&#8217;, <title>Revista do Instituto Historico e Geografico Brasileiro</title>, 178 (1943), 50&#8211;53.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-08-26">26 Aug. 1817.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Koster</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have learnt, no doubt, from Liverpool,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">From Koster&#8217;s father, John
                  Theodore Koster, who lived at Birkenhead Priory.</note> that while you were expecting to hear from me and supposed me to be quietly
               pursuing my usual employments at home, I was far away upon the continent. I went abroad to see whether a total change of scene and
               circumstance would wean me from recollections which time seemed rather to strengthen than to abate.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to Southey&#8217;s grief over the death of his son <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, on 17 April 1816.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> (of
               whom you may have heard us speak) were my companions. Our route was from Calais to Paris, Dijon, Besan&#231;on, Pontarlier, Neufchatel,
               Lausanne, Geneva, and M. Cenis to Turin and Milan. The Lakes Como, Lugano and Maggiori back into Switzerland by the Simplon &#8211; Friburg,
               Bern, the Bernese Alps, Lucerne, the wood cantons, Zurich, Schaffhausen, Donauschingen through the Black Forest to Friburg in the
               Brisgau, Kehl, Strasbourg back over the Rhine to Bedch, Rastadt, Heidelberg, Manheim, Frankfort, Maintz, Coblentz &#8211; Cologne,
               Aix-la-Chapelle and so home by Brussels, Lisle and St. Omer: A tour of about 3,000 miles, which we accomplished in thirteen weeks
               without any delay, accident, or unpleasant circumstances of any kind. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> During this whole time I saw no English newspapers after the first week; and it was from the Lugano gazette<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Gazzetta di Lugano</title> (1814&#8211;1822), a weekly Swiss paper of liberal views.</note> (the oracle
               of the North of Italy) that I first learnt of the insurrection of Pernambuco.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">An attempted
                  revolution in the Brazilian province of Pernambuco March&#8211;May 1817. Koster was based in the area and was a witness to the
                  events.</note> &#8211; Your letter of 24. Febr. reached me just as I was leaving town for the journey. That of the 21st of June I received
               on Thursday last, three days after my return. I enclosed the papers by the next nights post to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">Bishop of London</ref>, who would receive them yesterday, if he were at Fulham.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Bishop&#8217;s palace was at Fulham. At Koster&#8217;s instigation, the British expatriate community in
                  Pernambuco had sent Southey a letter requesting his help in securing for them a chaplain, rather than directly approaching the
                  church authorities. Discovering that responsibility for such appointments lay with the Bishop of London, Southey was attempting to
                  help.</note> The <hi rend="ital">fourth</hi> copy of my second volume<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Presentation copies of
                  the second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (1810&#8211;1819).</note> was designed for <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">your father</ref>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not my fault that the reviewal of your book did not appear three months earlier.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Koster&#8217;s <title>Travels in Brazil</title> (1816). Southey reviewed this book in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16
                  (January 1817), 344&#8211;387. This issue did not appear until 20 May 1817.</note> It was written as soon as the book appeared and printed
               immediately. Anything further did not depend upon me. I was glad to hear that about ten copies only of the quarto were left, and that
               an octavo edition was ready for publication.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The first edition of <title>Travels in
                     Brazil</title> was a quarto. The second edition of 1817 was a two volume octavo.</note> Here is good encouragement for you, if
               you needed any. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have sent my third volume to the press<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil
                  </title>(1810&#8211;1819).</note> and am hard at work upon it. During my absence the Santuario Mariano arrived for me from Lisbon. &#8211; a
               book which I had been soliciting in vain for several years.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Agostinho de Santa Maria
                  (1642&#8211;1728), <title>Santuario Mariano e Historia das Imag&#275;s Milagrosas de Nossa Senhora</title> (1707&#8211;1723), no. 3222 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> The last two volumes contain a good deal of Brazilian history, most of which (indeed almost
               all) has arrived too late for my present edition, &#8211; and whether I shall ever live to see a second is doubtful &#8211; or more than
                  doubtful.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1822 a second edition of the first volume only of the <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) was published.</note> However I shall leave the work as compleat as I can make it. In the Santuario (a
               book the title of which shows of what rubbish it is composed, &#8211; being an account of all the Images of N. Senhora in Portugal and the
               Conquests in ten volumes!) &#8211; I find mention of a history of Brazil by P. F. Vicent de Salvador.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Vicente do Salvador (1564&#8211;c.1636), <title>Historia do Brasil</title> was written in the 1620s, but not published until 1888.</note>
               It is referred to apparently as if it were printed; but I have nowhere else heard of such an author. Can you learn anything of him? It
               cannot be a mistake for F. <hi rend="ital">Manoel</hi> de Salvador and the Valeroso Lucedeno,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>O Valeroso Lucideno e Triunfo da Liberdade na Restaura&#231;&#227;o de Pernambuco</title> (1648) was a pseudonymous work by Manuel
                  Calado do Salvador (1584&#8211;1654), chronicling the war between the Portuguese and Dutch in Brazil in the 1630s and 1640s. It was much
                  relied on by Southey in the second volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &#8211; that is certain. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps you may still be able to inform me what in the opinion of the Brazilians themselves are the advantages which
               Brazil has derived from the expulsion of the Jesuits.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The Jesuit order was expelled from Brazil
                  in 1759 and from Paraguay in 1767.</note> My former volumes must vent unequivocal testimony to the impartiality with which I regard
               the Jesuits. I am not aware of any possible motives which could influence my judgement either for or against them and I cannot but
               consider the expulsion to have been founded upon false accusations and in every way impolitic as well as abominably unjust. &#8211; But you
               will wish to hear a little English news and English gossip, rather than to have me talking across the Atlantic upon the old subject. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">Mrs. Vardon</ref> is &#8211; lying in at Tournay. This I am sure is news which will surprize
               you, and I think an attestation of the fact ought to be sent to Spa &#8211; as an enducement to others to step in St. Remacles footstep.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">In the Belgian town of Spa, women wishing to become pregnant put a foot into a footstep cut in
                  stone and dedicated to St Remaclus (d. 673) &#8211; as Mrs Vardon had done when she visited the town with Southey and Koster on 8 October
                  1815.</note> We crost with her to Calais and had no suspicion of her pregnancy. At Calais we parted with her, and when we reached
               Brussels on our return found her apparently very near the time of her confinement. She was going to England with George<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">George Tarbutt Vardon (b. 1803). He emigrated to Canada in 1832 and worked in the Indian
                  Department.</note> who was to be placed at the military Academy at Sandhurst, and could not be admitted unless he appeared there the
               second Tuesday in August. <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMr">Mr. V.</ref> could not go with him being detained at Brussels
               with Martin<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Martin Vardon (dates unknown), the Vardons&#8217; younger son.</note> in consequence of
               an unlucky affair which I will presently explain. So she was right glad to join company with us, and set off half a day before us, that
               we who travelled faster might come up with her the next night at Lisle. We found her at Tournay, afraid to proceed and thence left her,
               the Doctor having pronounced rest necessary and given hopes that after a few days she might continue her journey. Her house in Hanover
               Square was ready and she did not expect the young Remacle to appear before the middle of October. We took George on with us and left
               her with Tom, Miss V. and Mary.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The Vardons&#8217; eldest daughter and their servant.</note> Tidings
               however have arrived that she has been brought to bed there. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Martins affair is briefly thus. Bows and arrows had been forbidden at the school, very properly, as the arrows were
               pointed with needles. Martin borrowed one from one boy to make a shot with it, and desired another of his schoolfellows to hold his
               book before his face that he might shoot at him (their common mode of play.) The boy lowered the book at the moment that the arrow was
               on the way, and it entered the corner of his eye. A cataract was coming on in this eye,&#8211; this produced inflammation and ended in the
               loss of the eye. And for this the parents have been wicked enough to prosecute Martin criminally! The cause had been discussed in two
               courts, and by the last accounts it to be carried to a third! </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thus much for the Vardons who have made a miserable business of educating their boys abroad. Tom<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Vardon (1799&#8211;1867; <title>DNB</title>), Librarian of the House of Commons 1831&#8211;1867.</note> is
               very much worsened, Dutch education having in great measure undone what Westminster had effected. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> is in high feather, and is coming to take lodgings at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick"> Keswick</ref>. So is <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &#8211; and
               the Rickmans<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Susannah Rickman</ref> and their children: Anne (b. 1808); William Charles (1812&#8211;1886); and
                  Frances (dates unknown).</note> are on their way to visit us. September therefore if the weather shall permit will be a month of
               compleat dissipation. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> is lodging at the bottom of the garden. <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">The house</ref> and property have been sold by auction. I was a bidder (by proxy) during my
               absence, and have not been well used about it. However my new landlord<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall was bought by
                  Isaac Fisher (c. 1773&#8211;1819) a member of a Borrowdale farming family and a gold and silversmith in Cockspur Street, London.</note> a
               silversmith in Cockspur Street, and a Borrowdale man by birth, talks civilly and promises largely. All here is well, and I have about
               250 volumes on the way from Milan and Brussels, &#8211; including the Acta Sanctorum, which I have at last seen paid for.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had bought in Brussels the massive, 53&#8211;volume compendium of hagiographies entitled <title>Acta
                     Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> Verbeyst<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1849), a famous bookseller in Brussels.</note> was delighted to see me, and even paid
               me a visit at the Hotel. I saw Grumpy, Henri, and the other coachman, all of whom were rejoiced to see me again. We called on M. Ouwerx
               at Huy,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Francois-Joseph Ouwerx (dates unknown) of Huys, a manufacturer of soap, whom Southey
                  and Koster had met on their tour of the Low Countries on 5&#8211;6 October 1815.</note> &#8211; and we slept at Sombref, renewing our
               acquaintances everywhere. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for English politics you are probably as well informed of the event of the last four months as I am, who have picked
               up my only knowledge from French, Italian and German papers. You will have seen my papers in the Quarterly,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is probably referring in particular to &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October
                  1816), 225&#8211;278, which provoked the attack on him in the House of Commons by William Smith on 14 March 1817.</note> &#8211; they have not
               been without effect, &#8211; and as for the uproar which a set of cut-throats raised against me in consequence, you know me well enough to
               understand how perfectly invulnerable I am to all such attacks, and how indifferent to abuse. There is no copy here of my letter to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">Wm. Smith</ref>,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had responded to
                  William Smith with <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title>
          </note> or I would inclose it, &#8211; however I will send one with
               my next publication, whatever that may be, &#8211; most likely it will be the Tale of Paraguay.<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> I am at present more hated than any man living by the Buonapartists and the
               anarchists, &#8211; they are biting at my heel, and I set my foot upon their necks.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Joshua</title> 10: 24: &#8216;Come near, put your feet upon the necks of these kings. And they came near, and put their feet
                  upon the necks of them&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Mr. Wilberforce</ref> and talked with him about you. When I
               write to him I shall tell him about the Chaplainship but not as requesting him to interfere in the choice, &#8211; then would be an
               impropriety in this which you will easily perceive. I made him perfectly understand why the history of the Abolition was more wanted in
               Brazil than any argument upon the question; and I have little doubt but that the society will print you chuse to supply.<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Koster had argued the &#8216;Impolicy of the Slave Trade&#8217; in his <title>Travels in Brazil</title> (London,
                  1816), pp. 445&#8211;456; and Southey had suggested that Koster should translate into Portuguese an abridgement of Clarkson&#8217;s
                     <title>History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African Slave-Trade by the British
                     Parliament</title> (1808). </note> The work of abridgement you will find very easy. All here desire their love.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs affectionately.</salute>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>