<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3178</idno><idno type="nines">rce4449</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3178. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 4 August 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3178.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of Wales, MS 48123D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, 307–309 [in
                  part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3178" type="letter"><head>3178. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>,<date when="1818-08-04"> 4 August 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Bologne<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; F/ 18/
                  282<lb/> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 48123D. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, 307–309 [in
                  part].</note></head><opener><dateline><date when="1818-08-04">4 Aug. 1818.</date></dateline><salute> My dear Wynn</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I envy you your French wines, &amp; in a less degree your French
               cookery also, – both indispensable in the Aldermans Heaven,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Many local councils contained aldermen (either elected or
                  appointed), who often held office for life. Their gluttony (at public expense) was
                  proverbial.</note> where the stomach is infinite, the appetite endless, &amp; the
               dinner eternal. I should envy also your bathing upon that noble beach, if <del>I had
                  not</del> Derwentwater were {not} within reach, &amp; still better the rock-baths
               in Newlands, which are the perfection of bathing.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The rock–baths near Tom’s home in the Newlands valley, <ref type="m" target="places.html#EmeraldBank">Emerald
                  Bank</ref>.</note> What you say of the country about Boulogne is just what I should have
               supposed it be, from what we saw upon the road, &amp; the place itself is a very
               interesting one. I <del>xxxx</del> slept there &amp; did not leave it till noon the
               next day, happening to have an acquaintance there in Sir Jere Homfray;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Jeremiah Homfray (1759–1833; <title>DNB</title>),
                  a Welsh ironmaster and speculator in mineral rights, living in Boulogne since
                  being declared bankrupt in 1813. Southey visited him in May 1817 during his
                  continental expedition of that year.</note> (my neighbour <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barkers</ref> Uncle). – I had been told that
               the road to Paris was uninteresting, but to me it appeared far otherwise, – for even
               if it had not possessed an historical interest of the highest kind to an Englishman,
               the scenery itself is in many parts very striking. </p><p rend="indent1"> I have never seen the French Espriella.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph-Antoine de Gourbillon (dates unknown) and T. W. Dickinson
                  (dates unknown), <title>L’Angleterre et les Anglais, ou Petit Portrait d’une
                     Grande Famille, Copié et Retouché par Deux Témoins Oculaires</title>, 3 vols
                  (Paris, 1817) an adaptation of Southey’s 1807 travelogue <title>Letters from
                     England: By Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title>.</note> A French newspaper in
               which I was liberally abused for having written a most atrocious libel upon my own
               country was shown me at Huy; – &amp; some obliging person thought proper to favour me
               with a second paper of the same kind from Paris, with a few vituperative lines of
               English upon the cover. I guessed that the case must be as you have now described it,
               – &amp; I thought no more about it. But it might be worth while to have the matter
               explained in the QR.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title> did not publish an article on the French version of Southey’s
                  travelogue, or comments on Southey in the French press.</note> because the good
               effects would be felt in my next years account with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Patres Nostro</ref>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Longmans, Southey’s publisher, whose business premises were in
                  Paternoster Row.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Had you been in England I should have wished you to see my letter to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> before it
               past thro the press.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">At the general election
                  in June–July 1818 the Lowther family’s dominance of Westmorland was challenged by
                  Henry Brougham’s candidature. Wordsworth worked hard for the Lowthers, but Southey
                  had kept his distaste for Brougham much more low-key – hence his outrage at
                  reports that Brougham had condemned both Southey and Wordsworth at the hustings on
                  30 June 1818. Southey composed a lengthy reply, but was dissuaded from publishing
                  it until it appeared as a ‘Postscript’ to the second edition of <title>Carmen
                     Triumphale</title> (London, 1821), pp. 45–53 (it did not name Brougham).
               </note> Local circumstances made it becoming in me to resent an insult which was
               offered <del>in the</del> before my neighbours &amp; acquaintance, – utterly without
               provocation, (for I had not written a syllable concerning the election nor
                  <del>spoken</del> interfered with it in any way,) – &amp; <hi rend="ital">more
                  suo</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">‘In his usual manner’.</note>
               with as little regard to decency as to truth. I am giving him a thorough dressing, –
               which will have its effect here, &amp; when you see the offensive passages which have
               drawn upon him this castigation <del>you will not think</del> &amp; bear in
                  <del>xxx</del> {mind} the temper which he has excited in the rabble of this
               country, you will think me right in grappling with him as I have done. This is not a
               case in which there is occasion to enter into any sort of explanation, or
               justification of myself, – I have simply to say that all which he has said of me is
               absolutely false, &amp; then to lay on &amp; pummel him without mercy. – Had it not
               been for the Special Constables whom he thought proper to call Bludgeon men,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 6 July
                  1818, reported Brougham’s speech after the close of the election, in which he
                  condemned the use of special constables under the authority of a Bow Street
                  officer from London to keep order at the polling booths and threatened legal
                  proceedings over their actions.</note> he would have carried his election
                  a-la-<ref type="m" target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref>,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Burdett was MP for Westminster 1807–1837 and mobilised
                  a great deal of popular support; at the 1818 general election his pro-government
                  opponent, Sir Murray Maxwell (1775–1831; <title>DNB</title>), was severely injured
                  by a paving stone hurled at him by those opposed to his candidature.</note><hi rend="ital">vi et armis</hi>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">‘By force
                  of arms.’</note> He invited the Kendal mob to meet him at Appleby,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Some of the worst election violence was in Kendal,
                  while the polling station was at Appleby, the county town of Westmorland.</note>
               &amp; they went accordingly.</p><p rend="indent1"> You will be better pleased to hear that if the Carriers do not
               disappoint me I may expect tomorrow to receive my three cases of books <del>from
                  Brussels,</del> with the Acta Sanctorum,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had bought in Brussels in 1817 the massive compendium of hagiographies
                  entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643–1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue
                  of his library.</note> &amp; some fourscore volumes besides, – the gatherings of
               my last years journey from Como to Brussels. Far better &amp; far more agreably would
               my time &amp; thoughts be <del>xxxxx</del> {employed} with the Saints of old than
               with the Sinners of the present day, – with past events &amp; in other countries than
               with the current politics of our own. Heaven knows I have no predilection for a train
               of thought which brings with it nothing elevating &amp; nothing chearful. But I
               cannot shut my eyes either to the direct tendency of the principles which are now at
               work, or to their probable success, – inevitable indeed &amp; at no very distant
               time, – unless some means be taken for checking the progress of the evil.</p><p rend="indent1"> The state of religious feeling appears to differ much in different
               parts of France, – in most places we found {that} the churches were very ill
               attended, – but at Auxonne they were so full, that we literally could not decently
               walk in to examine them as we wished to have done. – In Switzerland the Protestant
               Cantons have suffered more than the Catholic ones. I had good opportunities of
               enquiring into this in the Pays de Vaud, – &amp; the state of religion <del>of</del>
               {in} Geneva is now notorious. Upon the banks of the Rhine all the inhabitants who
               were not actually employed in the fields seemed to be busy in performing a pilgrimage
               – it was a most striking sight to see them, men women &amp; children, toiling along
               bareheaded, under a July sun, singing German hymns. I suspect that the progress of
               irreligion has kept pace with the extent of French books in {the} Catholic part of
               Europe, &amp; that where they have not found their way, the people remain in the same
               state as before. But if things remain quiet for one generation the Catholic Church
               will recover its ascendancy – its Clergy are wise as serpents; – &amp; with all their
               errors, one cannot, considering all things, but heartily wish them success.</p><p rend="indent1"> You should go to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Omers, if it were only to
               groan over the ruin of its magnificent cathedral.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The medieval Cathedral of Saint-Omer. It was closed during the
                  French Revolution in 1792. The diocese was suppressed in 1801 in the Concordat of
                  that year and the bishop’s seat moved to Arras.</note> The country between that
               place &amp; Lisle is the perfection of cultivated scenery, &amp; the view from Cassel
               the finest I have ever seen over a flat country. – God bless you my dear Wynn – I
               half hope Parliament may be sitting in December that I may meet you in town.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>