<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2847</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4118</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2847. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 20 September 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2847.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 294. ALS; 3p. .  Previously  published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 211&#8211;212 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2847" type="letter">
        <head>2847. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>, <date when="1816-09-20">20 September 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>.<lb /> Endorsement: 20 Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816<lb />
                  MS: Huntington Library, RS 294. ALS; 3p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 211&#8211;212 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1816-09-20">20 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I am again desired to come to London it will be very silly after
               the letters I have written.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had
                  conveyed to Southey the ministerial suggestion that he should edit a
                  pro-government journal; Southey had declined.</note> they are to this purport, &#8211;
                  <del>xxxx</del> to express my full <del>xxxx</del> opinion of the real state of
               things &amp; expose the actual danger in broad terms: &#8211; to recommend as the only
               means of <del>prevent</del> averting it that the batteries which are now playing
               breach upon the Government be silenced, &#8211; in other words that the punishment for
               sedition be made such as to prevent a repetition of the offence; &#8211; &amp; if verdicts
               cannot be procured that the H Corpus<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Habeas
                  Corpus is the principle in English law that prevents detention without trial. It
                  was suspended in 1794&#8211;1795 and again in 1817&#8211;1818.</note> be suspended &amp; the
               Anarchists silenced by that means. I have endeavoured to make the necessity of these
               measures felt, &amp; shown that for my own part I cannot be better employed any where
                  <del>else</del> than here, &amp; that if it be thought advisable that I should
               either covertly or openly give up some time to political writing, it would counteract
               in great measure the effect of any thing which might proceed from me, <del>if I</del>
               were I to accept of any thing in shape of office or augmented pension;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had received a government pension of &#163;200
                  per annum since 1807.</note> &#8211; this therefore I have decidedly declined, &#8211; but
               have offered to employ my pen zealously in recommendation &amp; defence of vigorous
               measures. &#8211; Should I therefore be again desired to visit London, my journey will pass
               as an ordinary occurrence, &#8211; &amp; nothing extraordinary will occur in it, except
               that I shall be introduced to {some of} the first officers of Government &#8211; instead of
               the second to whom my acquaintance has hitherto been limited: <del>I can only repeat
                  in conversation what I have said in writing</del> &#8211; &amp; this may pass for a very
               natural occurrence. I can only repeat in conversation what I have already said in
               writing; &amp; perhaps concur in arranging a journal, of which most certainly I
               will not undertake the management: &#8211; that office is beneath me, &amp; would
               require a sacrifice of character as well as time. The matter of danger is one which
               could not fail to present itself, &#8211; as for that matter I know very well what I have
               at stake in the event of a revolution, &#8211; were the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunts</ref> &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitts</ref> to have the upper hand. There is no man whom the Whigs &amp;
               the Anarchists hate more inveterately, because there is none whom they fear so much.
               Nothing that I could do would increase their good disposition towards me, &#8211; &amp; it
               would be folly to dream of <del>lessening</del> abating it. If the G. will but act
               vigorously &amp; promptly all may yet be well, &#8211; if they will not &#8211; I shall have no
               time to spare from my history of Brazil:<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; Of which history I send the conclusion of a chapter,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                  (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, pp. 588&#8211;631 (Chapter 29).</note> &#8211; the next in order does
               not follow upon the same paper because the transcription was begun before this was
               finished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I heartily wish you were in an <hi rend="ital">efficient</hi>
               situation. Every thing may be done with foresight &amp; resolution, &#8211; without them
               every thing must go to ruin.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>