<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2966</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4237</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2966. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 5 April 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2966" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2966.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2966" type="letter">
        <head>2966. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1817-04-05">5 April 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
            <lb /> Endorsements: 5 April 1817; 5 April 1817. with conclusion of Ltr to W Smith
                  M.P.<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Unpublished.<lb /> Note on MS: the letter contains an enclosure, a draft of part of
                  Southey&#8217;s <title>A Letter to William Smith</title> (1817).</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here is the <hi rend="ital">finale</hi>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The final part of Southey&#8217;s pamphlet <title>A Letter to William
                     Smith, Esq. M.P. from Robert Southey Esq.</title>, published by Murray at the
                  end of April 1817.</note> As a whole the composition would be better if 2 1/2 of
               these pages were omitted &#8211; &amp; the paragraph &#8216;Such <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W. S.</ref>&#8217; were made to
               follow <del>it</del> immediately the slander stroke, &amp; to begin thus. Had you Sir
               perused the writings of the man whom you have traduced you could not have mistaken
               his views &amp;c. {But} There is a fitness in stating some thing of my opinions &#8211; tho
               it weakens the force of the Tender Epistle. You will give me your opinion, the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Docstors</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turners</ref>, all which I shall duly
               ponder when the proof arrives &#8211; for the proof must be sent me. You will like the
               conclusion. Think of my forbearance in not adding this about the Bull &#8220;What have you
               to do with my horns <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> S.</ref>? I have too much regard for the
               domestic tranquillity of you &amp; your family to offer any insinuation respecting
                  <hi rend="ital">yours</hi>.&#8221;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a
                  suggestion that Smith was a cuckold. He was married to Frances Coape (1758&#8211;1840)
                  and the couple had ten children. For the allusion to a bull that Southey did
                  include in his draft, see below: &#8216;You wished to take the Bull by the horns, &amp;
                  you have had your wish. Such a feat may be very well for a Spanish picador or an
                  English piccassin when the Bull is to be butchered or baited for the amusement of
                  a herd of bipeds &#8211; but for a plain Country gentleman to provoke an animal who is
                  unoffendingly feeding in his own pasture, is neither a very wise nor a very safe
                  bravado. It would be prudent first to enquire whether his horns were lopt.&#8217; The
                  passage did not appear in the printed version. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All that is needful is to take care of prosecution<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">That is, to avoid publishing anything that would
                  expose Southey to prosecution for libel.</note> &amp; of this I think there can be
               no danger, the provocation having been so notorious &amp; so great.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith had denounced Southey in the House of Commons on
                  14 March 1817 in the debate on the Seditious Meetings Bill, condemning &#8216;the
                  settled, determined malignity of a renegado&#8217; and comparing Southey&#8217;s arguments
                  against radical views in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816),
                  227, with those expressed in <title>Wat Tyler</title> (1817), Act 2, lines
                  103&#8211;112.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As for a challenge I have taken care to state my principles
               concerning duelling, &amp; if the man be fool enough after this to challenge I shall
               turn him over to the Magistrates.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was
                  worried that Smith would challenge him to a duel, a practice that was illegal,
                  though over a thousand duels were fought in the United Kingdom between 1785 and
                  1845.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The title must be simply A Letter to W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> S. Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Member for Norwich by RS. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will determine how many to print &#8211; I
               should think 500 quite enough, &#8211; profit is out of the question &amp; I want no loss. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had written something more about the state of things but it was
               leading me too far, &amp; making <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> S.</ref> the post upon whom I hang my opinions, instead of
               the man who was tied to the post for whipping. So this matter is transferred to the
                  QR.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;Rise and Progress of
                  Popular Disaffection&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511&#8211;552
                  (published 20 May 1817).</note> &#8211;It has delayed my journey till the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. on the 24 I hope to breakfast with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Docstor</ref>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall look impatiently for the proofs &#8211; about two sheets in all.
               The shorter for such things the better.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1817-04-05">Saturday 5 April 1817</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> If any thing is omitted in this Tender Epistle it is of little
                  consequence. If I should be compelled to write a second, it will be to show that
                  the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">Slandersmith</ref> &amp; his
                  party are the men who have changed their principles, &#8211; a strong ground,
                     <del>upon</del> {from} which I should be able to batter them with tremendous
                  effects. </p>
          <p rend="center"> To William Smith Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The text that follows is a draft of Southey&#8217;s
                     pamphlet <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title>, published by Murray at the end of April 1817.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="center"> &#8211;&#8212;</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Sir</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> You are represented in the newspapers as having entered during an
                  important discussion in Parliament into a comparison between certain passages in
                  the Quarterly Review, &amp; the opinions which were held by the author of Wat
                  Tyler three &amp; twenty years ago.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith
                     had denounced Southey in the House of Commons on 14 March 1817 in the debate on
                     the Seditious Meetings Bill, condemning &#8216;the settled, determined malignity of a
                     renegado&#8217; and comparing Southey&#8217;s arguments against radical views in the
                        <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 227, with those
                     expressed in <title>Wat Tyler</title> (1817), Act 2, lines 103&#8211;112.</note> It
                  appears farther, according to the same authority, that the introduction of so
                  strange a criticism in so unfit a place, did not arise from the debate, but was a
                  premeditated thing; that you had prepared yourself for it by stowing the Quarterly
                  Review in one pocket, &amp; Wat Tyler in the other; &amp; that you deliberately
                  stood up for the purpose of <del>applying xxxxx of the House &amp;
                     xxxxxxxxxx</del> {reviling} an individual who was not present to vindicate
                  himself, &amp; in a place which afforded you protection.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">As Smith made his statements in the House of Commons, he could
                     not be prosecuted for slander.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> My name indeed was not mentioned, but that I was the person whom
                  you intended was notorious to all who heard you. For the impropriety of
                  introducing such topics in such an assembly, it is farther stated, that you
                  received a well-merited rebuke from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wynn</ref>, who spoke
                  on that occasion as much from his feelings towards one with whom he had lived in
                  uninterrupted friendship for nearly thirty years, as from a sense of the respect
                  which is due to Parliament.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had
                     spoken immediately after Smith on 14 March 1817 to defend Southey.</note> It is
                  however proper that I should speak explicitly for myself. This was not necessary
                  in regard to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Brougham</ref>, &#8211; he only carried the quarrels as well as the
                  practices of the Edinburgh Review into the House of Commons, &amp; talked
                  defamation instead of writing it.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                     may be referring to Brougham&#8217;s speech in the House of Commons on 24 February
                     1817, when he contrasted the unwillingness of the government to prosecute
                     Southey&#8217;s early radical play, <title>Wat Tyler</title>, for sedition, with its
                     eagerness to pursue radical publications.</note> But as calumny Sir has not
                  been your vocation it may be useful, even to yourself, if I comment upon your
                  first attempt. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> First, as to the Quarterly Review. You can have no other authority
                  for ascribing any particular paper in that journal to one person or to another
                  than common report; in following which you may happen to be as much mistaken as I
                  was when upon the same grounds I supposed M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith to be a man of candour, incapable of grossly &amp; wantonly <hi rend="ital">insulting</hi> an individual.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> The Quarterly Review stands upon its own merits. It is not
                  answerable for any thing more than it contains. What I may have said, or thought
                  in any part of my life no more concerns that journal than it does M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith or the House of Commons, &amp; I am as
                  little answerable for the Journal, as the Journal for me. What I may have written
                  in it is a question which you, Sir, have no right to ask, &amp; which certainly I
                  will not answer. As little right have you to take that for granted which you
                  cannot possibly know. The <del>xxxxxx</del> question as respects the Quarterly
                  Review is not who wrote the paper which happens to have excited M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smiths displeasure, but whether the facts which
                  are there stated are true, the quotations accurate, &amp; the inferences just. The
                  Reviewer, whoever he may be, may defy you to disprove them.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Secondly as to Wat Tyler. Now Sir though<del>t</del> you are not
                  acquainted with the full history of this notable production, yet you could not
                  have been ignorant that the person whom you attacked at such unfair advantage was
                  more sinned against than sinning. You knew that this poem had been written very
                  many years ago in his early youth. You knew that a copy of it had been
                  surreptitiously obtained, &amp; made public by some skulking scoundrel, who had
                  found booksellers not more honourable than himself to undertake the
                     publication.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1795 Southey visited
                     James Ridgway (1755&#8211;1838) and Henry Symonds (1741&#8211;1816), radical booksellers,
                     in Newgate prison, to discuss the publication of his Jacobin drama <title>Wat
                        Tyler</title>; see Robert Southey to Edith Fricker, [c. 12 January 1795],
                        <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</title>. Part One, Letter
                     123. Ridgway and Symonds did not publish it and it remained in manuscript until
                     a pirated publication, designed to embarrass the now anti-Jacobin Southey,
                     appeared in 1817. Having taken advice from <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, Southey launched a suit in
                     Chancery in order to gain an injunction suppressing the publication. His case
                     was not heard until 18&#8211;19 March 1817, and Southey lost. The &#8216;pirate&#8217; publishers
                     were William Sherwood (1776&#8211;1837), Samuel Dunbar Neely (dates unknown) and
                     Robert Jones (dates unknown) and the &#8216;skulking scoundrel&#8217; is probably a
                     reference to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">William
                        Winterbotham</ref>, who shared a room in Newgate with Ridgway and Symonds
                     and swore an affidavit that Southey had given <title>Wat Tyler</title> to him
                     and the radical publisher, Daniel Isaac Eaton (1753&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>),
                     to do with as they would.</note> You knew that it was published without the
                  writers knowledge, for the avowed purpose of insulting him, &amp; with the hope of
                  injuring him if possible. You knew that the transaction bore upon its face every
                  character of baseness &amp; malignity. You knew that it must have been effected
                  either by robbery or by breach of trust. These things M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith you knew! If I am rightly assured indeed, when <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wynn</ref>
                  reminded you of them, your countenance &amp; gestures indicated that you were
                  uneasy upon your seat. And well, Sir, you might be so! I verily believe that if it
                  were possible to revoke what is irrevocable, you would at this moment be far more
                  desirous of blotting from remembrance the unfortunate speech which stands upon
                  record in your name, than I should be of cancelling the boyish <del>xx</del>
                  composition which gave occasion to it. Wat Tyler is full of errors, but they are
                  the errors of youth &amp; ignorance; they bear no indication of an ungenerous
                  spirit, or of a malevolent heart.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> For the book itself, I deny that it is a seditious performance,
                  for it places in the mouths of the personages who are introduced, nothing more
                  that a correct statement of their real principles. That it is a mischievous
                  publication, I know; the errors which it contains being especially dangerous at
                  this time. Therefore I came forward without hesitation to avow it, to claim it as
                  my own property which had never been alienated, &amp; to suppress it. And I am
                  desirous that my motives in thus acting should not be misunderstood. The piece was
                  written under the influence of opinions which I have long since outgrown, &amp;
                  repeatedly disclaimed, but for which I have never affected to feel either shame,
                  or contrition; they were taken up conscientiously in early youth, they were acted
                  upon in disregard of all worldly considerations &amp; they were left behind in the
                  same straight-forward course as I advanced in years. It was written when
                  republicanism was confined to a very small number of the educated classes, when
                  those who were known to entertain such opinions were exposed to personal danger
                  from the populace, &amp; when a spirit of Anti-Jacobinism was predominant, which I
                  cannot characterize more fully than by saying that it was as unjust &amp; as
                  intolerant, tho not quite as ferocious as the Jacobinism of the present day. Had
                  the poem been thus published during any quiet state of the public mind, the act of
                  dishonesty in the publisher would have been the same, but I should have left it
                  unnoticed, in full confidence that it would have been forgotten as speedily as it
                  deserved. But in these times when it may be doubted whether the publication has
                  not proceeded <del>xx</del> as much from mischief as from malignity, it was
                  incumbent upon me to come forward as I have done {&amp; as I would have done} even
                  if I could have foreseen the <del>xx</del> audacious defence which was to be made,
                  &amp; the false &amp; injurious <del>counter claim</del> {pretension} which was to
                  be cast into the scale against my solemn oath. It <del>xxxxx</del> became me to
                  disclaim whatever had been erroneous &amp; intemperate in my former opinions as
                  frankly &amp; as fearlessly as I once maintained them. And this I did not
                     <del>xx</del> as one who felt himself in any degree disgraced by the exposure
                  of the crude &amp; misdirected feelings of his youth (feelings right in
                  themselves, wrong only in their direction) but as one whose life may set malice at
                  defiance, whose name is honourably distinguished abroad as well as at home, &amp;
                  who is unremittingly endeavouring to deserve well of his country &amp; of
                  mankind.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> When therefore M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Smith informed the House of
                  Commons that the author of Wat Tyler thinks no longer upon certain points as he
                  did in his youth, he informed that legislative assembly of nothing more than what
                  the author has shown during very many years in the course of his writings, &#8211; that
                  while events have been moving on upon the great theatre of human affairs, his
                  intellect has not been stationary. But when the Member for Norwich asserts (as he
                  is said to have asserted) that I impute evil motives to men merely for holding now
                  the same doctrines which I myself formerly possessed, &amp; when he charges me (as
                  he is said to have charged me) with the malignity <del>xxx</del> {&amp;} baseness
                  of a renegade, the assertion &amp; the charges are as <hi rend="ital">false</hi>,
                  as the language in which they are conveyed is coarse &amp; insulting. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Upon this subject I must be heard farther. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> The Edinburgh Review has spoken somewhere of those vindictive
                  &amp; jealous writings in which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey has brought forward
                  his claims to the approbation of the public.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 18
                     (August 1811), 283, which expressed disgust with Southey, Wordsworth, Coleridge
                     and Joanna Baillie for the &#8216;keen and vindictive jealousy, with which they have
                     put in their claim for public admiration&#8217;.</note> This is one of those passages
                  for which the Editor of that Review has merited an abatement in heraldry, &#8211; no
                  such writings ever have been written, &amp; indeed by other like assertions of
                  equal veracity the Gentleman has richly entitled himself to bear a <hi rend="ital">gore sinister tenn&#233;</hi> in his escutcheon.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">In heraldry a gore is a charge formed by an inwardly curved
                     line. A gore sinister tenn&#233; was an abatement of arms that was believed (without
                     foundation) to have been imposed in medieval times upon the bearer for
                     cowardice in the face of the enemy. </note> Few authors have obtruded
                  themselves upon the public in their individual character less than I have done. My
                  books have been sent into the world with no other introduction than an explanatory
                  preface as brief as possible, arrogating nothing, vindicating nothing: &amp; then
                  they have been left to their fate. None of the innumerable attacks which have been
                  made upon them has ever called forth on my part a single word of reply,
                  triumphantly as I might have exposed my assailants not only for their ignorance
                  &amp; inconsistency, but frequently for that moral turpitude which is implied by
                  willful &amp; deliberate mis-statement. The unprovoked insults that have been
                  leveled at me both in prose &amp; rhyme never induced me to retaliate, tho it will
                  not be supposed that the ability for satire was wanting, but happily I had long
                  since subdued the disposition. I knew that men might be appreciated from the
                  character of their enemies as well as of their friends, &amp; I accepted the
                  hatred of sciolists, coxcombs &amp; profligates, as one sure proof that I was
                  deserving well of the wise &amp; of the good. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> It will not therefore be imputed to any habit of egotism, or any
                  vain desire of interesting the public in my individual concerns, if I now come
                  forward from that privacy in which both from judgement &amp; disposition it would
                  have been my choice to have remained. While among the mountains of Cumberland I
                  have been employed upon the mines of Brazil,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil </title>(1810&#8211;1819).</note>
                  the War in the peninsula,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                        <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; such
                  other varieties of pursuit as serve to keep the intellect in health by alternately
                  exercising &amp; refreshing it; my name has served in London for the very
                  shuttle-cock of discussion. My celebrity has for a time eclipsed that of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hunt the Orator<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry
                     &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), radical politician.</note> &amp;
                  may perhaps have impeded the rising reputation of Toby the Sapient Pig.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;learned pig&#8217; was a well-known
                     fairground show; see Southey&#8217;s <title>Letters From England: By Don Manuel
                        Alvarez Espriella</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, pp. 48&#8211;49.</note> I
                  have reigned in the newspapers as paramount as <ref type="m" target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcott</ref> during the last
                  month of her tympany. Nay columns have been devoted to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Southey &amp; Wat Tyler which would otherwise have been employed in bewailing the
                  forlorn condition of the Emperor Napoleon, &amp; reprobating the inhumanity of the
                  British Cabinet for having designedly exposed him like Bishop Hatto to be devoured
                  by the rats.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                     (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815) was exiled to St Helena in
                     1815. Southey narrated the cautionary tale of Hatto I (c. 850&#8211;913; Archbishop
                     of Mainz, 891&#8211;913) in &#8216;God&#8217;s Judgement On A Bishop&#8217;, <title>Morning
                        Post</title>, 27 November 1799.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> That I should ever be honoured by such a Delicate
                     Investigation<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The Delicate
                     Investigation of 1806 was set up by the government to investigate claims that
                     Princess Caroline of Brunswick (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), estranged wife
                     of the Prince of Wales, had given birth to an illegitimate child in 1802. The
                     Princess was exonerated.</note> of my political opinions was what I never could
                  have anticipated even in the wildest dreams of unfledged vanity. Honour however
                  has been thrust upon me as upon Malvolio.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8217;Some are born great, some achieve greatness, and some have greatness thrust
                     upon them&#8217;, Malvolio in <title>Twelfth Night</title>, Act 2, scene 5, lines
                     145&#8211;146.</note> The verses of a boy, of which he thought no more than of his
                  school-exercises, &amp; which had they been published when they were written would
                  have past without notice to the family <del>xx</del> vault, have not only been
                  perused by the Lord Chancellor in his judicial office, but have been twice
                  produced in Parliament for the edification of the Legislature.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">John Scott, 1st Earl of Eldon (1751&#8211;1838;
                        <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1801&#8211;1806, 1807&#8211;1827, had given the
                     judgement in Southey&#8217;s suit for an injunction to prevent the publication of
                        <title>Wat Tyler</title>, on 18&#8211;19 March 1817.</note> The appetite for
                  slander must be sharp set, when it can prey upon such small gear! As however the
                  opinions of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey have not been thought unworthy to
                  occupy so considerable a share of attention, he need not apprehend the censure of
                  the judicious if he takes part in the discussion himself so far as briefly to
                  inform the world what they really have been, &amp; what they are. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> In my youth when my stock of knowledge consisted of such an
                  acquaintance with Greek &amp; Roman history as is acquired in the course of a
                  regular scholastic education, when my heart was full of poetry &amp; romance,
                  &amp; Lucan<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Marcus Annaeus Lucanus (39&#8211;65
                     AD), Roman poet and republican.</note> &amp; Akenside<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Mark Akenside (1721&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>), poet and
                     physician, who had a reputation for youthful republicanism.</note> were at my
                  tongues end, I fell into the political opinions which the French Revolution was
                  then scattering throughout Europe, &amp; following those opinions with ardour
                  wherever they led I soon perceived that inequalities of rank were a light evil
                  compared to the inequalities of property &amp; those more fearful distinctions
                  which the want of moral &amp; intellectual culture occasions between man &amp;
                  man. At that time &amp; with those opinions, or rather feelings (for their root
                  was in the heart &#8211; not in the understanding) I wrote Wat Tyler, as one who was
                  impatient of &#8216;all the oppressions that are done under the sun.&#8217;<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Ecclesiastes</title> 4: 1.</note> The
                  subject was injudiciously chosen, &amp; it was treated as might be expected by a
                  youth of twenty in such times {who regarded} only one side of the question.
                     <del>xxx contemplated</del>. There is no other misrepresentation. The
                  sentiments of the historical characters are correctly stated. Were I now to
                  dramatize the same story there would be much to add, but little to alter. I should
                  not express those sentiments less strongly but I should oppose to them more
                  enlarged views of the nature of man &amp; the progress of society. I should set
                  forth with equal force the oppressions of the feudal system, the excesses of the
                  insurgents, &amp; the treachery of the Government, &amp; hold up the errors &amp;
                  crimes <del>xxx</del> which were then committed as a warning for this &amp; for
                  future ages. I should write as a man, not as a stripling, with the same heart,
                  &amp; the same desires but with a ripened understanding &amp; competent stores of
                  knowledge. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> It is a fair &amp; legitimate inference that no person would have
                  selected this subject &amp; treated it in such a manner at such a time unless he
                  had in a certain degree partaken the <del>opinions</del> {sentiments} which are
                  expressed in it: in <hi rend="ital">what</hi> degree he partook them is a question
                  which it requires more temper as well as more discretion to <del>xxxxxxx</del>
                  {resolve}, than you Sir have given any proof of possessing. This can only be
                  ascertained by comparing the piece with other works of the same author, written
                  about the same time, or shortly afterward &amp; under the influence of the same
                  political opinions: by such a comparison it might be discovered what arose from
                  his own feelings &amp; what from the nature of dramatic composition. But to select
                  passages from a dramatic poem, &amp; ascribe the whole force of the sentiments to
                  the writer as if he himself held them without the slightest qualification is a
                  mode of criticism manifestly absurd &amp; unjust. Whether it proceeded in this
                  instance from excess of malice, or deficiency of sense, is a point which they who
                  are best acquainted with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith may
                  be able to determine. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> It so happens that sufficient specimens of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Southeys way of thinking in his youth are before the world, without breaking open
                  escritoires, or stealing any more of his <del>unpublished</del> {juvenile} papers
                  which he may have neglected to burn. The poem to which with all its faults, he is
                  indebted for his first favourable notice from the public, may possibly have been
                  honoured with a place in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smiths
                  library, as it received the approbation of all the dissenting journals of the
                     day.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796)
                     was reviewed favourably in the <title>Analytical Review</title>, 23
                     (February 1796), 170&#8211;177, the <title>Critical Review</title>, 17 (February
                     1796), 191&#8211;195 and the <title>Monthly Review</title>, 19 (April 1796), 361&#8211;368.
                     All of these journals were supported by radicals and Nonconformists, like
                     William Smith. The latter possessed a fine library at his country seat at
                     Parndon House, Essex.</note> It is possible that their recommendation may have
                  induced him to favour Joan of Arc with a perusal, &amp; not improbably in a mood
                  which would indulge its manifold demerits in style &amp; structure for the sake of
                  its liberal opinions. Perhaps too he may have condescended to notice the Minor
                     Poems<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Minor
                        Poems</title> (1815), a selection of his shorter pieces.</note> of the same
                  author, sanctioned as some of these also were at their first appearance by the
                  same critical authorities. In these productions he may have seen expressed an
                  enthusiastic love of liberty, a detestation of tyranny wherever it exists &amp; in
                  whatever form, an ardent abhorrence of all wicked ambition, &amp; a sympathy not
                  less ardent with those who were engaged in war for the defence of their country,
                  &amp; in a righteous cause, &#8211; feelings just as well as generous in themselves, tho
                  sometimes misdirected. He might have seen also frequent indications that in the
                  opinion of the youthful writer a far happier system of society was possible than
                  any under which mankind are at present existing, or have ever existed since the
                  patriarchal ages, &#8211; &amp; no equivocal aspirations after such a state. In all this
                  he might have seen something that was erroneous &amp; more that was visionary, but
                  nothing that savoured of intemperance or violence. I insist therefore that
                  inasmuch as Wat Tyler may differ in character from these works, the difference
                  arises necessarily from the nature of dramatic composition. I maintain that this
                  is the inference which must be drawn by every honest &amp; judicious mind, &amp; I
                  affirm that such an inference would be strictly conformable to the fact.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Do not however Sir suppose that I should seek to shrink from a
                  full avowal of what my opinions have been: neither before God or man am I ashamed
                  of them. I have as little cause for humiliation in recalling them as Gibbon had
                  when he related how he had knelt at the feet of a Confessor.<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>)
                     recalled how he sat at the feet of a Roman Catholic priest in 1753, and
                     converted to Catholicism. Gibbon explained that &#8216;Youth is sincere and
                     impetuous; and a momentary glow of enthusiasm had raised me above all temporal
                     considerations&#8217;; see <title>The Miscellaneous Works of Edward Gibbon</title>, 7
                     vols (Basle, 1796&#8211;1797), I, p. 58.</note> For while I imbibed the republican
                  opinions of the day, I escaped the atheism &amp; the leprous immorality which
                  generally accompanied them. I cannot therefore join with Beattie in blessing</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent3">&#8211; the hour when I escaped the wrangling crew</l>
            <l rend="indent3">From Pyrrhos maze &amp; Epicurus sty<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">James Beattie (1735&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                           Minstrel; or, the Progress of Genius. A Poem</title> (London 1771&#8211;1774),
                        Book 1, stanza 42, lines 6&#8211;7. Pyrrho (c. 360&#8211; c. 270 BC) was the founder of
                        Scepticism and Epicurus (341&#8211;270 BC) of Epicureanism &#8211; in Beattie&#8217;s poem
                        they represent religious doubt and indulgence in sensuality. This was a
                        favourite quotation of Southey&#8217;s; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford,
                        [started before and continued on] 12 June 1796, <title>The Collected Letters
                           of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 159.</note>
            </l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="indent0"> for I was never lost in the one, nor defiled in the other. My
                  progress was of a different kind. From building Castles in the air to framing
                  Commonwealths was an easy transition; the next step was to realize the vision,
                  &amp; in the hope of accomplishing this I forsook the course of life for which I
                  had been designed,<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s uncle,
                     Herbert Hill, had financed Southey&#8217;s time at Balliol College, Oxford in
                     1792&#8211;1794 in the expectation that Southey would become a clergyman in the
                     Church of England.</note> &amp; the prospects of advancement, which I may say
                  without presumption were within my reach. My purpose was to retire with a few
                  friends into the wilds of America &amp; there lay the foundations of a community
                  upon what we believed to be the political system of Christianity.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">The Pantisocratic scheme propounded by Southey and
                     Coleridge in 1794&#8211;1795.</note> It matters not in what manner the vision was
                  dissolved. I am not writing my own memoirs, &amp; it is sufficient simply to state
                  the fact. We were connected with no clubs, no societies, no party. The course
                  which we would have pursued might have proved destructive to ourselves, but as it
                  related to all other persons, never did the aberrations of youth take a more
                  innocent direction.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith, I know that
                  you were not ignorant of this circumstance. The project while it was in view was
                  much talked of among that sect of Christians to which you belong, &amp; some of
                  your friends are well acquainted with the events of my life.<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">At the time when Southey and Coleridge were
                     promoting Pantisocracy both held Unitarian opinions. Smith was also a
                     Unitarian.</note> What then I may ask did you <hi rend="ital">learn</hi>
                  concerning me from this late surreptitious publication? Nay, Sir, the personal
                  knowledge which you possessed was not needful for a full understanding of the
                  political opinions which I entertained in <del>xxxxxx part of</del> youth. They
                  are expressed in poems which have been frequently reprinted &amp; are continually
                  on sale: no alterations have ever been made for the purpose of withdrawing,
                  concealing, or extenuating them. I have merely affixed to every piece the date of
                  the year in which it was written, &#8211; &amp; the progress of years is sufficient to
                  explain the change.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had first
                     added dates to editions of his shorter poems in <title>Poems</title> (1799),
                     when he was still a radical. The dates indicated his poetic, rather than his
                     political or religious, development.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> You M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith, may
                  possibly be acquainted with other persons who were republicans in the first years
                  of the French Revolution &amp; who have long since ceased to be so, with as little
                  impeachment of their integrity as of their judgement. Yet you bring it as a
                  heinous charge against me, that having entertained enthusiastic notions in my
                  youth, three &amp; twenty years should have produced a change in the opinions of
                  one whose life has been devoted to unremitting study &amp; who in those branches
                  of study upon which political science is founded may say in the words of Bentley
                  to you, &amp; to such as you, that he has forgotten more than ever you
                     learnt.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Bentley (1662&#8211;1742;
                        <title>DNB</title>), classical scholar and Master of Trinity College,
                     Cambridge. Richard Cumberland (1732&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>) had reported that
                     when a schoolmaster had promised to make Cumberland as learned as his
                     grandfather, Richard Bentley, the latter had exclaimed to the schoolmaster:
                     &#8216;Pshaw, Arthur, how can that be, when I have forgot more than thou ever
                     knew&#8217;st?&#8217;, <title>Memoirs of Richard Cumberland. Written by Himself</title>, 2
                     vols (London, 1807), II, p. 33.</note> You are pleased in your candour to admit
                  that I might have been sincere when I was erroneous, &amp; you, who are a
                  professor of modern liberality, are not pleased to admit that the course of time
                  &amp; of events may have corrected me in what was wrong, &amp; confirmed me in
                  what was right. On the contrary, if the uncontroverted reports of your speech may
                  be credited, you dared affirm that any alteration must be imputed to base &amp;
                  corrupt motives. True it is that the events of the last four &amp; twenty years
                  have been lost upon you: <del>x</del>perhaps <hi rend="ital">you</hi> judge me by
                  yourself, &amp; you may think this a fair criterion, &#8211; but I must protest against
                  being measured by any such standard. Between you &amp; me Sir there can be no
                  sympathy, even tho we should sometimes happen to think alike. We are as unlike in
                  all things as men of the same time, country &amp; rank in society can be imagined
                  to be: &amp; the difference is in our mind &amp; mould as we came from the Potters
                  hand. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> And what Sir is the change in the opinions of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey which has drawn upon him the ponderous displeasure of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith? This was a point upon which it
                  behooved you to be especially well informed before you applied to him the false
                  &amp; insolent appellation which you are said to have used, &amp; which I am
                  authorized in believing that you have used. He has ceased to believe that old
                  monarchical countries are capable of republican forms of government. He has ceased
                  to think that he understood the principles of government, &amp; the nature of men
                  &amp; society before he was one &amp; twenty years of age. He has ceased to
                  suppose that men who neither cultivate their intellectual or their moral faculties
                  can understand them at any age. He has ceased to wish for revolutions even in
                  countries where great alteration is to be desired, because he has seen that the
                  end of anarchy is military despotism. But he has not ceased to love liberty with
                  all his heart &amp; with all his soul &amp; with all his strength: he has not
                  ceased to detest tyranny wherever it exists &amp; in whatever form. He has not
                  ceased to abhor the wickedness of ambition, &amp; to sympathize with those who
                  were engaged in the defence of their country &amp; in a righteous cause; &#8211; if
                  indeed he had, he might have been sure of the approbation of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith &amp; the sober opponents of their
                  country&#8217;s cause, but of the whole crew of Ultra Whigs &amp; Anarchists, from
                     Mess<hi rend="sup">rs </hi>
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham </ref> &amp;
                     Clodius,<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Clodius Pulcher (93&#8211;52
                     BC), Roman politician notorious for unscrupulous populism, conspiracy and
                     sexual immorality.</note> down to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref>, Cethegus<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Cornelius Cethegus (d. 63 BC), executed for
                     his part in the Catiline conspiracy against the Roman Republic in 63 BC.</note>
                  &amp; Co.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> The one object to which I have ever been desirous of contributing
                  according to my power, is the removal of those obstacles by which the
                     <del>xxxxxxx</del> {improvement} of mankind, is impeded, &amp; to this the
                  whole tenor of my writings whether in prose or verse bears witness. This has been
                  the pole star of my course, the needle has shifted according to the movements of
                  the state vessel wherein I am embarked but the direction to which it points has
                  always been the same. I did not fall into the error of those who having been the
                  friends of France when they imagined that the cause of liberty was implicated in
                  her success, transferred their attachment from the Republic to the military
                  Tyranny in which it ended, &amp; regarded with complacency the progress of
                  oppression because France was the oppressor. &#8216;They had turned their faces toward
                  the East in the morning to worship the rising sun, &amp; in the evening they were
                  looking eastward still, obstinately affirming that still the sun was there.&#8217;<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                        1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 23.</note> I on the contrary altered my position
                  as the world went round. For so doing M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith is said to have insulted me with the appellation of Renegade,
                  &amp; if it be indeed true that the foul aspersion past his lips, I brand him on
                  the fore head with the name of <hi rend="ital">Slanderer</hi>. Salve the mark as
                  you will Sir, it is ineffaceable! You must bear it with you to your Grave, &amp;
                  the remembrance will outlast your Epitaph.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> And now Sir learn what are the opinions of the man to whom you
                  have offered this public &amp; notorious wrong, &#8211; opinions not derived from any
                  contagion of the times, nor entertained with the unreflecting eagerness of youth,
                  nor adopted in connection with any party in the state, but during many years of
                  leisure &amp; retirement, gathered patiently, from books, observation, meditation
                  &amp; intercourse with living minds who will be the light of other ages.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Greater changes in the condition of this country have been wrought
                  during the last half century than an equal course of years had ever before
                  produced. Without entering into the proofs of this proposition, suffice it to
                  indicate, as among the most efficient causes, the steam &amp; the spinning
                  engines, the mail coach, &amp; the free publication of the debates in Parliament:
                  hence {follow}, in natural &amp; necessary consequence, increased activity,
                  enterprize, wealth, &amp; power; but, on the other hand greediness of gain,
                  looseness of principle, half knowledge (more perilous than ignorance) vice,
                  poverty, wretchedness, disaffection, &amp; political insecurity. The changes which
                  have taken place render other changes inevitable; forward we must go for
                     <del>xxxx</del> {it} is not possible to retrace our steps; the hand of the
                  political horologe cannot go back like the shadow upon Hezekiahs dial;<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">2 <title>Kings</title> 20: 8&#8211;11, in which God moved
                     the shadow on the sundial of Hezekiah (c. 739&#8211;c. 687 BC; King of Israel 729&#8211;687
                     BC) backwards as a sign to him.</note> &#8211; when the hour comes it must strike.
                  Slavery has long ceased to be tolerable in Europe: the remains of feudal
                  oppression are disappearing even in those countries which have improved the least:
                  nor can it be much longer endured that the extremes of ignorance, wretchedness
                  &amp; brutality should exist in the very centre of civilized society. There can be
                  no safety with a populace half Luddite, half Lazzaroni.<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors">The Luddites protested against the introduction of new machinery
                     in the East Midlands hosiery trade 1811&#8211;1817; the Lazzaroni were the poorest
                     urban class in Naples, often typified as beggars, who were generally seen as
                     reactionary in their politics.</note> Let us not deceive ourselves. We are far
                  from that state in which any thing resembling equality would be possible, but we
                  are arrived at that state in which the extremes of inequality are become
                  intolerable. They are too dangerous as well as too monstrous to be borne much
                  longer. Plans which would have led to the utmost horrors of insurrection have been
                  prevented by the government and by the enactment of strong, but necessary laws.
                  Let it not however be supposed that the disease is healed because the ulcer may
                  skin over. The remedies by which the body politic can be restored to health must
                  be slow in their operation. The condition of the populace, physical moral &amp;
                  intellectual, must be <del>bettered</del> {improved} or a <hi rend="ital">Jacquerie</hi>, a <hi rend="ital">Bellum Servile</hi>,<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors">A popular revolt; or a civil war of the poor
                     against the rich.</note> sooner or later will be the result. It is the people
                  at this time who stand in need of reformation, not the Government.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> The Government must better the condition of the populace; &amp;
                  the first thing necessary is to prevent it from being worsened. <del>Xxxxx xxx
                     xx</del> It must no longer suffer itself to be menaced, its chief magistrate
                  insulted, &amp; its most sacred institutions<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">The Church of England.</note> vilified with impunity. It must
                  curb the seditious press, &amp; keep it curbed. For this purpose, if the laws are
                  not at present effectual, they should be made so; nor will they then avail unless
                  they are vigilantly executed. If the press be not curbed <del>xx xxxxx</del> its
                  abuse will most assuredly one day occasion the loss of its freedom.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> This is the first &amp; most indispensable measure; for without
                  this all others will be fruitless. Next in urgency is the immediate relief of the
                  poor. I differ, <hi rend="ital">toto coelo</hi>,<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;To the whole extent of the heavens: diametrically&#8217;.</note>
                  from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Owen of Lanark in one main point.<note n="43" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen (1771&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>),
                     manager and owner of the mills and model community at New Lanark in Scotland
                     1799&#8211;1825 had developed an extensive plan for relieving distress, embodied in
                     his <title>Report to the Committee of the Association for the Relief of the
                        Manufacturing and Labouring Poor</title> (1817). Owen had visited Southey in
                     Keswick in 1816 and 1817. </note> To build upon any other foundation than
                  religion is building upon sand. But I admire his practical benevolence, &#8211; I love
                  his enthusiasm, &#8211; &amp; I go far with him in his earthly views. What he has
                  actually done entitles him to the greatest attention &amp; respect. I sincerely
                  wish that his plan for the extirpation of pauperism should be fairly tried. To
                  employ the poor in manufactures is only shifting the evil, &amp; throwing others
                  out of employ by bringing more <del>xxxxx</del> {labour, &amp; more produce of
                  labour}, into a market which is already overstocked.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> A duty scarcely less urgent than that of diminishing the burthen
                  of the poor rates is that of providing for the education of the lower classes.
                  Government must no longer, in neglect of its first &amp; paramount duty allow them
                  to grow up in worse than heathen ignorance. They must be trained up in the way
                  they should go: they must be taught to &#8220;fear God &amp; keep his commandments, for
                  this is the whole duty of man.&#8221;<note n="44" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Ecclesiastes</title> 12: 13.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Mere reading &amp; writing will not do this: they must be
                  instructed according to the <del>institutions of their country</del> {established
                  religion}; they must be fed with the milk of sound doctrine, &amp; not dry
                     <del>xxxx</del> nursed in dissent: for states are secure in proportion as the
                  great body of the people are attached to the institutions of their country. A
                  moral &amp; religious education will induce habits of industry; the people will
                  know their duty &amp; find their interest &amp; their happiness in following it.
                     <del>Xxxx xxx xxxxx</del> Give us the great boon of parochial education, so
                  connected with the Church as to form part of the Establishment, &amp; we shall
                  find it a bulwark to the State as well as to the Church. Let this be done, let
                     <del>xxxx xxxxx</del> saving Banks be generally introduced,<note n="45" place="foot" resp="editors">The first savings bank for the poor, which paid
                     interest on small deposits, was opened by Henry Duncan (1774&#8211;1846;
                        <title>DNB</title>), at Ruthwell, Dumfriesshire in 1810.</note> let new
                  channels for industry be opened (as soon as the necessities of the State will
                  permit) by a liberal expenditure in public works, by colonizing our waste lands at
                  home &amp; regularly sending off our swarms abroad, &amp; the strength wealth
                  &amp; security of the nation will be in proportion to its numbers.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> It is likewise incumbent upon government to take heed lest, in
                  {its} solicitude for raising the necessary revenue, there should be too little
                  regard for the means by which it is raised. It should beware of imposing such
                  duties as create a strong temptation <del>for</del> {<del>xx</del> to} evading{e}
                  them. It should be careful that all its measures tend as much as possible to the
                  improvement of the people, &amp; especially careful that nothing be done which can
                  tend in any way to corrupt them It should reform its prisons; &amp; apply some
                  remedy to the worst grievance which exists, &#8211; the enormous expenses, the
                  chicanery, &amp; the ruinous delays of the law.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Machiavelli says that legislators <del>should</del> {ought to}
                  suppose all men to be naturally bad.<note n="46" place="foot" resp="editors">Niccolo Machiavelli (1469&#8211;1527), <title>Discourses on the First Decade of
                        Titus Livius</title> (1531), Book 1, chapter 3, &#8216;it is necessary to whoever
                     arranges to found a Republic and establish laws in it, to presuppose that all
                     men are bad and that they will use their malignity of mind every time they have
                     an opportunity&#8217;.</note> I differ <del>upon this point</del> from that most
                  sagacious statesman. <del>Xx xxxxx xxxxx xxxx</del> {Fitter it is that}
                  Governments should think well of mankind; for the better they think of them, the
                  better they will find them, &amp; the better they will make them. Government must
                  reform the populace, the people must reform themselves. This is the true reform,
                  {&amp; compared to this all else is <hi rend="ital">flocci, nauci, nihili,
                     pili</hi>.}<note n="47" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Worthless things&#8217;: from a
                     list of noun declensions in Latin grammars.</note>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Such M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith are {in
                  part} the <del>opinions</del> {views} of the man whom you have traduced. Had you
                  perused his writings, you could not have mistaken them; &amp; I am willing to
                  believe that if you had done this, &amp; formed an opinion for yourself, instead
                  of retailing that of wretches who are libellous by trade &amp; live by sedition
                  &amp; slander, you would neither have been so far forgetful of your parliamentary
                  character, or of the <del>xxxx</del> {decencies} between man &amp; man, as so
                  wantonly, so unjustly, &amp; in such a place, to have attacked one who had given
                  you no provocation. And how Sir did you expect that the affair would end? Did you
                  take this step in full knowledge that the man whom you were injuring knew his
                  duties towards God &amp; man too well to violate upon any provocation the laws of
                  both, or did you suppose that I should demand what the world is pleased to call
                  satisfaction? Perhaps Sir you would have waived your privilege, <del>&amp;</del>
                  aimed at the life of him whose reputation you had attempted to stain, &amp;
                  exposed your own in a quarrel wherein you know yourself to be the aggressor. I
                  shall not put you to the trial. Your estates &amp; your distillery<note n="48" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith and his family had been involved in various
                     distilleries in London since 1804.</note> would remain for your family, &amp;
                  the bells of Norwich would ring as merrily at your successors election as they had
                  done at yours. My place in the world could not be so easily supplied, were I
                  actuated by no higher considerations.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Or did you imagine that I should sit down quietly under the wrong,
                  &amp; treat your attack with the same silent contempt as I have done all the abuse
                  &amp; <del>slander</del> {calumny} with which, from one party or the other, Anti
                  Jacobins or Jacobins, I have been assailed in daily, weekly, monthly &amp;
                  quarterly publications since the year 1796 when I first became known to the
                     public.<note n="49" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. with the publication of
                     the first edition of the radical epic <title>Joan of Arc</title>.</note> The
                  place where you made the attack, &amp; the manner of the attack, prevent this. You
                  wished to take the Bull by the horns, &amp; you have had your wish. Such a feat
                  may be very well for a Spanish picador or an English piccassin when the Bull is to
                  be butchered or baited for the amusement of a herd of bipeds &#8211; but for a plain
                  Country gentleman to provoke an animal who is unoffendingly feeding in his own
                  pasture, is neither a very wise nor a very safe bravado. It would be prudent first
                  to enquire whether his horns were lopt.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> One thing Sir you have effected. You have secured for yourself a
                  lasting remembrance. The Records of Parliament are not the only books in which
                  your name will be found hereafter. How far the writings of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Southey may be found to deserve a favourable acceptance from after ages, time will
                  decide; but a name, which whether worthily or not, has been conspicuous in the
                  literary history of its age, will <del>not</del> certainly not perish. Some
                  account of his life will always be prefixed to his works &amp; transferred to
                  literary histories, &amp; to the biographical dictionaries, <del>xx xxx</del> not
                  only of this, but of other countries. There it will be related, that he lived in
                  the &#8220;bosom of his family&#8221;, in absolute retirement; that in all his writings there
                  breathed the same abhorrence of oppression &amp; immorality, the same spirit of
                  devotion, &amp; the same ardent wishes for the amelioration of mankind; &amp; that
                  the only charge which malice could bring against him was that as he grew older his
                  opinions altered concerning the means by which that amelioration was to be
                  effected; &amp; that as he learnt to understand the institutions {of his country,}
                  he learnt to appreciate them rightly, to love, &amp; to revere &amp; to defend
                  them. It will be said of him that in an age of personality, he abstained from
                  satire; &amp; that during the long course of his literary life, often as he was
                  assailed, the only occasion on which he ever condescended to reply was when a
                  certain M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Smith insulted him in Parliament with the
                  appellation of renegade. On that occasion he came forward, vindicated himself
                  &amp; treating his <del>unprovoked assailant</del> {calumniator} with just &amp;
                  memorable severity. Whether it shall be added that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith redeemed his own character, by coming forward with
                  manly courage &amp; acknowledging that he had spoken rashly &amp; unjustly,
                     <del>xxxxxx xx xx xxxx</del> {concerns himself, but is not of the slightest
                  importance to me.} <del>x xxxx xxxxxxxx x myself</del> {&amp; may take my
                  satisfaction} &amp; leave the matter safely to posterity.</p>
          <signed rend="indent1"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>