<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2761</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4032</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2761. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 18-[19] April
                  1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2761" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2761.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                  Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 161&#8211;165 [dated 18 April 1816].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2761" type="letter">
        <head>2761. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-04-19">18-[19] April
                  1816</date>
          </head><p>Address: G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
                  Postmark: E/ 22 AP 22/ 1816<lb /> Endorsement: 18 &amp; 19 April 1816/ Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
            <lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng.
                  Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 161&#8211;165 [dated 18 April 1816].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Wherefore do I write to you? &#8211; Alas because I know not what to
                  do.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s son, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, had died on 17 April
                  1816.</note> Tomorrow perhaps may bring with it something like the beginning of
               relief. Today &#8211; I hope I shall support {myself} &#8211; or rather that God will support me,
               for I am weak as a child, &#8211; in body even more than in mind. My limbs tremble under
               me, &#8211; <del>xxxx</del> long anxiety has wasted me to the bone &amp; I fear it will be
               long before grief will suffer me to recruit. I am seriously apprehensive for the
               shock which my health seems to have sustained. Yet I am wanting in no effort to
               appear calm &amp; to console others &amp; those who are about me give me credit for a
               fortitude which I do not possess. Many blessings are left me &#8211; abundant blessings, &#8211;
               more than I have deserved, more than I had ever reason to expect, or even to hope. I
               have strong ties to life, &amp; many duties yet to perform. Believe me I see these
               things as they ought to be seen. Reason will do something, Time more, Religion most
               of all. The loss is but for this world; &#8211; but <del>should I</del> as long as I remain
               in this world I shall feel it</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Some way, my feelings will out themselves. &#8211; I have thought of
               endeavouring to direct their course, &amp; may perhaps set about a monument in verse
               for him &amp; for myself which may make our memories inseparable.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey began, but did not finish, such a poem,
                  entitled &#8216;Consolation&#8217;. Sections were published after his death as &#8216;Fragmentary
                  Thoughts Occasioned by his Son&#8217;s Death&#8217; in <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England
                     Tale (Unfinished): With Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp.
                  93&#8211;95, and &#8216;Additional Fragment, Occasioned by the Death of his Son&#8217;,
                     <title>Poetical Works of Robert Southey. Complete in One Volume</title>
                  (London, 1850), p. 815.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There would be no wisdom in going from home, &#8211; the act of returning
               to it would undo all the benefit I might receive from change of circumstance for some
               time yet. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> feels
               this, &#8211; otherwise perhaps we might have gone to visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> in his new habitation,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey had rented a farm at Warcop in Westmorland.</note>
               &#8211; Summer is at hand &#8211; while there was a hope of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herberts</ref> recovery this was a
               frequent subject of pleasurable consideration &#8211; it is now a painful thought, &amp; I
               look forward with a sense of fear to the season which brings with it life &amp; joy
               to those who are capable of receiving them. You more than most men are aware of the
               extent of my loss &amp; how as long as I remain here every object within &amp;
               without, &amp; every hour of every day must bring it fresh to recollection. Yet the
               more I consider the difficulties of removing, the greater they appear, &amp; perhaps
               by the time it would be possible I may cease to desire it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> will give
               you <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondsons</ref> account of the dissection. Do with the
               paper what you please. I would not have it returned, &#8211; you may destroy it, or lay it
               among the papers belonging to our correspondence. &#8211; Whenever I have leisure (will
               that ever be?) I will begin my own memoirs, to serve as a post-obit for those of my
               family who may survive me.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not
                  write his memoirs. The closest he came was in the seventeen autobiographical
                  letters he wrote to John May in 1820&#8211;1825, published in Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 1&#8211;157 [in part].</note> They will be so far provided for as to
               leave me no uneasiness on that score. My life insurance is &#163;4000. My books, for there
               is none to inherit them now, may be worth 1500, &#8211; my copy rights perhaps not less,
               &amp; you will be able to put together letters &amp; fragments which when I am gone
               will be acceptable articles in the market. Probably there would on the whole be
               10,000 &#163; forthcoming, &#8211; the whole should be <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> during her life &amp;
               afterward divided equally among the surviving children. I shall name <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref> for executors both men of
               business, &amp; both my dear &amp; zealous friends. But do you take care of my papers
               &amp; publish my remains. I have perhaps much underrated the value of what
                  <del>may</del> {will} be left. A selection of my reviewals may be <del>made</del>
               reprinted with credit to my name &amp; <del>of</del> with profit.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey himself later edited such a collection,
                     <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title> (1832).</note> &#8211; You will not wonder
               that I have fallen into this strain. One grave is at this moment made ready, &#8211; &amp;
               who can tell how soon another may be required? I pray however for continued life.
               There may be, &#8211; probably there are &#8211; many afflictions for me in store, &#8211; but the
               worst is past. I have more than once thought of <ref type="m" target="people.html#RobertsEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Roberts</ref>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  father of Bedford&#8217;s cousin Barr&#233; Charles Roberts, who had died in 1810 aged 21.
                  Bedford had published Roberts&#8217;s <title>Letters and Miscellaneous Papers &#8230; With a
                     Memoir of His Life</title> (1814) and Southey had then composed a poetical
                  tribute, &#8216;Written in the Volume of Letters &amp; Miscellaneous papers by Barr&#232;
                  Charles Roberts&#8217;. The latter was unpublished until it appeared as &#8216;Written in an
                  unpublished Volume of Letters, and Miscellaneous Papers, by Barr&#233; Charles
                  Roberts&#8217;, <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), III, pp.
                  157&#8211;159, where it is mis-dated &#8216;Keswick, 1814&#8217;.</note> &#8211; when he hears of my loss
               it will for a moment freshen the recollections of his own.</p>
        <p rend="center">____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is now clear that there were two distinct diseases, &#8211; the
               collection of matter in the pericardium which proved fatal, &amp; a suppression in
               the biliary passages during the progress of the other disease, which was removed, but
               left a severe fever behind it, &amp; it was when that fever disappeared that I wrote
               to you saying there were marks of amendment. &#8211; You will learn from the deranged or
               deformed structure of the colon that he never could have been a healthy man</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is some relief to write to you, &#8211; after the calls which have this
               day been made upon my fortitude. I have not been found wanting, &#8211; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> throughout the whole long
               trial has displayed the most exemplary self-controul. We never approached him but
               with composed countenances, &amp; words of hope, &#8211; &amp; for a mother to do this hour
               after hour &amp; night after night while her heart was breaking &#8211; is perhaps the
               utmost effort of which our nature is capable. Oh how you would have admired &amp;
               loved him had you seen him in these last weeks! But you know something of his
               character. Never perhaps was a child of ten years old <del>xxxx</del> so much to his
               father. Without ever ceasing to treat him as a child I had made him my companion as
               well as playmate &amp; pupil, &#8211; &amp; he had learn to interest himself in my
               pursuits, &amp; take part in all my enjoyments.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have sent <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>.
               poor child she is dreadfully distressed, &amp; it has ever been my desire to save
               them from all the sorrow that can be avoided, &amp; to mitigate as far as possible
               what is inevitable. Something it is to secure for them a happy child hood. Never was
               a happier than <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herberts</ref>. He knew not what unkindness or evil were except by name.
               His whole life was past in chearful duty, &amp; love &amp; enjoyment. If I did not
               hope that I have been useful in my generation, &amp; may still continue to be so I
               could wish that I also had gone to rest as early in the day. But my childhood was not
               like his</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let me have some money when you can, that these mournful expenses may
               be discharged. For five weeks my hand has been palsied, &#8211; &amp; this brings with it a
               loss of means, an evil inseparable from my way of life. Tomorrow I shall endeavour to
               resume my employments. You may be sure also that I shall attend to my health, <del>as
                  xxxx</del> nothing which exercise &amp; diet can afford will be neglected, &#8211; &amp;
               whenever I feel that change of air &amp; of scene could benefit me, the change shall
               be tried. I am perfectly aware <del>of the</del> {how} important <del>the</del> an
               object this, &#8211; the fear is lest my sense of its moment should produce an injurious
               anxiety.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">You would save me some pain by correcting the remaining proofs, &#8211; for the
               sight of that book must needs be trying to me.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The proofs of <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo </title>(1816), which
                  was painful to Southey because the &#8216;Proem&#8217; contained an account of his joyful
                  homecoming in December 1815 from his journey to the Low Countries. </note> Alter
               the two last lines thus </p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent3">Hold fast the faith which animates thy mind</l>
            <l rend="indent3"> And in thy song proclaim these hopes for humankind.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
                <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to
                           Waterloo</title> (1816), Part Two, Book 4, &#8216;The Hopes of Man&#8217;, stanza 63,
                        lines 5&#8211;6. &#8216;[V]ision&#8217; replaced &#8216;prospect&#8217; in the line &#8216;The vision of thy
                        Country&#8217;s bliss is given&#8217;, stanza 63, line 2. In stanza 62, line 5 &#8216;As to
                        the best prospects&#8217; replaced &#8216;Even as the best hopes&#8217;. </note>
            </l>
          </lg>
          <p>Line 2 of this stanza &#8211; read <hi rend="ital">vision</hi> for
                  prospect, &amp; in the preceding stanza read &#8211; As the best <hi rend="ital">prospects of mankind</hi> are dear<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8217;You would &#8230; dear&#8217;: inserted at the top of fol.1r.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>