<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3121</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4392</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3121. Robert Southey to [James
                  Stanger], 13 April 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3121.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles. ALS;
                  2p. (c). .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3121" type="letter">
        <head>3121. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#StangerJames">James
                  Stanger</ref>],<date when="1818-04-13"> 13 April 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Mr Southey/ 13 Apl
                  1818<lb /> MS: Young Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles. ALS;
                  2p. (c).<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> May I request you to give me, or procure <del>from</del> from any of
               your friends a letter of introduction to the Bishop of Calcutta<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Fanshaw Middleton (1769&#8211;1822;
                     <title>DNB</title>), first Anglican Bishop of Calcutta 1814&#8211;1822.</note> for
                  M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Homfray,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeremiah Homfray (1790&#8211;1850) was the eldest son of Sir Jeremiah Homfray
                  (1759&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), a Welsh ironmaster and speculator in mineral
                  rights, living in Boulogne since being declared bankrupt in 1813. The younger
                  Jeremiah did go out to Calcutta, where he became a leading figure in the
                  development of the Indian coal industry.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barkers</ref> cousin, &#8211; the eldest son
               of Sir Jere. H. a man for whom nature &amp; education have done every thing, &#8211; but
               who having been bred at Eton &amp; at Oxford with the prospect of an ample
               inheritance, by one of those mutations to which commerce is obnoxious, has his
               fortune to seek at the age of six or seven &amp; twenty. &#8211; Every thing may be said of
               him as a man of good sense, good principles, &amp; right English spirit. Indeed I
               have seldom seen a young man who left upon me so favourable an impression.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">He goes out with mercantile views, &amp; will need great interest to be allowed to
               remain there, while a requisition from a Merchant there for allowing him to settle is
               sent home. I suppose the place is found by his Uncle M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Wilson,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Wilson (1760&#8211;1829), whose
                  company traded from 6 Warnford Court, in the City of London. His first wife was
                  Catherine Homfray (1764&#8211;1801).</note> an adventurous merchant, who looks for great
               advantages from the opening of the trade. What however I request is a letter
               recommending him to such notice &amp; good offices as he may be thought to deserve
               when he is known.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I mention the Bishop, because I believe you know him personally,
               &amp; tho I do not, he may be disposed to shew more attention to Homfray from knowing
               that I feel much interested in his welfare. But if you can favour me with any other
               letters, so much the better. The only persons whom I know in India are in the other
               presidencies &#8211; Sir J. Malcolm<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  diplomatist, administrator, soldier and author Sir John Malcolm (1769&#8211;1833;
                     <title>DNB</title>), whose works included <title>The History of Persia, from
                     the most Early Period to the Present Time: containing an Account of the
                     Religion, Government, Usages, and Character of the Inhabitants of that
                     Kingdom</title> (1815), reviewed by Southey&#8217;s friend, Reginald Heber, in the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 236&#8211;292. Malcolm had served
                  in India since joining the East India Company&#8217;s army as an ensign in 1783. At this
                  time he was at the height of his fame, having defeated the Mahratta Confederacy in
                  December 1817 and he was, in effect, the ruler of much of central India 1817&#8211;1820.
                  He was later Governor of Bombay 1827&#8211;1830.</note> to whom I could have written
               without scruple, &#8211; &amp; my old friend &amp; schoolfellow <ref type="m" target="people.html#StracheyGeorge">George Strachey</ref>, who is now I believe
               Chief Secretary at Madras, &amp; whose superior in all <del>good</del> {the best}
               qualities of heart &amp; understanding it would have been difficult to find when he
                  <del>xxx</del> went out to India about twenty years ago.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not been idle during these dark months. And when my paper upon
               the means of meliorating the lower classes appears, you will see that among other
               means of sure, easy &amp; practicable reform I have not forgotten the first thing
                  needful.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A paraphrase of
                     <title>Luke</title> 10: 42. Rickman and Southey&#8217;s &#8216;On the Means of Improving
                  the People&#8217; appeared in<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818),
                  79&#8211;118.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All below stairs desire their kindest remembrances.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> most truly, respectfully &amp; affectionately your</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-04-13">13 April 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>