<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2807</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4078</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2807. Robert Southey to William
                  Peachy, 6 June 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2807.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2807" type="letter">
        <head>2807. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William
                  Peachy</ref>, <date when="1816-06-06">6 June 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/
                  Southampton<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 10 JU 10/ 1816<lb /> Seal:
                  black wax; design illegible<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-06-06">6 June. 1816.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The expectation that you would have left England before a letter
               could find you has alone prevented me from writing to you for some weeks past. At the
               time when your former favour reached me, I was in too much distress to answer it.
               Upon that subject suffice it to say that great &amp; irreparable as our loss is,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s son <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> had died on 17 April
                  1816.</note> He who gives the burthen of affliction gives the strength to bear it,
               &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> has borne it
               with exemplary fortitude throughout, &#8211; we have both looked for consolation where,
               &amp; where only, it is to be found, &#8211; in resignation to the will of God, &amp; in
               the assurance that these trying separations are only for a time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not impossible that I may meet you on the continent.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s continental journey was delayed until
                  May&#8211;August 1817.</note> I think of running over about autumn, seeing the course of
               the Rhine &amp; going thro those parts of Belgium which were left untouched in my
               last journey. The change will perhaps recruit me, &amp; I stand somewhat in need of
               such excitement. I should rejoice much to fall in with you in my excursions. The
                  Vardons<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMr">Thomas</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">Elizabeth Vardon</ref>.</note> with whom we
               joined company last year have taken a house at Louvain &#8211; should you pass thro that
               city on your way from the Rhine, &#8211; perhaps you may find me with them, &#8211; or certainly
               learn whether I am in that part of the world.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Ponsonbys<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant
                  John Ponsonby (dates unknown) of the Royal Navy and his wife (name and dates
                  unknown). </note> have removed to Castle-Hill,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Castle Hill is a few miles to the north of Keswick, by
                  Bassenthwaite Lake.</note> &#8211; thus lessening our little neighbourhood. I expect
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> to visit me in a few
               days, the fellow traveller to who I am indebted for the views of the scene of action
               in my Pilgrimage.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Seven sketches made by
                  Nash at the Waterloo battlefield were engraved and used as illustrations in
                  Southey&#8217;s <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> That
               poem will be followed too closely (if it could have been helped) by another, which
               under the title of Carmen Nuptiale, or the Lay of the Laureate, will be published, as
               soon as it has been presented to the Princess, &#8211; such being the etiquette.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen
                     Nuptiale</title> (1816). It celebrated the marriage of Princess Charlotte, only
                  child of the Prince Regent, to Prince Leopold of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld (1790&#8211;1865;
                  King of the Belgians 1831&#8211;1865) on 2 May 1816.</note> It is now I believe in the
               bookbinders hands, &amp; when it has been equipped in a full dress suit, my friend
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> (the
               Commissary General) will present it. The metre is the same six-lined stanza as that
               of the Pilgrimage, &amp; the matter very unlike the usual strain of verse upon such
               occasions. The booksellers will not advertise it till it is actually published, &#8211;
               first as a point of etiquette, &amp; for the not less material reason that it may
               interfere with the sale of my &#8220;last poem&#8221; as little as possible, &#8211; for in these days
               it is the &#8220;last poem&#8221; that is asked for, like the last new fashion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref> is printing an
               account of his six years residence in Brazil, &amp; his travels in that country.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Koster&#8217;s <title>Travels in Brazil</title>
                  (1816); reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817),
                  344&#8211;387.</note> The book has no pretentions to what is called fine writing, &amp;
               is the better for it, being, like the better class of our old traveller, the plain
               &amp; faithful narrative of an attentive &amp; accurate observer. The state of
               society which he describes, is exceedingly curious, &amp; such as will always make
               his book valuable. His sister Charlotte (the deaf sister)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte Koster (b. 1783). In his <title>Travels in
                     Brazil</title> (London, 1816), pp. v&#8211;vi, Henry Koster stated &#8216;The drawings for
                  the plates were executed by a near relative, from very rough sketches of my own,
                  assisted by description&#8217;. There were ten plates in all in the book, including two
                  maps. Southey may be referring here to &#8216;A Lady going to a visit&#8217; (p. 188) and &#8216;A
                  Planter and his Wife on a Journey&#8217; (p. 384) in particular.</note> has made some
               excellent drawings of Brazilian costume, <del>xxxx</del> from dresses &amp;c which he
               brought home, &amp; from his descriptions, aided by her own knowledge of Portugueze
               fashions. The whole family, except <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterJohnTheodore">the father</ref>, are
               lodging at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dares at present.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Theodore Koster, his wife, and seven daughters: Harriet
                  (b. 1780); Charlotte (b. 1783); Juliana Elizabeth (1788&#8211;1790); Maria Susanna (d.
                  1790); Lucretia (1795&#8211;1822); Emma (1797&#8211;1817) and Elizabeth (1799&#8211;1875). They had
                  rented Chestnut Hill Cottage (where Shelley had stayed in 1811&#8211;1812), owned by the
                  farmer Gideon Dare (1768&#8211;1849). </note> The house stopt payment early in the year,
               owing to the failure of a house in London. So compleatly however is Kosters character
               unimpeached, that a deputation of Liverpool Merchants now in London to make some
               representations to Government respecting the Brazil trade, have added him to their
               number, &#8211; the best proof of the respect in which he is held, notwithstanding his
               contradictious manner, &amp; his political opinions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope you will meet with no unpleasant delays in France, &#8211; but the
               sooner you are out of that country the better. Its finest provinces are in a very
               disturbed state. I very much doubt whether the habits &amp; temper of the people will
               bear so free a government as has been given them. Nothing seems so difficult as to
               give a free government to a people who have not been educated for freedom, &amp; yet
               God knows the affairs of the world must ever go on miserably when each thing depends
               upon the will &amp; caprice of a Sovereign or a favourite. &#8211; I look to hear of some
               cabinet revolution at Madrid, which shall consign Ferdinand to a convent as an
               incurable madman, &amp; seat his brother upon the throne in his stead.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808,
                  1813&#8211;1833). He had suppressed the liberal constitution and imprisoned its
                  supporters in 1814. His nearest male heir was his brother, Charles, Count of
                  Molina (1788&#8211;1855), who was even more of a reactionary than Ferdinand.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A curious fact in political science is beginning to develop itself.
               We used to hear of America as <del>an instance</del> proving that countries could go
               on well without an established church. A society has now been formed in Connecticut
               to devise means (in default of one!) for providing religious instruction for the
               people; they declare that an immediate, universal, vigorous effort must be made
                  <del>to provide xxxxxxxx xx</del> for this purpose, <del>xx</del> &amp; that such
               an effort is indispensable to prevent the great body of the nation from sinking down
               to a state of absolute heathenism.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is referring to Lyman Beecher (1775&#8211;1863), <title>An Address of the
                     Charitable Society for the Education of Indigent Pious Young Men for the
                     Ministry of the Gospel</title> (New Haven, Connecticut, 1814). This address was
                  widely reported in Britain, e.g. the <title>Literary Panorama and National
                     Register</title>, 7 (June 1816), 468&#8211;471. Southey had subscribed to this
                  publication since 1809 &#8211; it was no. 1734 in the sale catalogue of his library.
                  Southey later used this information in his article on &#8216;New Churches&#8217;,
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549&#8211;591 (at 550&#8211;551).</note>
               It is calculated that of the eight million inhabitants of the United States, five
               million are destitute of competent religious instruction for want of ministers! &#8211; We
               may be sure that the want will not be supplied by the present race of rulers in
               America, &#8211; &amp; in a <del>fe</del> very few generations the consequences will be
               seen! &#8211; This is very curious &amp; offers much matter for serious thought.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now my dear Sir remember us most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>, let
               me hear of your movements from time to time, &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">very sincerely yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">I am very glad to hear of L<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Guerins medal<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentfied.</note> &#8211; it was but
                  yesterday that I was talking of his sailing on dry ground.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>