<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3002</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4273</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3002. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 15 June 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3002" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3002.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3002" type="letter">
        <head>3002. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1817-06-15">15 June 1817</date>
          </head><p>Address: Inghilterra/ To/ G. C.
                  Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9 Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb />
                  Postmarks: FPO/ JY 1/ 1817; 12 o&#8217;Clock/ JY 1/ 1817 N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />
                  Endorsement: 15 June 1817. Milan.<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 3p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1817-06-15">15. June. 1817.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName> Milan</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Even a few lines will be welcome from a far land. We arrived here
               yesterday, &amp; depart tomorrow, turning our faces homeward. We go to Como, where I
               expect to find <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, &#8211; a greater pleasure could hardly be in expectation. About
               this day week we hope to have recrost the Alps, &amp; to be on the way to or from
               Chamouny, starting for that place from Martigny. Then we make again for the Chateau
               de Echichens, where M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Awdry (<ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> brother in
                  law)<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry (1766&#8211;1844), solicitor
                  in Reybridge and husband of Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert
                  Hill&#8217;s wife, Catherine.</note> is residing, &amp; where I feel among relations
               &amp; friends. Owing to the unusual lateness of the season we were too early for
               Switzerland, &amp; they who advised me to cross by S Gothard<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The St Gotthard Pass connects the northern, German-speaking
                  area of Switzerland with the southern, Italian-speaking part, and opens the route
                  to Italy.</note> forgot to add it would be necessary to take a carriage to pieces.
               This has sent us by a very circuitous route, at much cost of time, but gain of
               scenery, for having entered Switzerland from Besan&#231;on we went by Lausanne &amp;
               Geneva to Chamberry, gave two days to the Chartreuse,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Head monastery of the Carthusian order, founded 1084; located
                  high in an Alpine valley north of Grenoble.</note> &amp; crost by M Cenis<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A mountain pass between France and
                  Italy.</note> to Turin. &#8211; I send a box from hence to Prince Esterhazy,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Prince P&#225;l Antal Esterh&#225;zy de Gal&#225;ntha
                  (1786&#8211;1866), Austrian nobleman and Ambassador to Britain 1815&#8211;1842. </note> &amp;
               tho every possible care will be taken to advise M. R<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathan Mayer Rothschild (1777&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), London
                  banker and founder of N. M. Rothschild &amp; Sons in 1811.</note> what is his name
               of it, it may be as well that you should mention it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Every thing has gone well with us. I have kept up with my journal &#8211;
               by great exertion, &amp; when I return shall be glad, &amp; with good reason, that I
               had resolution to make the journey &#8211; my sprits are the best in the world for my
                  companions,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Humphrey Senhouse and
                  Edward Nash.</note> &#8211; for myself, they were better at home, &amp; will be better
               when I am at home again: then I shall probably feel benefit from the journey.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I sent a small parcel of books from Paris addressed to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &#8211; it was not large enough to
               justify me in troubling <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> friend. From Frankfort <hi rend="ital">perhaps</hi>, certainly from
               Brussels, I shall dispatch a larger cargo. I wrote home from Calais, Paris,
               Neufchatel &amp; Turin. I wish you would write to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &amp; say so, adding that you have heard from Milan, &amp; that we
               were all well. It is Sunday evening, <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> are gone to the
                  Opera,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">La Scala opera house in
                  Milan.</note> &#8211; there is what in England would be called a Sixpenny hop going on
               under my feet, &#8211; &amp; I remain, <del>xxxxx</del> to bring up my journal, &amp;
               scrawl this, hasty letter to you, to the fiddle &amp; the clamour below.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will wish to ask a hundred questions, &#8211; &amp; you will see how
               impossible it is that I should answer them. I can only tell you that <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> fairly stands a comparison with the
               Alps which I have seen, &amp; that he will outlast those which we have crost. I fear
               it must be five weeks before we reach England, let me find a letter at the Dover post
               office with 20 &#163;. I shall draw on <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> either from
               Frankfort (if <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>
               letter should obtain me credit there) or at Brussels, where I am known &amp; have it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The weather has been tremendously hot since we left Switzerland.
               Summer began on the 1 June, &#8211; &amp; my summer cold with it &#8211; except as far the nose
               is concerned I am in good health, but as for the tincture of the skin both <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> &amp; myself might
               pass for Moors. &#8211; Mackenzie was more than civil to me at Paris,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Colin Alexander Mackenzie (?1778&#8211;1851), a wealthy
                  Scot who was employed on a number of delicate diplomatic missions and may well
                  have been a government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of the Commissioners of
                  Liquidation, Arbitration and Deposit, who adjudicated on claims by British
                  citizens for loss of property against the French government. Southey dined with
                  him on 17 May 1817.</note> &#8211; he was in a high degree attentive &amp; obliging.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Mag:
                  Rot.</ref>, that at Geneva I ate seven rolls for breakfast. In that
               proportion the Wolf has eaten &amp; drank ever since he landed on the continent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Oh that I could hear all was well at home &amp; in <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref>. I have thought sometimes too
               of your Carb Uncle &#8211; Your health in a glass of lemonade, &#8211; with which I have splashed
               the letter.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>