<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2957</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4228</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2957. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 26 March 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2957" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2957.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from
                     the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
                  67&#8211;69.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2957" type="letter">
        <head>2957. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1817-03-26">26 March 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Vale Royal/ Northwich <lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Endorsement: 26 March/ 1817<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from
                     the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
                  67&#8211;69.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I do not by any means regret the application to Chancery,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s application to the Court of Chancery for
                  an injunction to prevent the publication of <title>Wat Tyler</title> was refused
                  on 18&#8211;19 March 1817.</note> &#8211; it was the strait-forward course, &#8211; &amp; the
               question could not have been referred to a Court of Law (being so plain a case) if a
               false defence<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Winterbotham had claimed that
                  Southey had given <title>Wat Tyler</title> to him and Daniel Isaac Eaton
                  (1753&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>) to publish and had surrendered any copyright in
                  the work.</note> had not been set up &amp; supported by perjury. &#8211; There is a
               strong impression upon my mind that <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref> is dead; &amp; it is much less <del>xxx</del> improbable to me
               that a fellow should have been found to <del>xxxx</del> swear falsely in his name,
               than that he, &#8211; a Dissenting Minister &#8211; &amp; a man who was said to have undergone
               the same change in his opinions as I have done, should in the first place be guilty
               of so base an act as to publish the book &amp; then to defend the act by a direct
               perjury. My Magazines in which it appears to me that I have read of his death are
               unluckily forty miles off at the binders. But I have taken measures for ascertaining
               this matter; &#8211; &amp; if it should prove that <del>I</del> my suspicions are well
               founded the transaction will assume a very different aspect from what it now wears. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Luckily I have the rough draft of my first Letter, &#8211; &amp; shall
               therefore throw them both into one,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had written two letters which he originally hoped to publish in the
                     <title>Courier</title>: the &#8216;first letter&#8217; was Southey to William Smith, 17
                  March 1817 (Letter 2943). This was followed by a second, Southey to the Editor of
                  the <title>Courier</title> [19 March 1817] (Letter 2946). These two letters were
                  sent to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, on 17 and 19 March 1817 (Letters 2944 and
                  2948), for him to forward to the newspaper. In the event, Wynn&#8217;s absence from home
                  led to a delay in his receiving the letters. By the time he did so, the public
                  debate had moved on and Southey therefore decided not to publish them in the
                     <title>Courier</title>, but instead to incorporate them into his pamphlet
                     <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (1817).</note> &#8211; but this
               I will delay till I have satisfied myself about <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A word or two about my intolerance. I <del>xx</del> recollect but two
               persons of whom I have spoken with acrimony in the true sense of the word. Whitbread
               in the Register, &#8211; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LancasterJoseph">Joseph
                  Lancaster</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey regularly
                  denounced the radical MP, Samuel Whitbread (1764&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), for
                  his opposition to the war in Spain, e.g. <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                     1809</title>, 2.1 (1811), 303 and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                     1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 295&#8211;296. His criticisms of Joseph Lancaster&#8217;s
                  educational schemes were collected in <title>The Origin, Nature, and Object of the
                     New System of Education</title> (1812).</note> In the first case I was treating
               of a leading politician whose opinions would have laid this country at
                  Buonapartes<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte
                  (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note> mercy, &#8211; in the second
               I was exposing one whom I <hi rend="ital">knew</hi> to be a quack, a rogue, &amp; a
               liar. As for my allusions to the Ed. Review<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had publicly criticised the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> on a
                  number of occasions, e.g. in <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814). He returned
                  to the attack in <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (London,
                  1817), refuting the <title>Edinburgh</title>&#8217;s accusation that he was guilty of
                  &#8216;vindictive and jealous writings&#8217; (p. 9) and claiming that he &#8216;accepted the hatred
                  of sciolists, coxcombs, and profligates, as one sure proof that I was deserving
                  well of the wise and of the good&#8217; (p. 11).</note> it would surprize me much if I
               were censured for speaking as I think upon that subject, abstaining as I have
               uniformly done from any thing in the way of personal defence during fifteen years of
               continual attack on their part. In the article which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith</ref> pulld out of
               his pocket<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith had denounced Southey in
                  the House of Commons on 14 March 1817 in the debate on the Seditious Meetings
                  Bill, condemning &#8216;the settled, determined malignity of a renegado&#8217; and comparing
                  Southey&#8217;s arguments against radical views in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                  16 (October 1816), 227, with those expressed in <title>Wat Tyler</title> (1817),
                  Act 2, lines 103&#8211;112.</note> I have called <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref> an incendiary for one
               of the wickedest paragraphs <del>xxx</del> that ever was written; &#8211; &amp; I have
               bestowed the same appellation upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref>:<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 273 Southey drew attention to a paragraph in
                  Leigh Hunt&#8217;s<title> Examiner</title>, 9 (8 December 1816), 769. The latter dealt
                  with the injuries of a man attacked during the Spa Fields insurrection of 2
                  December 1816. Although the <title>Examiner</title> condemned the assault, it
                  called &#8216;the corruptionists, who in luxury and cold blood can
                     <title>provoke</title> such excesses, <title>greater scoundrels</title>&#8217;.
                  Southey&#8217;s <title>Quarterly</title> essay (275) also attacked William Cobbett for
                  stating that the revolutionaries at Spa Fields were unconnected to the organisers
                  of the meeting, <title>Political Register</title>, 31 (7 December 1816),
                  733.</note> &#8211; <del>xx</del> can any man in his senses think them misapplied? And
               for the passage which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smith</ref> read (p. 227) <del>xx it xxxxxx xx</del> it neither names
               any individual nor alludes to any, <del>x</del> but deals in generals, relating to
               those metaphysicians who begin by denying the difference between right &amp; wrong.
               Of such men as myself there is plain mention (p 237)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 236&#8211;7,
                  dealt with those (among whom Southey included himself) who had opposed the war
                  against Revolutionary France in 1793&#8211;1802 through a &#8216;deep, though mistaken
                  principle&#8217;, but supported war against Napoleonic France in 1803&#8211;15 because they
                  &#8216;loved liberty&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; so far have I been from having ever sought to put
               my former opinions in the shade, &#8211; that they are placed in broad day light in the
               Pilgrimage to Waterloo;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The
                     Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816), e.g. Part Two, Book 2, &#8216;The Evil
                  Prophet&#8217;, stanza 6.</note> &#8211; nor have I ever cancelled a line in my early poems on
               this account; &#8211; They who blame me for intolerance should remember <del>xxx</del> the
               abuse which has been incessantly poured upon me</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref>
               wrote me a very handsome letter upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Smiths</ref> conduct, saying that he felt as if he had
               to clear his own character from a stain till he assured me that he was not in the
               house at the time<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey wrote to
                  Wilberforce thanking him on 23 March 1817 (Letter 2953).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It will be unfortunate if I should miss you on my transit. I shall be
               in London (God willing) on the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> pass a week with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> in
               Hampshire &amp; leave London for the continent if possible on the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> of May.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1817-03-26">26 March. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>