<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2841</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4112</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2841. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 11 September 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2841" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2841.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2841" type="letter">
        <head>2841. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1816-09-11">11 September 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Llangedwin/ near/
                  Oswestry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent2"> There are but few points upon which you &amp; I should disagree when we understood each other.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The following passages respond to Wynn&#8217;s comments on Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;On the Poor&#8217;, published in the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187&#8211;235.</note> Upon that of the farms we are perfectly agreed, &#8211; my position
               being that the smallest which can be cultivated with adequate advantage to the cultivator is best. &#8211; Your plan respecting the churches
               is so simple &amp; so good that one wonders it should not have been hit upon before, &#8211; &amp; the very means proposed would include good
               in itself &#8211; for the service is at present too long. I have not seen the E Review &#8211; but from all I hear it seems <del>xxx</del> fit that
               I should regularly see it, for the advantage which it would give me. Some day I shall come <del>it</del> upon it with a heavy hand
               &amp; a whip of scorpions. Malthus&#8217;s proposal which this precious Review has reviewed, you will see treated, exactly as you regard it,
               in my former paper upon the Poor (N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 16.)<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356. It contained (320&#8211;327) a denunciation of Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population</title> (1798) and in particular Malthus&#8217;s proposal in the
                  second edition of 1803 to abolish poor relief for children born after a certain date. Malthus was a Whig and his work received a
                  number of supportive comments from Whig journals, e.g. <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 11 (October 1807), 100&#8211;116.</note>
          <del>x</del> &amp; I wish you would cast your eye <del>upon</del> {over} those pages of that paper which speak of the state of public
               opinion as influenced by the newspapers. for some years I have believed (&amp; most reluctantly believed <del>xx</del>) that we are
               hurrying on towards a Revolution, which according to all <del>xx</del> symptoms will not be less bloody nor less destructive than what
               has been witnessed in France.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article on the Poor Laws in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356, especially 341&#8211;343.</note> The three men in the world <del>of</del> {in} whose
               judgement I have the <del>highest</del> most confidence have, I know, the same ominous apprehension; &amp; each has formed it for
               himself, uninfluenced by, &amp; even unknown to, the others.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The three men were possibly <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">John Hookham Frere</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                     Rickman</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Daniel Stuart</ref>.</note> I am afraid that this danger will
               never be perceived on your side the house, &#8211; it seems in the nature of party<del>s</del> spirit to make men suppose that they can
               always direct the whirlwind, &amp; believe that the storm which wrecks their rivals will blow them into port. I wish you were in office
               for many reasons &amp; for this among others, &#8211; that if you were, I think you <del>xxx</del> would lend your aid manfully &amp;
               efficiently towards checking an evil, which if it be not checked will, I verily believe, involve us in utter ruin. Nine tenths of the
               provincial papers are now as mischievous as ever Paine<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Paine (1737&#8211;1809;
                     <title>DNB</title>), author of <title>The Rights of Man</title> (1792).</note> was, &#8211; &amp; you know better than I do what is the
               complexion of the London weekly magazines of sedition.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey may have had in mind weekly
                  newspapers with a national circulation, like the <title>Political Register</title> (1802&#8211;1835) and <title>Examiner</title>
                  (1808&#8211;1886).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From what you told me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberReginald">Reginald Hebers</ref> notions I imagine that
               he &amp; I should agree in the main in <del>your</del> {our} views respecting a sort of comprehension of the Methodists, -<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Plans for reintegrating Methodism within the Church of England.</note> toward which your plan for
                  <del>the xxx</del> service in the school houses would contribute greatly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since you were here I have been much in company, to the dissipation of more time than I can well afford to lose. We
               have had here the Secretaries of the Bible Society one of whom I knew formerly at Bristol<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  Secretaries of the British and Foreign Bible Society (founded 1804): John Owen (1766&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), Curate of Fulham
                  1795&#8211;1813; and Joseph Hughes (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Baptist Minister who held various posts at Bristol&#8217;s Broadmead Baptist
                  Church 1791&#8211;1796, where he met Southey.</note> &#8211; the King of Prussias Librarian,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel
                  Heinrich Spiker (1786&#8211;1858). An English translation of his account of his experiences in Britain was later published as
                     <title>Travels through England, Wales, &amp; Scotland, in the Year 1816</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820). His meeting with Southey
                  was described on I, pp. 269&#8211;272. Naturally, Spiker was most interested in Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Rogers</ref>, &#8211; Glover,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Glover (1767&#8211;1849;
                     <title>DNB</title>), the watercolour painter who owned Blowick Farm in Patterdale, on Ullswater.</note> young <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> who is lodging here, <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G
                  Beaumont</ref> (also resident) &#8211; Owen of Lanark<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen (1771&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>),
                  manager and owner of the mills and model community at New Lanark in Scotland 1799&#8211;1825.</note> &#8211; a son of the Duke of Brescia<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &#8211; My <hi rend="ital">Tea &#8211; Table d&#8217;hote</hi> as I call
               it is supplied with as curious a succession of guests at this season of the year as could be found perhaps any where in England. <del>x
                  xx</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard"> Heber</ref> talks of coming. &#8211; I have been twice on Causey Pike since our expedition
               there, &#8211; on one of these walks the two Ediths<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May Southey</ref>.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> were with me, &#8211; they carted it to the foot of the hill, &#8211; &amp; on our descent we
               dined beside the stream in the bottom. The other was with <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Rogers</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George
                  Beaumont</ref> &#8211; neither of whom had been there before: &#8211; Wordsworth agrees with me that there is no finer point in the whole land
               of mountains.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will send Oliver Newman in a few days.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished epic on
                  seventeenth-century New England, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;.</note> &#8211; A book of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref>
               lettering must [MS illegible] for an opportunity of conveyance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What think you of a club of Atheists meeting twice a week at an Alehouse in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, to enjoy the pleasure of denying God &amp; Devil, &#8211; &amp; the Landlady of their way of thinking? &#8211; Our Reverend
               Porpoise here is a Magistrate also;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Denton (c. 1758&#8211;1820), Vicar of Crosthwaite, Keswick
                  1786&#8211;1820; as a magistrate, he was responsible for licensing alehouses.</note> &#8211; but he nods in the reading desk, &amp; sleeps on
               the bench.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1816-09-11">11 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1816</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>