<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3003</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4274</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3003. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 30 June 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3003" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3003.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Morgan
                  Library, New York. Misc English, MA Unassigned. ALS; 4p.
               .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3003" type="letter">
        <head>3003. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>, <date when="1817-06-30">30 June 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: Angleterre/ To/ John
                  Rickman/ S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Stephens Court/ New Palace Yard/Westminster<lb />
                  Stamped: SS; [partial] EPAR/ ARLIE; [partial] P P/ MORSES<lb /> Postmark: FPO/
                  JY.10/ 1817<lb /> Endorsements: J Sontarbin; France Switzerland/ 1817<lb />
                  Watermark: A French horn/ bugle; M. &amp; I. A. HUBERT/ IN BASLE <lb /> MS: Morgan
                  Library, New York. Misc English, MA Unassigned. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1817-06-30">30 June. 1817.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName> Chateau d&#8217;Echichens.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I write from the Pays de Vaud, &#8211; where <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               Hills</ref> sister<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  was staying with John Awdry (1766&#8211;1844), solicitor in Reybridge and husband of
                  Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife,
                  Catherine.</note> is residing, about eight miles from Lausanne, &amp; two from the
               borders of the Lake of Geneva. We are resting here on our way back from Milan.
               Thursday we begin our course again, &amp; after a weeks deviation into the very heart
               of Switzerland by the Lakes of Thuin &amp; Lucerne, we hasten homeward by Strasbourg
               Manheim, Frankfurt &amp; the Rhine. Four weeks from this time will I trust bring me
               to London, &#8211; this is going three beyond my furlough, tho we have lost no time &amp;
               spared no exertion. A week must be set down to the unusual lateness of the season.
               When we arrived in Switzerland, parts of the country which we should have taken on
               the way to Italy were not practicable because of the snow; &#8211; it was necessary
               therefore to leave them till our return, &amp; this sent us round by Mount
                  Cenis,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A mountain pass between France
                  and Italy, the traversal of which had been eased by a road constructed between
                  1803 and 1810.</note> whereby at the expence of a week or ten days circuit we have
               seen the Chartreuse,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The head monastery of
                  the Carthusian Order, founded 1084, north of Grenoble.</note> Savoy &amp;
               Piedmont. Now then for a hasty sketch of our route.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From Calais by Amiens &amp; Chantilly to Paris &#8211; Picardy is
               interesting historical ground, &#8211; for even after Waterloo an Englishman may remember
                  Crecy<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey compares the British
                  victory over the French at Waterloo (18 June 1815), with the victory over France
                  at the battle of Cr&#233;cy (26 August 1346) in the Hundred Years War.</note> with
               pride. five days at Paris, where I saw Humboldt,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander von Humboldt (1769&#8211;1859), the traveller, scientist
                  and, in his voluminous writings, a leading authority on Latin America.</note> but
               was disappointed by not meeting Espoz y Mina,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Espoz y Mina (1781&#8211;1836), Spanish guerrilla
                  leader in the Peninsular War. He was in exile after leading an unsuccessful revolt
                  against the royalist regime in September 1814.</note> for which I had waited a
               day. Fontainebleau, Auxerre, Dijon, Besan&#231;on, &amp; over the Jura mountains to
               Neufchatel. At Besan&#231;on the fine scenery began. Yverdun where we went to see
                  Pestalozzi,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Heinrich Pestalozzi
                  (1746&#8211;1827), Swiss educational reformer.</note> &#8211; such a man that if I had him in
               a cage I could make a fortune by carrying him from fair to fair. I like him well as
               an oddity, &amp; a kind hearted, warm hearted strange fellow, &#8211; but as for his
               system, &#8211; it is one proof more how easily quackery of any kind makes its way in the
               world. Lausanne. Geneva, &#8211; a place which stinks worse than Lisbon or Edinburgh, &#8211; it
               is the very odour of heresy, &#8211; just as the cradle of Calvinism<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Calvin (1509&#8211;1564), the founder of Calvinism,
                  which insisted souls were predestined to salvation or damnation, was based in
                  Geneva from 1541 and the town&#8217;s established church, the Protestant Church of
                  Geneva, followed his ideas.</note> ought to stink. And it is built as if the very
               Demon of Calvinism had been the architect, &amp; the prevailing principle had been
               not merely a contempt, but a hatred of any thing ornamental or beautiful. Chamberry
               here as we were to cross the French frontier, the Grand Chartreuse being in France,
               we were obliged to procure billets of health, owing to the report of an infectious
               disease in Piedmont. When we went to the third office thro which it was necessary to
               pass, the officer exclaimed when is this abominable comedy to end! He told us that
               upon every billet he had certified that no infectious disorder had existed in
               Piedmont, &#8211; but that the Prefect of the Isere<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand de Bertier de Sauvigny (1782&#8211;1864), French &#233;migr&#233;, Army officer and
                  administrator. He was Prefect of Is&#232;re 17 October 1816&#8211;27 August 1817.</note> &#8211;
               had some end in view by keeping up the delusion. Mount Cenis. The Savoyards were
               complaining loudly some that the King of Sardinia<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Victor Emmanuel I (1759&#8211;1824; King of Sardinia
                  1802&#8211;1821).</note> would send them no grain, others that the Piedmontese would
               allow none to pass. But the roads were absolutely thronged with carriages conveying
               it, &#8211; the top of the Cenis was literally like a fair or a market. The scarcity has
               been very severe in Savoy, &amp; in great part of France, &#8211; still more so in some
               parts of Switzerland &amp; Italy: &#8211; but with this as with robbers &amp; pestilence,
                  <del>xxxx xxxx</del> {evil} is heard of at a distance &amp; sometimes not to be
               heard of on the spot which has been named as the scene. Where we have been we have
               certainly found that provisions were dear, &#8211; rather more so in relation to their
               average price than they have been in England: &#8211; grain is now coming by land from
               Marseilles to Switzerland. But in a very few weeks there is every appearance of
               plenty. The hay harvest is getting in, &amp; it is an abundant one. They must by this
               time be cutting the corn in Italy: &amp; here as well as there every thing is looking
               well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Turin. Milan. Como, &#8211; there I found <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, &amp; heard of the
                  Princess<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline of
                  Brunswick-Wolfenb&#252;ttel, Princess of Wales (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>),
                  estranged wife of the Prince Regent. She lived at the Villa d&#8217;Este on Lake Como
                  1815&#8211;1817.</note> who bids fair to rank in history with Messalina &amp; Joan of
                  Naples.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Two royal women who were
                  infamous for marital infidelity: Messalina (c. 17/20&#8211;48 AD), third wife of
                  Claudius (10 BC-AD 54; Emperor of Rome 41&#8211;54 AD); and Joan I (1328&#8211;1382; Queen of
                  Naples 1343&#8211;1382).</note> Her relations are infamous to the last degree of infamy,
               &#8211; the only respectable personage of the whole suite being &#8211; a Pelican, who has a
               carriage to himself &#8211; or herself &#8211; when the said Pelican travels. Of the three
               Gentlemen in attendance, the Prime Minister has been in six different <del>x</del>
               jails in Italy, &amp; you know it is not for a trifle that a man obtains admission
                  <del>at</del> into an Italian jail.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Bartolomeo Pergami (1783/4&#8211;1842). He had initially been hired as a servant,
                  but by this stage was running the Princess&#8217;s household. He was widely rumoured to
                  be her lover, but the information given here about his past is gossip, probably
                  relayed to Southey by Landor.</note> &#8211; the second would have been a gentleman of
               high fashion in that part of the <del>world</del> {Holy Land} which is now covered by
               the Dead Sea,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Sodom and Gomorrah, two
                  cities destroyed by God for the sinfulness of their inhabitants,
                     <title>Genesis</title> 13&#8211;19. The sin primarily associated with Sodom in
                  Christian traditions was homosexuality, so Southey is implying that one of
                  Caroline&#8217;s attendants was homosexual. Again, this information is merely local
                  gossip and it is not possible to identify this member of Caroline&#8217;s household, or
                  the one Southey claims was an assassin (the &#8216;practitioner with the stiletto&#8217;) with
                  any certainty.</note> &#8211; &amp; the third has distinguished himself as a
               practitioner with the stiletto. These wretches plunder her in every imaginable way,
               &amp; she keeps up the most lavish expenditure by the simple means of never paying
               her debts. To Como it is said she will not return on this account. &#8211; Lugano, the Lago
               Maggiore. Over the Simplon.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Simplon
                  pass, in the Swiss Alps, between Brig and Domodossola in Italy.</note> The Valais,
               &#8211; the most beautiful country that can be imagined, &amp; with the most miserable
               inhabitants, Cretins &amp; goitres being more numerous than I could possibly have
               supposed. I am satisfied that the water is the cause, for where the inhabitants drink
               clear water these dreadful curses are not found.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">These conditions were actually caused by a lack of iodine in
                  the soil.</note> They are frightful beyond description. From Martigny a three days
               excursion on mules to Chamounix, &amp; the <hi rend="ital">Mer de Glace</hi>, an
               absurd name for <del>ice of the</del> {a} Glacier {which ought to be called the
                  <del>Lake</del> Valley of Ice}. There is neither beauty nor sublimity in a
               Glacier. Yesterday we arrived here, &#8211; tanned to the colour of the Copper Indians,
               &amp; glad of a little rest. During seven weeks <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> &amp; myself have never lain later than six &#8211; then only on the
               days when we were not travelling, &amp; have much more frequently risen at four than
               at five.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The great industry of the people has surprized me. It is the same
               every where. There is more waste ground within twenty miles of London, upon any one
               line of road, than we have seen in the whole seven weeks that we have been
               travelling. France, Switzerland, Savoy, Piedmont, the Milanese, &#8211; it is every where
               the same, every shelf of the rocks is cultivated, &amp; houses &amp; villages are
               perched, where you might suppose it would tire a jack daw to reach them. And yet
               every where there is a degree of squalid poverty, which if it be not explained by the
               pressure of present scarcity, &amp; the effects of a war which in the first place
               drained the male population, &amp; lately brought armies thro the country, would
               appear altogether inexplicable. The women seem to be incessantly employed in
               agricultural labour &amp; almost as soon as they cease to be children, become old at
               once, &amp; look more like living mummies than like human beings, from constant
               exposure, filth, hard work &amp; perhaps insufficient nourishment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Alps, &#8211; if the world should last another six thousand years, <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> will still be Skiddaw, but
               there will be no Alps, they will have mouldered down, &amp; formed a table land with
               the wreck. I could not have imagined such a scene of ruins. This it is which
               occasions the difficulty in making roads, &amp; in keeping them up when made. The
               Mount Cenis road is constructed with the greatest care &amp; skill, not the smallest
               runnel is permitted to cross the way; there are walls built up the side of the hill
               to conduct it to an arch under the road, &amp; stone channels by the road side, &#8211;
               otherwise a single wet season would break up all that is done. Landslips are so
               frequent, that a part of the new line has been given up as too dangerous, &amp; a new
               road is now constructing at prodigious expence in so spiral a line, that it passes
               four times over a cataract as steep as <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lodore">Lodore</ref>. The
               torrents &amp; the rivers are of the colour of pease porridge, &amp; much of the same
               consistency. The Rhone is of this colour when it enters the Lake of Geneva, &amp; it
               issues out of it a clear deep blue: &#8211; it comes in the Bahar el Abiad, &amp; goes out
               the Bahar el Azrak.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Arabic names for the
                  White and Blue Nile. Southey had discussed these rivers in some detail in his
                  review of James Bruce (1730&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels to Discover
                     the Source of the Nile in the Years 1768, 1769, 1770, 1771, 1772 and
                     1773</title> (1805), <title>Annual Review for 1805</title>, 4 (1806),
                  2&#8211;16.</note> Of course all that it brings in is left behind &amp; must in time
               fill up the Lake, &#8211; a process which is very rapidly going on.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From Milan I sent home a large case of books, directed according to
               the arrangement which had been made for me in England. Will you tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> that I saw
               the first letter dispatched which was to announce them to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Rothschild,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathan Mayer Rothschild
                  (1777&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), London banker and founder of N. M. Rothschild
                  &amp; Sons in 1811.</note> &#8211; but that least there should be any mistake about the
               second, which my agent, a certain Signor Discacciati,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Discacciati (dates unknown) showed Southey around the city on
                  his visit to Milan in June 1817 and arranged the transport and insurance of the
                  books he bought. He also attempted to arrange contact with Landor.</note> seemed
               very much disposed to inclose to Cornaghi the printseller at Charing Cross, or
               Cockspur street,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Paul Colnaghi
                  (1751&#8211;1833), head of the printsellers, P. &amp; D. Colnaghi, based at 23 Cockspur
                  Street in London. Colnaghi was originally from an area near Milan.</note> I wish
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">GCB.</ref> would call upon the said Cornaghi. This second letter
               should inform Rothschild that such a box directed &amp;c &amp; marked E.N. is arrived
               by such a ship; &#8211; now as the box will be shipt from Genoa, I could not see the letter
               written at Milan, not knowing by what ship it would be sent; &amp; I am apprehensive
               Discacciati will content himself with merely apprizing Cornaghi of it, who is his
               Magnus Apollo.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Great Apollo&#8217;; in other
                  words his great oracle.</note> &#8211; There are some curious books there. Among others
               the Bibliotheca Rabbinica of Bartolucci.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Guilio Bartolocci (1613&#8211;1687), <title>Bibliotheca Magna Rabbinica de
                     Scriptoribus et Scriptus Hebraicis</title> (1675&#8211;1694), no. 236 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; I wrote to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">G. C. B</ref> from Milan.
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> is gone to the Greek
               Islands. He made six attempts &amp; all in vain to reach the top of Vesuvius &#8211; this I
               heard at Lausanne from an Englishman<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified. </note> at the Table d&#8217;Hote.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very anxious to be at home at once, &amp; somewhat uncomfortable
               at tarrying longer on the continent than my first intention, least it should throw me
               behind you in my movements to the North. &#8211; My journey has been very prosperous, &amp;
               I shall come back with much more knowledge than I took out, &#8211; a capital which always
               turns to account. &#8211; I anticipated the result of the State Trials,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">These trials resulted from a public meeting at
                  Spa Fields, London, on 2 December 1816. A group of revolutionaries attempted to
                  lead part of the crowd in an attack on the Tower of London and the Bank of
                  England. James Watson (1766&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>) was acquitted of High
                  Treason after a trial on 9&#8211;16 June 1817 and the charges against Arthur Thistlewood
                  (1774&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), Thomas Preston (1774&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>)
                  and John Hooper (dates unknown) were dropped.</note> &#8211; &amp; foresee the
               consequence. Sooner or later it seems fated that the abuse of all our best
               institutions will bring on their destruction: &#8211; &amp; this will be brought about not
               by the ambition of the Ruler but by the want of principle in the people. When the
               principle of private virtue fails, all institutions which are built upon it must
               fall. &#8211; I think of the subject propounded in your letter, &amp; think <del>xxxx</del>
               that the remedy is effectual, &#8211; but it requires an establishment {&amp; reform} of
               Alms Houses upon a principle which I have somewhere hinted at in the QR. &amp; an
               extensive scheme for providing at first for vagabond children.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;On the Poor&#8217;,
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187&#8211;235, which emphasised the
                  importance of education and commended attempts to provide for the aged poor
                  through contributory schemes that produced a form of pension (230&#8211;231).</note> The
               means I think could be devised, &#8211; but look about in vain for the men who would carry
               such a scheme into effect. Nevertheless, in these times, &#8211; which are the worst we
               have <del>xxxx</del> ever seen &#8211; nil desperandum.<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Do not despair&#8217;.</note> I will perpend them among the Alps of
               Switzerland &amp; we will talk it over among my own mountains. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               R</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>