<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3057</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4328</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3057. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 26 December 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3057.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 6p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3057" type="letter">
        <head>3057. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1817-12-26">26 December 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15 Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/
                  London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 29 DE 29/ 1817<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 6p.<lb />
                  Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <p> Richard Rodda<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Rodda (1743&#8211;1815), Methodist preacher and circuit minister from
                  Cornwall.</note> one of Wesleys preachers says, &#8220;My mother fell into a deep consumption. She was brought so low that she could not
               walk across the room. After many things had been tried in vain, she was perfectly {xxx} restored by making a hole in the ground, &amp;
               breathing into it for a quarter of an hour every morning.</p>
        <p rend="right"> Arminian Magazine.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Arminian Magazine</title>, 7 (June 1784), 300.</note>
               Vol 7. p. 300</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p> &#8220;A friend of mine of good quality living sometime in Virginia was sore troubled for a long time with the Bloody Flux, having tryed
               several remedies by the advice of his friends without any good effect, at last was induced with a longing desire to drink the fat
               dripping of a goose newly taken from the fire, which absolutely cured him, who was in despair of ever recovering his health again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> {I believe I have read something of the disease being cured by <hi rend="ital">ghee</hi> &#8211; clarified butter.}</p>
        <p rend="right"> Josselyns New Englands Rarities.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Josselyn (fl. 1638&#8211;1675), <title>New
                     England&#8217;s Rarities, Discovered in Birds, Beasts, Fishes, Serpents, and Plants of that Country</title> (London, 1672), pp. 9, 93;
                  no. 1531 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> p. 9.</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p> &#8220;I shall conclude this section, says Josselyn, with a strange cure effected upon a Drummers Wife, much afflicted with a Wolf in her
               breast. The poor woman lived with her husband at a town called by the Indians Casco but by the English, Famouth, where for some time
               she swaged the pain of her sore by bathing it with strong malt beer, which it would suck in greedily, as if some living creature. When
               she could come by no more beer (for it was brought from Boston along the coasts by merchants) she made use of Rhum, a strong water
               drawn from Sugar Canes, with which it was lulled asleep; at last, to be rid of it altogether, she put a quantity of arsenic to the
               rhum, and, bathing of it as formerly she utterly destroyed it &amp; cured herself: but her kind husband, who sucked out the poison as
               the sore was healing, lost all his teeth, but without farther danger or inconvenience.</p>
        <p rend="right"> D<hi rend="sup">o</hi> p 93</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p> &#8220;While the septennial bill<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Septennial Act (1715) lengthened the maximum time between
                  general elections from three years, as fixed by the Triennial Act (1694), to seven years.</note> was in agitation, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Friend,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Friend (1675&#8211;1728; <title>DNB</title>), physician and Whig
                  supporter.</note> the celebrated physician called on Lord Townshend<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Townshend, 2nd
                  Viscount Townshend (1674&#8211;1738; <title>DNB</title>), Secretary of State for the Northern Department 1714&#8211;1716, 1721&#8211;1730.</note>
               &amp; informed him that Lord Somers<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Somers, 1st Baron Somers (1651&#8211;1716;
                  <title>DNB</title>), Solicitor-General 1689&#8211;1692, Attorney-General 1692&#8211;1693, Lord Keeper of the Privy Seal 1693&#8211;1697, Lord
                  Chancellor 1697&#8211;1700, Lord President of the Council 1708&#8211;1710.</note> was at that moment <hi rend="ital">restored to the full
                  possession of his faculties by a fit of the gout, which suspended the effect of his paralytic complaint</hi>. Townshend immediately
               waited upon Somers, who as soon as he came into the room embraced him &amp; said &#8216;I have just heard of the work in which you are
               engaged &amp; congratulate you upon it: I never approved the triennial bill, &amp; always considered it in effect the reverse of what
               it was intended. You have my hearty approbation in this business, &amp; I think it will be the greatest support possible to the liberty
               of the country. </p>
        <p rend="right"> Coxes Mem of Sir Rob. Walpole.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of the Life and
                     Administration of Sir Robert Walpole</title>, 3 vols (London, 1800), I, p. 130; no. 752 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> 8vo edition. Vol 1. 130</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p> &#8220;my brother had been dangerously ill for a long time. But tho he was attended by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> F. &amp; a physician from
               Leeds, &amp; was got a good deal better he was still very feeble. &#8211; On catching a fresh cold, his disorder returned; &amp; was attended
               with so violent a pain in his left side, that it was with the utmost difficulty he drew his breath; &amp; was thought to be in great
               danger of a Consumption. On this I advised him to apply the Brimstone plaister to his side. He did so on going to bed, &amp; was much
               better the next morning. This encouraged him to keep it on, &amp; in four or five days (changing it once a day) his pain was entirely
               gone. Since then his health is amazingly restored. And I never saw any thing have so extraordinary an effect in so short a time. I
               thought it my duty to give you this information: as you may have frequent occasion to recommend this most excellent medicine to others. </p>
        <p rend="right"> John Pawson.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Pawson (1737&#8211;1806), Methodist preacher and ordained Minister;
                     <title>Arminian Magazine</title>, 9 (December 1786), 679.</note> Arminian Magazine. Vol 9. p 679.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;We observed one of the soldiers rubbing, or rather kneading one of his comrades forcibly on the neck &amp; arms, &amp;
               pulling his joints. This is the Albanian cure for a cold in the limbs.</p>
        <p rend="right"> Hobhouses Travels<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cam Hobhouse (1786&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A
                     Journey Through Albania and Other Provinces of Turkey in Europe and Asia, to Constantinople, During the Years 1809 and
                     1810</title>, 2 vols (London, 1813), I, pp. 36, 178, 270.</note> 1.36</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;They have as singular a remedy for a fever. The patient stretches out his arm, &amp; the Doctor runs his thumb
               forcibly along the principal artery from the wrist up to the shoulder. This he repeats several times, till he has thrown the man into a
               profuse perspiration, whom he then covers up warmly, &amp; considers in a fair way of recovery. Nor is he often deceived, as the
               opening of the pores in such cases must, I suppose but seldom fail of producing a favourable effect. D<hi rend="sup">o</hi> p 178</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At the modern Orchomanos<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A town in Boeotia, Greece.</note> there is a shepherd
               named Demetrius, the fattest man I ever saw, who in the summer passes the hottest hours of the day up to the neck in the neighbouring
               river. This practice not only does not injure him, but has become by habit so necessary to him, that he declares he should not, without
               it, be able to support the rage of the summer sun. D<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 270</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the Prophecies of Merlin which were written long before the discovery of the New World<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Le Compte de la Vie de Merlin et des ses Faiz, et Compte de ses Prophecies</title> (n.d.), deriving from
                  earlier medieval prose texts and gathering together various prophecies attributed to Merlin. Southey drew on it in <title>The Byrth,
                     Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title>
                  (1817).</note> is the following passage. The Lady of the Lake says, &#8216;Merlin tu fais peche que de coste si belle damoyselle comme je
               suis tu te couches, et puis avec dautres femmes tu vas gesir donc jen pourroye estre mallada.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Merlin you&#8217;re committing a sin because you lie with me, a beautiful young lady, and yet I could contract a disease from other
                  women you are going to interact with&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="right"> ff 74.</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> in Malabar has seen the paroxysm of fever stopt by
               giving a pill of assafoetida<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">A gum exuded from the root of the herb Ferula, native to
                  India.</note> when it is coming on. It is a practice of the natives.</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;In cure of sicknesses the Barbary Moors use very plain medicines, &amp; whatever be the disease, cauterizing is first
               practiced, which they do with no more art or curiosity than with a knife red-hot to gash &amp; cut the place where the pain lies. To
               cure the head ache they take the root tauz-argent &amp; rosemary, burning them in an earthen pot, over which the diseased holds his
               head for the fume, then holding the same in a cloth about the head present ease is given. This tauz-argent is a root much celebrated
               for an excellent &amp; lasting perfume, &#8211; there is great store thereof about Salle &#8211; the Moors use it in airing &amp; perfuming their
               rooms.</p>
        <p rend="right"> Lancelot Addisons West Barbary<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Lancelot Addison (1632&#8211;1703), <title>West Barbary,
                     or, A Short Narrative of the Revolutions of the Kingdoms of Fez and Morocco</title> (London, 1671), p. 223.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nicholas Hostresham who flourished 1443 wrote a treatise Contra dolorem renum, thus beginning, Lapis quandoque
               generatus in renibus.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas of Horsham (fl. 15th century), <title>Contra Dolorem
                     Renum</title> (i.e. &#8216;Diseases of the Kidneys&#8217;): &#8216;the stone is sometimes generated in the kidneys&#8217;.</note> &#8220;I observe this the
               rather, because his practice was wholly at home, (it not appearing that he ever went beyond the sea), &amp; this is contrary unto the
               confidence of such who have vehemently assumed, that the Stone was never heard of in England until hops, &amp; beer made therewith,
               (about the year 1516) began to be commonly used&#8221;.</p>
        <p rend="right"> Fullers Worthies.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Fuller (1608&#8211;1661; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     History of the Worthies of England</title>, 2 vols (London, 1811), II, p. 394; no. 1134 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> Vol 2. 394. last edition</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Elsewhere Fuller calls the Stone &#8216;the Students disease.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Fuller, <title>History
                     of the Worthies of England</title>, 2 vols (London, 1811), II, p. 364.</note> And in some of my dissenting books I find it
               frequently spoken of as the scourge of dissenting ministers in the beginning of the last century; &#8211; this leads me to guess that it has
               been less frequent since the use of <hi rend="ital">tea</hi>. At least it is certainly not the peculiar disease of sedentary students
               in this age.</p>
        <p rend="center"> &#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <p> An officer (whether his name was Napier or Stanhope<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Lieutenant-Colonel James Stanhope
                  (1788&#8211;1825), MP for Buckingham 1817&#8211;1818, Fowey 1818&#8211;1819, Dartmouth 1822&#8211;1825. He fought at Waterloo (18 June 1815), despite being
                  badly wounded at the Siege of San Sebastian (1813). A musket shot could not be removed from near his spine and the constant pain
                  eventually contributed to his suicide in 1825.</note> I cannot be certain, &#8211; &amp; it is of little consequence) went into the Battle
               of Waterloo with an abscess forming, &amp; in a most painful state. He had been about to depart for England to have it opened. The
               extraordinary exertion &amp; animal expenditure of that day were such that absorption took place, &amp; Nature worked a compleat cure.
               &#8211; This I heard from Lady Spencer:<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Lavinia Spencer, n&#233;e Bingham (1762&#8211;1831), wife of the
                  bibliophile, George John Spencer, 2nd Earl Spencer (1758&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; &amp; as it was one or other of 4 names
               which I have mentioned, you may possibly find out the farther particulars if you desire them. To me the case seems to bear upon the
               sweating system {practice} of Lewis &amp; Clarke<del>s</del>,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Meriweather Lewis (1774&#8211;1809) and
                  William Clark (1770&#8211;1838), <title>Travels to the Source of the Missouri River, and Across the American Continent to the Pacific
                     Ocean</title>, 3 vols (London, 1815), III, pp. 209&#8211;210.</note>
          <del>practice</del>; by which the body is almost as violently affected as by salivation, while nothing poisonous is introduced into the
               system. </p>
        <p> My dear Harry</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here are some extracts for you, which may as well be sent off as lie longer in my desk. Some thing or other of this
               kind is always falling in my way, &amp; it is impossible that I may stumble upon something of real value. &#8211; I find that Baxters wife
               took &#8216;breast-milk&#8217; for what was supposed to be consumption,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey noted this fact in his
                     <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4 series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), II, p. 111. But he was probably mistaken;
                  Richard Baxter&#8217;s (1615&#8211;1691; <title>DNB</title>) wife, Margaret (1636&#8211;1681), did recover from an illness diagnosed as consumption
                  and followed a diet based on milk; see Richard Baxter, <title>Memoirs of Mrs Margaret Baxter</title> (London, 1826), pp. 8, 98. But
                  it was Baxter who took breast-milk when ill, <title>Reliquiae Baxterianae</title> (London, 1696), p. 82.</note> &#8211; &amp; that Baxter
               himself for I know not what complaint took the very expensive prescription of a golden bullet, &#8211; (a dear kind of bolus Sir Doctor.) It
               staid in him so long, that his &#8220;praying neighbours&#8221; thought their sermons needful, &amp; he past it while they were praying for
                  him.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Baxter, <title>Reliquiae Baxterianae</title> (London, 1696), p. 81: &#8216;I got a
                  Gold Bullet and swallowed it (between 20 <hi rend="ital">s.</hi> and 30 <hi rend="ital">s.</hi> weight); and having taken it, I knew
                  not how to be delivered of it again: I took Clysters and Purges for about three Weeks, but nothing stirred it; and a Gentleman
                  having done the like, the Bullet never came from it till he died, and it was cut out: But at last my Neighbours set a Day apart to
                  fast and pray for me, and I was freed from my Danger in the beginning of that day.&#8217; </note> This is a comical story. At present
               physicians take the gold themselves instead of prescribing it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The suspension of paralysis by a fit of the gout is a curious fact.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have heard that my box of books from Milan is arrived in London &#8211; a real joy, &#8211; for I had almost despaired of
               it. I hope the larger cargo from Brussels will turn up also when they are enquired for. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very busy Braziling, reviewing, Wesleyizing, &amp; every now &amp; then a little at the Paraguay Poem,<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was working on the third volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819), <title>The
                     Life of Wesley; and Rise and Progress of Methodism </title>(1820) and <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> upon which
               I shall soon set dens et unguis.<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;tooth and claw&#8217;.</note> I wait for the third volume of a
               French book<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Baptist Germain Fabry (1770&#8211;1821), <title>Le Ge&#769;nie de la Re&#769;volution
                     Conside&#769;re&#769; dans l&#8217;Education ou Me&#769;moires pour Servir a l&#8217;Histoire de l&#8217;Instruction Publique, Depuis 1789 jusqu&#8217;a&#768; Nos
                     Jours</title> (1817&#8211;1818), required for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> which <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has sent me, before I can compleat my introductory chapter to the Peninsular
               War &#8211; it contains the compleat details of <del>xxxxx</del> the system of education established by Buonaparte,<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821), Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815.</note> &#8211; nothing could ever have been
               published more precisely in time for my purpose. Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> &#8211; God bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1817-12-26"> 26 Dec. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>