<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3077</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4348</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3077. Robert Southey to John Rickman, [c. 14 February
                  1818] </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3077.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 331. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                     Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 178&#8211;179 [dated February 1818]. Dating note: Dating from
                  content, the letter was probably provoked by Southey learning of the Evanses&#8217; petition (13 February 1818) to the House of
                  Commons.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3077" type="letter">
        <head>3077. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1818-02-14">[c. 14 February
                  1818] </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
            <lb /> Endorsement: RS./ Feby
                  1818<lb /> MS: Huntington Library, RS 331. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 178&#8211;179 [dated February 1818].<lb /> Dating note: Dating from
                  content, the letter was probably provoked by Southey learning of the Evanses&#8217; petition (13 February 1818) to the House of
                  Commons.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received the beginning on Monday,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of Rickman and Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;On
                  the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308.</note> &amp; sent off the end the following night, &#8211;
               which if it does not save much time, (a <hi rend="ital">little</hi> it will save) may prevent impatience. To have the proofs sent thro
               you would plainly indicate the author, &#8211; because they always come franked from the Admiralty,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of the <title>Quarterly Review</title> would be sent under Admiralty franks because John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848;
                     <title>DNB</title>) worked there as Second Secretary to the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1806, 1807&#8211;1845; so if Rickman sent the journal any
                  proofs directly they would arrive franked from the office of The Speaker, identifying Rickman as the author, rather than
                  Southey.</note> &#8211; that pretext therefore is not available. The <hi rend="ital">end</hi> I shall be able to send you in time for it
               to travel back, on account of delaying the beginning <del>for</del> till the printed Parl: Proc: may license its departure. You will
               see that all which I have done is to put in a little garnish, of no more use than the ornaments on a Twelfth Cake.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A decorative cake traditionally made on Twelfth Night (6 January).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What I had prepared is now on my desk in the shape of 30 printed Quarterly pages, &amp; about as much ms. as would make
               20 more. Of all this I have engrafted scarcely two pages upon your matter, &#8211; about five more are rendered useless. The rest with a new
               beginning, a little remodelling, &amp; about ten pages in addition will form a <del>xxxx</del> paper for the next number, for which it
               will not be difficult to find a text, the subject being, the means of improving the people.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;On the Means of Improving the People&#8217; appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818),
                  79&#8211;118.</note> And here I shall dwell upon that increase of the educated class, which has overstocked all the ways of life for which
                  the<del>y</del> adventurers were educated: the condition of women also in that rank will necessarily be included. &#8211; <del>it</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn"> Murray</ref> prints 12000 of the Review,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In fact
                  14,000 copies of <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818) were printed and 13,000 sold.</note> &#8211; this is writing to a
               large number of readers, &amp; a large proportion of them are disposed to believe what they read, however unable they may be to learn,
               mark &amp; <del>xxxx</del> inwardly digest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is no necessity for noticing poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrydgesSirEgerton">Sir E. B.</ref>
          <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not discuss Sir Egerton Brydges&#8217; <title>Arguments in Favour of the Practicability of
                     Relieving the Able-bodied Poor by Finding Employment for them ... Addressed to the Committee on the Poor Laws</title>
                  (1817).</note> &#8211; I made a little extract from <ref type="m" target="people.html#CourtenayThomas">Courtenay</ref>, in the form of a
               note I think. He advertises upon the subject now.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Peregrine Courtenay (1782&#8211;1841;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Treatise upon the Poor Laws</title> (1818) was one of the works reviewed in &#8216;On the Means of
                  Improving the People&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 79&#8211;118. It was quoted briefly in a note in &#8216;On the Poor
                  Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 287.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whenever this reformation takes place (if they venture to make it) &#8211; a tub for the Whale would be an excellent thing, &#8211;
               another <ref type="m" target="people.html#SouthcottJoanna">Joanna Southcott</ref> &#8211; or a Red Man, &#8211; or sending <ref type="m" target="people.html#Burdett">Sir Francis</ref> to the Tower.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Various distractions of popular
                  attention: Southcott&#8217;s supposed pregnancy with the returning Shiloh received great public attention in 1814; the occasional
                  appearance of Native Americans in London always caused great interest; and in 1810 the confinement of Sir Francis Burdett in the
                  Tower of London for libelling parliament had created a huge furore.</note> &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How absurdly the <del>men in</del> power <del>have</del> has been used which Ministers had in their hands. They not
               only shut up fellows who might as well have been left at liberty to run their heads into a halter, but in the case of Evans they
                  <del>x</del> arrested a man, whom even a London jury would have found guilty for his proposal of a Spencean Revolution.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Evans (1763&#8211;before 1831; <title>DNB</title>), and his son Thomas John Evans (c.1798&#8211;?), were both
                  detained without trial on 9 February 1817&#8211;20 January 1818, when habeas corpus was suspended, as part of the government&#8217;s actions
                  against the Society of Spencean Philanthropists, several of whose members had been responsible for the abortive uprising at Spa
                  Fields on 2 December 1816. Ironically, Evans had played no role in events at Spa Fields. Evans was the author of <title>Christian
                     Policy: the Salvation of the Empire</title> (1816), which Southey had reviewed in &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 269&#8211;271; Thomas Evans&#8217;s petition, complaining of his treatment in prison, was read in the
                  House of Commons on 13 February 1818.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">farewell</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>