<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3119</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4390</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3119. Robert Southey to Chauncy Hare Townshend [fragment], 12 April 1818 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3119" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3119.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850) .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 301&#8211;303.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3119" type="letter">
        <head>3119. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Hare Townshend</ref> [fragment], <date when="1818-04-12">12 April 1818 </date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 301&#8211;303.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-04-12"> April 12. 1818.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Chauncey.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just finished <ref type="m" target="people.html#MilmanHenryHart">Henry Milman</ref>&#8217;s poem, a work of great
                  power.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Samor, Lord of the Bright City</title> (1818), an epic by Henry Hart
                  Milman.</note> But the story is ill constructed, and the style has a vice analogous to that which prevailed in prose about 170 years
               ago, when every composition was overlaid with strained thoughts and far-fetched allusions. The faults here are a perpetual stretch and
               strain of feeling; and the too frequent presence of the narrator, bringing his own fancies and meditations in the foreground, and
               thereby &#8211; as in French landscape-engraving &#8211; calling off attention from the main subject, and destroying the effect. With less poetry
               Samor would have been a better poem. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MilmanHenryHart">Milman</ref> has been endeavouring to adapt the
               moody and thoughtful character of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>&#8217;s philosophical poetry to
               heroic narration: they are altogether incompatible; and <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> himself,
               when he comes to narrate in his higher strains, throws it aside like a wrestler&#8217;s garment, and is as severe a writer as Dante,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Dante Aligheri (c. 1265&#8211;1321).</note> who is the great master in this style. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#MilmanHenryHart">Milman</ref> can perceive or be persuaded of his fault, he has powers enough for any thing; but
               it is a seductive manner, and I think that as our poetry in Cowley&#8217;s days<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. in the
                  seventeenth century, in the time of Abraham Cowley (1618&#8211;1667; <title>DNB</title>).</note> was overrun with conceits of thought, it
               is likely in the next generation to be overflown with this exuberance of feeling.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is a great error. That poetry (I am speaking of heroic narrative) which would reach the heart, must go straight to
               the mark like an arrow. Away with all trickery and ornaments when pure beauty is to be represented in picture or in marble; away with
               drapery when you would display muscular strength. Call artifices of this kind to your aid in those feebler parts which must occur in
               every narrative, and which ought to be there to give the other parts their proper relief.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MilmanHenryHart">Henry Milman</ref> was here, with an elder brother,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably his eldest brother William George Milman (1781&#8211;1857), who had spent an extended period in Keswick in 1813;
                  see Southey to Thomas Southey, 24 February 1813, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter
                  2224.</note> about four years ago, who lodged at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> for some twelve months. He
               is a fine young man: and his powers are very great. They are, however, better fitted for the drama than for narration; the drama admits
               his favourite strain of composition, and is easier in its structure.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Hart Milman&#8217;s first
                  poetical publication had been the verse drama <title>Fazio</title> (1815).</note> Indeed, it is as much easier to plan a play than a
               poem of such magnitude as Samor, as it is to build a gentleman&#8217;s house than a cathedral.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you know anything of Sir George Dallas?<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir George Dallas, 1st Baronet
                  (1758&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), expert on Indian affairs.</note> He has sent me some marvellous verses by a son of his not yet
                  thirteen;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Charles Dallas (1804&#8211;1874), youngest son of Sir George Dallas. His
                     <title>Ode to the Duke of Wellington, and Other Poems</title> was published in 1819. One of the works it contained was part of
                  his drama, <title>Sallust; or the Tyrant Punished</title>, in which Dallas had acted the leading role aged eleven; see Samuel
                  Griswold Goodrich (1793&#8211;1860), <title>The Cabinet of Curiosities</title>, 2 vols (Hartford, 1822), II, pp. 117&#8211;118.</note> as great
               a prodigy as I have ever read of. Verse appears as easy to him as speech; Latin verse is at his fingers&#8217; end like English; and he has
               acted a part in a play of his own composition like another young Roscius.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A generic term for an
                  actor, after the Roman actor, Quintus Roscius Gallus (c. 126&#8211;62 BC).</note> . . . . . . .</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am busy with history myself, and have written no poetry for many months; why this disuse, there is here hardly room
               to explain, if it were worth explanation. The account of Lope de Vega in the last Quarterly is mine, as you would probably guess.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s notice of Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de
                     Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 1&#8211;46.</note> I have
               read widely in Spanish poetry; and might in historical and literary recollections call myself half a Spaniard, if, being half a
               Portuguese also, this would leave any room for the English part of my intellectual being. I anticipate much pleasure in showing you the
               treasures with which I am surrounded here upon these shelves. God bless you!</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R. S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>