<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2806</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4077</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2806. Robert Southey to Chauncy Hare Townshend [fragment], 5 June 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2806" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2806.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850) .  Previously  published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 185&#8211;187.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2806" type="letter">
        <head>2806. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Hare Townshend </ref>[fragment], <date when="1816-06-05">5 June 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb /> Previously published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 185&#8211;187.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-06-05">June 5. 1816.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for both your letters. The history of your school-boy
                  days<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Townshend had been educated at Eton
                  before proceeding to Trinity Hall, Cambridge in 1816.</note> reminds me of my own
               childhood and youth. I had a lonely childhood, and suffered much from tyranny at
               school, till I outgrew it, and came to have authority myself. In one respect, my
               fortune seems to have been better than yours, or my nature more accommodating. Where
               intellectual sympathy was not to be found, it was sufficient for me if moral sympathy
               existed. A kind heart and a gentle disposition won my friendship more readily than
               brighter talents, where these were wanting . . . . </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I left Westminster in a perilous state, &#8211; a heart full of feeling and
               poetry, a head full of Rousseau and Werter, and my religious principles shaken by
                  Gibbon:<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Writers and books that had
                  influenced Southey as a youth: Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712&#8211;1778), in particular
                  his, <title>Julie, ou la Nouvelle H&#233;lo&#239;se</title> (1761); Johann von Goethe
                  (1749&#8211;1832), <title>Die Leiden des Jungen Werther</title> (1774); and Edward
                  Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), particularly his <title>The History of the
                     Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</title> (1776&#8211;1788).</note> many
               circumstances tended to give me a wrong bias, none to lead me right, except
               adversity, the wholesomest of all discipline. An instinctive modesty, rather than any
               purer cause, preserved me for a time from all vice. A severe system of stoical
               morality then came to its aid. I made Epictetus, for many months, literally my
                  manual.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Epictetus (c. AD 55&#8211;135), Greek
                  Stoic philosopher: &#8216;there are few characters that I contemplate with more
                  reverence than the slave Epictetus. his book was {once} for some months my pocket
                  companion&#8217;, Robert Southey to John May, 15 August 1797, <title>The Collected
                     Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 247.</note> The French
               revolution was then in its full career. I went to Oxford in January, 1793, a Stoic
               and a Republican. I had no acquaintance at the college, which was in a flagitious
               state of morals. I refused to wear powder, when every other man in the university
               wore it, because I thought the custom foolish and filthy; and I refused even to drink
               more wine than suited my inclination and my principles. Before I had been a week in
               the college, a little party had got round me, glad to form a sober society, of which
               I was the centre. Here I became intimate with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SewardEdmund">Edmund
                  Seward</ref>, whose death was the first of those privations which have, in great
               measure, weaned my heart from the world. He confirmed in me all that was good. Time
               and reflection, the blessings and the sorrows of life, and I hope I may add, with
               unfeigned humility, the grace of God, have done the rest. Large draughts have been
               administered to me from both urns. No man has suffered keener sorrows, no man has
               been more profusely blest. Four months ago no human being could possibly be happier
               than I was, or richer in all that a wise heart could desire. The difference now is,
               that what was then my chief treasure is now laid up in Heaven.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your manuscript<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Presumably
                  the manuscript poem sent by Townshend; see Robert Southey to Chauncy Hare
                  Townshend, 16 May 1816, Letter 2790.</note> goes by the next coach. I shall be
               glad to see the conclusion, and any other of your verses, Latin or English. Is any
               portion of your time given to modern languages? If not, half an hour a day might be
               borrowed for German, the want of which I have cause to regret. I was learning it with
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">my son</ref>; and shall never have heart
               to resume that as a solitary study which in his fellowship was made so
                  delightful.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Southey had died on
                  17 April 1816.</note> The most ambitious founder of a family never built such
               hopes upon a child as I did on mine; and entirely resembling me as he did, if it had
               been God&#8217;s will that he should have grown up on earth, he would have shared my
               pursuits, partaken all my thoughts and feelings, and have in this manner succeeded to
               my plans and papers as to an intellectual inheritance. God bless you!</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>