<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2826</idno><idno type="nines">rce4097</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2826. Robert Southey to William Wilberforce, 25
                  July 1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2826.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. AL; 4p. .  Previously  published: R. I. Wilberforce and S. Wilberforce, The Correspondence of William
                     Wilberforce, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 349–351 [in part].  Note on MS: the end of the final paragraph of the
                  letter and the signature are missing from the MS; the text of these is supplied from The Correspondence of William
                     Wilberforce. </p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2826" type="letter"><head>2826. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref>, <date when="1816-07-25">25
                  July 1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Poet Southey LLD/ * his Son’s death<lb/> MS: Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. AL; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: R. I. Wilberforce and S. Wilberforce, <title>The Correspondence of William
                     Wilberforce</title>, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 349–351 [in part]. <lb/> Note on MS: the end of the final paragraph of the
                  letter and the signature are missing from the MS; the text of these is supplied from <title>The Correspondence of William
                     Wilberforce</title>. </note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1816-07-25">25 July. 1816</date></dateline><salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The Portugueze, or Brazilian, Government is neither by prejudice, or mistaken principle friendly to the continuance of
               the slave trade, or of slavery.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The slave trade was legal in Brazil until 1850 and slavery
                  itself was not abolished until 1888.</note> Every argument moral &amp; religious which during two centuries the Jesuits enforced
               with admirable perseverance in behalf of the Indians, holds good at this day for the Negroes, &amp; the abolition of the Indian slave
               trade &amp; emancipation of the Indian race are precedents in point.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The enslavement of
                  indigenous peoples in Brazil was not legal from 1537 onwards, but was widely practiced until the importation of African slaves in
                  the eighteenth century gradually reduced the demand for native slaves.</note> The laws are favourable to manumission, – the Priests
               encourage it, – there is no prejudice against the people of colour, &amp; the very few laws which establish a distinction are very
               generally disregarded. But owing to the immense extent of the country, &amp; the lax habit of obedience which must always be found in
               distant colonies &amp; thinly peopled regions, the Sovereign<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John VI (1767–1826), Prince Regent
                  1799–1816, King of Portugal 1816–1826. He fled to Brazil in 1807–1808 to escape the French invasion and did not return to Portugal
                  until 1821.</note> may be said to hold his authority only during pleasure. The Government (not from any disposition to tyranny, –
               but from the inveterate diseases which have eaten like a cancer into the heart of the state) is oppressive &amp; vexatious; the most
               abominable abuses exist in every department; – the leaven of revolution is at work; &amp; were the Court to take any direct steps
               towards the abolition, the very persons, who from their hearts abhor slavery, would take advantage of the discontent &amp; tumult which
               such measures would inevitably produce, &amp; join with the slave party to bring about what they look forward to as the deliverance of
               their country. Before therefore <del>xxx xxx xxx</del> the abolition can be effected in Brazil, a change must be wrought in the public
               mind.</p><p rend="indent1"> The same disgraceful error which you had to combat with in France<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The French
                  government was required to abolish the slave trade by an Additional Article to the Treaty of Paris (1815); when the French
                  government recovered its West African colonies in 1817 it did not reinstitute the trade, though it continued clandestinely.</note>
               prevails in Brazil, – a belief that the Abolition in England was the work of selfish policy. It is an unhappy <del>xxx xxx</del>
               characteristic of these times that nations &amp; sovereigns never obtain credit for any thing generous or good when they really deserve
               it. Arguments addressed directly to themselves the Brazilians would receive with suspicion, – a faithful history of what was done in
               this country, of the efforts which were made, the enthusiasm which was excited, &amp; the perseverance which after so many years
                  <del>xxx</del> triumphed over so many &amp; such formidable obstacles, – is liable to no such distrust: it would not come in a
               questionable shape; – it would be read with interest, &amp; I have every reason to believe, with effect also, by the Priests, – who
               have most influence over the public mind. Let me add also that the Portugueze have been as much undervalued for their literary
               inclinations &amp; attainments as they were for their military spirit &amp; {their} patriotism. By leaving out the introductory matter,
               curtailing the debates, &amp; condensing such parts of the narrative as will bear abridgement, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> work might be reduced to half its bulk, &amp; in that state a small volume might
               contain it, – ordinary paper with no unnecessary margin or space between the lines <del>xxxxxxx will</del> being best adapted to a
               people who have little money &amp; no taste for typographical luxuries.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Clarkson,
                  <title>History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African Slave–Trade by the British
                     Parliament</title> (1808). Southey was proposing a Portuguese translation of this work by his friend, <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref>. Southey’s arguments on the situation with regard to slavery in Brazil are
                  very similar to those put forward by Koster in his <title>Travels in Brazil</title> (London, 1816), pp. 445–456.</note> Something of
               this kind would be more effectual than anything argumentative &amp; addressed to themselves. The arguments upon the Impolicy (so ably
               treated in <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref> essays) are inapplicable to Brazil.</p><p rend="indent1"> In this country the battle is to be fought again, but there is no doubt of the event.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Despite the 1807 abolition of the African slave trade to British colonies, slavery itself was not abolished until
                  1833.</note> I suppose the letters which were so singularly announced in the Courier some weeks ago, are no other than these
               villainous &amp; impudent tissues of calumny &amp; falsehood.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly <title>The Edinburgh
                     Review and the West Indies; with Remarks on the Slave Registry Bill; Observations on the Pamphlets of Messrs. Stephen and
                     Macaulay, &amp;c. In Forty Letters, Addressed to the Editor of the Glasgow Courier</title> (1816), which opposed Wilberforce and
                  the Registry Bill of 1816. The letters had first been published in the <title>Glasgow Courier</title> in 1816 and then collected and
                  expanded into book form.</note> I am preparing a paper for the Quarterly Review upon the West India Islands, – with the view of
               making it bear upon this subject.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">No article by Southey on this subject was published in the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, after Murray made it clear he did not wish Southey to write from a pro-abolitionist
                  standpoint.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have sent to inquire if M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Francis be in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Clement Robert Francis (1792–1829), clergyman, Fellow of Caius College,
                  Cambridge and nephew of Southey’s friend, James Burney. </note> – It is not two years since your excellent friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> J Bowdler was here,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bowdler (1783–1815; <title>DNB</title>), a lawyer,
                  religious writer, friend of Wilberforce’s and prominent member of the Clapham Sect, met Southey in the Lakes in 1814. The day
                  Southey recalls is probably that described in Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 22–[23] October 1814, <title>The Collected Letters
                     of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2492. Bowdler had died, after suffering from tuberculosis for some years, on 1
                  February 1815.</note> – &amp; <del>xx xxx</del> after a day which I am sure all the party at one time must [MS obscured] eminently
                  <del>xxx</del> {delightful}, I dined with him &amp; poor John Calthorpe in the kitchen of an old farm house.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Calthorpe (1793–1816), a Lieutenant in the Royal Navy, the younger brother of another of
                  Wilberforce’s friends, George Gough-Calthorpe, 3rd Baron Calthorpe (1787–1851). Wilberforce was MP for Bramber, one of whose seats
                  Calthorpe controlled, in 1812–1825. John Calthorpe was killed in a riot in Jamaica on 10 June 1816. </note> They are gone! &amp; I
               who survive them, – have survived also my best earthly hopes, &amp; highest earthly enjoyments. They only who knew me in my daily
               habits can imagine, or believe, how great has been the extent of my loss, or how it is possible that a child of ten years should have
               been so entirely the companion as well as pupil of his father. I was recovering my Greek in the process of teaching <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, – we were learning German together, – &amp; were to have begun Saxon in the same
               manner, as soon as the Saxon Chronicle should have been published.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1815 ‘A new edition of
                  the Saxon Chronicle, with an English translation and notes’, edited by James Ingram (1774–1850; <title>DNB</title>), Rawlinsonian
                  Professor of Anglo-Saxon at Oxford 1803–1808, was advertised as ‘In the Press’, <title>The Tradesman</title>, 14 (January 1815), 55.
                  However, it did not appear until 1823. Southey had two copies, nos 2593 and 2594 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> For
               his age there was no better Latin scholar, {in Greek he was fit for the fifth form at Westminster<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">In other words a public schoolboy of 13–14 years old.</note>} &amp; he was acquiring with little expence of time,
               &amp; no trouble, the French &amp; Spanish. – With all these acquirements going on, his life was like a continued holyday, so much was
               it his disposition &amp; mine to mingle sport with study, &amp; find recreation in all things. He was the constant companion of my
               walks, &amp; felt as much interest in my pleasures as I did in his. <del>Xxx</del> His disposition was as beautiful as his intellect, –
               &amp; therefore I had ever an ominous apprehension that he was not intended to grow up on earth, – where it was not possible that his
               nature could be improved, &amp; but too certain that it must in some degree be sullied. The feeling which thus prepared me for this
               privation, has not been without its use in enabling me to <del>bear</del> submit to it with resignation. I hope &amp; believe that I
               have borne this affliction as it becomes a Christian. The stoicism which I endeavoured to practice in youth, (&amp; not without signal
               benefit) might have supported, – but it could not have consoled me. My heart is weaned from the world, – &amp; the brightest spot in
               the prospect before me is when <del>the</del> {a} light from Heaven shines upon the grave.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  manuscript of the letter ends here; the remainder of text is supplied from the version published in <title>The Correspondence of
                     William Wilberforce</title>, 2 vols (London, 1840), II, pp. 349–351.</note> –Yet do not imagine that I give way to sorrow, or
               indulge in vain retrospects &amp; guilty regret. – The Lord gave – the Lord hath taken away – blessed be the name of the Lord!<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Job</title>, 1: 21.</note> Never were these words pronounced with more heartfelt sincerity
               than when I repeated them in the most painful scenes &amp; moments of my life. I am thankful for the abundant blessings which I still
               possess, – but of all things most thankful for having possessed <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">a son</ref> whom I
               loved so entirely, who was so entirely worthy to be loved, &amp; whom I shall one day rejoin.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was mourning the death of his son Herbert on 17 April 1816.</note></p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me, my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2">Respectfully and truly yours,</salute><signed rend="indent3"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>