<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3214</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4485</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3214. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 28 November 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3214.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                     and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 321&#8211;323 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3214" type="letter">
        <head>3214. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1818-11-28">28 November 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 1 DE 1/ 1818<lb /> Endorsement: 28 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1818; 28 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  1818<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                     and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 321&#8211;323 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Ascertain for me, if you can, whether I am disqualified from voting at an election either by my pension or
                  <del>xx</del> by my office.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was not disqualified from voting through holding a public
                  office, or a pension. Only specific categories of office&#8211;holders could not vote, most importantly Post Office employees, Stamp
                  officers and customs and revenue officers (until 1868).</note> Because in case I am not, (but this is between ourselves) I shall
               constitute myself a free holder of Westmorland.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth had asked Southey to join in the
                  purchase of the Ivy How estate, Little Langdale; see Wordsworth to Thomas Monkhouse, 4 December 1818, <title>The Letters of William
                     and Dorothy Wordsworth. The Middle Years. Part 2. 1812&#8211;1820</title>, ed. E. De Selincourt, 2nd edn rev. Mary Moorman and Alan G.
                  Hill (Oxford, 1970), p. 509. A share in this estate would qualify the co-owners as 40 shilling freeholders, thus enabling them to
                  vote in county elections in Westmorland. The entire scheme was an attempt by Wordsworth to create more votes for the Lowther
                  interest in the county, so boosting its chances of success in the next general election and preventing Westmorland being won by
                  Brougham.</note> The present mode of carrying on the contest here is in conformity to a scheme of Lord Stanhopes, by buying up
                  freeholds.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles, 3rd Earl Stanhope (1753&#8211;1816; <title>DNB</title>), a radical in politics.
               </note> This has been set on foot by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>, &amp; the same system must
               be resorted to on the other side.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham had unsuccessfully contested the Westmorland seat
                  against the interests of the Earl of Lonsdale at the general election of 1818 and would do so again in 1820 and 1826. The creation
                  of 40 shilling freeholds purely to boost the number of supportive voters was a common charge made against opponents at elections.
                  Brougham had claimed in the Commons as early as 8 May 1818 that Lonsdale had been able to acquire the remaining privileges of the
                  Barony of Kendal from the Crown on favourable terms and had used this opportunity to manufacture 40 shilling freeholds for his
                  supporters by enclosing land and converting copyhold tenements into freeholds.</note> An opportunity offers at this time of just
               such a purchase as is required. And if by vesting 100 &#163; in this way I get only three per cent for the money, the principle is well
               vested, &amp; the <del>xxx of</del> twenty shillings a year<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably a reference to the Land Tax
                  (a very controversial tax in place since 1692) that Southey would have to pay on this land.</note> well paid for the privilege. I
               want nothing from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Ld Lonsdale</ref>, nor indeed do I <del>perceive</del> know that
               there is any possible way in which <del>xx</del> he, or the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Prime Minister</ref>
               himself could benefit a man, who will not for any earthly advantage that could be offered him, consent to sacrifice his retirement, his
               leisure &amp; his pursuits. But tho he cannot serve me, I shall be very glad to <del>xxx</del> enable myself to serve him, as one whom
               I both like &amp; respect for his personal character &amp; his political conduct. There cannot be a more obliging man. It is my own
               fault that I am not a frequent visitor at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lowtherestate">Lowther</ref> &#8211; <hi rend="ital">that</hi> I
               shall never be, &#8211; but it will gratify me &amp; become me, to show my sense of his repeated civilities in a better way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is a most remarkable season with us. On the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of November we had French beans at dinner,
               &amp; now (on the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi>) there has not been the slightest snow on the mountains, nor the slightest appearance of
               frost in the valley. The late flowers continue to blossom still. And the early ones are pushing forward as if it were spring. The great
               scarlet poppy has two large buds ready to burst, &amp; your favourite blue thistle has brought forth a flower. But what is more
               extraordinary the annual poppies whose stalks, to all appearance dead &amp; dry, were left in the ground, merely till <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lovell</ref> should give directions for clearing them away, have in many
               instances shot out fresh leaves <del>&amp; produced</del> of <del>the xxxxx</del> diminutive size, &amp; produced <del>xx</del>
               blossoms correspondently small, &#8211; not bigger than a daisy. This is in our own garden, which as you know, has no advantages of shelter
               or situation, &#8211; in happier spots the gardens have more the appearance of September than of winter. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> will tell you that I have been speaking a good word in behalf of the
               historical painters.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey promoted, in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820),
                  549&#8211;591, Haydon&#8217;s <title>New Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the Encouragement of
                     Painting</title> (1818). </note> (By the bye get <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> to take you to see <ref type="m" target="people.html#HaydonBenjamin">Haydons</ref> great picture,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Haydon was working
                  on his magnum opus, &#8216;Christ&#8217;s Entry Into Jerusalem&#8217; (first exhibited in 1820 and now at Mount St Mary&#8217;s Seminary, Cincinnati), which
                  included a portrait of Wordsworth.</note> which is prodigiously fine.) &#8211; I am now upon the Copyright question which I shall make as
               short as possible, &#8211; a few days will finish it &amp; a few days more finish a paper upon the Catacombs, &#8211; in which I have
                  <del>collected</del> {brought forth} a great <del>number of</del> collection of facts from out-of-the-way sources, some of them very
                  curious<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article on the &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217; appeared in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 196&#8211;219. His article &#8216;Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris&#8217; appeared in the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359&#8211;398. </note> The Copyright must have place in the present number, &#8211; &amp;
               no doubt it will, being much more for <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> interest than mine. The Catacombs
               will <del>xxx</del> eke out my ways &amp; means for the next quarter, &amp; then I shall have done with the QR for the next six months,
               &amp; in future I shall only just keep my hold in it for occasional convenience. I am in excellent trim for work. Brazil 416 pages
                  printed.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The final volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note>
               Wesley 384 &#8211; the remainder of the first volume in the printers hands &amp; a good portion of the notes.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> The second volume
               is begun &amp; about an eighth part of it ready. I go to it as soon as <del>the xxxx of xxxx</del> my dispatches are sent off. This
               morning I finished the second book of Oliver Newman. You see I have resumed it in good earnest, &#8211; &amp; I hope to report progress often
               during the winter.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217; remained unfinished and was published posthumously as a
                  fragment in 1845; see <title>Oliver Newman: a New England Tale (Unfinished): with Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp.
                  1&#8211;92. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall not move southward till both the Brazil &amp; the Wesley are finished. Three <del>xxx</del> winter months will
               do wonders, as I hope to be entirely free from interruptions. Other circumstances would not allow me to leave home before March,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Edith Southey was pregnant with Charles Cuthbert Southey, who was born on 24 February
                  1819.</note> nor will I move then unless these works are off my hands. I shall then start fairly, without impediment, &amp; in full
               force for the Peninsular War.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                  (1823&#8211;1832).</note> And thus my life passes looking to the completion of one work for the sake of beginning another. &#8211; &amp; having
               to start afresh for a new career as often as I reach the goal. And so I suppose it will be, till I break down &amp; founder upon the
               course. But if I live a few years longer, in possession of my faculties I will do great things. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must soon begin to think about my exercise for the Mus: Doc.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s annual
                  New Year&#8217;s Ode as Poet Laureate, part of which would need to be set to music by <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">William Shield</ref>, Master of the King&#8217;s Music, in case it was required to be performed at Court.</note> [MS torn] nothing
               more.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-11-28">28 Nov. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>