<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2829</idno><idno type="nines">rce4100</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2829. Robert Southey to Josiah
               Conder [fragment], 13 August 1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2829.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Eustace R. Conder, Josiah Conder: A Memoir (London, 1857)
                  .  Previously  published: Eustace R. Conder, Josiah Conder: A Memoir
                  (London, 1857), pp. 179–182.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2829" type="letter"><head>2829. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah
               Conder</ref> [fragment], <date when="1816-08-13">13 August 1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Eustace R. Conder, <title>Josiah Conder: A Memoir</title> (London, 1857)<lb/>
                  Previously published: Eustace R. Conder, <title>Josiah Conder: A Memoir</title>
                  (London, 1857), pp. 179–182.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address><date when="1816-08-13">August 13, 1816</date>.</dateline></opener><p rend="indent1"> The date which I have just written reminds me that yesterday
               completed my forty-second year. Few men have lived longer – if the expression may be
               allowed – in the same length of time. I have been married more than twenty years, and
               have experienced, in no common degree, both good and ill; wrongs and benefits,
               happiness and affliction, changes of opinion, loss of dear friends, of parents, and
               of children. I am younger, perhaps, in constitution than in years, but older in
               feelings than in either. Both <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my father</ref>  and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">mother</ref> died at the age of
               fifty. Their deaths, in both instances, were accelerated, if not occasioned, by
               wasting anxieties; but the race is not long-lived, and I do not expect to prove an
               exception to it. I used to pray for continued life; without being weary of life, I
               have ceased to do this. No person could have supplied my place to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s son, who had died on 17 April 1816, had been tutored at
                  home.</note> daughters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Four of Southey’s
                     daughters were still living: <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>.</note> neither require nor admit of the same
               tuition; and as they will be decently provided for after my departure, they can spare
               me, and I need not be solicitous concerning them. </p><p rend="indent1"> Do not mistake me. I possess abundant blessings, and am capable of
               enjoying them. With what feelings I have long contemplated death many of my poems
               will indicate; – it may be seen in “Thalaba,” in “Kehama,” and in “Roderick,”<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801),
                     <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810), and <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                     Goths</title> (1814).</note> – still more in the proem to an unfinished poem,
               written two years ago.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘Proem’ to
                     <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> The late loss which I have
               sustained has not created these feelings, but it has rendered them more vivid. The
               strongest root which fastened me to the world is broken, and I have now more ties in
               heaven than upon earth, I have borne the loss with much self-command, and perfect
               resignation. Common sense, common humanity, some little mixture of pride perhaps, and
               the stoicism which I laid to my heart in youth might have produced the first; and of
               all virtues there is surely none which deserves to be held so cheaply as that of
               resignation to what is inevitable and irremediable. But I hope I have persuaded
               myself feelingly that what has happened is best; that I acquiesce in the
               dispensation, and neither indulge nor acknowledge a wish that it should have been
               otherwise. My will is annihilated, and my heart is strong; but, in spite of that
               outward control which I am constantly able to maintain, recollections will come upon
               me by day and by night, and every hour, which make me feel the weakness of
               philosophy, and the inestimable value of the faith which looks beyond the grave. The
               best teachers are Love and Affliction. Enough, or too much of this. I thought to have
               sent you some remarks on some of your last numbers,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. recent volumes of the <title>Eclectic Review</title>, of
                  which Conder was the editor.</note> but the time went by, and the feeling has
               evaporated. They related to some wrong-headed and mischievous politics (coming, I
               believe, from Foster),<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Baptist
                  minister, essayist and republican John Foster (1770–1843; <title>DNB</title>). He
                  supported parliamentary reform, Catholic emancipation and popular education and
                  opposed the Corn Laws. He was a regular contributor to the
                  <title>Eclectic</title>.</note> and to the unbecoming manner in which the Abbé
               Edgeworth’s memoirs were mentioned . . . <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey objected to the abrupt and ‘unbecoming’ dismissal of <title>Memoirs
                     of the Abbé Edgeworth</title> (1815) in the <title>Eclectic Review</title>,
                  n.s. 5 (February 1816), 173–174: ‘These Memoirs consist chiefly of three or four
                  letters of the Abbé, and his account of the execution of Louis the Sixteenth.
                  Exclusive of what relates to the King’s pedigree, they contain little information
                  that was not long since known by all who have either read or heard of the French
                  Revolution.’</note></p><p rend="indent1"> When we see men doing their duty with heroic devotion, if a
               difference of opinion prevent us from feeling sympathy or expressing admiration, we
               have some reason to suspect that our own opinions are not what they ought to be. I
               can feel equal respect and equal compassion for Madame Roland and Madame Elizabeth,
               for the better part of the Girondists, and the better part of the Vendeans.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The Girondin hostess, Marie-Jeanne Roland de la
                  Platiere (1754–1793), whose <title>Appel a l’Impartiale Posteritè</title> (1795)
                  Southey had admired; the younger sister of Louis XVI (1754–1793; King of France
                  1774–1792), Madame Elizabeth (1764–1794), who refused exile and died on the
                  guillotine; the Girondins were the leading faction in the French Revolution before
                  being displaced by the Jacobins in May–June 1793; the Vendée was a pro-royalist
                  area of North Western France that saw attacks on revolutionaries in 1793–1796 and
                  again in 1815.</note> My mind was not always capable of this equity. In the days
               of Jacobinism I did not like to contemplate the virtues of the Royalist party; and
               when the Queen of France<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Marie Antoinette
                  (1755–1793), Queen of France, executed on 16 October 1793.</note> suffered, I
               strove to qualify or quench the compassion and indignation which I could not help
               feeling at her murder, by dwelling upon her vices and her imputed crimes. In this, as
               in many other things, time has done me good, and taught me to do more justice to
               human nature. In this new <hi rend="ital">Quarterly</hi> I have written upon the
               Vendean war,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 1–69.</note> and upon the Poor.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s ‘On the Poor’, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187–235.</note> For this latter article <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> pays me £100. Chance-hits in literature have
               sometimes produced even more disproportionate profit to the writer; but for a
               deliberate price this is very great, and much more than I should ever have thought of
               asking I conclude this letter after and amid many interruptions. Yours, very
               truly,</p><closer><signed rend="indent1">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed></closer></div></body></text></TEI>