<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3159</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4430</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3159. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 7 July 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3159" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3159.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick
                  Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.93. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3159" type="letter">
        <head>3159. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>,<date when="1818-07-07"> 7 July 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Southey/ Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square London <lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 10 JY 10/ 1818<lb /> Endorsment: July 1818<lb /> MS: Keswick
                  Museum and Art Gallery, KESMG 1996.5.93. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have seen the attack which that blackguard <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> has thought proper to make
               upon me, without the slightest provocation, &#8211; for I have not written a word about the
               election, nor ever spoken about it out of my own family, nor cared three straws for
               the event.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">It was reported in the
                     <title>Courier</title> on 4 July 1818 that Brougham, campaigning as a Whig in
                  the 1818 general election in Westmorland, had attacked Southey and Wordsworth from
                  the hustings on 30 June 1818. </note> Fool as well as liar that he is, he shall
               have his deserts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> has
               stung him to the quick by some masterly letters which tho {rather} above the level of
               electioneering readers <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> has sense enough to understand in their full force.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth, campaigning for his patron, the Earl
                  of Lonsdale, published (anonymously) <title>Two Addresses to the Freeholders of
                     Westmorland</title> (1818).</note> And as <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; myself,
                  <del>be</del> Heaven knows why seem destined to be coupled together like Valentine
               &amp; Orson, or Robin Hood &amp; Little John,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The eponymous heroes of the fifteenth-century French romance &#8211; twin brothers
                  who, after being abandoned in the woods as children and separated, are later
                  reunited. Orson becomes the servant and comrade of Valentine, who had become a
                  knight. Little John, likewise, was the comrade and assistant of the romance&#8211;hero
                  Robin Hood. At the start of his literary career, in the mid 1790s, Southey had
                  planned to publish a volume of poems with Robert Lovell under the pseudonyms
                  &#8216;Orson&#8217; and &#8216;Valentine&#8217;. This did not materialise.</note> this fellow with his
               characteristic imprudence has chosen to make war upon me in return. &#8211; Be it so then!
               War he shall have. I am giving him a <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">WilliamSmithiad</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had responded to an attack on him in parliament by William Smith on
                  14 March 1817 with the pamphlet <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.
                     P.</title> (1817).</note> And when he has received one blow from my hand, he
               will not mistake for it the stroke from any other in future. &#8211; I wish I had been
               present to have given him the lie on the hustings.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was dissuaded from publishing a retort to Brougham that
                  he termed the &#8216;Tender Epistle&#8217;. Parts of it were printed, without mention of
                  Brougham&#8217;s name, in a &#8216;Postscript&#8217; to the second edition of <title>Carmen
                     Triumphale</title> (London, 1821), pp. 45&#8211;53.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> I trust is
               going on well. Give my kindest love to her, what do you call the boy?</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> has
               received his books from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">During his European
                  tour in 1817, Southey had bought, on May&#8217;s behalf, Hippolyte Helyot (1660&#8211;1716),
                     <title>Histoire des Ordres Religieux et Militaires</title> (1792); Edmond
                  Mart&#232;ne (1654&#8211;1739) and Ursin Durand (1682&#8211;1771), <title>Voyage Litteraire de Deux
                     Religieux Benedictins de la Congregation de Saint Maur</title> (1717); and an
                  unidentified work. These books, along with Southey&#8217;s purchases, after many delays,
                  were then left for collection at Longmans.</note> If he should not, desire him to
               make inquiry for them. My only reason for doubt upon the subject, is that I wished
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> to have seen the boxes opened, for the sake of
               separating those <del>wh</del> few which belong to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> &amp; when the <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Grand Dormouse</ref>
               called in <ref type="m" target="places.html#PaternosterRow">the Row</ref> for that purpose, it
               could not be done. So he left his directions with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Patres
                  Nostri</ref>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Longmans business
                  was located in Paternoster Row, London.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Westminster Election has amused me much &#8220;with the humours of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hunt&#8221;.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217;
                  Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), the radical politician, was a candidate for
                  Westminster in the election of 1818. He attracted large crowds to his election
                  meetings but polled only 84 votes. Hunt was from Widdington on Salisbury Plain,
                  rather than Bristol, but he had invested in a Bristol brewery and contested the
                  seat in 1812, christening himself &#8216;Bristol Hunt&#8217;.</note> Certainly that
                  <del>xxxxxxx</del> townsman of ours does no credit to Bristol. He is not game. Did
               you observe that the <hi rend="ital">Maximus Piscis</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               Crompton had nearly come in for some place in Lancashire?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Dr Peter Crompton (1760&#8211;1833) of Eaton House, Liverpool, a
                  wealthy radical who supported John Thelwall in the 1790s and who contested
                  elections at Nottingham (1796, 1807, 1812), Preston (1818) and Liverpool (1820).
                  At Preston in 1818 he won 1245 votes, only 353 votes behind the second elected
                  candidate. In 1804 Crompton had visited Southey in Keswick; see Southey to John
                  Rickman, 6 August 1804, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part
                     Three</title>, Letter 975, where he described Crompton as a &#8216;nondescript fish&#8217;,
                  so &#8216;maximus pisces&#8217; or &#8216;greatest fish&#8217; is undoubtedly an ironic
                  description.</note> I am sorry that <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T. Acland</ref> is
               thrown out.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas Dyke Acland was an
                  independent-minded supporter of the government; he was defeated by a Whig
                  candidate for the county of Devon in 1818, but regained his seat in
               1820.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was very busy upon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles papers<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey refers to a proposed memoir of Robert
                  Walpole (1736&#8211;1810), the British envoy to Portugal 1771&#8211;1800, which John May had
                  suggested.</note> when yesterdays Courier came with Broughams diatribe &amp;
               called me off. The interruption however will not be long. What I have to say will be
               soon said, &#8211; it will be <hi rend="ital">a la ver rot&#238;</hi> which you know is short
               &amp; sweet.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;in the manner that a worm is
                  roasted&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1818-07-07">Tuesday 7 July 1818.</date>
          </p>
          <p> I expect <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> after his hay harvest.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> takes me to
                  task for not having particularly given her love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> &#8211; &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref>.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>