<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2849</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4120</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2849. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 5 October 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2849" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2849.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 215&#8211;218 [in
                  part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2849" type="letter">
        <head>2849. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-10-05">5 October 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
                  Postmark: E/ 8 OC 8/ 1816 <lb /> Seal: black wax, with &#8216;S&#8217;, &#8216;In Labore Quies&#8217; motto
                  below<lb /> Endorsement: Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 8 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.
                  1816<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 215&#8211;218 [in
                  part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-10-05">5 Oct. 1816.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not looked with impatience for farther news from you, because
               whatever news you might have to send, I must needs finish a paper in time for the
               present number &#8211; for the love of 100 &#163;.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was reviewing a series of volumes by travellers in England. The piece
                  appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 537&#8211;574, under
                  the title &#8216;Works on England&#8217;.</note> I have no intention of going to London unless
               there be a necessity for it. Application was made to me thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch</ref> some months ago to revise a great
               book by Raffles upon the island of Java before it goes to press,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas Stamford Raffles (1781&#8211;1826;
                     <title>DNB</title>), founder of Singapore and author of a <title>History of
                     Java</title> (1817).</note> &#8211; I leant ear to it for the lucre of gain, but have
               heard nothing more; &#8211; had it come to anything it might have brought me to town in
               November, but if I could be as well employed <hi rend="ital">quoad</hi>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;In respect of&#8217;.</note> money at home (which seems
               likely) in other respects <del>the</del> {home} employment would be better. I could
               wish myself independent of such considerations &#8211; if it were worth a wish as long as
               ones necessities are supplied. It is my fate to have more claimants upon me than
               usually fall to <del>a mans</del> {the} share of a man who has a family of his own, &#8211;
               &amp; if <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> circumstances could
               be mended by a lift in his profession,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom
                  Southey was working (not very successfully) as a farmer; Southey suggests here
                  that he could be given some employment in the Navy, in which, though he had been a
                  Captain since 1811, he had never commanded a ship.</note> &#8211; it would be a relief
               to me as well as to him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> That I shall make an appeal to the good sense of the country upon the
               existing state of things &amp; the prospect before us, is very likely since my
               attention has been thus called to it. Indeed if there be a probability of doing good
                  <del>by it</del>, there seems little reason for any further stimulus, &amp; the
               thing may be done certainly as well, &amp; perhaps more becomingly without any
               farther intimation from the Powers Above.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">See
                  Southey&#8217;s letters to Grosvenor Charles Bedford,7, 8 and 10 September 1816 (Letters
                  2835, 2836 and 2839) for the ministerial suggestion that Southey should be
                  employed to write, or edit a journal, attacking the government&#8217;s critics. Southey
                  had declined and was contemplating writing a book on the &#8216;State of the
                  Nation&#8217;.</note> I incline at present to write anonymously, &#8211; or under some
               fictitious name, &#8211; for were the book to attract notice (&amp; if it does not it
                  <del>is</del> will be useless) &#8211; a mystery about the author would very much
               increase its sale. In that case a change of publishers <del>will</del> would
               contribute to keep the secret, &#8211; &amp; if I seek a new one Nicol<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Nicol (d. 1855?), a friend of
                  Bedford&#8217;s.</note> would obviously be the man. In meditating upon this work I grow
               ambitious, &amp; think of presenting such a view of things as whether it produce
               immediate benefit or not, may <del>be</del> have a permanent value both for matter
               &amp; composition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Pray inform me with the least possible delay whether as P. L.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Poet Laureate.</note> I am exempt from serving
               parish Offices, the people of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> having this day thrust honour upon me in the Office of
                  Surveyor<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">All parishes had a duty, under
                  legislation of 1555, to repair public highways within the parish boundaries. Since
                  1691 they were obliged to appoint a Surveyor of Highways, an office that was held
                  for one year, but whose acceptance was compulsory. The duties were often avoided
                  but could be very onerous, including organising parishioners to fulfil their
                  statutory duty to provide six days labour to repair the roads.</note> &#8211; (what the
               Devil it means they best know) <del>but</del> my appeal against the appointment must
               be made on the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this month. Whatever the office be I have
               neither knowledge, leisure, or inclination for it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very glad you are Quarterlizing me.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford drafted a review of Southey&#8217;s Laureate poems for the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, but it was not published.</note> Abuse does
               good, &amp; of that I have plenty, &#8211; but praise is more useful; &amp; is not so
               liberally bestowed. I have seen a number of the Champion in which my name stands for
               text to a <del>diss</del> sermon nothing relating to me; &#8211; but at the conclusion it
               is said that the change in my opinions as implied in my last writings is that I
               recommend implicit submission, &#8211; hence it should appear that the said Champion had
               not read those writings.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is here
                  referring to two articles, titled &#8216;Mr Southey&#8217;, by &#8216;The Itinerant&#8217; in <title>The
                     Champion</title>, 15 September and 29 September 1816, particularly the second
                  article.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt</ref> I know incessantly attack me, (&#8211;
               I have a good name for the latter Sir Tarquin of the <hi rend="ital">Round
                  Table</hi>,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Hazlitt, early in 1817,
                  republished a number of his essays for Hunt&#8217;s <title>Examiner</title> in a book
                  with the Arthurian title <title>The Round Table</title>. These included his
                  critical &#8216;Observations&#8217; on Wordsworth&#8217;s 1814 poem <title>The Excursion</title>. In
                  the Arthurian legends, Sir Tarquin was a treacherous knight who fought against his
                  former friends. The Lake poets considered themselves betrayed by Hazlitt, having
                  hosted him at Greta Hall in 1803 and assisted him in escaping from the anger of
                  the townsfolk after he caused a furore in a Keswick inn by spanking a local woman
                  when she laughed at his advances.</note> &#8211; he &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref> advertising Essays under that title)
               this barking makes a noise, &amp; noise calls attention; &#8211; so that as long as they
               have it not in their power to pass sentence upon me as a
                  counter-revolutionist<del>s</del>, such enmity is in its degree useful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The children<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s four
                  surviving daughters: <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith
                     May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>.</note> thank God are well,
               &amp; so am I as far <del>t</del> as the husk is <del>x</del> concerned: &#8211; but the
               interior is as unlike what it was twelvemonths ago as the darkest November day is
               unlike the bright sunshine of a genial May morning. Time enough has not yet elapsed
               to make me feel that if <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">H.</ref>
               were living he would no longer be the H <del>whom</del> from whom I am separated for
                  life.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Southey had died on 17 April
                  1816.</note> When this comes to be the case the retrospect will be less painful.
               At present whenever I relapse into recollection of what has been, &amp; every hour
               brings with it something that calls up these thoughts <del>every object &amp; every
                  xxxxxxxx</del> it is an effort to <del>abstain</del> refrain from tears. I go
               about my business as usual, &#8211; perform the ordinary functions of life, &#8211; see company,
               &#8211; go <del>out</del> visiting, &#8211; take <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> up the mountains, &#8211; talk, &#8211; reason, &#8211; jest, &#8211; but my <del>thoug</del>
          <hi rend="ital"> heart</hi> meanwhile is haunted, &amp; tho thank God I neither
               undervalue the uses of <del>my</del> this world nor wish in any way to shrink from my
               part in it, &#8211; I could be right willing to say <hi rend="ital">Valete</hi>.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Farewell&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is too deep a strain, &#8211; give me my cap &amp; bells! the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> is building <ref type="m" target="places.html#RosthwaitePlace">a house in Borrowdale</ref>, &amp; the river
               comes to visit her there. I recommend a life boat, a life-preserver, a cork
               under-waistcoat to be slept in, &#8211; &amp; some lessons in swimming. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.</ref> would not go up
               Causey Pike with us, <del>I say</del> she has been upon the Stool of Repentance ever
               since, &amp; this is a subject of much dispute between us. <del>She obstinately
                  denies that she is upon the Stool, &amp;</del> I say she is upon the Stool; &amp;
               she denies it; &amp; I persist, &amp; she grows angry, &amp; then I pity her for
               being upon the Stool, &amp; then she calls me names, &#8211; &amp; so we go on, &amp; I
               condole with her upon her present condition (being almost as pitiable as <del>that
                  sh</del> the Nincompoopery in which she once existed six whole weeks,) &#8211; &amp; I
               threaten her with a letter of condolence from you upon the subject, &#8211; &amp; then her
               indignation falls upon you. Indeed I believe it would be unsafe for any person to
               mention the word Stool in her hearing.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you send me some money? &#8211; I am <hi rend="ital">pauper &amp;
                  inops</hi>.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Poor and in want&#8217;.</note>
               The next number will float me.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">In
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 299&#8211;345, Southey reviewed
                  Domingo Badia y Leblich (1766&#8211;1818), <title>Travels of Ali Bey in Morocco,
                     Tripoli, Cyprus, Egypt, Arabia, Syria, and Turkey, Between the Years 1803 and
                     1807</title> (1816); and, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816),
                  537&#8211;574, a series of volumes by travellers in England, under the title &#8216;Works on
                  England&#8217;. This issue did not appear until 12 November 1816, though, thus delaying
                  Southey&#8217;s payment.</note> &#8211; I have a thousand things to say to you if you were
               here, &#8211; &amp; have planned many expeditions into the vales &amp; up the mountains
               when next you come. Remember me to all at home.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>