<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2692</idno><idno type="nines">rce3963</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2692. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 7 January
                  1816</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2692.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 149. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2692" type="letter"><head>2692. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1816-01-07">7 January
                  1816</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298
                  <lb/>Postmarks: [both partial] 10 o’Clock/ JA 10/ 1816; E/ 10 JA <lb/>MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 149. ALS; 4p.
                  <lb/>Unpublished.</note></head><p rend="indent1"> Ever since my return my chief employment has been rhyming – which I hope has been done to a good tune; – <del>xxx</del>
               the work has grown under my hands, &amp; is not yet compleated.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> I call it “<hi rend="ital">A</hi> Poets Pilgrimage to the Field of
               Belle Alliance” (<hi rend="ital">A</hi> or <hi rend="ital">The</hi> as any one may happen to like best who will give an opinion upon
               such a subject.) This evening I have finished the fourth part, which makes between 8 &amp; 900 lines in all.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey probably meant that he had drafted the ‘Proem’ and Books 1–3 of Part One of the poem (840 lines in the
                  published version). But he was nowhere near finishing; the poem grew to include another Book in Part One and four Books in Part Two,
                  though the ‘hymn for victory’ was not written.</note> there are yet two more parts to be written, &amp; perhaps a hymn for victory
               to conclude with. The sooner it is published the better, but I shall not for that reason push Pegasus<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> In Greek mythology Pegasus was a winged horse; the fountain Hippocrene on Mount Helicon was created from his
                  hoof-print and all who drank from it received poetic inspiration.</note> beyond his speed, – for tho the occasion be temporary I
               have endeavoured to make something which shall {not} prove a mere temporary poem. It is in the six-lined stanza (like the story of
                  Gualbertos<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> ‘St. Juan Gualberto’, first published in <title>Annual Anthology</title>, 2 vols
                  (Bristol, 1799–1800), II, pp. 1–19.</note>) – a form which naturally induces a tint of language in keeping with the title of a
               Pilgrimage. I hope there will be no delay about the engravings. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">My fellow traveller</ref>
               who gives me the drawings lives next door to Burn,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burn (1750–1821) was a friend of the
                  Southeys from their days in Portugal. A member of the Lisbon Factory, he was well-known to Herbert Hill and John May and had first
                  met Southey in Lisbon in 1796. He moved to London in 1806.</note> &amp; I have desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> to commence an acquaintance with him, – the latter as my fact-otum being to convey them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. Some of the subjects are sufficiently picturesque, &amp; these prints will give an
               interest to the book.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Seven engravings of places around which the fighting at the Battle of
                  Waterloo (18 June 1815) centred, after drawings by Nash, appeared in <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>
                  (London,1816) as a frontispiece and between pp. 56–57, pp. 62–63, pp. 68–69, pp. 70–71, pp. 88–89, and pp. 90–91.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I have heard nothing from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref> since we left him,
               &amp; this I regret, for I wish much to know how your leg is; – the weather has been very unfavourable at one time; &amp; you I fear
               are not disposed to allow the part that rest which it requires.</p><p rend="indent1"> Two divisions of my foreign purchases have arrived in England, &amp; left London a week ago in one of <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Vardons</ref> ships for Newcastle. Vardon says the Acta Sanctorum are among
                  them.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey hoped he had bought the 53–volume compendium of hagiographies, <title>Acta
                     Sanctorum </title>(1643–1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. To his disappointment, he had only bought the
                  6–volume abridgement (1783–1794), no. 152 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> I wish this so much, that I doubt it for two
               weighty reasons (he not being a man who knows the Acts of the Saints from the Acts of the Sinners) – the bookseller was to draw on me
               for payment for them, &amp; of this no intimation has reached me; – &amp; I do not think so large a set of books (52 weighty folios)
               would come in one case, especially as my other purchases from the same man<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Baptiste Ver
                  Beyst (1770–1849), a famous Brussels bookseller.</note> were themselves of considerable bulk – more than 100 volumes, some thirty
               being folio or quarto. I am anxious for their arrival, many of them being very curious books</p><p rend="indent1"> Your Lewis Guicciardini will help me to a few notes, – a great assistance this to a lean book, which must needs have a
               substantive shape.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey provided notes from Luigi Guicciardini (1521–1589), <title>Belgicae,
                     sive Inferioris Germaniae, Descriptio</title> (1613) in <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (London, 1816), pp. 202,
                  205.</note> My journal had better not be cut up for this purpose more than is absolutely necessary; – it will turn to much better
               account as a post obit<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey means that the manuscript journal he kept on his 1815 tour of
                  the Netherlands and Belgium should not be mined too heavily to provide notes to <title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>
                  (1816) because to do so would diminish its value to his family as a posthumous publication. The journal was finally published as
                     <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902).</note></p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> has compleatly recovered; Cumberland air, &amp; her usual house &amp;
               habits soon set all to rights again. So long an intermission of her lessons has had no ill effect, except that she had a little music
               to recover, which I care nothing about; She reads Caesar<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Julius Caesar (100–44 BC),
                     <title>Commentarii de Bello Gallico</title>, a text used to teach those beginning to learn Latin.</note> as well as I did at her
               age, &amp; reads off the Inca Garcilaso<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Garcilaso de la Vega (1539–1616), <title>Commentarios
                     Reales que Tratan del Origen de los Yncas</title> (1609), no. 3800 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> into
               English with the utmost fluency. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> began Homer with the new year, &amp;
               as soon as the Saxon Chronicle is published, he &amp; I are to begin it together.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> A copy of
                  the ‘Anglo-Saxon Chronicle’, so that Southey and Herbert could study Old English. In 1815 ‘A new edition of the Saxon Chronicle,
                  with an English translation and notes’, edited by James Ingram (1774–1850; <title>DNB</title>), Rawlinsonian Professor of
                  Anglo-Saxon at Oxford 1803–1808, was advertised as ‘in the press’, <title>The Tradesman</title>, 14 (January 1815), 55. However, it
                  did not appear until 1823. Southey had two copies, nos 2593–2594 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> How easily are
               languages acquired in youth, if no needless difficulties are placed in the way!</p><p rend="indent1"> You saw my set of Vondels works, the Dutch poet. He has one drama upon the fall of Lucifer &amp; another upon the fall
               of man.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey possessed 11 volumes of the various works of Joost van den Vondel (1587–1679),
                  no. 3091 in the sale catalogue of his library. Vondel’s plays included <title>Lucifer</title> (1654), <title>Adam in
                     Ballingschap</title> (1664) and <title>Samson of Heilige Wraeck</title> (1660). Whether Vondel influenced John Milton’s
                  (1608–1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667) and <title>Samson Agonistes</title> (1671) or the similarities
                  between the two poets’ works are attributable to their sharing of similar sources, is still debated.</note> Whether Milton had read
               them I shall see, but that Milton was acquainted with his Tragedy of Samson appears to me from a <del>very</del> cursory glance at
               parts of this composition beyond a doubt.</p><p rend="indent1"> The second volume of Park,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mungo Park (1771–1806; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Travels in the Interior Districts of Africa: Performed in the Years 1795, 1796, and 1797, with an Account of a Subsequent
                     Mission to that Country in 1805</title>, 2 vols (1816).</note> which is to keep company with <del>xx</del> the first upon your
               shelves, is I believe on its way to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. I shall find an opportunity of sending it
               to its proper place.</p><p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the Ursine<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey referred to his cousins, Hill’s children, Edward, Herbert, Erroll and Alfred, as ‘the bears’. Edward Hill,
                  the eldest, was ‘Ursa Major’.</note> nobility. I hope the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Ursa Major</ref> goes on
               well with his Latin, &amp; can speak Cousin Oberts name as if it began with an R. Tell him he must not be such a Ougue as to ob my name
               of a letter. Love from both the Ediths,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> and Edith May Southey.</note> I am desired to say that your
                  elegancies<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> Upper stocks – trousers reaching from the waist to the knee; and nether stocks –
                  hose reaching from knee to ankle. Garments favoured by Herbert Hill.</note> are in hand – whether <del>or not</del> they will set
               the fashion in these remote parts <del>is doubtf</del> may be doubted.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1816-01-07">7 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1816</date></closer></div></body></text></TEI>