<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3024</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4295</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3024. Robert Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 17 September 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3024.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Art Library, London, MS
                  Forster 48 D.32 MS 29. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                     New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York,
                  1965), II, pp. 173&#8211;174.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3024" type="letter">
        <head>3024. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1817-09-17">17 September 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Como/ Italy.<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298;
                  ANGLETERRE<lb /> Postmark: P/ 25/ 17<lb /> MS: National Art Library, London, MS
                  Forster 48 D.32 MS 29. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                     <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York,
                  1965), II, pp. 173&#8211;174.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-09-17">17 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
               1817</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have sent you the collected edition of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> poems, his Excursion, his
               White Doe, <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Kosters</ref> Travels in
               Brazil, &amp; the first &amp; second volumes of my History of that country.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Reading for Landor during his residence in
                  Italy: Wordsworth, <title>Poems by William Wordsworth: Including Lyrical Ballads,
                     and the Miscellaneous Pieces of the Author</title> (1815), <title>The
                     Excursion</title> (1814), <title>The White Doe of Rylstone</title> (1815);
                  Henry Koster, <title>Travels in Brazil</title> (1816); Robert Southey,
                     <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> They are directed to the
               care of Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Mirabaud,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably the firm of Jacques Mirabaud (1784&#8211;1864), a Swiss banker who had set up
                  a branch of the family business in Milan in 1814.</note> &#8211; &amp; shipt on board a
               vessel for Genoa, &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>
               {people} have sent me word of the shipment, &amp; stupidly enough have neglected to
               specify the name of the vessel. &#8211; I judged rightly of the attempt at revolution in
               Brazil; &#8211; the Isaac Ribeiro Person of the Lugano gazette proved to be as I feared,
               Padre Joam Ribeiro Pessoa,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Gazzetta
                     di Lugano</title> (1814&#8211;1821) was a liberal weekly newspaper, widely read in
                  Switzerland and northern Italy. It had carried a slightly garbled report of the
                  death of Joam Ribeiro Pessoa de Melo Montenegro (1766&#8211;1817), a priest who was a
                  member of the provisional government set up during a revolt against Portuguese
                  rule in Pernambuco, 8 March&#8211;18 May 1817. He committed suicide in the town of
                  Paulista after the defeat of the revolutionary forces and the fall of Recife, the
                  provincial capital.</note> &#8211; from whom I was expecting communications upon several
               important points. He has paid the penalty of rashness, &#8211; &amp; I believe by his own
               hand. <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> has sent over a
               full account of the troubles; the revolutionists when they became desperate proposed
               to set fire to the city, &amp; massacre the royalists who were in their power, &#8211;
               &amp; it was in great measure by <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Kosters</ref> exertions, &amp; influence with them, that they abstained from thus
               closing their miserable career. Nothing could be more ill-judged than the attempt,
               &amp; nothing more injurious to Brazil.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our journey home was as prosperous as we could desire. The Lake of
               Lugano seemed to exceed <del>Como</del> the Laris in variety &amp; in beauty, &amp;
               the Maggiore where we crost it to exceed both: &#8211; but probably in such scenery that
               which is present must always obtain the preference. The Isola Bella<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The entire island of Isola Bella in Lake Maggiore is
                  taken up by the seventeenth-century palace of the Borromeo family and its
                  gardens.</note> is at once the most costly &amp; the most absurd effort of bad
               taste that ever has been produced by wealth &amp; extravagance. What you had been
               told of the hissing of serpents in the vaults proved to be the noise of the Bats, who
               have taken possession of the ground-tier in this ridiculous place. We saw them in
               great numbers flying in &amp; out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Taking all things into consideration I should prefer the
               neighbourhood of Lausanne to any place on the continent which I have seen, for a
               residence. The loveliest places which we saw were the little tract between the Lakes
               of Thun &amp; Brientz, &#8211; &amp; the Lake &amp; valley of Lungern, than which the heart
               of man could desire nothing lovelier. On my return <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> did not appear to have lost any thing
               in magntitude, &#8211; the mountains around the Lake had, &amp; <del>there seem</del> I
               perceived a poverty &amp; coldness in the valley: this however wore off in a few
               days, &amp; <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is now as
               beautiful as ever.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I sent your letter to Munday<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Munday (c. 1773&#8211;1844), the Oxford-based bookseller, printer and publisher
                  of Landor&#8217;s <title>Idyllia Nova Quinque Heroum atque Heroidum</title> (1815).
                  Landor was to complain vociferously that Munday had not sent copies of the poem to
                  himself or his friends.</note> in a frank, but have heard nothing of the poems in
               consequence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The prospect of affairs in England is better than when I left it. The
               acquittal of those scoundrels<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">James Watson
                  (1766&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>) was acquitted of a charge of high treason
                  following a trial on 9&#8211;16 June 1817. He was accused of instigating the attempted
                  revolution arising from the Spa Fields meeting on 2 December 1816. Following his
                  acquittal his three co-accused, Arthur Thistlewood (1774&#8211;1820;
                  <title>DNB</title>), Thomas Preston (1774&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>) and John
                  Hooper (dates unknown) were released without trial.</note> did not produce the
               reaction which might have been apprehended from it; &amp; tho the seditious press is
               as active as ever, the poison which it administers does not operate with the same
               effect upon a full stomach as upon an empty one. The harvest, generally speaking, is
               safe, &amp; most abundant: even here another week or ten days of such weather as we
               have had for the last fortnight will bring it all in. Trade has revived, &#8211; so we
               shall have an interval of tranquillity, &#8211; if we know how to profit by it. Some thing
               will be done about the Poor Laws next session, &amp; from the report of the Committee
               (which has been drawn up by Sturges Bourne<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William Sturges Bourne (1769&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), MP for various seats
                  1802&#8211;1831, Secretary to the Treasury 1804&#8211;1806, Lord of the Treasury 1807&#8211;1809,
                  Commissioner of the Board of Control 1814&#8211;1816, 1818&#8211;1822, Home Secretary 1827,
                  First Commissioner of Woods and Forests 1827&#8211;1828. He was one of Canning&#8217;s closest
                  allies. Sturges Bourne chaired a Select Committee on the Poor Laws appointed in
                  1817 (and reappointed 1818&#8211;1819), which recommended abolishing poor relief for the
                  able-bodied unless it was delivered through the workhouse, pauper schools for
                  those on relief aged 3&#8211;14 and the introduction of a loans system for those who had
                  &#8216;squandered&#8217; their earnings. The latter proposal was eventually included in an Act
                  of 1819.</note>) there is reason to believe that it will be done wisely. Indeed I
               look to the gradual extinction of these laws, &amp; the restoration of that English
               character in the lower classes which, of late years, they have been so rapidly
               destroying.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have done little since my return, &#8211; this being the season of
               idleness. But there is a busy winter before me, during which, if no ill fortune
               intervene, I hope &amp; expect to make great progress in many things. Here is one of
               my Inscriptions. &#8211; Busaco<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">At the battle of
                  Bussaco, on 27 September 1810, an Anglo-Portuguese force successfully defended a
                  ten mile ridge against a French army that was attempting to invade Portugal. For
                  Southey&#8217;s account, see <title>Edinburgh Annual Register for 1810</title>, 3.1
                  (1812), 462&#8211;463; <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1823&#8211;32), II, pp. 751&#8211;757. The poem was published as &#8216;For the Deserto de Busaco&#8217;,
                     <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), III, pp.
                  136&#8211;137.</note> is the place</p>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">Reader, thou standest upon holy ground</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Which Penitence hath chosen for itself,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And War disturbing the deep solitude</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Hath left it doubly sacred.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A Carmelite monastery was founded at Bussaco in 1628, and renowned for its
                     walled enclosure (&#8216;Deserto&#8217;) enclosing an arboretum.</note> On these
                  heights</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The host of Portugal &amp; England stood</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Against the French arrayed, when Massena,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Proud of Rodrigo &amp; Almeida won,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Napoleonic Marshal Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817) led the French
                     campaign against Portugal in 1810 and 1811. His army captured Ciudad Rodrigo on
                     9 July 1810 and Almeida on 27 August 1810.</note>
          </l>
          <l rend="indent3">[MS torn]st forward, thinking the devoted realm</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Full sure should fall a prey. He in his pride</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Scorn&#8217;d the poor numbers of the English foe,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And deemd the children of the land would fly</l>
          <l rend="indent3">From his advance like sheep before the wolf</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Scattering, &amp; lost with terror. Ill he knew</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The Lusitanian spirit! ill he knew</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The <del>heart, the arm</del> {arm the heart} of England! ill he
                  knew</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Wellington</ref>! &#8211; He learnt to know them here.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">That spirit &amp; that arm, that heart, that mind</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Here on Busaco gloriously approved,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">When hence repelld the beaten boaster wound</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Below his course circuitous, &amp; left</l>
          <l rend="indent3">His thousands for the beasts &amp; ravenous fowl</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The Carmelite who in his cell recluse</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Was wont to sit &amp; from the skull receive </l>
          <l rend="indent3">Death&#8217;s silent lesson, wheresoeer he walk</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Henceforth may find his teachers. He shall find</l>
          <l rend="indent3">The Frenchmans bones in glen &amp; grove, on rock</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And height, whereer the wolves &amp; carrion birds</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Have strewn them, washd in torrents, bare &amp; bleachd</l>
          <l rend="indent3">By sun &amp; rain, &amp; by the winds of heaven.</l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="center"> _____</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our journalists are puzzled to understand for what reason Russia is
               likely to interfere in behalf of Spain against the revolutionary governments in S
                  America.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Britain and Russia were the two
                  greatest world powers following the defeat of France in 1815. Essentially, Britain
                  wished for a weak Spanish government that could not challenge British influence in
                  Portugal or the Mediterranean or prevent Britain dominating trade with the Latin
                  American countries in revolt against Spain. Russia took the opposite view, hoping
                  a stronger Spanish government would obstruct Britain in southern Europe and ensure
                  that trade with Latin America was open to all powers equally. At this time there
                  were widespread newspaper reports that Russia would aid Spain in regaining its
                  Latin American colonies. These may have been stimulated by rumours concerning a
                  secret agreement between Russia and Spain of 11 August 1817, under which Russia
                  agreed to sell eight warships to Spain.</note> They do not perceive that Russia
               has possessions in the N. W. <del>America</del> {coast}, &amp; that the
               Yankee-Americans (we must not call them <hi rend="ital">Anglo</hi>-Americans) are
               regarded equally by both powers as interlopers on that coast.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The Russian-American Company, founded in 1799, had
                  fur-trading colonies on the coast of Alaska and as far south as Fort Ross,
                  California. The Spanish Crown claimed ownership of California as part of Mexico
                  and both countries were in competition with United States fur traders, who had
                  arrived overland from the east, and with the British Hudson&#8217;s Bay Company. </note>
          <del>Nor do I</del> The price of this assistance from Russia will be a partition
               treaty, <del>limiting</del> {defining} the bounds of New Mexico, &amp; leaving all
               beyond those bounds to Russia. &#8211; There is no getting at the real state of affairs in
               Spanish-America, but as far as I can judge, Spain is likely to prove victorious in
               Mexico &amp; in Venezuela.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Revolts against
                  Spain had been ongoing in Mexico since 1810 and Venezuela since 1811, but in both
                  areas Spanish forces had the upper hand in 1817. </note> Peru &amp; Chile must
               follow the fate of B Ayres, &#8211; which will yield more easily to a Spanish army than it
               did to an English one.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1806 a British
                  expedition took Buenos Aires but was soon repulsed, and a further expedition in
                  1807 was easily defeated by local citizens. The area had been effectively
                  self-governing since 1810 and had declared independence in 1816. Peru and Chile
                  were still largely under Spanish control at this time.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>