<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2935</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4206</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2935. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 7 March 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2935" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2935.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                  4812D. ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2935" type="letter">
        <head>2935. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1817-03-07">7 March 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Hamilton Place/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmark: FREE/ 10 MR 10/ 1817<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                  4812D. ALS; 3p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have taken a great deal of trouble for me, &#8211; &amp; I feel
               sincerely obliged for it. The amended affidavit cannot be sworn till tomorrow.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had learned that <title>Wat
                     Tyler</title>, a radical play he had written in 1794, had been published
                  without his consent. His affidavit was part of his legal action to obtain an
                  injunction to prevent the play&#8217;s circulation.</note> A Master of Chancery<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Masters in Chancery were solicitors who
                  carried out routine duties for suits in the Court of Chancery, including taking
                  affidavits.</note> comes here from Cockermouth once a week &amp; Saturday is his
               day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> I see gave me
               credit for being &#8216;high in the confidence of his M. Ministers.&#8221;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey may be referring to Brougham&#8217;s speech in the House of
                  Commons on 24 February 1817, when he contrasted the unwillingness of the
                  government to prosecute Southey&#8217;s early radical play, <title>Wat Tyler</title>,
                  for sedition, with its eagerness to pursue radical publications.</note> &#8211; This
               will give some support to a ridiculous opinion {which} already prevails so as to
                  <del>annoy me with</del> {occasion many annoying} applications, that I am not only
               a very wealthy but a very important personage. &#8211; My place of residence, &amp; my
               habits of life are oddly suited for a Courtier, &#8211; &amp; a politician!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a letter to night from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref>, written from Birmingham,
               on his way to London, ( &#8211; unless he should pick up an engagement on the road). In
               town he says he shall be sure of a good dinner whilst the Clive family<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the family of Edward Clive, 1st Earl of
                  Powis (1754&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), army officer, Governor of Madras 1798&#8211;1803
                  and leading landowner and politician in the Welsh Borders.</note> stay &#8211; with whom
               has he ingratiated himself there? Oh if those talents of his had <del>been</del>
               taken a right course; what another <hi rend="ital">right hand</hi> should I have
               found in him! &#8211; I know not how better to serve him, nor indeed in what other way,
               than by helping him from time to time in his present course, without letting him
                  <del>x</del> in any manner rely upon me, which, to do him justice, he has never
               shown any disposition to do.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He tells me that in Wolverhampton, Bilston &amp; that neighbourhood
               &#8220;the inhabitants seem strongly tinctured with the poison infused by the various
               inflammatory publications dispersed among them; &amp; by the institution of twopenny
               clubs, where the deleterious rhapsodies of <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> are poured into their greedy
               ears.&#8221; &#8211; Unless some means be devised of punishing such <del>fellows as</del>
               libellers as this in such a manner as may prevent the repetition of the offence, &#8211;
               all other measures must be nugatory. I know not how this is to be done unless it be
               by transportation, &amp; trusting to the spirit of the times for remitting that
               punishment in cases where it could be too severe.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry for Horners<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Horner (1778&#8211;1817; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish barrister and
                  economist; Whig MP for St Ives 1806&#8211;1807, Wendover 1807&#8211;1812, St Mawes 1813&#8211;1817.
                  He died on 8 February 1817. He was one of the founders of the <title>Edinburgh
                     Review</title> in 1802, but had supported Spanish opposition to France in
                  1808&#8211;1813, which may have softened Southey&#8217;s opinion of him. Horner&#8217;s meal with
                  Southey probably occurred on 19 October 1805, when Southey entertained Jeffrey,
                  after sharing the coach from Scotland with him.</note> death, &#8211; he supt with me
               here many years ago &amp; left upon me a much more favourable impression than his
               companions, of whom <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> was one. I thought
               him a mild, even-minded man. And indeed in these days it is no light merit for a
               member of the H. C. to maintain that character. You have men who carry the manners as
               well as the principles of the N. Convention<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The National Convention, the single assembly chamber which ruled France
                  1792&#8211;1795, during the period of The Terror.</note> there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope you will be in town the latter end of April during the time of
               my transit.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1817-03-07">7 March. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>