<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2732</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4003</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2732. Robert Southey to Hew
                  Dalrymple, 6 March 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2732" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2732.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of
                  Scotland, Acc. 10698. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2732" type="letter">
        <head>2732. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Hew
                  Dalrymple</ref>, <date when="1816-03-06">6 March 1816</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Sir Hew Dalrymple, Bart/ &amp;c
                  &amp;c &amp;c/ 23. Upper Wimpole Street/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
                  Postmark: E/ 9 MR 9/ 1816<lb /> Seal: [partial] red wax; arm raising aloft cross of
                  Lorraine<lb /> Watermark: J DICKINSON &amp; CO/ 1811<lb /> MS: National Library of
                  Scotland, Acc. 10698. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-03-06">6 March. 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is but four &amp; twenty hours since your letter of Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 12 came to my hands, inclosed in a parcel from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Murray</ref>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had the honour of receiving your former communications. Addressed
               as they were to the Writer of a paper in the Quarterly Review, I did not feel myself
               called upon to reply to them, &amp; therefore avoided a task which could not but be
                  painful.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> In his first article on the
                  &#8216;Life of Wellington&#8217;, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (April 1815),
                  215&#8211;275, especially at 242&#8211;243, Southey had criticised the conduct of Dalrymple
                  when, arriving in Portugal as commanding officer, he had, at the Convention of
                  Cintra, signed 30 August 1808, allowed a defeated French army free passage out of
                  the country with its weapons and supplies intact. Dalrymple responded by writing
                  to the <title>Quarterly Review</title> and then sending Southey papers giving his
                  version of events.</note> On no occasion have I ever felt myself more painfully
               embarrassed than in replying now to this personal address. There is in it a tone of
               wounded feeling, expressed in a manner so manly &amp; so devoid of all irritation,
                  <del>that</del> as to command my sincere respect, but my opinion of the Convention
               of Cintra remains unaltered.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> After a
                  national outcry in Britain over the Convention of Cintra (1808), a Court of
                  Inquiry was appointed and sat 14 November&#8211;27 December 1808, but it failed to
                  punish its authors, Dalrymple and Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813;
                  <title>DNB</title>). They were, however, never afterwards given command and
                  Southey fully endorsed the dim view that the Inquiry took of Dalrymple and
                  Burrard&#8217;s conduct.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are some points upon which you have corrected errors into which
               I had fallen: these shall be carefully rectified in the great work upon which I am
                  engaged.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                     the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 576&#8211;581,
                  delivered a measured verdict on the Convention of Cintra (1808), balancing its
                  &#8216;military advantages&#8217; against &#8216;some political errors&#8217; (p. 577).</note> In
               particular what you say of the Bishop &amp; Junta of Porto is of importance. I can
               easily imagine that the publication of your documents upon that subject in the Report
               of the Inquiry might have been imprudent; but I perceive also that it might have
               established the propriety of the political measures which you pursued; &amp; readily
               admit that any error in the manner of <del>xxxx</del> restoring the Regency becomes
               of inferior moment.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Minutes of
                     the Proceedings of the Court of Inquiry upon the Treaty of Armistice and
                     Convention of Cintra</title> (1808), although it did not publish Dalrymple&#8217;s
                  documents, made it clear that, (p. 34) on the evacuation of the French occupying
                  army, he resisted the attempts of Antonio de Sao Jose de Castro (1754&#8211;1843), the
                  Bishop of Oporto, and the Junta set up in that city in June 1808, to be recognised
                  as the rulers of Portugal, in the interests of restoring the authority of John VI
                  (1767&#8211;1826), Regent of Portugal 1799&#8211;1816, King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826. Dalrymple
                  felt that much of the hostility to him in Portugal derived from his attitude on
                  this issue.</note> &#8211; The mistake of Oviedo for Oporto originated in one of the
               many misprints in the folio Report: being accustomed always to think of the latter
               word in its Portugueze form without the O. the possible mistake did not occur to me,
               as it ought to have done, until the absurdity of the erroneous statement was
                  considered.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The misidentification is
                  made in Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;Life of Wellington&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                  13 (April 1815), 215&#8211;275 (243).</note> With regard to the stipulation concerning
               the Russian fleet, the observations in the Edinburgh Annual Register expressly refer
               to the Armistice, &#8211; not to the Convention.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  In <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 357&#8211;381,
                  Southey had criticised the conduct of the armistice with the French troops in
                  Portugal that preceded the Convention of Cintra (1808). The bearing which the
                  presence of the Russian fleet had on Dalrymple and Burrard&#8217;s actions is discussed
                  at p. 366. There was a Russian fleet at anchor in Lisbon and while Russia was an
                  ally of France, it was not at war with Portugal. Admiral Dmitri Senyavin
                  (1763&#8211;1831) insisted he would resist an attempt by the British fleet to take
                  Lisbon, but he did not aid the French troops on land.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My own deliberate judgement upon the whole transaction, in all its
               bearings, I must not conceal. But no man can be more desirous of discharging
               faithfully the duty of an historian. I will state your views of the subject as fully,
               as distinctly &amp; as forcibly as is in my power; &amp; I will not fail to point out
               the advantages which resulted from having dispossessed the French of Almeida &amp;
               Elvas, &#8211; the possession of either of which points <del>would</del> {might} probably
               have led to their occupation of Lisbon in the ensuing spring.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> These towns were gained by the British at the Convention of
                  Cintra (1808).</note> And in delivering <del>the</del> {an} opinion which is too
               strongly rooted in <del>my</del> {the} principles of political wisdom to be
                  <del>altered</del> {shaken} by any minor considerations, &#8211; that manner will best
               accord with my own feelings which may appear to be least offensive to yours.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you Sir for the documents with which you have favoured
               me,</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">&amp; have the honour to remain</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> your most obedient</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">humble Serv<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
          </salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>