<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3184</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4455</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3184. Robert Southey to Caroline
                  Bowles, 25 August 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3184" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3184.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47889.
                  ALS; 4p.  .  Previously  published: Edward Dowden (ed.), The
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles (Dublin and
                  London, 1881), pp. 11&#8211;12 [in part; undated].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3184" type="letter">
        <head>3184. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline
                  Bowles</ref>,<date when="1818-08-25"> 25 August 1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/
                  near Lymington/ Hampshire<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Endorsement: To Miss
                  Caroline Bowles/ Keswick 25 August, 1818<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 47889.
                  ALS; 4p. <lb /> Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and
                  London, 1881), pp. 11&#8211;12 [in part; undated].</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8216;For ever rankled in her heart The poisoned shafts undying
                  smart&#8217;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey here provides further
                  criticism of Bowles&#8217;s poem, &#8216;Ellen Fitzarthur&#8217;, which she had sent to him for his
                  opinion. Almost all the deletions and changes that Southey suggested were
                  incorporated when the poem was published by Longman in 1820.</note> &#8211; It is the
                  <hi rend="ital">shaft</hi> that rankles, not the smart, &#8211; which is the object of
               the rankling. The simplest &amp; surest criticism is to bring every expression thus
               to the test of reason, &#8211; &#8216;Many a filial prayer she <hi rend="ital">traced</hi>.&#8217; &#8211;
               This word ought not to be used in this sense: <del>xx</del> &amp; there is an
               ambiguity in these six lines: the impression which they convey is literally that
                  <del>xx</del> a prayer had been rejected, &#8211; <del>xx</del> &amp; in the succeeding
               couplet it rather surprized me to find the meaning to be that letters had been
               supprest. These latter circumstances indeed cannot be very easily related in verse &#8211;
               &#8216;Task&#8217; &amp; &#8216;past&#8217; are not allowable as rhymes. A monument of snow would be modelled
               or moulded, not sculptured. &#8216;That the warm blood <hi rend="ital">forbid</hi> to
               start&#8217;, &#8211; &#8216;forbidden&#8217; is the proper word. &#8211; &#8216;By sickness &amp; <hi rend="ital">exaction</hi> drained&#8217;; &#8211; better not interrupt the sense of natural distress by
               this word which for a moment diverts attention to common roguery in the
               hardheartedness of vulgar life. &#8216;Unbro<hi rend="ital">k</hi>e by sight or sound&#8217;;
                  &#8216;<hi rend="ital">unbroken</hi>&#8217; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The feeling which keeps Ellen from entering the Church is strikingly
               conceived, but it is too violent a figure to <del>xxxx xxxx</del> represent a gate
               speaking. &#8211; You describe the warm red beams of evening upon the painted windows of
               the church <hi rend="ital">before</hi> evening service which nowhere I believe begins
               at a later hour than three.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Nevertheless,
                  this image was retained in <title>Ellen Fitzarthur: a Metrical Tale, in Five
                     Cantos</title> (London, 1820), p. 83.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The picture of the Prodigal Son<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Ellen Fitzarthur: a Metrical Tale, in Five
                     Cantos</title> (London, 1820), p. 86.</note> is so well introduced
                  <del>that</del> &amp; so naturally, that any embarrassed or forced expression
               becomes particularly unpleasant, &amp; what would be past over without notice in a
               less interesting passage, would be painfully felt there. The awkwardness is in these
               words, &#8211; &#8220;&amp; bade to deck &#8211; his form.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The long pilgrimage <hi rend="ital">lay</hi> before her. &#8211; Unbro<hi rend="ital">k</hi>e(n) by hamlet &amp;c.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The widow speaks of a bloom glowing on Ellens cheek, &amp; compares
               it to the glow of health &amp; youth. This is an oversight.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These remarks are not worth much in themselves; but it is of some
               consequence to remove any grammatical inaccuracies however slight, &amp; it is of far
               more to impress upon a writer the necessity of adhering as strictly to sound sense in
               verse as in prose. For however brilliant a poem may be in parts, &amp; however
               popular it may be because of that brilliance, if the poet either from a false system
               or from the want of system, writes nonsense, his works will inevitably be forgotten,
               or only remembered to his dispraise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <hi rend="ital">judgement</hi> therefore must always be exercised
               in writing, &#8211; &amp; it is the last thing which a poet learns to exercise. The world
               may put up for awhile with something that looks like sense if it be flashy &amp;
               striking, &#8211; &amp; thus it is that every age has had its favourites, whose reputation
               passes away like that of <del>xxx</del> an actor or a beauty in high life when anyone
               with equal pretensions comes forward.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When you have revised the poem send it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, &amp; if you do not like that
               he should know your name &amp; address, say in a note that you send for his
               inspection the poem concerning which I had written to him, &amp; desire him to make
               known his determination concerning it to me. And then if he chuses to print it, I
               will refer him to you. Whether he will or no, or what the reception of the poem may
               be, if he should, I cannot pretend to augur. The last thirty years have produced a
               great change in these things. Even when I began to write there was a fair field,
               &amp; whoever appeared in it was sure to obtain notice. Now it is so crowded, that
               poems are entirely neglected which would then have been regarded with wonder &amp;
               applause.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell me what else you have written (for you must have written other
               things) &#8211; &amp; what you think of writing, if you have any thing planned. A happy
               subject may attract attention, &#8211; &amp; a word of advice respecting the plan may be
               worth fifty <del>xxxxxxxxxx</del> after it is executed. &#8211; I wish you may be able also
               to tell me that your health is improved &amp; that with it your heart is recovering
               strength &amp; genial feelings.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Believe me sincerely yrs</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1818-08-25"> 25. Aug. 1818. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>