<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2972</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4243</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2972. Robert Southey to William
                  Peachy, 9 April 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2972" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2972.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 28603.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of
                     Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                  153&#8211;155.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2972" type="letter">
        <head>2972. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William
                  Peachy</ref>, <date when="1817-04-09">9 April 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/
                  Post Office/ Rugby/ Warwickshire<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Seal: black wax,
                  with &#8216;S&#8217;, &#8216;In Labore Quies&#8217; motto below<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 28603.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp.
                  153&#8211;155.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-04-09">9 April. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> So many interruptions &amp; harrassing affairs have occurred to me of
               late, one after the other, that I have unavoidably delayed writing to you, till I
               almost fear a direction even to Rugby <del>will</del> may fail to find you
                  there.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons, James
                  Henry (1803&#8211;1884) and Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), were at Rugby
                  School.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have seen my name pretty frequently in the newspapers, &amp;
               may perhaps like to know the real circumstances of the business. I wrote Wat Tyler in
               the summer of 1794 before I was twenty years of age; &#8211; it was the <del>xxxx</del>
               composition of two or three mornings, &#8211; thrown off at a heat &amp; without the
               slightest correction or revision. <ref type="m" target="people.html#LovellRobert">Lovell</ref> took
               it to London in the autumn &amp; put it into Ridgeways hands, that he might consider
               whether he would publish it. It was left in his hands, &amp; in the December of the
               same year I went to town myself for three days, &amp; called on Ridgeway who was then
               in Newgate.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had sent <title>Wat
                     Tyler</title> to James Ridgway (1755&#8211;1838), and Henry Symonds (1741&#8211;1816),
                  radical booksellers, for publication; see Robert Southey to Edith Fricker, [c. 12
                  January 1795], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>,
                  Letter 123. Ridgway and Symonds did not publish it and it remained in manuscript
                  until a pirated publication, designed to embarrass the now anti-Jacobin Southey,
                  appeared in 1817. Having taken advice from Rickman, Wynn and Turner, Southey
                  launched an unsuccessful suit in Chancery so as to gain an injunction suppressing
                  the publication.</note> He &amp; Symonds (also a prisoner) <del>sa</del> told me
               they would print it, &amp; if any profit accrued I was to have such a proportion as
               they should think <del>fit</del> equitable. There the matter ended. I returned to
               Bristol, no proof sheet ever came to me, I concluded that upon farther reflection
               they thought the thing unfit for publication, &amp; my own after thought coincided so
               entirely in this judgement, that I made no application to know why the printing was
               delayed, nor ever enquired for the manuscript, thinking in fact no more of it than of
               a college or school exercise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By whom this thing after an interval of three &amp; twenty years has
               been published I know not. Upon seeing it announced I immediately gave instructions
               to apply for an injunction in Chancery, &#8211; the case being as plain as day light, that
               the property was mine, &amp; that a man might just as well take from me any of the
               papers in my writing desk, as print that without my consent, &amp; in defiance of me.
               A counter-affidavit was procured from a Dissenting Minister by name <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref>, which does not contain a single word of truth.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Winterbottom&#8217;s affidavit, 15 March 1817,
                  National Archives C31/372 Pt. 2.</note> I saw this man once in my life, which was
               in Ridgeways apartment upon the occasion already mentioned, &amp; I never saw him at
               any other time, nor was ever at any other time within the walls of Newgate, &#8211; he
               swears that I visited him frequently there, that he believes it to have been in the
               year 1796 (for the purpose of making it appear that I was of age at the time) &#8211; &amp;
               that I <hi rend="ital">gave</hi> him the Manuscript to do with it whatever he
               pleased, &#8211; &amp; he swears to persons being present whom I never saw in the whole
               course of my life.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel Isaac Eaton
                  (1753&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), radical publisher; and Daniel Holt (1766&#8211;1799),
                  printer of the <title>Newark Herald</title> (1791&#8211;1794), a prisoner in Newgate
                  1793&#8211;1797 after being convicted of seditious libel.</note> He says that the copy
               which has been printed must have been surreptitiously taken from that in his
               possession, &#8211; but he came forward with <hi rend="ital">his</hi> claim in opposition
               to <hi rend="ital">mine</hi>. The Chancellor therefore finding the right of property
               contested, referred it to a Court of Law,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s suit in Chancery was heard on 18&#8211;19 March 1817 before John Scott,
                  1st Earl of Eldon (1751&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1801&#8211;1806,
                  1807&#8211;1827. He ruled that he could not grant an injunction in a court of equity
                  because Southey had not unequivocally established his ownership of the manuscript
                  in question and he would need to do this in a court that applied the law of the
                  land, rather than equity.</note> &#8211; &amp; of course I did not chuse to incur
               farther expences in establishing a claim which was opposed by direct perjury. &#8211;
               Moreover my object was that of avowing the work, &amp; disclaiming its opinions &amp;
               this I had done.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have now a letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                  Smith</ref> in the press which will be published in the course of next week.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Smith had denounced Southey in the House of
                  Commons on 14 March 1817 in the debate on the Seditious Meetings Bill, condemning
                  &#8216;the settled, determined malignity of a renegado&#8217; and comparing Southey&#8217;s
                  arguments against radical views in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16
                  (October 1816), 227, with those expressed in <title>Wat Tyler</title> (1817), Act
                  2, lines 103&#8211;112. Southey justified his change of views, and attacked Smith, in
                  his <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P. </title>(1817). </note> It is a
               plain exposition of what my political {opinions} have been, &amp; what they are; with
               a wholesome castigation for the said <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                  Smith</ref>. I would have one franked to you if I knew where to direct it. On
               Monday next I go to my brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> for a
               week, &amp; my place is taken with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> in the mail
               for London, on the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. We start for the Continent, God willing,
               on the first of May.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been disturbed about <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">the house which we inhabit</ref>. The
               Estate is to be sold under an Extent in Aid, &#8211; [MS torn] I have had to think
               seriously whether it be best to purchase it, or <del>ri</del> incur the very probable
               risk of seeing it cut up into small lots, &amp; having the remainder of my lease
               discomforted by building in the field &amp; upper part of the nursery garden.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall had suffered from the complicated
                  financial and legal entanglements of its owner, Samuel Tolson Jnr (dates unknown),
                  who was by April 1817 in Carlisle jail for debt; a creditor had taken out an
                  injunction (an &#8216;extent in aid&#8217;) against him, seeking recompense by forcing a sale
                  of the estate. </note> This is a point upon which I have not yet been able to
               decide</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Fearons bill is paid,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Joseph Fearon (1767&#8211;1839).</note> &amp; your assessed taxes, for
               both of which I have taken care to have stampt receipts. Should you arrive before my
               return to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> my <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Governess</ref> will render up the bills &amp; accounts.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I can give you no directions to any authors who might serve as guides
               in Ireland, &#8211; a country of which I know <del>neither</del> less than <del>J</del> of
               Japan or China. There was a tour by Twiss,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Twiss (1747&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Tour in Ireland in
                     1775 </title>(1776).</note> published in my childhood, which you have probably
               seen, &amp; I dare say you know in what manner the Irish revenged themselves for the
               freedom of his observation by placing his portrait in a very scurvy place, with a
               poem in which his name was coupled to a scurvy rhyme.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">On the bottom of a chamber pot, inscribed with the rhyme &#8216;Let
                  everyone piss/ On lying Dick Twiss&#8217;.</note> And there is Sir J Carrs Tour.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Carr (1772&#8211;1832;
                  <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Stranger in Ireland; or, A Tour in the Southern
                     and Western Parts of that Country in the Year 1805</title> (1806).</note> I
               have heard of a book concerning Ireland well spoken of by some such name as Dewar or
               Drewer, &#8211; it is some four or five years old,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel Dewar (1787?-1867), <title>Observations on the Character, Customs,
                     and Superstitions of the Irish </title>(1812).</note> &#8211; &amp; there are two
               huge quartos of statistic information by Edward Wakefield.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Wakefield (1774&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An
                     Account of Ireland, Statistical and Political</title> (1812), no. 3094 in the
                  sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>
               &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>