<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3156</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4427</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3156. Robert Southey to William Peachy, 20 June
                  1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3156" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3156.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.
                   .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                  II, pp. 184&#8211;187.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3156" type="letter">
        <head>3156. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1818-06-20">20 June
                  1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/ Post Office/ Salisbury.<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 23 JU 23/ 1818<lb /> Seal: [partial] red wax, design illegible<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.
                  <lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965),
                  II, pp. 184&#8211;187.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-06-20">20 June. 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should have written ere {this} to express my thanks for the Lamp, if I had known in what direction to aim a flying
               shot. It arrived safely, &amp; written directions came with it, sufficiently explicit, <del>f</del> I dare say, for its use. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">My daughter Edith</ref> could not rest till she had discovered the whole art &amp;
               mystery of the mechanism. As yet it has not been lighted for two reasons; &#8211; first because we have had no darkness since it arrived, &#8211;
               that is, the evenings have been so long, that we have needed no artificial light till supper. And secondly (which reason <del>xxx</del>
               had it been given first might have swallowed up all the others like Aarons rod)<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Exodus</title> 7: 12, where Aaron&#8217;s rod turns into a serpent and devours the serpents of the Egyptian sorcerers.</note>
               there has till this day been no oil in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> which the shopkeepers could recommend,
               &#8211; this very day some is expected, &amp; as soon as it arrives we shall certainly have an illumination. Pray make my best
               acknowledgements to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> for this favour. The thing itself
               (as well as the invention) is certainly a beautiful one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Would <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barkers</ref>
          <ref type="m" target="places.html#RosthwaitePlace"> house</ref>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Barker was in serious
                  financial difficulties and was trying to let the property she had built at Rosthwaite.</note> suit M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Neave<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified: presumably, an acquaintance of Peachy&#8217;s.</note>? or that which Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gee had at Rydale?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Captain George Gee (d. 1827) of Wraxall, Somerset, who
                  was renting Ivy Cottage at Rydal. He was the son of Thomas Gee, a Bristol merchant, and an old schoolmate of Southey&#8217;s in Bristol.
                  He seems to have played an important backstage role in organising the Lowther family&#8217;s election contests in Westmorland in 1818,
                  1820 and 1826.</note> either of these may be had. Gee is at Bowness. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilberforce</ref> has written to me about a house for the middle of August, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref> is willing to let him have his,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Bank,
                  near Latrigg, just to the north of Keswick.</note> &#8211; I am daily expecting the answer to this proposal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is not altogether without news. They talk of lowering the Lake two feet, by
               clearing the bed of the river from the place where it leaves the lake to its junction with the Greta. Secondly &#8211; Monk Hall<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A farmhouse near the River Greta in Keswick, once a fortified pele tower, now demolished.</note> has
               been on fire this morning, &amp; just saved from destruction &amp; thirdly we have had a person here, who tho he is now acting the
               swindler is both by education, manners &amp; profession a gentleman, &amp; may perhaps not be altogether unknown to you. His name is
                  May,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">William May (1763&#8211;1827) from East Looe, Cornwall, who received a medical qualification
                  in Leyden in 1787 and became an Extra-Licentiate of the Royal College of Physicians in 1788. He seems to have practiced mainly in
                  Truro and Plymouth.</note> &amp; he practised as a Physician at Taunton several years ago, &amp; afterwards I believe at Truro. This
               said D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> May wrote me a note from the Royal Oak,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A principal inn in
                  Keswick.</note> saying that he was well acquainted with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S.</ref>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">This was not impossible, given that May was an Extra-Licentiate
                  of the Royal College of Physicians and Henry Herbert Southey was a Licentiate; and that both had published books on consumption &#8211;
                  May&#8217;s <title>Essay on Pulmonary Consumption</title> (Plymouth, 1792) and Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s <title>Observations on Pulmonary
                     Consumption</title> (1814).</note> &amp; requesting permission to call upon me that I might give him directions as to the best
               method of seeing the country. This was late in the evening, &amp; I accordingly invited him to breakfast the next day. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">My brother</ref> has never seen him, &amp; there was no necessity of introducing himself
               with a lie, because he had seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> formerly at
                  <ref type="m" target="places.html#Stowey">Stowey</ref>, &amp; prescribed for her.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Curate
                  at St Mary&#8217;s, Nether Stowey in 1790&#8211;1800 was a Cornishman, William Roskilly (d. 1810). William May seems to have been a friend of
                  Roskilly&#8217;s and, while visiting him in Nether Stowey, accompanied him to tea with the Coleridges and gave Sara Coleridge advice on
                  weaning the young Hartley Coleridge; see Sara Coleridge to Thomas Poole, [June 1817], <title>Minnow among Tritons: Mrs. S. T.
                     Coleridge&#8217;s Letters to Thomas Poole</title>, ed. Stephen Potter (London, 1934), p. 53.</note> He dined with Sir F. Morsehead that
               day, whose father he had known at Verdun.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Frederick Treise Morshead, 2nd Baronet
                  (1783&#8211;1828) lived at Derwent Lodge, Keswick; his father, Sir John Morshead, 1st Baronet (1747&#8211;1813), MP for Callington 1780&#8211;1784, MP
                  for Bodmin 1784&#8211;1802, went to live in France in 1802 and, when war between Britain and France broke out again, was detained in
                  Verdun, with many other British citizens. He was not able to return to Britain until 1809. He knew William May, who was also at
                  Verdun; indeed May was imprisoned for 14 months in 1805&#8211;1806 for writing a letter in which he protested against Morshead&#8217;s
                  treatment.</note> He talked incessantly, &amp; very amusingly of his foreign adventures, &#8211; but not a word of the country, &#8211; &amp; I
               understood that his head quarters were Kendal. Some ten days afterwards he returned &amp; took lodgings at John Aireys<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John Airey (dates unknown) was a bookseller, stationer and pencil manufacturer in Keswick.</note>, &amp;
               endeavoured to get into practise by offering to visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondsons</ref> patients. Among
               others he went to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gritton<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Gritton, n&#233;e Russell (c. 1770&#8211;1818),
                  wife of Thomas Gritton (1756&#8211;1828), the Minister of the Independent Chapel at Keswick 1793&#8211;1828. She died on 15 May 1818.</note> who
               was then very near death; &#8211; he refused a fee, &#8211; but returned to Kendal, found out Grittons son,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Percival Russell Gritton (1789&#8211;1880). At this time he was a pocket book maker in Kendal.</note> told him his mother was dying,
               &amp; that it was of the utmost importance he should attend her, &#8211; made the poor fellow bring him over in a chaise, tho the woman (as
               he well knew would be the case) was in <hi rend="ital">articulo mortis</hi>
          <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Death
                  throes.</note> when he arrived, &#8211; accepted two guineas which Gritton had sent him after the visit, &amp; extorted from him by a note
               three more. Airey soon got rid of him because he called up the family to light his fire at four o clock; &amp; it was soon learnt that
               he was living by his sleights &amp; had a heavy bill at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lowood">Lowood</ref>. However he got shirts
               &amp; cravatts from Miss Crosthwaite<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">A member of a family that ran many businesses in Keswick.
                  These included the mercers, drapers and grocers shop, run under the name M. and D. Crosthwaite.</note>, &amp; inexpressibles from
               John Cockbaine<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cockbaine (1786&#8211;1873), Keswick draper and tailor.</note>, making John
               procure the cloth, &amp; Miss C. have the shirts made. He then gave out that he was going to Buttermere, locked the empty drawers at
               his lodgings (at Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Scotts)<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> &amp; as no one would
               trust him with horse or carriage, (for he was in debt at the Royal Oak) set off on foot, with two boys, each carrying a trunk. It was
               not long before Scott discovered that he had decamped, &amp; then young Jackson of the Oak<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  innkeeper of the Royal Oak at Keswick at this time was Joseph Jackson (dates unknown), so this presumably refers to one of his
                  sons.</note> set out on <del>hors</del> one horse to pursue him, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cockbaine<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Cockbaine, n&#233;e White (1793&#8211;1859). She married John Cockbaine in 1813 and the couple had nine children.</note> on
               another; but they went separately.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They learnt that he took the Penrith road, but could find no tidings of him at Threlkeld, however they guest rightly
               &amp; pursued to Materdale. Jackson came up with him first, &amp; got from him three pounds, being about half his debt; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cockbaine overtook him at Pooley Bridge, &amp; demanded the money or the &#8211; inexpressibles. Would not this be a rich subject
               for Wilkie?<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">David Wilkie (1785&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), painter of comic genre pictures of
                  rural life, such as <title>Village Politicians</title> (1806). Sir George Beaumont was one of his patrons.</note> She would follow
               him, she said, wher[MS torn] he went, &amp; keep by his side, till he either restored the inexpressibles, or paid for them. The Doctor,
               I believe, has been a man of gallantry in his time, &#8211; but he was not desirous of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cockbaine for a companion,
               &amp; with a very ill grace, he paid her one guinea out of &#163; 2&#8211;5/<hi rend="sup">s</hi> which was Johnnys demand; &amp; the Virago
               returned, in a soaking rain, as stiff as you may suppose after a ride of nearly forty miles, &#8211; but triumphant. What is become of him is
               not known; &#8211; but some part of his conduct bears marks of insanity. It is manifest that some how or other, he had blasted his character
               before he came here, &amp; it would not surprize me to hear that he had finished his career by suicide.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see that Sir F. Vane<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Frederick Fletcher Vane, 2nd Baronet
                  (1760&#8211;1832), of Hutton-le-Forest near Penrith, MP for Winchelsea 1792&#8211;1794, Carlisle 1796&#8211;1802, Winchelsea 1806&#8211;1807. He was a Whig
                  and a supporter of Brougham&#8217;s assault on the Lowther family&#8217;s control of Westmorland at the 1818 general election. Possibly as a
                  diversionary tactic, he agreed to fight Cockermouth in June 1818, though this was a burgage borough totally under Lowther control.
                  He polled only 2 votes. The Whigs also put forward John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Carlisle 1786&#8211;1790,
                  1791&#8211;1812, 1816&#8211;1820, MP for Cumberland 1820&#8211;1828, to contest Cumberland, but he did not go to the poll and the sitting MPs were
                  returned unopposed.</note> stands for Cockermouth, &amp; that the County is to be contested, &#8211; we know not as yet by whom. Should
               this contest be a severe one it will bring <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> down again. The effect of
               Hunts standing for Westminster is amusing enough, every vote which he gets is one lost to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Burdett">Burdett</ref>, &amp; therefore half as good as if it were given for Sir M. Maxwell, or Romilly,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), in contesting the Westminster constituency in the 1818 general
                  election, threatened to split the radical vote and harm Sir Francis Burdett&#8217;s chances of re-election. The other candidates were Sir
                  Samuel Romilly (1757&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>), the Whig politician and legal reformer; John Cartwright (1740&#8211;1824;
                     <title>DNB</title>), the veteran radical; and, for the ministry, Sir Murray Maxwell, a naval hero (1775&#8211;1831;
                  <title>DNB</title>). Burdett and Romilly were returned; Maxwell was financially ruined and also severely injured by a paving slab
                  thrown from the crowd.</note> &#8211; in such a contest as this one must even wish for Romillys success: tho for my own part I would
               rather give a vote for Major Cartwright <del>thin</del> as thinking him if he were in the house, far the least mischievous of the
               two.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The country has been in its utmost beauty, &amp; we have now some refreshing rain. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; her sisters<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and Mary Lovell.</note> join with me in kind remembrance to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L.</ref> continues miserably weak &amp; ill. The rest are going on well; &amp; I am expecting ere long my Acta
               Sanctorum (52 vol. folio)<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794): the massive compendium of
                  hagiographies that Southey had bought in Brussels, no. 207 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. </note> &#8211; a great event in my
               life.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>