<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3020</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4291</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3020. Robert Southey to Joseph
                  Cottle, 2 September 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3020.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Berg
                  Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 3p.  .  Previously  published: Joseph
                  Cottle, Reminscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey
                  (London, 1847), p. 236 [in part; with a postscript taken from Robert Southey to
                  Joseph Cottle, 6 February 1819, tacked onto the end].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3020" type="letter">
        <head>3020. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Joseph
                  Cottle</ref>, <date when="1817-09-02">2 September 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Cottle/ Brunswick Square/ Bristol<lb /> Endorsement: September 2 <hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1817 on 2 <hi rend="sup">d</hi> part of/ Messiah<lb /> MS: Berg
                  Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 3p. <lb /> Previously published: Joseph
                  Cottle, <title>Reminscences of Samuel Taylor Coleridge and Robert Southey</title>
                  (London, 1847), p. 236 [in part; with a postscript taken from Robert Southey to
                  Joseph Cottle, 6 February 1819, tacked onto the end].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Cottle</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I take it for granted that you have learnt long ere this, from some
               channel or other, that when your packet was sent off to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, I was upon the continent. Here I found
               it on my return a few days ago, &amp; the earliest leisure which I could find has
               been given to its attentive perusal. This lapse of time is not to be regretted,
               because it will have <del>abated</del> blunted the edge of your resentment, &amp; I
               doubt not by this time you regard the criticism of the Monthly Review just as it
               deserves. Such things are utterly unworthy of notice. The easiest &amp; wisest course
               is to despise them; &#8211; recollect the abuse which I have endured for so many years,
               &amp; you will <del>kn</del> perceive that I practise what I preach.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Cottle&#8217;s <title>Messiah: A Poem in Twenty-Eight
                     Books: Part the First</title> (1815), had been savaged by the <title>Monthly
                     Review</title>, 82 (March 1817), 323&#8211;324, as &#8216;such a farrago as no human
                  imagination could possibly have conceived to be within the compass even of the
                  modern English press&#8217; and &#8216;merely a flat versification of the Bible, degrading the
                  sacred volume as far as it can be degraded by human means&#8217; (324). Cottle was
                  working on the second volume of his <title>Messiah</title> and was possibly
                  considering retaliating in a preface. He had sent a copy to Southey, for his
                  opinion. <title>Messiah: A Poem in Twenty-Four Books. Part the Second</title>
                  appeared in 1819. The <title>Monthly Review</title>, 92 (August 1820), 407&#8211;412,
                  described it as containing not a &#8216;particle of poetry&#8217; and dismissed its author as
                  possessing &#8216;not a ray, nor the shadow of the genius of a poet&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Yet I should be sorry to lose your preface, &#8211; your prose has a
               natural ease which no study could acquire, &amp; the whole personal part is related
               in <del>a</del> {the best} manner. All of this you should retain, &amp; the more you
               added to it the better I should like it. But it is not worth while to reprint a piece
               of mere scurrility which if it be not reprinted will never be re-read or
               remembered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps I anticipate your own judgement when I say that if the poem
               ends with the death of S John the Baptist it remains imperfect &#8211; for this assuredly
               is not the conclusion of your subject &#8211; the Ascension or the Pentecost would be the
               proper close.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Cottle rejected the advice,
                  concluding <title>Messiah &#8230; Part the Second</title> (1819) with the death of John
                  the Baptist.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For a long time I have found it necessary to review no poetry, &amp;
               even to lay down a law {for myself} upon this subject &#8211; like the laws of the Medes
               &amp; the Persians.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Daniel</title>
                  6: 15, &#8216;it is a law of the Medes and Persians that no injunction or ordinance that
                  the king establishes can be changed&#8217;. </note> The principles of the Quarterly
               Review in matters of poetry differ widely from mine, &#8211; &amp; indeed care has been
               taken (&amp; that too rather in an offensive manner) to <hi rend="ital">unsay</hi> in
               a criticism upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> poems what I had incidentally said upon a former
                  <del>xxxxxxxx</del> occasion.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably
                  a reference to the hostile review of Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>Poems</title> (1815) and
                     <title>The White Doe of Rylstone</title> (1815) in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 14 (October 1815), 201&#8211;225 (published 12 March 1816), which
                  opined &#8216;mere simplicity of language is no merit at all, if it be purchased at the
                  expense of perspicuity&#8217; (223) and that if Wordsworth was not &#8216;a favourite with the
                  public, he can have nobody to blame but himself&#8217; (225).</note> The last poetical
               work which I reviewed was the World before the Flood, &amp; that article was not
               inserted till after long delay &amp; a long struggle, in which I was compelled to
               assert that my personal feelings were concerned, &amp; in some manner my character
               also, &#8211; for I had let <ref type="m" target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref> know that I should review it.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had reviewed <title>The World Before the Flood</title>
                  (1813), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 11 (April 1814), 79&#8211;87. For his
                  struggle to get the review published, see Robert Southey to John Murray, [c. 13
                  May 1814], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>,
                  Letter 2421.</note> This however was a very unpleasant circumstance &amp; for this
                  <del>xxx</del> &amp; other obvious reasons, I made a resolution, the propriety of
               which I have had frequent occasion to perceive. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have made a long journey in company with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">a friend of my own age</ref> from
               this country, &amp; with <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Mr Nash</ref>,
               the artist who gave me the drawings of Waterloo.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Seven of the eight engravings in <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage
                     to Waterloo</title> (1816) were derived from sketches by Nash.</note> We went
               by way of Paris &amp; Bescan&#231;on into Switzerland, visited the Grande Chartreuse crost
               Mount Cenis, {proceeding} to Turin &amp; Milan, &amp; then turned back by the Lakes
                  <del>x</del> Como Lugano &amp; Maggiore, &amp; over the Simplon. Our next business
               was to see the mountainous part of Switzerland. From Berne we sent our carriage to
               Zurich &amp; struck into what is called the Oberland (Upper-land). After ten days
               spent thus in the finest part of the country we rejoined the carriage, &amp; returned
               thro the Black Forest: the most interesting points upon our homeward road, were
               Danaushingen (where the Danube rises) Friburg, Strasburg, Baden, Carlsruh,
               Heidelberg, Manheim, Frankfort, Maintz, &#8211; Cologne, &amp; to by Brussels &amp; Lisle
               to Calais. I kept a full journal, which might easily be made into an amusing &amp;
               useful volume or two, &#8211; but I have {no} leisure for <del>such a task</del> it. You
               may well suppose what an accumulation of business is upon my hands after so long an
               absence, &amp; when for four months I have been spending money instead of earning it.
               The time however has been well employed. I have derived great advantage both in
               knowledge &amp; in health, &amp; every person remarks that I look better than they
               ever remember to have seen me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have dispatched your MS by the Coach this day, but it has so many
               coaches to change that it may probably be two or three days longer than this letter
               on the road. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
               desires her kindest remembrances both to you &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#Cottlefamily">your sisters</ref>. Is there no
               hope of seeing you one day in this country?</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Cottle</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-09-02">2 Sept. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>