<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2708</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3979</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2708. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 4 February 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2708" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2708.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                  c. 25. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 148&#8211;150 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2708" type="letter">
        <head>2708. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-02-04">4 February 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster
                  <lb />Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb />Postmark: E/ 7 FE 7/ 1816 <lb />Endorsement: 4 February 1816 <lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett.
                  c. 25. ALS; 4p. <lb />Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 148&#8211;150 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-02-04">4 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have an official from the Treasury<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Unidentified.</note> this evening telling
               me, as you anticipated that the prayer of my petition is inadmissible.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had asked for
                  the customs duty on the books he had bought on his continental journey in 1817 to be removed or reduced.</note> To be sure it is
               much better they should repeal the duty than grant an exemption from it speciali grati&#226;,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;As a
                  special privilege&#8217;.</note> &#8211; but if they will do neither the one nor the other, the Devil reward them say I.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is it true that the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WalesCharlottePrincess">Princess Charlotte</ref> is likely
               to be married? you will guess why I wish to know.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had written, in March&#8211;June 1814,
                  fifty stanzas celebrating the engagement of Princess Charlotte, only child of the Prince Regent, to William, Hereditary Prince of
                  Orange (1792&#8211;1849; King of the Netherlands 1840&#8211;1849). He had to abandon the poem when the engagement was broken off, but he was
                  able to reuse most of it in his <title>Lay of the Laureate</title>. <title>Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816), which celebrated
                  Charlotte&#8217;s marriage to Prince Leopold of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld (1790&#8211;1865; King of the Belgians 1831&#8211;1865) on 2 May 1816.</note> Tho
               if I had not written half a marriage poem I certainly would not begin one; <del>because</del> for between ourselves I have not been
               well used about the Laureateship, &#8211; they require task verses from me, not to keep up the custom of having been befiddled,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Traditionally, the Poet Laureate&#8217;s New Year Odes were set to music and performed at Court.</note> but
               to keep up the task, &#8211; instead of putting an end to this foolery in a fair &amp; open manner, which do would the court credit, &amp;
               save me a <del>x</del> silly expense of time &amp; trouble. I shall compleat what I have begun &#8211; because it is begun, &amp; to please
               myself, not to obtain favour with any body else, &#8211; but when these things are done, if they continue to look for New Years Odes from the
               Laureate, they shall have nothing else.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has been here for the last fortnight, looking about for a house. I cannot write
               verses <del>of</del> in the presence of any person &#8211; except <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my wife</ref> or my
               children: &#8211; Tom therefore, without knowing it has impeded my Pilgrimage.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> was published in May 1816.</note> But I can prosify let who will be present, &amp;
                  Brazil<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> is profiting by this
               interruption.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Were you not here when poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> introduced M. Simond? &#8211; And
               have you seen the said M Simonds &#8216;Travels in England by a native of France?&#8217;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Louis Simond
                  (1767&#8211;1831), <title>Journal of a Tour and Residence in Great Britain, During the Years 1810 and 1811</title> (1815); reviewed
                  by Southey in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 537&#8211;574.</note> You will like the liveliness &amp; the pervading
               good sense; &amp; you will smile at the complacency with which he abuses Handel &#8211; <del>Xxxx</del> Raphael, &amp; Milton.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Simond heard the music of Georg Frederic Handel (1685&#8211;1759; <title>DNB</title>) at St Paul&#8217;s Cathedral,
                  London, noting &#8216;it is not the first time I have had the misfortune to be tired of Handel&#8217;s music&#8217;, <title>Journal of a Tour and
                     Residence in Great Britain, During the Years 1810 and 1811</title>, 2 vols (London, 1815), I, p. 183; the pictures of
                  Raphael (1483&#8211;1520) were described as &#8216;hard like cut tin&#8217;, I, p. 110; and Simond&#8217;s dislike of John Milton (1608&#8211;1674;
                     <title>DNB</title>) was expressed in his assessment of Southey, I, pp. 350&#8211;354.</note> He honours me with a couple of pages, an
               amusing mixture of journalizing, personal civility, &amp; critical presumption. My poems <hi rend="ital">&amp; Miltons</hi> he says
               have few <del>reader</del> readers altho they have many admirers. he <del>quotes</del> applies to me the famous speech of the Cardinal
               to Ariosto Dove <hi rend="ital">Diavolo</hi> &amp;c<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> When Ludovico Ariosto (1474&#8211;1533)
                  presented his <title>Orlando Furioso</title> (1532) to the Cardinal Ippolito d&#8217;Este (1509&#8211;1572), the Cardinal exclaimed &#8216;Dove
                  diavolo, Messer Ludovico, avete pigliato tante coglionerie?&#8217;: &#8216;Where the devil, Master Ludovico, have you found all this
                  stuff?&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; thinks I write nonsense, &#8211; <del>xxxx</del> however it is better than Miltons, <del>but</del> Miltons love
               &amp; theology being <del>both</del> coarse &amp; material, whereas I have tenderness &amp; spirituality!!! He sets down two or three
               things which I told him, states my opinions as he is pleased to suppose, &amp; concludes that the reason why I disapprove of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Malthuss writings is that I do not understand them.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> The political
                  economist Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), whose pessimism on the subject of population increase Southey intensely
                  disliked, e.g. in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note> Bravo M. Simond! Yet in the main it is a fair
               &amp; able book, &amp; I wonder how so sensible a man can write with such consummate self assurance upon things above his reach.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I long to have my Brazilian history finished that that of the war may go to press in its stead;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) was delayed by his reviewing and by
                  his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &amp; could I abstain from Reviewing, three months would accomplish this
               desirable object, &#8211; but &#8216;I must live&#8217; &#8211; as the French libeller said to Richelieu,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was
                  referring to Armand Jean du Plessis, Cardinal Richelieu (1585&#8211;1642), Chief Minister of France 1624&#8211;1642. However, he had probably
                  mistaken the story because he had confused an earlier paragraph on Richelieu with the account of this incident in George Ensor
                  (1769&#8211;1843), <title>The Independent Man: Or, An Essay on the Formation and Development of Those Principles and Faculties of the
                     Human Mind Which Constitute Moral and Intellectual Excellence</title>, 2 vols (London, 1806), II, p. 321. The libeller was
                  actually Pierre-Fran&#231;ois Guyot Desfontaines (1685&#8211;1745), who defamed the minister Marc-Pierre de Voyer de Paulmy, Comte d&#8217;Argenson
                  (1696&#8211;1764) and, when questioned, gave the explanation Southey records. D&#8217;Argenson replied that he did not see the necessity of
                  Desfontaine living.</note> &#8211; &amp; unlike the Cardinal I know you will see the necessity for my so doing. However I am in a fair
               train, &amp; verily believe that after the present year I <del>shall</del> &amp; the Constable shall travel side by side in good
                  fellowship.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> To &#8216;outrun the constable&#8217; was to live beyond one&#8217;s means, so Southey was
                  suggesting his income would match his expenditure.</note> &#8211; You will be glad to hear that I have got the correspondence of the
               Portugueze Committee with the official details of the conduct of Massenas army &amp; the consequent state of the people &amp; the
                  country.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Napoleonic Marshal Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817) led the French campaign against
                  Portugal in 1810 and 1811; Southey narrates his actions in <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp.
                  710&#8211;784. The House of Commons in 1811 voted &#163;100,000 to relieve the civilian population of Portugal and a committee was appointed by
                  Sir Charles Stuart (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), the British Envoy to Portugal 1810&#8211;1814, to distribute the money. One of its
                  members was Southey&#8217;s friend, the English merchant in Lisbon, John Bell.</note> If I live to compleat this work I verily
                  <del>hope</del> believe it will tend <del>more</del> to mitigate the evils of war hereafter, by teaching men in command what
               ineffaceable infamy will pursue them if they act as Barbarians.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">your Mother &amp; Miss Page</ref>. I wish you could ascertain for me whether the Comedias de Gil
               Vicente (a Portugueze)<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Portuguese playwright and poet Gil Vicente (c. 1465&#8211;c. 1536). His
                  plays were not published until 1562, when they were ordered into five categories, one of which was &#8216;Comedies&#8217;.</note> are in the
               Kings Library,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> The library of over 65,000 volumes assembled by George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of
                  the United Kingdom 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). It was given to the nation in 1823.</note> &amp; also the Portugueze Cancioneiro
               of Resende.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors"> The <title>Cancioneiro Geral</title> (1516), collected by Garcia de Resende
                  (1470&#8211;1536).</note> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Nicol<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Nicol (d. 1855?) was the son and
                  business partner of George Nicol (1740?&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), who was Bookseller to the King, 1781&#8211;1820.</note> perhaps could
               discover with little trouble by referring to the catalogue or ask the Librarian<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Sir Frederick
                  Augusta Barnard (1743&#8211;1830; <title>DNB</title>), Royal Librarian 1774&#8211;1828.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>