<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2703</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3974</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2703. Robert Southey to William
                  Peachy, 28 January 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2703.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British
                  Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2703" type="letter">
        <head>2703. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William
                  Peachy</ref>, <date when="1816-01-28">28 January 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another
                  hand] Major General Peachy/ <del>Bury St Edmunds</del>/ Beresfords Hotel/ Cork
                  St<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: FE/ 2/ 1816; 4 oClock/ FE 2/
                  1816<lb /> Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb /> MS: British
                  Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-01-28">28 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1816.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was the more vexed at finding you had left <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> (tho indeed the season of the year made me expect it) when we
               returned because we missed each other by only two days. Had we happened to take the
               same road we might have met, &#8211; but we came by Nottingham &amp; Halifax &amp; you I
               believe went by way of Lancaster.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our journey was very pleasant, &amp; in all things fortunate, &#8211; for I
               may even call the illness of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">the child</ref>. <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> During the Southeys&#8217; continental
                  tour, Edith May&#8217;s illness had delayed them at Aix-la-Chapelle, 10&#8211;17 October
                  1815.</note> so, since by detaining us at Aix la Chapelle it threw us in the way
               of some foreign officers, men of great ability &amp; high character. One of them was
               the very Aid-de Camp of Blucher who was with him when he was ridden over on the field
               of battle at Ligny.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> At the battle of
                  Ligny, 16 June 1815, Gebhard Leberecht von Bl&#252;cher (1742&#8211;1819), Field Marshal in
                  command of the Prussian army, was trapped under his horse and ridden over by
                  French cavalry. The officer whom Southey met was Ferdinand Augustus Leopold
                  Francis von Dresky (dates unknown), who led the 2nd Regiment of Silesian infantry
                  at the Battle of Ligny.</note> Another is the man {to} whom according to the
               account of all his comrades, Blucher was indebted for having won the battle of
                  Donowitz.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of Dennewitz, 6
                  September 1813, in which a French force was defeated by a combined army from
                  Prussia, Russia and Sweden. It was an important turning point in the war in north
                  Germany. The officer concerned was a Major Petry (dates unknown).</note> A third,
               Major Foster of the German Legion, was with the Duke of Brunswick in his memorable
               retreat, &amp; had been with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref> in all his battles from Busaco to
                  Thoulouse.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Constantine Charles Henry
                  Ernest Frederick Augustus Gustav Adolph de Forster (dates unknown), of the King&#8217;s
                  German Legion, a British Army unit made up of expatriate Germans. Forster had
                  previously served with Frederick William, Duke of Brunswick-Wolfenbuttel
                  (1771&#8211;1815). He commanded the German volunteer force raised to fight the French,
                  known as the Black Brunswickers, which had retreated to Britain in 1809. They then
                  participated, under the overall command of Wellington, in the Peninsular campaign,
                  including the victories at Bussaco in Portugal (27 September 1810) and Toulouse in
                  southern France (10&#8211;12 April 1814).</note> We lived five days with these officers,
               &amp; some of them escorted us out of the city when we departed for Maastricht.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The hatred which the Prussians bear the French &amp; their admiration
               of Lord Wellington &amp; the English was such as they ought to be. I gave as a toast
               the first day, &#8216;the Belle Alliance between Prussia &amp; England, &#8211; may it endure as
               long as the memory of the battle,&#8221;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                  Battle of Waterloo (18 June 1815). The Prussians wished to call the battle &#8216;La
                  Belle Alliance&#8217;, after the farmhouse at which Blucher and Wellington met near the
                  end of the battle.</note> &#8211; &amp; they all rose &amp; embraced &amp; shook hands
               with me; &#8211; overhauling my hand in a most unmerciful manner to discover whether I were
               a free-mason. We agreed admirably in one point, &#8211; in thinking that France had not
               suffered sufficient punishment, &amp; that for the security of Europe her territory
               ought to have been lessened. Were I to judge of the Prussian only by those whom I
               know, my opinion of them would be highly favourable; but their general conduct
               throughout Belgium has been the worst possible. There is but one character of them, &#8211;
               every one complains of their rapacity &amp; their insufferable insolence, &#8211; qualities
               in which they were said to have equalled the French, &amp; never to have palliated
               them, like the French, by their manners, &#8211; no monkey-moods, but always the tyger. I
               was grieved to <del>lear</del> hear this, &#8211; but so it is; &amp; <del>xx</del>
               wherever the military spirit predominates as strongly as it does in Prussia, the
               result is likely to be the same.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The British troops were as much extolled for their inoffensive
               conduct as for their courage. Never surely did the name of Englishman stand so high,
               &#8211; it seemed every where to command respect, attention &amp; kindness. We made two
               visits to the field of battle; &#8211; the second was for the purpose of obtaining some
               views of the more important points, which <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> an artist who was of our party made for me, &amp; which he
               is now preparing for the engraver that they may accompany my poem.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Seven sketches made by Nash at the Waterloo
                  battlefield were engraved and used as illustrations in Southey&#8217;s <title>The Poet&#8217;s
                     Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> Do not expect from it a
               description of the Battle. Modern battles are not subjects for poetry, &amp; if the
               objection to treating them as such were less weighty, I should still not choose to
               enter into a competition with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>. My plan
               differs from his <hi rend="ital">in toto</hi>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s <title>The Field of Waterloo; a Poem</title> (1815).</note> The
               title may in great part explain it; &#8216;A pilgrimage to Waterloo.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Our route home was by Courtray, Menin, Ypres, Dunkirk &amp; Calais, a
               line of such military ground that for that reason I was glad to see it. otherwise it
               is very uninteresting, &#8211; the only fine object being the great square at Ypres; &#8211; that
               indeed, tho partaking of the dilapidated appearance of the city is exceedingly fine;
               &#8211; indeed there is nothing finer in the Low Countries. Of all the cities which I ever
               saw Bruges pleased me most, &#8211; &amp; I found great beauty in the proper Flemish
               landscape, &#8211; such as it about Bruges &amp; in the Pays de Wals between Antwerp &amp;
               Ghent. The only grand scenery {thro} which we past was upon the Meuse from Namur to
               Liege, &#8211; <del>I</del> you probably know this line of country, &#8211; which excels any
               river scenery that I had ever seen before. I saw enough in the neighbourhood of Huy
               to convince me that this country is as fine in its detail, &amp; recesses, as in its
               general effect. With Spa I was disappointed, the armies who bivouacked about it in
               1813 cut down the wood, &amp; have thus given a naked appearance to the country.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I purchased a good many books, but have as yet only received a small
               part of them. &#8211; The destruction of the convent libraries has been very great, &amp;
               reminds me of the havock made at our own Reformation. &#8211; A bookseller told me that he
               had sold above 100,000 weight of books to be destroyed! This man<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1849), famous
                  Brussels bookseller.</note> knew the value of books, &amp; spoke of it with an
               unaffected feeling of regret. I found a general horror of the Revolution, &#8211; a general
               belief that Buonaparte<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Napoleon Bonaparte
                  (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814,1815).</note> had been purposely let
               loose from Elba (the absurdity of which it was in vain to combat) &amp; a general
               &amp; proper sense of dissatisfaction that, he had not been punished for all his
               crimes, &#8220;O my God! said the peasant who led me over the field of battle, &#8211; my house
               was full of wounded men: &#8211; it was nothing but sawing off arms &amp; sawing off legs &#8211;
               O my God! &#8211; &amp; all for one man! &#8211; why did not you put him to death?&#8221;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s first visit to the battlefield was on
                  3 October 1815. This report of his guide&#8217;s speech is very close to the words
                  Southey noted in his journal; see <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in
                     the Autumn of 1815</title> (Boston and New York, 1902), p. 98.</note> &#8211; Among
               the lower classes this feeling was universal. Their sense of right &amp; wrong had
               been outraged, &amp; they seemed to think that if such a criminal were suffered to go
               unpunished, there was an end of justice upon earth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey</ref> &amp; her
               sisters<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell.</ref>
          </note> join in kind remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>. Present my remembrances also &amp;
               believe me my dear Sir</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>