<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2938</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4209</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2938. Robert Southey to William Taylor, 12 March
                  1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2938" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2938.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from J. W. Robberds (ed.), A Memoir of the Life
                     and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843) .  Previously  published: J. W. Robberds
                  (ed.), A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                  471&#8211;475.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2938" type="letter">
        <head>2938. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">William Taylor</ref>, <date when="1817-03-12">12 March
                  1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from J. W. Robberds (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life
                     and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843)<lb /> Previously published: J. W. Robberds
                  (ed.), <title>A Memoir of the Life and Writings of the Late William Taylor of Norwich</title>, 2 vols (London, 1843), II, pp.
                  471&#8211;475.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-03-12">March 12, 1817. </date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Friend,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope you are mistaken in your apprehensions.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Taylor&#8217;s letter appears not to
                  have survived, but it clearly contained concerns about his health.</note> In physics as in metaphysics, a <hi rend="ital">little</hi> knowledge is a great evil to the possessor. Many are the mortal diseases of which I have observed symptoms in myself
               and in those with whom I am most nearly connected; for, in cases of this kind, the worst possibility is that upon which we are usually
               disposed to fix. Thus I hope it is with you, and that I may meet you in town relieved of your tumour, or satisfied that it is, like a
               crop of excrescences upon my scalp, not hurtful, though neither ornamental nor useful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have wanted spirits to write to you, for those redundant ones which I enjoyed during so many years, have taken their
               flight for ever; and what I can now muster are not more than are equal to the demand upon them. In this respect, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert&#8217;s</ref> death has produced a greater change in me than the course of time perhaps could
               ever have effected.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Southey had died on 17 April 1816.</note> This would not surprize
               you, if you had seen my manner of life with him. But no more of this.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am going to the Continent in May, purposing to be seven or eight weeks absent from England. My companions, unless I
               should be disappointed in either of them, are a Cumberland friend (<ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey
                  Senhouse</ref>, of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>) and <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>, an artist, who was with me at Waterloo and made the drawings there.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Nash had
                  produced seven of the eight drawings for <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> Switzerland and the Rhine
               are our objects; and our present plan is to reach Turin and Milan, and turn back to Geneva, for the purpose of seeing as much of the
               Alps as we can. I shall be in London the last week in April, and return to it the first in July.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s tour turned out to be longer than this estimate, lasting from May&#8211;August 1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will see that I have noticed the impudent plagiarism of M. Alphonse de Beauchamp, whose book I purchased at
               Brussels, where it put my friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref>, who happened to be thoroughly well
               acquainted with the original, in a fever of indignation.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Alphonse de Beauchamp&#8217;s (1767&#8211;1832)
                     <title>Histoire du Br&#233;sil</title> (1815) had criticised the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810),
                  whilst simultaneously borrowing heavily (and with no acknowledgement) from it; see Southey to John May, 6 October 1815, <title>The
                     Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2660. Southey later publicised the plagiarism in his
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, p. viii. Beauchamp had also borrowed from the writings of
                  others in his <title>Histoire de la Guerre de la Vend&#233;e et des Chouans, depuis son Origine jusqu&#8217;&#224; la Pacification de 1800</title>,
                  first published in 1806, with corrected second and third editions following in 1807 and 1809. Southey had pointed this out in an
                  article in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 1&#8211;69, describing Beauchamp as one who &#8216;when plagiarism fails him,
                  makes as little scruple of supplying the want of knowledge by invention as he does of appropriating to himself the labours of
                  others&#8217; (13).</note> This man is a notorious thief. M. De Puisaye accuses him of having stolen about one hundred pages from him in
               his &#8216;History of La Vendee.&#8217; General Turreau has plucked a few more feathers out of his tail; and in the same book I tracked him in like
               manner to other authors.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>M&#233;moires du Comte Josephe de Puisaye, Lieutenant-G&#233;n&#233;ral,
                     &amp;c. &amp;c. qui pourront servir &#224; l&#8217;Histoire du Parti Royaliste Fran&#231;ais, durant la derni&#233;re R&#233;volution</title>, 6 vols
                  (London, 1803&#8211;1808), VI, pp. 95, 113, 567; and Louis-Marie Turreau, Baron de Garambouville (1756&#8211;1816), <title>M&#233;moires pour servir
                     &#224; l&#8217;Histoire de la Guerre de la Vend&#233;e</title>, 2nd edn (Paris, 1815), pp. 188&#8211;191. Southey pointed out Beauchamp&#8217;s indebtedness
                  throughout his review article on accounts of La Vend&#233;e, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 1&#8211;69 (e.g. 9, 13).</note>
               My third volume is gone to the press: far the greater part will be from unprinted documents.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As soon as I return home in the summer, my &#8216;History of the Peninsular War&#8217; will go to the printer.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> For this I have ample
               materials and the best sources of information. When you read it, I do not despair of convincing you that philosophy and freedom have
               suffered much more from their inconsistent friends than from their bigotted enemies. In spite of both, I hope they will prosper. But we
               shall not agree so well in our definition of philosophy as we shall of freedom. In my judgment, any philosophy that weakens our belief
               of immortality is a curse to mankind. Of this I am assured, that, were it not for that belief, the burthen of life would be heavier
               than I could bear, although no man has more reason to be thankful for his lot.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In poetry I have done little of late; yet in the course of the year I expect to bring forth a &#8216;Tale of Paraguay,&#8217; about
               some 1500 lines in length, and in Spencer&#8217;s stanza.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was not
                  published until 1825. The main body of the poem ran to 224 Spenserian stanzas, the verse form used in Edmund Spenser&#8217;s (1552?&#8211;1599;
                     <title>DNB</title>) <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590&#8211;1596).</note> I have begun a desultory poem in blank verse, pitched in
               a higher key than Cowper&#8217;s, and in a wiser strain of philosophy than Young&#8217;s;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Cowper
                  (1731&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Task</title> (1785), and Edward Young (c. 1683&#8211;1765; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     Complaint, or, Night-Thoughts on Life, Death, and Immortality</title> (1742&#8211;1746). </note> but as yet I have not recovered heart
               enough to proceed with it; nor is it likely that it will be published during my life.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The new
                  poem was &#8216;Consolation&#8217;. Although it was never completed, work towards it can be seen in the two posthumously-published pieces:
                  &#8216;Fragmentary Thoughts Occasioned by His Son&#8217;s Death&#8217;, <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished): With Other Poetical
                     Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 93&#8211;95, and &#8216;Additional Fragment, Occasioned by the Death of His Son&#8217;, <title>Poetical Works
                     of Robert Southey. Complete in One Volume</title> (London, 1850), p. 815. </note> Too much of my time is occupied in reviewing.
               Of this I must not complain, because thence it is that I draw by far the larger part of my ways and means; this kind of literary labour
               being, in my case, as largely overpaid as every other has been inadequately remunerated. You probably will know my hand in the
               Quarterly; yet it is often ridiculously mistaken there. They give me credit at Cambridge for writing upon Baptismal Regeneration &#8211; a
               subject upon which I should think it no credit to bestow even a thought;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The article Southey
                  had not written was in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 475&#8211;511; it was authored by John Davison (1777&#8211;1834;
                     <title>DNB</title>), with input from John Keble (1792&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>); at this time both were connected to the Anglican
                  theological hot-house of Oriel College, Oxford. </note> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref>, of the
               Examiner, supposes that I reviewed his &#8216;Rimini,&#8217; whereas I wrote an indignant letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to express my utter disapprobation of the reviewal.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Leigh Hunt, <title>The
                     Story of Rimini, a Poem</title> (1816), the subject of a disparaging notice in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 14 (January
                  1816), 473&#8211;481. The article&#8217;s author was John Wilson Croker. Southey had objected to it in a letter to Murray, 24 August 1816,
                  Letter 2831.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> France, if she should escape any further commotions, is in danger of relapsing into her old despotism, not from any
               desire on the part of the king to re-establish it, but from the utter unfitness of the people for a representative government. In the
               present state of the most civilized nations, it seems clear, that there can be no other good form of government; and yet how to fit a
               people for this, who have been entirely unaccustomed to it, or to anything approaching, is a problem which has not yet been solved.
               France might have taught me this truth; but I did not learn it till my hopes from the Cortes were disappointed.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">When the Bourbon regime was restored in France under Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France 1814&#8211;1824),
                  the monarchy had been obliged to concede the Charter of 1814, which instituted a bicameral Parliament. This had not prevented a
                  &#8216;White Terror&#8217; in 1815&#8211;1816 in which the administration was purged of officials loyal to the Revolution. About 6,000 people were
                  tried for various political offences and there were 300 mob lynchings in the South of France. The Cortes had ruled those parts of
                  Spain not occupied by France in 1810&#8211;1813 and created the liberal Constitution of 1812. Southey felt its doctrinaire hostility to
                  the Church, nobility and monarchy had made it difficult to create a stable Spanish political system.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you! To say how I should rejoice to see you here, I hope, is needless; but I beseech you, whenever you have
               no tie to prevent you from so long a journey, remember that for fourteen years I have earnestly desired it.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had lived in Keswick since 1803.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>