<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3000</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4271</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3000. Robert Southey to Edith Southey, 11 June
                  1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3000" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3000.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 267&#8211;271 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3000" type="letter">
        <head>3000. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1817-06-11">11 June
                  1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: Angleterre/ To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland<lb />
                  Stamped: [illegible]<lb /> Postmarks: B/ JU/ 24 1817; E FO/ JU-24/ 1817<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 267&#8211;271 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Turin.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-06-11">Wednesday 11 June 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Edith</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wrote to you on this day fortnight from Neufchatel, since which time all has gone well with us &amp; we have
               travelled over very interesting ground. Half a day brought us to Yverdun, where the other half was past for the sake of seeing
                  Pestalozzi.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The Swiss educational reformer, Johann Heinrich Pestalozzi (1746&#8211;1827). The
                  &#8216;Pestalozzi Method&#8217; argued that children should learn through activity and through things, rather than words. As part of this,
                  children should be free to pursue their own interests and draw their own conclusions.</note> The next day to Lausanne, where for the
               mere beauty of the place we staid a day. Sunday to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Awdrys 7 miles off on the way to Geneva. Here I found Miss
               Bigg &amp; was received by the Awdrys like a person connected with them by family ties.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  Awdry family were John Awdry (1766&#8211;1844), solicitor in Reybridge and his wife Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert
                  Hill&#8217;s wife, Catherine. &#8216;Miss Bigg&#8217; was a third, unmarried sister, Alethea Bigg (1777&#8211;1847). Southey visited them at Echichens on
                  1&#8211;3 June and 29 June-3 July.</note> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> A. has evidently been the flower of the family, &amp; a sweet flower she
               must have been in her prime. I was much pleased both with her, &amp; her husband who is a great friend of the <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Generals</ref>. The General was there ten or twelve days, &#8211; he would walk home from Morges one
               night, a mile distant lost his way &amp; did not get to the house till one o clock, lights being set up in the trees of the Chateau to
               guide him, &amp; men sent out in all directions. This adventure as you may suppose occasions much mirth among his Swiss acquaintances
               to whom he talked half in French &amp; half in English about D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Johnson &amp;c<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>), author and lexicographer.</note> &#8211; just as he <del>xxxxxxx</del>
               {does} in England. We staid Monday with the Awdrys, &amp; shall return to rest with them on our way back. <del>Wed</del>{Tues}day to
               Geneva seeing Ferney<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferney, on the French-Swiss border; home of Francoise-Marie Arouet
                  (Voltaire) (1694&#8211;1778) in 1759&#8211;1778.</note> in the way. Wednesday we halted to see this famous, most ugly, most odd, &amp; most
               striking city, compared to which Lisbon is a city of sweet savours. Friday to Aix, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">that</hi> Aix where the adventure
               of King Charlemagne &amp; the Archbishop happened: <del>which</del> Pasquier (in whom I found the story) mistakes it for Aix la
                  Chapelle.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Aix-les-Bains, mistaken for Aix-la-Chapelle (Aachen) in Etienne Pasquier
                  (1529&#8211;1615), <title>Recherches de la France</title>, 3 vols (Paris, 1611), II, p. 272. Southey used Pasquier&#8217;s story about
                  Charlemagne (742&#8211;814; Holy Roman Emperor 800&#8211;814) in his poem &#8216;The Ring&#8217;, <title>Morning Post</title>, 22 February 1798. Southey
                  noted Pasquier&#8217;s mistake in <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), V, p. 86.</note> There is a Lake here, &amp;
               a magnificent one it is. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">N.</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">S.</ref> both made sketches of it before breakfast on Friday. We reached Les Echelles that
               night, &amp; Saturday visited the Chartreuse, -<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Head monastery of the Carthusian order, founded
                  1084. </note> this was a horse expedition, &amp; a whole days work; but we were most amply rewarded for the heat &amp; fatigue which
               we endured. I am fully disposed to believe with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> that there is
               nothing finer <del>xxx</del> in Switzerland than this.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth had visited in 1790.</note>
               The place took us two stages out of our way, which we had to retrace on Sunday, &#8211; they happened to be remarkably interesting ones,
               having the mountain pass of the Echelles in one, with a tunnel thro the mountain, &amp; by the road in the other the most glorious
               waterfall I ever beheld, that evening we entered the Savoy Alps at Aiguebelle &amp; slept at La Grande Maison, a sort of large
                  Estalagem<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A Portuguese term for a sort of inn.</note> in the midst of Borrodale scenery upon
               a large scale. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">N.</ref> made a view from the window. I do not stop to describe things
               because my journal will do all this. Monday we continued our way up the valley, following the course, or rather ascending the river
               Arco, &#8211; such a river! &#8211; the colour of my coat precisely, which tho M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hyde<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Hyde (d. 1820) was Southey&#8217;s London tailor.</note> admits it to be a very genteel mixture as well as well calculated to hide the
               dust, is a very bad colour for a river, &#8211; but for force &amp; fury, it exceeds any thing that I had ever before seen or imagined, we
               followed it as far as Lans le Bourg, a little town at the foot of Mount Cenis, &amp; itself as high above the sea as the top of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>. Yesterday (Tuesday) we crost Mount Cenis &#8211; descended into the plain of
               Piedmont, &amp; after the longest of all our days journeys in point of time reached Turin just as it grew dark. The washerwoman has
               been called in. I have brought up my journal, &#8211; yesterday alone cost me more than five pages so you may judge how difficult it is to
               keep time with it. We stay here tomorrow &amp; then start for Milan. <hi rend="ital">This</hi> place (Turin) is our farthest point from
               home, &amp; from Milan we turn our faces homeward on Monday by way of Como &amp; the Simplon. We are to visit Chamouny on the way from
               Martigny. My next letter will probably be from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Awdrys when I have recrossed the Alps or even before we recross
               them which will be in about ten days I shall almost fancy myself in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> From Besan&#231;on to this place it has been one succession of fine scenery, yet with such variety that every day has
               surprised us. Fine weather began on the first of June, &amp; here in Italy we have found a great difference of climate. On the other
               side the Alps the cherries are not larger than green peas; here they are ripe. Currants, oranges &amp; Alpine strawberries are in the
               markets, &amp; apricots, which are perfectly worthless.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wonder where the fleas are: for I have neither seen nor felt them. One Persevejo<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Portuguese for &#8216;bug&#8217;.</note> found us out at Lans le Bourg, where I certainly did not expect to be attended by any
               such enemies, considering the temperature of the place. Here <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">N.</ref> found one on his
               linen this morning &amp; we are as hot as at Lisbon. But we turn our face to the NE when we leave this place &amp; when we depart from
               Milan we shall approach &#8216;cooler climate&#8217;. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">S</ref> has a touch of the growels to day
               so that our resting here could not have come in better time, he is better this evening, &amp; I hope will rise tomorrow in good
               condition again. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">N</ref> is as well as he ever is, &#8211; but he also is glad of a little
               rest. Rest or motion are the same to me. God be thanked I am quite well, I like the travelling days best, because at night I feel
               myself so much advanced on the way, &amp; I stand in need of the resting ones to bring up my journal &amp; write to England. I wrote
               from Geneva to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>. Our journey has been in all respects pleasant, &amp; I shall
               find the full advantage of it in the knowledge which it has given me, &amp; the new images, with which it has stored my memory. Of the
               Alps, I will only say here that they make me love <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> better than ever &amp; that
               Skiddaw will outlast them, &#8211; at least will outlast all that we have yet seen, for they are falling to pieces. The wreck &amp; ruin
               which they display in many places is hardly to be described, &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> offered me
               400&#163; for such a volume as Pauls Letters<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Scott, <title>Paul&#8217;s Letters to his
                     Kinsfolk</title> (1816), a description of his journey to the site of the Battle of Waterloo (18 June 1815) in the autumn of
                  1815.</note> &amp; my journal is in a fair way of extending to as much in length.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are burnt like gipsies, especially <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">S.</ref> &#8211; All friends round
                  <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> has been our daily toast; &amp; we drank it in all kinds &amp; qualities of
               wine. As for news we know not how the world goes on, &amp; have ceased to think about it, the only thing for which we are anxious is to
               get letters from home, &amp; this we shall do when we get to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Awdrys. If I could but know that all was well -</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you. Good night my own dear Edith</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1817-06-12">Thursday afternoon. </date>
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey"> S.</ref> rose this morning perfectly recovered. His yesterdays attack which
                  began with sickness &amp; ended in growels was evidently a salutary effort of nature &amp; a successful one to set all to rights.
                  This morning we have been seeing the churches, the university (where Alfieri<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The Italian
                     dramatist Vittorio Alfieri (1749&#8211;1803). He attended the Royal Academy at Turin intermittently 1759&#8211;1766.</note> studied or rather
                  wasted the years in which he should have studied) the churches &amp;c &#8211; &amp; we have seen the identical river into which Phaeton
                  tumbled, tho I believe no person can point out the precise place where he fell.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek
                     mythology Phaeton, stuck by Zeus&#8217;s thunderbolt, tumbled from the skies into the river Eridanos. Classical writers disagreed about
                     the location, and even the existence on earth, of this river, but some identified it as the Po, which runs through Turin.</note>
                  It is nearly five o clock we have dined, &amp; I have to write down all that I have noticed in Turin, before we walk out for the
                  last time, then to return at 8 to our coffee, pack up our clean linen, &amp; make all ready for rising tomorrow at four o clock.
                  Yesterday the weather was tremendously hot, today it is hot enough but much cooler. I have not been bitten by the mosquitos, tho one
                  rascal woke me <del>xx</del> with his trumpet at La Maison Grande. Tomorrow night I <del>xxxx</del> shall be in bodily fear of them,
                  for we shall be in the low lands of Lombardy. &#8211; By the time this reaches you we shall be again in Switzerland, &amp; our way home
                  will then appear as nothing. </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> Except a small package at Paris (&amp; but a small one) I have not bought more books than could be packed into my
                  portmanteau or stowed into the carriage. The booksellers shops wherever we have been are miserable. As something to set off against
                  this disappointment, we have met with no fleas, to my great surprize. Neither in France, Switzerland, Savoy, or Italy do they ever
                  wash their floors, &amp; yet there are no fleas. I have neither seen nor felt one, &amp; therefore doubt whether the very few red
                  spots which I have noticed from time to time upon my skin were flea bites. Once more God bless you my dear Edith. &#8211; If you want
                  money, write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> for it, &#8211; he has money in his hands. &#8211; I do
                  not think of closing with <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> offer about this journal, &#8211; but shall think
                  seriously of putting together all my journals, including those in Portugal.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s three
                     journals from his Portuguese trip of 1800&#8211;1801 were published in Adolfo Cabral (ed.), <title>Robert Southey: Journals of a Residence in Portugal
                        1800&#8211;1801 and a Visit to France</title> (Oxford, 1960), pp. 1&#8211;61. His journal for his journey to the
                     Netherlands in 1815 appeared as <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of 1815</title> (1902). Other, briefer,
                     journals of British travels in 1799&#8211;1800, 1805 and 1809 appeared in <title>Common-Place Book</title>, ed. John Wood Warter, 4
                     series (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 517&#8211;534.</note> Love to all. Tell the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref> I like Borrodale better than before, &#8211; but that there are glorious places in Savoy for a Bhow leigh.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably an in-joke about the house that Mary Barker, nicknamed the Bhow Begum, was building in a
                     scenic part of Borrowdale.</note> God bless you.</p>
          <closer>
            <signed>RS</signed>
          </closer>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>