<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2946</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4217</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2946. Robert Southey to the Editor of The Courier, [19 March 1817]</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2946" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2946.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. ALS; 3p.  .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 252&#8211;255 [misdated 17 March 1817]. Note on MS: The letter
                  survives as an early draft, which is reproduced here. Southey made a fair copy,
                  which appears not to have survived, and he this sent as an enclosure to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn on 19 March [1817], Letter 2948. Wynn&#8217;s absence from home
                  meant there was a delay in his receiving it. By the time he did so the debate had
                  moved on and so Southey decided to incorporate this letter into his pamphlet
                     A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P. (1817). </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2946" type="letter">
        <head>2946. Robert Southey to the <ref type="a" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Editor of <title>The Courier</title>
          </ref>, <date when="1817-03-19">[19 March 1817]</date>
          </head><p>MS: Berg Collection, New York
                  Public Library. ALS; 3p. <lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 252&#8211;255 [misdated 17 March 1817].<lb /> Note on MS: The letter
                  survives as an early draft, which is reproduced here. Southey made a fair copy,
                  which appears not to have survived, and he this sent as an enclosure to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn on 19 March [1817], Letter 2948. Wynn&#8217;s absence from home
                  meant there was a delay in his receiving it. By the time he did so the debate had
                  moved on and so Southey decided to incorporate this letter into his pamphlet
                     <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P.</title> (1817). </p>
        <p rend="center"> To the Editor of the Courier</p>
        <p rend="center"> ____</p>
        <p>Sir,</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Allow me a place in your columns for my &#8220;last words&#8221; concerning Wat
                  Tyler.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The letter deals with the
                  publication in 1817, without Southey&#8217;s consent, of his Jacobin play <title>Wat
                     Tyler</title>, composed in 1794.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In the year 1794 this manuscript was placed by <ref type="m" target="people.html#LovellRobert">a friend of mine (long since deceased)</ref> in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ridgeways hands. <del>Going to</del> Being shortly afterwards in
               London myself for a few days, I called on M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ridgeway in Newgate;
               &amp; he &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Symonds agreed to publish it.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Ridgway (1755&#8211;1838), radical publisher.
                  Southey had visited him in Newgate Prison on 12 January 1795, to arrange
                  publication of <title>Wat Tyler</title>; see Southey to Edith Fricker [c. 12
                  January 1795], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>,
                  Letter 123. Ridgeway shared his rooms at Newgate with his fellow-publisher Henry
                  Symonds (1741&#8211;1816) and William Winterbotham. Ridgway and Symonds had been
                  imprisoned for four years in 1793 for publishing Thomas Paine&#8217;s <title>The Rights
                     of Man</title> (1791&#8211;1792), but continued to publish works from Newgate, including
                  Winterbotham&#8217;s <title>An Historical, Geographical, Commercial, and Philosophical
                     View of the American United States</title> (1795).</note> I understood that
               they had changed their intention because no proof sheet was sent <del>xxxx to</del>
               me, &amp; acquiescing readily in their cooler opinion, made no inquiry concerning it.
               More than two years elapsed before I revisited London,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had returned to London in February 1797 to embark on
                  his legal studies at Gray&#8217;s Inn.</note> &#8211; &amp; then if I had thought of the
               manuscript it would have appeared a thing of too little consequence to take the
               trouble of claiming it for the mere purpose of throwing it behind the fire. That it
               might be published surreptitiously at any future time, <del>from motives of
                  gratuitous wickedness</del> was a wickedness of which I never dreamt. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To these facts I have made oath.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had sworn an affidavit before a Master of Chancery; see
                  his letter to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 7 March 1817, Letter 2935.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Winterbottom</ref>, a Dissenting
               Minister, has sworn on the contrary that Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Ridgeway
               &amp; Symonds having declined the publication, <del>the</del> it was undertaken by
               himself &amp; Daniel Isaac Eaton;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Daniel
                  Isaac Eaton (1753&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), radical publisher. Winterbotham
                  claimed in his affidavit that when Southey had visited Newgate in January 1795 he
                  had given the manuscript of <title>Wat Tyler</title> to Eaton and Winterbotham,
                  and surrendered his copyright to them. </note> &#8211; that I <hi rend="ital">gave</hi>
               them the copy as their own property, &amp; gave them, moreover, a fraternal embrace
               in gratitude for their gracious acceptance of it; &amp; that he, the said <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref> verily believed he had a right <hi rend="ital">now</hi>, after an interval of three &amp; twenty years, to publish it
               as his own. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My recollection is perfectly distinct, notwithstanding the lapse of
               time; &amp; it was likely {to be so} as I was never on any other occasion within the
               walls of Newgate. The work had been delivered to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ridgeway; it
               was for him that I enquired, &amp; into his apartments I was shown. There I saw M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Symonds, &amp; there I saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Winterbottom</ref> also, whom I knew to be a Dissenting
               Minister. <hi rend="ital">I never saw Daniel Isaac Eaton in my life</hi>; &#8211; &amp; as
               for the story of the embrace every person who knows my disposition &amp; manners will
               at once perceive it to be an impudent falsehood. Two other persons came into the room
               while I was there, the name of the one was Lloyd, <del>xx</del> I believe he had been
               an officer in the army,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Thomas
                  Lloyd (1756&#8211;1827). Though born in London he had served with American forces in the
                  War of Independence 1776&#8211;1779 before becoming a stenographer reporting on debates
                  in Congress. He returned to England in 1791 and was imprisoned for debt in 1792,
                  receiving a further three years in Newgate (1793&#8211;1796) for putting up a political
                  poster in the Fleet prison. Lloyd later re-emigrated to the United States.</note>
               &#8211; that of the other was Barrow &#8211; I remembered him a Bishops-boy at Westminster.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Richard Barrow (c. 1770&#8211;1827),
                  committed to Newgate for two years in 1794 for &#8216;libels to excite rebellion&#8217; after
                  an incident at Miller&#8217;s Cookshop in Smithfield on 23 August 1794, when he and
                  another member of the London Corresponding Society were reported to have
                  distributed a seditious handbill. Barrow was later a surgeon at Hounslow. At
                  Westminster School &#8216;Bishop&#8217;s Boys&#8217; were four boys nominated by the Dean of
                  Westminster and the Master of the School. They were supported by a foundation
                  deriving from John Williams (1582&#8211;1650; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Lincoln
                  1621&#8211;1641. The advantages of a &#8216;Bishop&#8217;s Boy&#8217; were considerable and included
                  exemption from fees at Westminster School and the right to progress to a closed
                  scholarship at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge. Richard Barrow had not been a
                  &#8216;Bishop&#8217;s Boy&#8217; at Westminster but George Barrow (dates unknown), possibly his
                  brother, had been. So Southey has possibly confused the two.</note> I left the
               room with an assurance that Messr<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Ridgeway &amp; Symonds were
               to be the publishers; &#8211; in what way <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">Winterbottom</ref> might
               be connected with them I neither knew nor cared, &amp; <hi rend="ital">Eaton I never
                  saw</hi>. &#8211; There is no earthly balance in which oaths can be weighed against each
               other, &#8211; but character is something in the scale: And <del>that the</del> it is
               perfectly in character that the man who <del>should</del> has published Wat Tyler
               under the present circumstances, should swear &#8211; as <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Winterbottom</ref> has sworn.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thus much concerning the facts. As to the work itself, I am desirous
               that my feelings should neither be misrepresented nor misunderstood <del>by those in
                  whose opinion I</del>. It contains the <del>broad dramatic</del> statement of
               opinions which I have long outgrown, &amp; which are stated more broadly because of
               this dramatic form. Were there a sentiment or an expression which bordered upon
               irreligion or impurity, I should look upon it with shame &amp; contrition <del>With
                  regard to any enthusiastic notion of</del> {but I can feel neither for opinions
               of} universal equality, taken up as they were conscientiously in early youth, acted
               upon in disregard of all worldly considerations, &amp; left behind {me} in the same
               straight-forward course as I advanced in years. The piece was written when such
               opinions &#8211; or rather such hopes &amp; fancies, were confined to a very small number
               of the educated classes, when those who were deemed Republicans were exposed to
               personal danger from the populace, &amp; when a spirit of anti Jacobinism {prevailed}
               which I cannot characterise better than by saying that it was {as} blind &amp; as
               intolerant as the Jacobinism of the present day. The times have changed. Had it been
               published surreptitiously under any other political circumstances, I should have
               suffered it to take its course, in full confidence that it would do no harm, &amp;
               would be {speedily} forgotten <del>as xxxx</del> as it deserved. The present state of
               things, which is such as to make it doubtful whether <ref type="m" target="people.html#Winterbottom">
            <del>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Winterbottom</del>
          </ref> {the publisher} be not
               as much actuated by {public}<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">{publick}:
                  probably inserted in another, unidentified hand.</note> mischief as by
                  {private}<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">{private}: probably inserted
                  in another, unidentified hand.</note> malignity, rendered it my duty to appeal for
               justice, &amp; stop the circulation of what no man had a right to publish. And this I
               did, not as one ashamed &amp; penitent for having expressed crude opinions, &amp;
               warm feelings in his youth (feelings right in themselves, &amp; wrong only in their
               direction) &#8211; <del>or opinions which were xxxxxxxxx with those</del> but as a man
               whose life has been such that it may set slander at defiance; whose name is
               honourably distinguished abroad as well as at home, &amp; who is unremittingly
               endeavouring to deserve well of his country &amp; of mankind. </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1">Robert Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>