<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2705</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3976</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2705. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 31 January
                  1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2705.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 150.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2705" type="letter">
        <head>2705. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1816-01-31">31 January
                  1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ FE 3/ 1816 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 3 FE 3/ 1816<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 150.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-01-31"> 31 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.1816</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your stocks are on the road, &#8211; they are directed to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctors,</ref> &amp; travel by waggon: the second volume of Mungo Park<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mungo Park
                  (1771&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Travels in the Interior Districts of Africa: Performed in the Years 1795, 1796, and 1797,
                     with an Account of a Subsequent Mission to that Country in 1805</title>, 2 vols (1816).</note> is packed with them, &amp; I have
               taken this opportunity of sending your octavo Joan of Arc (which suffered on the way from Lisbon) &#8211; Gibbons Miscellanies, &amp;
               Plutarch&#8217;s Lives, of both which I have duplicates.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The second edition of Southey&#8217;s epic poem
                     <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1798); Edward Gibbon (1737&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Miscellaneous Works, with Memoirs of his
                     Life and Writings</title> (1814), no.1100 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; <title>Plutarch&#8217;s Lives</title>, no. 2267
                  in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> hopes that your other stocks are in better condition than the pattern one,
               &#8211; as otherwise you will stand in much need of these before they arrive; &amp; she hopes also that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> will forgive her for aiding &amp; abetting you in your continuance of a costume
               which seems to have <del>xxx</del> few admirers.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Upper stocks were trousers reaching from the
                  waist to the knee; nether stocks were hose reaching from knee to ankle.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Burn<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Burn (1750&#8211;1821) was a friend of the Southeys from their days in
                  Portugal. A member of the Lisbon Factory, he was well-known to Herbert Hill and John May and had first met Southey in Lisbon in
                  1796. He moved to London in 1806. Parliament had voted &#163;100,000 in 1811 to relieve the sufferings of the Portuguese people following
                  the French invasion of 1810&#8211;1811. The money was distributed by Commissioners, whose report was placed before the House of Commons on
                  6 July 1814.</note> has sent me the letters which the Committee received from Portugal, containing statements of the sufferings
               occasioned by Massenas<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Napoleonic Marshal Andr&#233; Massena (1758&#8211;1817) led the French campaign
                  against Portugal in 1810&#8211;1811; Southey narrated his actions in the <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (London, 1823&#8211;1832),
                  II, pp. 710&#8211;784.</note> army: &#8211; these are important documents of which I shall not fail to make good use. <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymple</ref>
          <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> See Robert Southey to Hew
                  Dalrymple, 6 March 1816 (Letter 2732), for Southey&#8217;s reply to Dalrymple&#8217;s offer.</note> also, thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray,</ref> has sent me some papers, &#8211; I am glad the communication has not been more direct, &#8211; for
               tho he will not be spoken of with more <del>xxx</del> severity for the Cintra Convention than <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Ld Wellington</ref>, there is nothing to come after on his part which may put that
               action out of remembrance.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> Dalrymple was one of the generals responsible for signing, on 30
                  August 1808, the Convention of Cintra, whereby the French army commanded by Jean-Andoche Junot (1771&#8211;1813) and defeated by
                  Anglo-Portuguese forces under Wellington at Vimeiro on 21 August, was allowed to retreat intact, with its weapons, from Portugal.
                  Wellesley, who did not sign the Convention, had been superseded in command by Dalrymple and by Sir Harry Burrard (1755&#8211;1813;
                     <title>DNB</title>). These veteran generals, just arrived in Iberia, were content to make peace. After a national outcry in
                  Britain, a Court of Inquiry was appointed, which failed to punish Burrard and Dalrymple. They were, however, never afterwards given
                  command.</note> &#8211; At the same time I received a good account of the Douro campaign in a letter from an officer who fell shortly
               afterwards at Talavera.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Battle of the Douro occurred on 12 May 1809 when British and
                  Portuguese troops under Wellington defeated French troops and took the city of Porto. The Battle of Talavera took place on 27&#8211;28
                  July 1809 as Wellington&#8217;s British forces and a Spanish army met the French on the road from Portugal to Madrid. The officer who
                  provided this letter is unidentified.</note> This was sent me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref>
               friend Haygarth.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> William Haygarth (1784&#8211;1825), poet and travel writer, son of the physician,
                  John Haygarth (1740&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I am rich in materials; &amp; more will be coming in. &#8211; I have requested <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> to procure me information concerning our negociations with the Spanish Court
               before the battle of Jena,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> French forces annihilated the Prussian army at Jena on 14 October
                  1806. At this time Spain was allied to France, but attempts were being made in both Spain and Britain to loosen the
                  connection.</note> &#8211; when <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Ld Grenville</ref> was minister.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> Lord Grenville, Wynn&#8217;s uncle, was Prime Minister in 1806&#8211;1807.</note> As soon as the Brazil<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey intended to follow his <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) with a <title>History of the Peninsular
                     War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is compleated I shall go to press.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <hi rend="ital">4</hi> Kings must have been an error of the pen,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> In
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, p. 347, where Southey mentions &#8216;The Three Kings of the
                  East&#8217;.</note> &#8211; I shall adopt your emendations when the proofs arrive. This night I shall finish that chapter, &amp; begin one upon
               the famous affair of Carde&#241;as the Bishop &amp; the Jesuits,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Chapter 25 of the <title>History
                     of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, pp. 381&#8211;448, dealt with the struggle between the Bishop of Paraguay,
                  Bernardino de Cardenas Ponce (1579&#8211;1668), and the Jesuits, in the 1640s.</note> this story will lead me by an easy transition to the
               affairs of Maranham Vieyra &amp;c<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> Chapter 26 of the <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                  (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, pp. 449&#8211;500, discussed Antonio Vieira (1608&#8211;1697), the Brazilian-born Jesuit renowned for his preaching,
                  and Provincial of the order in northern Maranhao.</note> &#8211; &amp; I shall take a spell which will carry me far on my journey before
               it be time to think again of my Quarterly ways &amp; means.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is here looking about for a house. He receives bad accounts from home of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">his wifes</ref> health &amp; spirits, &#8211; both seem in a sad state, one injuring the
               other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My fears concerning the Acta Sanctorum were well founded.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had worried
                  that the consignment of books he had bought in Brussels in 1815, now arriving in England, would not include the massive, 53&#8211;volume
                  compendium of hagiographies entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library. In
                  fact, he had bought the 6&#8211;volume abridgement (1783&#8211;1794), no. 152 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> The books which <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Vardon</ref> mistook for them were a selection of those lives which
               relate to <del>xxx</del> Belgium, chronologically arranged, with additions dissertations &amp;c &#8211; in three large quartos, which I got
               at a waste paper price; &#8211; a useful &amp; important work, but the Revolution broke it off. The cargo which has arrived consists of a few
               books purchased at Ghent, &amp; <del>xxx</del> a detachment from Brussels: the most important among them are Helyots Ordres Monastiques
               in 8 4tos,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors"> Hippolyte Helyot (1660&#8211;1716), <title>Histoire des Ordres Religieux et
                     Militaires</title> (1792), no. 1183 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; the Imago Primi S&#230;culi Soc. Jes:<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Imago Primi S&#230;culi Societatis Jesu a Provincia Flandro-Belgica</title> (1640), no. 1435 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> &#8211; &amp; the Anti-Jesuit Hist de Paraguay by their great enemy Bernardo Iba&#241;ez de Echavarry, &#8211; a book which it was
               most fortunate that I stumbled upon in time &amp; which has now arrived just as it is wanted.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Bernardo Iba&#241;ez de Echavarri (1715&#8211;1762),<title> Histoire du Paraguay sous les Jesuits</title> (1780), no. 2090 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; My larger purchase of about 115 volumes I have not yet heard of, but have written
               concerning them. They are perhaps detained till the bookseller can compleat his set of the Acta for me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The weather is bitterly cold, &#8211; but we are all well. My young ones have learnt to look for my &#8216;bumps&#8217; as diligently as
               the two elder<del>s</del> Bears,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was suffering from two growths upon his pate: his
                  children were acting as amateur phrenologists. The two &#8216;elder bears&#8217; were Herbert Hill&#8217;s eldest sons, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">Herbert, Jnr</ref>.</note>
               &#8211; this is turning an excrescence to some account. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> has
               been here; &#8211; he feels at home with us, &amp; we miss him much on his departure &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My poem would have been finished if <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> presence had not
               interrupted it. It will however be ready before the engravings.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816) was illustrated by eight engravings of places around which the fighting
                  centred, after drawings by Nash and by Charles Bell (1774&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>).</note> I have heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>, &#8211; &amp; he is at work for me &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the whole peerage</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>