<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3195</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4466</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3195. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 18 September 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3195" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3195.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 171. ALS; 4p..  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the
                     Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 97&#8211;99 [in
                  part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3195" type="letter">
        <head>3195. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>,<date when="1818-09-18"> 18 September 1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert
                  Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ SP
                  21/ 1818 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 21 SE 21/ 1818 <lb /> Seal: red wax, design
                  illegible<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 171. ALS; 4p.<title>
              <lb />
            </title>Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the
                     Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 97&#8211;99 [in
                  part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-09-18">18 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
                  1818.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My third volume<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819). 750 copies of the first volume
                  were printed, followed by 750 copies of the second and third volumes. The first
                  volume sold out by mid&#8211;1820 and this volume only was revised and reprinted in
                  1822.</note> is now about half way thro the press (42 sheets are printed. My
               profits last year {(ending at midsummer)} upon the two former volumes were 56&#163; for
               the first, 4&#8211;16&#8211; for the second. Of the second rather more than half are gone, of the
               first 102 are left, &amp; these will probably be carried off when the concluding
               volume appears. I fear there will be a good many copies wasted by the first volume
               having devolved into ignorant or careless hands. However the likelihood of the works
               coming to a second edition in my time seems greater than I had <del>xxx</del>
               expected. The <hi rend="ital">clean sheets</hi> came to me the other day, &amp; there
               is a great satisfaction in looking over them. The arrival of the Corographia
                  Brazilica<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Manoel Aires de Casal
                  (1754&#8211;1821), <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Rela&#231;&#227;o Historico&#8211;Geografica do Reino
                     do Brazil</title> (1817), no. 3252 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> was so just in time, that it would make up for many ill chances in
               life. &#8211; In your translation<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Voyage up the
                  Madeira in 1749, with a MS. Map&#8217;, no. 3849 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> of the Voyage up the Madeira you have not noticed the name either
               of the writer, or of the Commander of the Expedition: &#8211; the latter I conclude to
               {have been} <del>xxx</del> Joam de Sousa e Azovedo,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819),
                  III, pp. 359&#8211;360, related some of the journeys of Joao de Sousa Azevedo (dates
                  unknown). But, as Southey&#8217;s book makes clear, he was not the leader of the
                  expedition on the Madeira, which is described at <title>History of Brazil</title>,
                  3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 349&#8211;359.</note> whom the Corografia calls a
               famous Sertanista,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A Brazilian term for an
                  explorer of the wild forested interior; see Manoel Aires de Casal,
                     <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Rela&#231;&#227;o Historico-Geografica do Reino do
                     Brazil</title>, 2 vols (Rio de Janeiro, 1817), I, pp. 309&#8211;311, from which
                  Southey incorrectly assumed that Azevedo had led the Madeira expedition of
                  1749.</note> &amp; who went previously from M Grosso to Para by the R. Tapajos.
               Tonight I send off a continuation of the Chapter,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 37, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London,
                  1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 299&#8211;373.</note> &#8211; I have now nearly finished it, &amp; a
               great deal of curious matter it contains.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just turned over the leaves of the Acta Sanctorum;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The massive collection of hagiographies entitled
                     <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), which Southey had purchased in
                  Brussels in 1817. They became no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library. He had
                  bought the 6&#8211;volume abridged version in 1815, no. 152 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library.</note> the five or six first volumes I obtained many years ago from a
               public library, &amp; made good use of them: all the rest are new to me. The worthy
               editors seem, a little like myself, never to have been content with the enormous work
               which they had undertaken to perform, but upon every possible opportunity to have
               enlarged it by some gratuitous labour. Among these supererogatory works is a very
               curious code of Majorcan laws, with a series of as curious engravings, from the ms.
               exhibiting the whole household of the King of Majorca in their costume &amp;
                  employments.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Ad Leges Palatinas
                  Iacobii II Regis Majoricarum etc&#8217;, <title>Acta Sanctorum</title>, 53 vols (Antwerp
                  and Brussels, 1643&#8211;1794), 3 June (1701), pp. 1&#8211;82 (engravings between pp. 10&#8211;11).
                  This was a code of laws enacted by James II (1243&#8211;1311; King of Majorca
                  1276&#8211;1311).</note> &#8211; It is indeed a singularly valuable body of historical &amp;
               antiquarian <del>xxx</del> research, certainly the most laborious work that has ever
               yet been produced by any body of men. My copy is a very fine one, &#8211; the
                  bookseller<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptise Ver Beyst
                  (1770&#8211;1849), well-known Brussels bookseller.</note> at Brussels said it was the
               finest he had ever obtained. It belonged to the Franciscan Recollects<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Recollects were a reformed branch of the
                  Franciscan friars.</note> at Ghent. I shall make great use of it in due time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Kehama &amp; Roderic are both at this time in the press.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The fourth editions of <title>The Curse of
                     Kehama</title> (1810) and of <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title>
                     (1814) appeared in 1818.</note> The latter has done great things
               for me, &#8211; that is to say, it has set me on the right side of <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> books. Upon the whole it has
               brought me not less than 700&#163;. &#8211; It will take probably a full years sale before the
               new edition clears its expences, but my Life of Wesley will be out for the spring
                  sale,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of
                     Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> &amp; I
               hope that will supply <del>any</del> the deficiency. And whenever I can finish my
               Tale of Paraguay I may calculate upon immediately selling an edition of 2000.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825),
                  published in an edition of 1500; it sold poorly and realised less than &#163;80 in
                  profits in the first year. There was no second edition.</note> But in truth I
               would willingly have done with poetry, &amp; confine myself to those subjects for
               which I possess advantages that are not likely soon to meet in any one person.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref> is
               expected in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> to day, &#8211; with
               his wife,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Barbara Wilberforce, n&#233;e
                  Spooner (1777&#8211;1847).</note> &amp; his sons,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wilberforce (1798&#8211;1879), later a barrister and MP for
                  Hull 1837&#8211;1838; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceRobert">Robert
                     Wilberforce</ref>, later a clergyman and writer; Samuel Wilberforce (1805&#8211;1873;
                     <title>DNB</title>), later Bishop of Winchester 1870&#8211;1873; Henry Wilberforce
                  (1807&#8211;1873; <title>DNB</title>), later a journalist.</note> &amp; his
                  daughters,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Barbara Wilberforce
                  (1799&#8211;1821); Elizabeth Wilberforce (1801&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; his sons friends,
               &amp; his daughters friends, &amp; his men servants, &amp; his maid servants. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref>
                  &amp;<ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret"> Lady Beaumont</ref> are
               here. <hi rend="ital">He</hi> knew this country before I was born, &amp; passed a
               summer in it soon after his marriage three &amp; forty years ago. And both he &amp;
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady B.</ref> enjoy
               it as much now as ever they did. I expect a guest next week whom perhaps you may have
               heard the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> mention, &#8211; his name is <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncey Townsend</ref>, &#8211; a
               youth with every imaginable advantage that nature &amp; fortune can bestow. Old
               Townsend the traveller was his great-Uncle,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The geologist and travel&#8211;writer Joseph Townsend (1739&#8211;1816;
                     <title>DNB</title>), whose publications included <title>A Journey Through Spain
                     in the Years 1786 and 1787; with Particular Attention to the Agriculture,
                     Manufactures, Commerce, Population, Taxes, and Revenue of that Country</title>
                  (1791). Southey had met Townsend in London in 1797; see Southey to Joseph Cottle,
                  9 April 1797, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>,
                  Letter 210.</note> &#8211; from him he has acquired a taste for mineralogy, &amp; that
               taste will take me some tough walks among the mountains.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We have had no drought in the North, &#8211; nothing indeed could be more
               favourable than our weather, or finer than our harvest. But I fear you will suffer
               dreadfully in the spring. What is become of Blackstone<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Frederick Charles Blackstone (1795&#8211;1862), a relation by
                  marriage of Hill. Blackstone&#8217;s mother was Margaret Bigg-Wither (1768&#8211;1842), a
                  sister of Hill&#8217;s wife Catherine. Blackstone became Rector of Worting, Hampshire
                  1819&#8211;1831, Southey&#8217;s uncle Herbert Hill having held this living since 1815 (i.e.
                  deputising as parish priest until such time as Blackstone was ready to take up his
                  duties) &#8211; Blackstone was a Fellow of New College, Oxford and was not ordained
                  until 1819. Southey had met him in Switzerland in 1817 during his continental
                  tour.</note> that he has not yet made his appearance? <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">Gen. Peachy</ref> is looking out for
               him also, so that he will have a bed if he shall arrive at the same time with <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncey Townsend</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lowther</ref> drank
               tea with us last week, &#8211; bringing over <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> to introduce him,
               &#8211; for I had never seen him before. The <del>xxx</del> only other great person whom I
               have seen was the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand
               Murray</ref> himself, on his way to Edinburgh; &#8211; he I believe is the very
               grandest personage among mankind, now that there is no longer a Grand Mogul.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The Grand Mogul was a British term for the
                  ruler of the Mughal empire; at this time, Akhbar Shah II (1760&#8211;1837; Mughal
                  Emperor 1806&#8211;1837), though he had lost most of his authority to the British East
                  India Company.</note> There ought to be an article of mine upon Evelyns Journal in
               his next number, &amp; another upon the means of improving the people.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Memoirs, Illustrative
                     of the Life and Writings of John Evelyn</title> (1818) appeared in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 1&#8211;54. His article &#8216;On the
                  Means of Improving the People&#8217; appeared at 79&#8211;118 of the same issue.</note> &#8211; I am
               about to write upon the Copy right bill, &#8211; &amp; upon the New Churches.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217;,
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 196&#8211;219. His review of
                  Haydon&#8217;s <title>New Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they
                     Offer for the Encouragement of Painting</title> (1818) was held over until
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820), 549&#8211;91.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my
                  Aunt</ref> &amp; the children. How is your rheumatism? I hope it
               has not returned, &amp; that your strength is rallying. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt Mary</ref> was coming
                  <del>down</del> to me this autumn, but the hot weather brought on an illness,
               &amp; she now looks forward to a journey in the spring.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>