<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3183</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4454</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3183. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 15 August 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3183.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 170. ALS;
                     4p..  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3183" type="letter">
        <head>3183. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1818-08-15">15 August 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert
                  Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ AU
                  18/ 1818 NT; E/ 18 AU 18/ 1818 <lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 170. ALS;
                     4p.<title>
              <lb />
            </title>Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-08-15"> 15 Aug. 1818</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Corografia<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Manoel Aires de
                  Casal (1754&#8211;1821), <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Rela&#231;&#227;o Historico-Geografica do
                     Reino do Brazil</title> (1817), no. 3252 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library. Southey referenced this book in Chapter 37 of his <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, p. 308, when describing the
                  town of Villa Boa in the captaincy of Goias.</note> arrived just before your
               letter, &amp; in good time, for something I perceive must be added from it to the
               chapter which I am now transcribing. The book appears to contain more than we had
               anticipated, &amp; will be very useful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Gov. Johnstone could not have taken possession of the Island of
               Fernam de Noronha without committing a direct &amp; impudent act of hostility, &#8211; the
               place being fortified &amp; garrisoned in his time.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey dealt with this group of islands off the Brazilian coast in
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 300&#8211;304,
                  especially the ejection of some French settlers in 1737. Southey may also be
                  referring to George Johnstone (1730&#8211;1787; <title>DNB</title>), Governor of West
                  Florida 1763&#8211;1767 and naval commander. He was in charge of an unsuccessful
                  expedition to capture the Cape of Good Hope in 1781, in the course of which he
                  spent much time in the south Atlantic.</note> Have you not mistaken it for Tristam
               da Cunha, which I believe we <del>have</del> occupy at this time by cession from
               Jonathan Lambert, &amp; no doubt with the tacit consent of the Portugueze Court?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The remote Atlantic island of Tristan da Cunha
                  was discovered and named by Portuguese sailors in 1506, but was never occupied by
                  Portugal, or any other country, until its first settler, an American, Jonathan
                  Lambert (d. 1812), arrived in 1810 and declared himself sovereign and sole
                  possessor of the island. It was finally annexed by the United Kingdom in 1816.
               </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My long expected cargo came to hand last week, &amp; the Saints are
               at last installed upon my shelves.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The massive
                  collection of hagiographies entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum </title>(1643&#8211;1794),
                  which Southey had purchased in Brussels in 1817, had, after much delay, arrived.
                  It became no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> How much did I wish
               for you when I was opening &amp; inspecting these treasures. Joannes de Laets
                  work<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649),
                     <title>Historie ofte Iaerlijck Verhael van de Verrichtingen der Geoctroyeerde
                     West-Indische Compagnie</title> (1644), no. 1671 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library.</note> is a History of the W India Company to the year 1636.
               There will be much to collect from it for a second edition, which will be wanted
                  <del>one da</del> at some time, whether it be in my days or not. I am Dutchman
               enough to make my way thro historical matter without much difficulty. This book seems
               to be so little known that in the Bibliotheca Belgica (which is among my last
                  purchases)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Jan Frans Foppens (1689&#8211;1761),
                     <title>Bibliotheca Belgica</title> (1739), no. 942 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library.</note> it is omitted in the list of Laets works. &#8211; Ant:
                  Nebrissensis<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Antonio de Lebrija
                  (1441&#8211;1522), <title>Rerum a Ferdinando et Elisabeth Hispaniarum Regibus Gestarum
                     Decades II</title> (1545), no. 1925 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> is one of the finest books in my possession. (Granada 1545.)</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I doubt whether Barbosa (desirable as it would be to possess it) is
               worth its price.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Diogo Barbosa Machado
                     (1682&#8211;1772),<title> Bibliotheca Lusitana</title> (1741&#8211;1759).<title />This was the first major reference work of Portuguese
                  publications.</note> Bluteau would be far more useful to me.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Rafael Bluteau (1638&#8211;1734), <title>Diccionario da
                     Lingua Portugueza</title> (1789), no. 205 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> Barbosa is not an antiquarian, as Nic Ant:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicolas Antonio (1617&#8211;1684), <title>Bibliotheca
                     Hispana</title> (1672&#8211;1696). The second edition (1783&#8211;1788) was no. 3309 in the
                  sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> is in the first part of his work,
               &amp; I very seldom have felt myself at a loss for any information which he could
               have supplied. Before I go to press with the Hist: of Portugal I must buy a set of Du
                  Canges<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles du Fresne, Sieur du Cagne
                  (1610&#8211;1688), <title>Glossarium ad Scriptores Mediae et Infimae Latinitatis</title>
                  (1733&#8211;1736), no. 953 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey never
                  completed his &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;.</note> Glossaries &#8211; the only work of
               considerable expence which will be indispensable for me, &#8211; (tho I ought to have the
               Dict: of the Sp. Academy).<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Diccionario
                     de la Lengua Castellana compuesto por la Real Academia Espanola</title> (1780),
                  the authoritative dictionary of the Spanish language, published by the Royal
                  Spanish Academy. The 5th edition appeared in 1817.</note> I shall desire <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> to be upon the look out
               for it. Our great desiderata <del>xx the</del> are Castanheda,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Fernao Lopes de Castanheda (c. 1500&#8211;1559),
                     <title>Historia do Descobrimento e Conquista da India pelos Portugueses</title>
                  (1551&#8211;1561); Southey later possessed an edition from 1797, no. 3187 in the sale
                  catalogue of his library; and an Italian translation from 1577, no. 455 in the
                  sale catalogue of his library.</note> Gil Vicente<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Gil Vicente (c.1465&#8211;c. 1536), the chief dramatist and lyric poet of
                  Portugal. His <title>Works</title> were published first in 1561&#8211;1562. Southey
                  later possessed an edition of 1834, no. 3681 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library.</note> &amp; the Cancioneiro<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                     <title>Cancioneiro Geral</title> (1516), collected by Garcia de Resende
                  (1470&#8211;1536).</note>: &#8211; &amp; I think there is a reasonable hope that all three may
               be reprinted. My poor correspondent <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref> was about to have reedited the Spanish Cancioneiro if he had not
               been disgraced, &#8211; since which I have heard nothing of him</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has been with me, &amp; is
               about to take <ref type="m" target="places.html#EmeraldBank">a house &amp; thirty
                  acres of land</ref> within four miles of this place, the rent 50&#163;. He is to take
               possession at Lady day next.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">25 March 1819.
                  Lady Day was a traditional day on which to begin tenancies.</note> The removal is
               in all respects desirable, &#8211; he betters his situation, lowers his rent materially, &#8211;
               has a better market for the produce of his dairy, &amp; will be within an hours walk
               &#8220;for a well girt man&#8221;.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">A phrase used in
                  Herodotus (c. 484&#8211;425 BC), <title>Histories</title>, Book 1, paragraph 72, which
                  became a standard figure of speech.</note> I shall be glad to have him so near.
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">His wife</ref> is a woman with
               whom you would be much pleased.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall be grievously interrupted for the next eight or ten weeks.
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> &amp;<ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret"> Lady Beaumont</ref> are here. The
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> will make his
               appearance this evening, or tomorrow, on his way to Scotland. I expect my poor old
               friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref> for a day
               or two this week. &#8211; And the <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General</ref> who draws largely upon me for society will arrive in the course of
               the month. &#8211; Blackstone<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Frederick Charles
                  Blackstone (1795&#8211;1862), a relation by marriage of Hill. Blackstone&#8217;s mother was
                  Margaret Bigg-Wither (1768&#8211;1842), a sister of Hill&#8217;s wife Catherine. Blackstone
                  became Rector of Worting, Hampshire 1819&#8211;1831, Southey&#8217;s uncle Herbert Hill having
                  held this living since 1815 (i.e. deputising as parish priest until such time as
                  Blackstone was ready to take up his duties) &#8211; Blackstone was a Fellow of New
                  College, Oxford and was not ordained until 1819. Southey had met Blackstone in
                  Switzerland in his continental tour of 1817.</note> has not yet made his
               appearance. &#8211; But my worst interruption is the Quarterly &#8211; {I always look unwillingly
               to the demands which this brings upon me, &#8211; } not {so to} quarter-day, thank Heaven,
               &#8211; My ways &amp; means come easily, &#8211; both ends meet, &amp; his Majesty has not in all
               his dominions a subjects who is more contented with <del>t</del>his present lot or
               less anxious about the future. &#8211; I have just entered my 45<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               year. &#8211; I am glad to hear that you are free from rheumatism, &#8211; care &amp; nutritious
               diet will do much toward removing infirmity, &#8211; for you are of a hale &amp; longlived
               stock.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my
                  Aunt</ref> &amp; the children &#8211; </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>