<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3213</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4484</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3213. Robert Southey to Henry
                  Koster, 27 November 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3213" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3213.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Instituto Historico e
                  Geografico Brasileiro, Rio de Janeiro; text taken from Sousa-Lea&#771;o .  Previously 
                  published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e
                  Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, Revista do Instituto Historico e
                     Geografico Brasileiro, 178 (1943), 56&#8211;58.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3213" type="letter">
        <head>3213. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry
                  Koster</ref>, <date when="1818-11-27">27 November 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Instituto Historico e
                  Geografico Brasileiro, Rio de Janeiro; text taken from Sousa-Lea&#771;o<lb /> Previously
                  published: Joaquim de Sousa-Lea&#771;o, &#8216;Cartas de Robert Southey a Theodore Koster e
                  Henry Koster, anos de 1804 a 1819&#8217;, <title>Revista do Instituto Historico e
                     Geografico Brasileiro</title>, 178 (1943), 56&#8211;58.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Koster,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your list of Governors and Bishops,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">For the third volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> for all you have done for me, and all you
               are doing. I am hard at work as usual, and have at this time the 48th sheet of the
               third volume lying before me: when the volume reaches you, you will see in more parts
               than one of what you use you have been. The end of my long labours is at last fairly
               in view, there is a great pleasure in completing anything, more especially a work of
               such extent and difficulty as this, which I verily believe to be the most laborious
               history in our language. As soon as it is finished I go to press with the History of
               the Peninsula War,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                     the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> which will excite much more
               immediate attention. But I am far from regretting that so much time and labour has
               been bestowed upon a subject for which few English readers (such as readers now are)
               can be expected to feel much interest. No other person could have brought the same
               industry and the same advantages to the task: &#8211; an Englishman would have wanted the
               wide scope of Portuguese knowledge and the Portuguese feeling to which so many years
               conversance with Portuguese literature had given me; and on the other hand a native
               of Portugal or Brazil would have been shackled by many prejudices or political
               considerations, and his ignorance on some points would have counter-balanced his
               superior knowledge which he would have possessed on others. What I have done is in
               many parts very imperfect; it is nevertheless even now a great achievement, as long
               as I live I shall carefully correct and enlarge it from whatever documents written or
               printed, may come to my hands, and centuries hence, when Brazil shall have become the
               great and prosperous country which one day it must be, I shall be regarded there as
               the first person who ever attempted to give a consistent form to its crude,
               unconnected and neglected history. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whether anything may come of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Mr. Wilberforce&#8217;s</ref> good wishes and
               good endeavours remains yet to be seen: that he is not wanting in either is
                  certain.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Wilberforce had agreed to try and
                  use his influence to try and obtain a consular appointment in Brazil for Henry
                  Koster.</note> I wish you may be stationed at Para: the climate has been so much
               improved by the progress of cultivation that it is said to be better than that of any
               of the southern capitals. As a place of trade, it must become of more importance than
               even Recife, for Para must be the chief port for Mato Grosso, and the facilities of
               water communication in all directions seem to offer an interminable field for
               enterprise and commerce. And you would find materials for more than one volume in the
               new scenes which would be laid open, and the new sources of information. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have lately obtained, and just in time, the Corografia
                  Brazilica,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Manoel Aires de Casal
                  (1754&#8211;1821), <title>Corografia Brazilica, ou Rela&#231;&#227;o Historico&#8211;Geografica do Reino
                     do Brazil</title> (1817), no. 3252 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s
                  library.</note> which may possibly have reached <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> sooner than Recife. Had this book
               appeared sooner it would have been better for my purpose: however I have contrived to
               wean in its information as well as I could; and perhaps no person but myself will
               perceive that the matter might have been better arranged. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is remarkable that there are no Dominicans in Brazil, there were
               enough of them in Portugal, where they were quite as much in fashion as any other
               order, and yet I have not found any mention of them in your country. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> has not been with us this
               year, nor have I ever been farther from home than <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydale</ref>. I have had only <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">one guest</ref>, but my time as usual
               has been much interrupted by chance visitors. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother the Captain</ref> is about to take up
               his abode in Newlands at Lady Day next, perhaps you may remember the house, an
               unfurnished one belonging to Mrs. Barcroft, and known by the name of <ref type="m" target="places.html#EmeraldBank">Emerald Bank</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom and his wife had in 1810 lodged at a house in Castlerigg, to
                  the east of Keswick, owned by a local farmer Joseph Barcroft (c. 1753&#8211;1810); see
                  Robert Southey to William Peachy, 22 October 1810, <title>The Collected Letters of
                     Robert Southey. Part 4</title>, Letter 1820. The widowed Mrs Barcroft had
                  married John Sander in 1813. Lady Day (25 March) was a traditional day for the
                  start of tenancies.</note> His residing there will be useful in drawing me out of
               my den which I am too much in the habit of keeping.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Emerald Bank lies in the Newlands valley, about six miles to the
                  southwest of Southey&#8217;s home, Greta Hall.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Among the books which I bought of Ver Beyst<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1849), a well&#8211;known bookseller in
                  Brussels. Southey had bought a large consignment of books from him in 1817.</note>
               during my last journey is a history of the Dutch West Indian Company, by Johannes de
               Laet, written in Dutch and printed in 1644.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Joannes de Laet (1581&#8211;1649), <title>Historie ofte Iaerlijck Verhael van de
                     Verrichtingen der Geoctroyeerde West-Indische Compagnie</title> (1644), no.
                  1671 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> I had suspected that such
               a book must have existed, but could never obtain any intelligence of it, till to my
               great delight I found it upon our friends shelves. My last years purchases on the
               continent make a formidable appearance now that they are fairly arranged; the
                  &#8220;organ-room&#8221;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A room that used to contain an
                  organ when it was inhabited by William Jackson. It was formerly Coleridge&#8217;s
                  study.</note> is pretty well filled, and I show the Acta Sanctorum to all
               book-lovers with great pride, as the jewel of my library.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had bought the 53&#8211;volume compendium of hagiographies
                  entitled <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), no. 207 in the sale catalogue
                  of his library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A person whose name I forget,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Luccock (1770&#8211;1826), an English wool merchant, who lived in Brazil
                  1808&#8211;1818.</note> but who had been some years at the Rio, wrote to me from Leeds
               some little time ago, to consult me about publishing here in England &#8211; a Tupi grammar
               and vocabulary! Things in which I was perhaps the only other person in England who
               felt the slightest interest. My advice was if he had any journal, or any information
               concerning Brazil to publish <hi rend="ital">that</hi>, and bring in his grammar and
               vocabulary under cover of more promising matter, by way of appendix: and this he
               seems disposed to do.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Luccock took Southey&#8217;s
                  advice and published <title>Notes on Rio de Janeiro, and the Southern Parts of
                     Brazil; Taken During a Residence of Ten Years in that Country, from 1808 to
                     1818</title> (1820). As an Appendix he added &#8216;A Glossary of those Tupi Words,
                  which Occur in the Preceding Pages&#8217; (pp. 629&#8211;639). But the &#8216;Grammar and Dictionary
                  of the Tupi Language&#8217; that the book stated he hoped to publish if there was
                  sufficient interest (p. [640]) did not appear.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> With the third volume of Brazil I shall have to send you in the early
               spring my &#8220;Life of Wesley and Rise and Progress of Methodism&#8221; &#8211; two large volumes and
               of matter much more various and amusing than the subject may perhaps seem to you to
                  promise.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Wesley; and
                     the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> The conclusion of the
               first volume is in the printer&#8217;s hands, and parts of the additional notes go off to
               him by this night&#8217;s post. I know not whether you recognize my hand in the Q.R. In the
               last number I had Evelyn&#8217;s Memoirs, and the means of improving the people. In the
               next something about New Churches, and the Copyright question.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of <title>Memoirs, Illustrative of
                     the Life and Writings of John Evelyn</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 1&#8211;54, and his article &#8216;On the Means of
                  Improving the People&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April 1818), 79&#8211;118.
                  They were followed by Southey&#8217;s review of Haydon, <title>New Churches, Considered
                     with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the Encouragement of
                     Painting</title> (1818) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820),
                  549&#8211;591, and an &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                  21 (January 1819), 196&#8211;219.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All here desire their kindest remembrances, believe me my dear
               Koster,</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Your affectionate friend,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-11-27"> 27 Nov. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>