<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2908</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4179</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2908. Robert Southey to William
               Peachy, 28 January 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2908.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library,
                  Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2908" type="letter">
        <head>2908. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William
               Peachy</ref>, <date when="1817-01-28">28 January 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/
                  39 George Street/ Portman Square/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark:
                  E/ 31 JA 31/ 1817<lb /> Seal: black wax; design illegible<lb /> MS: British Library,
                  Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.<title>
              <lb />
            </title>
          </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-01-28">28 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1817.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> This letter, I trust will find you after your long travels
               comfortably settled for the winter in the great city, which tho&#8217; the ugliest of all
               capitals, is nevertheless, take it for all in all, without an equal either in ancient
               or modern times. I hope you will not have left London before the middle of April, &#8211;
               by which time it is my intention (if no unforeseen circumstances should occur to
               prevent me) to be there, &#8211; for two or three weeks, &amp; probably I may visit Paris
               before my return.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey undertook an
                  extensive continental tour in May&#8211;August 1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">the Captain</ref> has
               lately been with me. He is settled at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Warcop">Warcop</ref>, a village
               between Brough &amp; Appleby, pleasantly situated, in a beautiful country, &amp; in
               compleat retirement, &#8211; which agrees very well with his habits <del>&amp;</del>,
               inclinations &amp; half-pay. But he says he is obliged to lay in a stock of every
               thing, as he used to do on board ship. The commonest article of earthenware is not to
               be obtained without sending for it to Penrith, &#8211; not even a bason! &#8211; It is a cheap
               country, with not more law than we have at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,
               &amp; about as little Gospel; but luckily there as well as here, little or no
               distress is heard of, &amp; we have no village Hampdens,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hampden (1594&#8211;1643; <title>DNB</title>) was a leader of
                  parliamentary resistance to royal authority. &#8216;Village-Hampdens&#8217; derives from
                  Thomas Gray (1716&#8211;1771; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;Elegy Written in a Country
                  Churchyard&#8217; (1751), lines 57&#8211;58: &#8216;Some village-Hampden, that with dauntless
                  breast/ The little tyrant of his fields withstood&#8217;.</note> nor associations of the
               kind for mending the Constitution.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are going next week to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse&#8217;s</ref>
               for a few days, It is more than eight years since I was there, &amp; I shall see the
               place much altered. It was my intention to have gone this day, but I have been
               prevented by the promise of a visit from Owen of Lanark,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen (1771&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), manager and owner
                  of the mills and model community at New Lanark in Scotland 1799&#8211;1825.</note> &#8211; a
               very interesting personage, whose establishment you probably have seen. He is full of
               plans for the poor, &amp; this, I suppose takes him to London at this time. He has
               written a most injudicious pamphlett,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen&#8217;s <title>An Address delivered to the Inhabitants of New Lanark
                     ... at the opening of the New Institution Established for the Formation of
                     Character </title>(1816).</note> &amp; <del>has</del> is possessed with some
               very erroneous opinions; &#8211; but withall his intentions are so truly benevolent, his
               conduct so frank &amp; upright, &amp; above all the good which he has effected at
               Lanark is so clear &amp; undisputed that I cannot but entertain a high respect for
               the man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So you have been to Amsterdam before me! I hope you ate of the best
               cheese; &amp; the best herrings, &amp; tasted the finest Hollands.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A juniper-flavoured traditional spirit, from which
                  gin evolved.</note> Time was when you should have had the best Constantia there
               also, &#8211; but the <del>Con</del> vineyards belong to England now.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Constantia was a blended wine from the Cape Colony
                  in South Africa that was a favourite in Royal Courts in the late eighteenth and
                  early nineteenth centuries. The Cape Colony was finally transferred from the
                  Netherlands to Britain in the Anglo-Dutch Treaty (1814).</note> The newspapers
               have lately conferred upon me some Amsterdam honours, saying that I am <del>appointed
                  a</del> {chosen} member of the Royal Institute, &#8211; from any place such honours
               would be gratifying, &#8211; I need not tell you how peculiarly so from Amsterdam.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">According to the <title>Courier</title>, 2
                  January 1817, Southey had been appointed an Associate of the Second Class of the
                  Royal Institute of Science, Literature and the Fine Arts of the Netherlands
                  (founded 1808). The Institute&#8217;s headquarters are the Trippenhuis in
                  Amsterdam.</note> But I cannot display this new title in my title-pages, as no
               official intimation has been sent me. To say the truth the Dutch are the last people
               from whom I should have expected this, &amp; (except the French) the last from whom I
               have deserved it. And perhaps if the Institute had seen the second vol. of the
               History of Brazil they would not have <del>chose</del> elected me for an associate.
               This volume is now compleated, &#8211; I sent off the preface last night.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819), published in 1817, dealt with the struggle between
                  the Dutch and the Portuguese 1621&#8211;1654 to control Brazil.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I tell you in my last that Col. &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
               Scroggs favoured us with a visit on their marriage.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Mrs Dansey (d. 1826), widow of Lieutenant-Colonel William
                  Dansey (d. 1793), was an old acquaintance of Southey&#8217;s from Taunton. She was also
                  known to Peachy, whose first wife, Emma Charter, was from Bishop&#8217;s Lydeard, only
                  five miles from Taunton. On 11 July 1816 the Danseys&#8217; only daughter, Sibyll Jane
                  Dansey (d. 1848) married Lieutenant Colonel Sydney Scroggs (c. 1770&#8211;1845).</note>
               I did not recognize her at first sight, &amp; when the voice &amp; the features were
               recalled to remembrance, I was surprized at how an early an age she was shrunk &amp;
               faded. He seemed a placid gentlemanly person, with little of the soldier about him,
               &amp; less of the bridegroom.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Were we talking together just now we should probably be speculating
               upon what Parliament would do to check the revolutionary spirit which is going abroad
               &#8216;like a Lion seeking whom it may devour.&#8217;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">1 <title>Peter</title> 5: 8.</note> It is a spirit that may easily be laid,
               if Government act promptly &amp; decidedly; &#8211; but if they suffer it to go on, I know
               not where the mischief will end. The simple measures of reviving <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Ld Grenvilles</ref> bill against seditious meetings,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The Seditious Meetings Act 1795 clamped down on
                  political protest by requiring licenses from magistrates for public meetings of
                  fifty persons or more, and for all debating rooms where politics might be
                  discussed. Lord Grenville had moved the bill in the House of Lords.</note> &amp;
               making transportation the punishment for seditious libel, would be sufficient: &amp;
               if owing to the temper of the times there should be any difficulty in convicting such
               a fellow as <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref>, &#8211; in that case they should without
               hesitation suspend the Habeas Corpus, &amp; lay him in Limbo.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Habeas corpus was suspended in February 1817, allowing
                  imprisonment without trial. In March 1817 Cobbett fled to America.</note> &#8211; I
               happen to know that the Proprietor of one of the greatest morning papers is fool
               enough to believe that Hunt<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217;
                  Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>). The newspaper concerned was <title>The
                     Times</title>; John Walter II (1776&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>) was variously its
                  owner, manager and editor 1803&#8211;1847.</note> will overthrow both the Ministry &amp;
               opposition, &#8211; &amp; knave enough to trim his paper accordingly!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> is painting with great industry &amp;
               great success. &#8211; Our winter tho unusually stormy, is unnaturally mild, &#8211; the cattle
               are in the fields, &amp; the polyanthuses in full blossom! M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  Fryer<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Harrison Fryer
                  (1777&#8211;1855), surveyor, geologist and mining engineer from Newcastle. From 1808 he
                  spent part of each year at Keswick.</note> had one of his chimnies blown down
                  <del>at</del> some weeks ago, &#8211; the gales have done no other mischief here, &#8211;
               except that of destroying the only pear tree upon these premises which bore good
               fruit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; her
               sisters<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara
                  Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note>
               join with me in kind remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Peachy</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>