<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2997</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4268</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2997. Robert Southey to Edith
                  Southey, 17[-19] May 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2997.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>British Library, Add MS
                  47888. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters
                     of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II,
                  pp.159&#8211;163.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2997" type="letter">
        <head>2997. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith
                  Southey</ref>, <date when="1817-05-19">17[-19] May 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland/ England<lb /> Stamped: PORT-PAYE <lb />
                  Postmarks: FPO/ MY 24/ 1817; A MY/ 24/ 1817<lb /> MS: British Library, Add MS
                  47888. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters
                     of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II,
                  pp.159&#8211;163.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Paris.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-05-17">Saturday 17 May. 1817.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Edith</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nothing could be more prosperous than our journey has been thus far.
               I wrote to you from Calais informing you of our safe arrival there on Sunday morning.
               Whom should I meet there, but <ref type="m" target="people.html#BiddlecombeCharles">Biddlecombe</ref>, who is come to France with his daughter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The name of Biddlecombe&#8217;s daughter (b. 1799) is
                  unknown.</note> in hopes that the climate may cure her of hysteria &amp; habitual
               headache, &#8211; she is short &amp; plethoric with a countenance of prepossessing good
               nature. They are sometimes at Calais, sometimes at Boulogne, fearful as yet of going
               farther lest she should want an English physician, &#8211; but if she continues better they
               move on to Montpelier. We shipt off <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Vardon</ref> for Brussels by way of St Omer &amp; Lisle
               &amp; started ourselves at half past four in the afternoon; a little delay having
               been occasioned by the want of horses, for Lord Granville (Leveson Gower)<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Granville Leveson-Gower, 1st Earl Granville
                  (1773&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), Ambassador to Russia 1804&#8211;1805, 1806&#8211;1807 and
                  Ambassador to France 1824&#8211;1828, 1830&#8211;1835, 1835&#8211;1841.</note> carried off
                  <del>xx</del> 24 the same day. On the way to Boulogne at a place called Marquise
               we were delayed nearly an hour by the same cause &#8211;but it was well repaid by a
               conversation with a woman of 74<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> respecting her own sufferings in the Revolution. She had
               been bred up in an English family, spoke English not merely well, but beautifully. I
               have no time to transcribe from my journal <hi rend="ital">what</hi> she said, but
               never in real life did I hear any thing finer than the passion with which she
               expressed herself. As soon as we reached Boulogne which was not till night had closed
               (owing to this delay) I set off in search of Sir Jere<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Jeremiah Homfray (1759&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), a Welsh
                  ironmaster and speculator in mineral rights, living in Boulogne since being
                  declared bankrupt in 1813. Homfray was the uncle of Mary Barker.</note> but found
               at his door a bell which had no tongue &amp; a knocker which nobody would answer, so
               I was fain to return from the bootless quest. On Monday however <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">S</ref> &amp; I after the
               laudable custom upon which we had resolved &amp; having waited till after eight, went
               again to Sir Jere&#8217;s door, as, it was daylight I saw how to get in &amp; then knocking
               at the house door the youngest son<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert
                  Shedden Homfray (1804&#8211;1845), later a salt agent in Bengal.</note> made his
               appearance, &amp; called Sir Jere into a balcony from his private apartments. You may
               guess his surprize at seeing me, his hearty welcome &amp; his pressing hospitality.
               We breakfasted with him. Nothing could be more gracious than my Lady<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Homfray, n&#233;e Phillips (1770&#8211;1830), wife of
                  Sir Jeremiah Homfray. Though born in Cardiff, she went to school in Bristol and
                  knew many of Southey&#8217;s childhood acquaintances.</note> was to that Poet Man, &#8211; she
               talked of the Eubanks, the Lockyers &amp; my poor godfather Tommy Stephens,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">When Southey was born at his father&#8217;s
                  draper&#8217;s shop at 11 Wine Street, Bristol in 1774, the property at 12 Wine Street
                  was occupied by George Ewbank and Thomas Stephens, milliners (dates unknown).
                  James Lockier (dates unknown) was an upholsterer, timber merchant and property
                  developer whose premises were at 45 Wine Street.</note> and we became old
               acquaintances presently. The two grown up daughters<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Charlotte Homfray (d. 1855), who married James Lewis
                  (d. 1855) in 1824; and Marianne Homfray (1788&#8211;1819), who had married in 1806, but
                  had been divorced under Scottish law in 1813. Possibly Catherine-Diana Homfray
                  (1801&#8211;1858), who married Jacob-Aemilius Irving (1797&#8211;1856) in 1821 and Harriet
                  Newte Homfray (b. 1805) were too young to qualify as &#8216;grown up&#8217;.</note> are of
               very pleasing appearance, &#8211; but the eldest son, take him for all in all, is one of
               the most interesting &amp; hopeful men whom I have seen. Adversity has not been lost
               upon him He is engaged to go to Lima upon a scheme of draining the mines in Chile, &#8211;
               I hope he may be disappointed in this as it is probable he will be, but wherever he
               may go, if his life be spared, he cannot fail to distinguish himself.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeremiah Homfray (1790&#8211;1850) had been ordained as
                  a Church of England clergyman in 1814, but his father&#8217;s bankruptcy compelled him
                  to go out to Bengal, where he played a role in the development of the Indian coal
                  industry.</note> From Boulogne we made a short days journey, not starting till &#189;
               past 12, as far as Montrieul. Tuesday to Amiens. Wednesday to Chantilly to the hotel
               kept by <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Mr Nashs</ref> widow,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A widow, who ran the Hotel Bourbon Conde
                  in Chantilly and had proposed marriage to Nash in 1814. She had married since that
                  time.</note> &#8211; whose picture was taken by Chaucer five hundred years before she
               was born &#8211; for she is precisely his Wife of Bath.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The garrulous, greedy, shrewd, comic and egotistical pilgrim
                  in Geoffrey Chaucer (c. 1343&#8211;1400; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Canterbury
                     Tales</title>.</note> Thursday we arrived at Paris about one o clock, &amp; I
               had the resolution after having cleaned myself, not to stir out till I had brought up
               my journal. We then walked for an hour or two, dined at home at a late hour &amp; got
               to bed early. Friday <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">S</ref> &amp; I rose as usual at six &amp; walked to Montmartre before
               breakfast to obtain a view of the city from those heights. After breakfast we went to
               the Bankers &amp; then separated. My first business was to leave a card with Sir C
                  Stuart.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Stuart, Baron Stuart
                  de Rothesay (1779&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), Envoy Extraordinary at Lisbon
                  1810&#8211;1814, Ambassador to France 1815&#8211;1824, 1828&#8211;1830, 1841&#8211;1844.</note> Next to
                  Mackenzies<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Colin Alexander Mackenzie
                  (?1778&#8211;1851), a wealthy Scot who was employed on a number of delicate diplomatic
                  missions and may well have been a government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of
                  the Commissioners of Liquidation, Arbitration and Deposit, who adjudicated on
                  claims by British citizens for loss of property against the French government.
                  Southey dined with him on 17 May 1817.</note> &#8211; a personage employed to arrange
               the claims of English subjects upon this government. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> had given me a letter to him
               &amp; he insisted upon our dining with him today when we are to meet Mathias.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas James Mathias, (1754&#8211;1835;
                     <title>DNB</title>), satirist, author of <title>The Pursuits of Literature; a
                     Satirical Poem</title> (1794) and translator from Italian.</note> I then went
               in search of Chateaubriand<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Fran&#231;ois-Ren&#233;, Vicomte de Chateaubriand (1768&#8211;1848), the writer, diplomat
                  and supporter of the Bourbon regime. </note>
          <del>xx</del> with whom I left a card &amp; Stoddarts<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>). An
                  acquaintance of Coleridge in Malta, Stoddart was a lawyer who became the editor of
                  the <title>Times</title> 1814&#8211;1816. After he was dismissed from that post in 1816,
                  he edited a new pro-ministry paper, the <title>New Times</title> 1817&#8211;1826. His
                  note to Chateaubriand probably concerned their collaboration in a short-lived
                  Anglo-French conservative journal,<title> The Correspondent</title>, which
                  Stoddart had just launched.</note> letter. &#8211; M. Verdier<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Timoteo Lecussan Verdier (1754&#8211;1831), Portuguese man of
                  letters and mill-owner, of French origin. Southey had met him in Portugal in March
                  1801.</note> was not to be found. From the place where I looked for him I got to
               M. Beaudouins brothers<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Eustace Baudouin
                  (b. c. 1792) was the brother of Jean Baptiste Baudouin (b. c. 1780). The latter
                  was married to Anne Caroline Vallon (1792&#8211;1862), Wordsworth&#8217;s daughter by Annette
                  Vallon (1766&#8211;1841). Eustace, a prisoner of war in Britain, had previously visited
                  Wordsworth and Southey on his release; see Robert Southey to Thomas Southey, 10&#8211;14
                  July 1814, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>,
                  Letter 2458.</note> having seen half Paris on the way. I should tell you that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> in giving me his address had told me
               what I knew before but he added that it would not be necessary or pleasant to myself
               to appear to be acquainted with it. The daughter was the only person at home when I
               was admitted. &#8211; she did not know my name &amp; spoke no English. I made myself
               understood with my French, explained that I came to enquire for M Eustace B whom I
               had seen in Cumberland with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Mr
                  W.</ref> She immediately said <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">M. W</ref> was her
               father, &amp; we had a tete a tete of about an hour long <del>very</del> much like a
               scene in a sentimental comedy. She is a very interesting young woman, with much more
               of natural feeling than of French manners, &amp; intriguingly like John
                  Wordsworth,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wordsworth
                  (1772&#8211;1805), William&#8217;s sailor brother, drowned when his ship, the
                     <title>Abergavenny</title>, foundered off Portland Bill.</note> much more than
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthDorothy">his own
               sister</ref>. The little French Dorothy<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Louise Caroline Baudouin (1816&#8211;1869).</note> is very like her
               mother, a sweet infant, in perfect health &amp; good humour. I waited some time in
               expectation that the husband would come in, &amp; when I could afford to wait no
               longer, I promised to breakfast with them the next morning. She wept a good deal
               &amp; was very much affected during our conversation. &#8211; I returned to the Hotel
               according to appointment and went with my fellow travellers to call on <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilliamsHelenMaria">Helen Williams</ref> &#8211; she was not at home. Next to the Police Office,
               then to dinner at a Restaurateurs, where we fared sumptuously. From thence first to
               an act of French comedy at one Theatre, secondly to an act of French tragedy at
               another (I pray you admire our economy of time), and thirdly to the Coffee House of
               the Thousand Columns, of which you may read in the Visit to Paris,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">John Scott (1784&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>A Visit to Paris</title> (London, 1814), pp. 131&#8211;132.</note> where we
               concluded the day with coffee, noyau,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Cr&#232;me de noyaux, an almond-flavoured liqueur.</note> ice, and a sight of the
               Lady who sits at the bar to be looked at &#8211; a very odd play, and as I remarked to my
               companions utterly unlike any thing at Watenlath<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">A secluded valley on the east side of Derwentwater, about six
                  miles south of Southey&#8217;s home.</note> or even in Borrodale. We got home and to bed
               before ten o clock. This morning <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">S.</ref> and I started again at six, leaving <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> to his slumbers. We perambulated half
               Paris, before at nine o clock he left me at M. Beaudouins door. The mother was there
               to meet me &#8211; not a word of English could any of the three speak, and I had to make my
               way in French which I did to admiration. M. Beaudouin is like his brother, but
               considerably taller, very fond of his child, a fair presumption that he is not less
               fond of his wife. She on her part (and her mother also) speaks of him as the best of
               husbands. We parted sworn friends, and I was stopt on the way down stairs to take
               leave of the baby, who had been pleased to smile very graciously upon us and take me
               into favour. They live in small lodgings pleasantly situated. I breakfasted in their
               fashion upon meat pie, gruyere cheese, and white wine, after which the mother made me
               drink coffee, would have made me drink tea also if I had not obstinately refused, and
               proposed <hi rend="ital">punch</hi>. This was a curious visit. It lasted about two
               hours, after which I returned home and began this letter. I have been walking again
               since for about three hours, buying books, and eating ice. Now I am drest in my
               nankeens and white waistcoat, and we are waiting for <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> to proceed to dinner at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Mackenzies. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilliamsHelenMaria">Helen
                  Williams</ref> has invited us for tomorrow evening at 8 o clock. We start at six
               for Versailles where I shall find Eustace Beaudouin, whom I hear from his brother has
               not forgotten <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref>,
               and retains his dislike to potatoes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Sunday evening. 6 o clock. Just returned to Versailles. M. Beaudouin
               has danced off for Paris, much to my disappointment, and something I dare say to his
               own. We have had a fatiguing day in walking thro the enormous palace of Versailles,
               the two Trianons, and the gardens. I am employing the few minutes while dinner is
               preparing in hastily concluding this for tomorrows post, and at 8 o clock we go to
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilliamsHelenMaria">H. M.
               Williams</ref>. Chateaubriand has called during our absence. Tomorrow we
               go to the Catacombs and the Louvre and dine again with Mackenzie for the purpose of
               meeting the man in the world whom I most desire to meet, Espoz y Mina.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Espoz y Mina (1781&#8211;1836), Spanish
                  guerilla leader in campaigns against French forces occupying his country during
                  the Pensinsular War. He fled into exile after attempting a revolt against the
                  absolutist regime in Spain in September 1814.</note> Humboldt<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander von Humboldt (1769&#8211;1859), geographer,
                  naturalist and traveller in South America.</note> also will be asked to meet me.
               Probably I may see him this evening also. The weather is delightful. We are all as
               well as can be, and the last week seems like a whole year from the rapid succession
               of scenes thro which we have past. Tuesday morning we depart. I shall write from the
               first town in Switzerland where we shall halt long enough. You may guess how
               difficult I find it to keep up my journal. As for Paris it is as extraordinary a
               place, as the most extraordinary accounts describe it, a perpetual mixture of
                  Ranelagh<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Ranelagh Gardens, where the
                  London public, rich and poor, enjoyed outdoor entertainments.</note> and
               Bartholomew Fair<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">The annual four-day
                  fair held at Smithfield, London, every September until 1855, featured shows and
                  spectacles of all kinds.</note> in the streets and public walks, filth and finery.
               The whole population seems to live in public, as if their houses were only built to
               sleep in. They eat at Restaurateurs, drink at coffee houses, and sit in the streets,
               men and women alike. There are sixteen well drest young women, gay and lively,
               sitting round a table all day on the Boulevard, at work upon womens shoes. Dancing
               dogs, puppet shows, gambling, battledore and shuttlecock &#8211; tis like Bedlam let loose,
               or the manners of a masquerade exhibited in real life. I have seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharps</ref>
          <hi rend="ital">ten</hi> Punches;<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Presumably Punch and Judy shows seen by Richard Sharp during his time in
                  Paris.</note> and what is more extraordinary this evening (Sunday evening) seeing
               a great crowd in the place where the King<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis XVI (1754&#8211;1793; King of France 1774&#8211;1792). He was executed on 21
                  January 1793 at the Place de la Revolution.</note> was beheaded I went up and
               found it was a girl standing on her head. But the beauty &#8211; the picturesque beauty of
               the city&#8211; exceeds any thing that has been said of it. In that point of view a painter
               would find it inexhaustible. The river is wider than the Severn at Worcester, and
               divides itself more than once. The quays are open and spacious. There are heaven
               knows how many bridges, and the mixture of them with old building, modern palace, and
               trees forms an assemblage as unique as it is striking. I have seen the face of Paris
               compleatly, and shall feel heartily glad to leave it. It will absolutely feel like
               rest to get into the carriage for our departure. It is a wretched place for books
               except for their own modern publications, and as for the literature of other
               countries, I have more French books in my library &#8211; very many more &#8211; than there are
               English ones in all the book sellers shops which I have entered.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Cook has allowed me to get nearer the end of the page than I had
               expected, for which I am not sorry tho the wolf is impatient. We had some wild boar
               for dinner the first day, collared,<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Strips of boar rolled and slow cooked.</note> and a great delicacy it is.
               Frogs are out of season. About this day week I suppose this letter may reach you. I
               shall think of you at the post time, and at that time I trust we shall be in
               Besancon, or not far from it. We have been one week in France, and I see no reason to
               apprehend that we shall outstay our intended time by a single day. Three weeks will
               probably bring us to Milan, a fourth to Geneva, and allowing another whole week for
               Switzerland on this second traverse, we shall travel from Basle to Calais with
               perfect ease in a fortnight, giving M. Ouverx<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Francois-Joseph Ouwerx (dates unknown) of Huys, a soap manufacturer, whom
                  the Southeys had met on their tour of the Netherlands in 1815.</note> a day upon
               the road.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <date when="1817-05-19"> Monday morning.</date> I have got time to tell you that at
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilliamsHelenMaria">H.
               Williams&#8217;</ref> last night I met <ref type="m" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">Kenyon</ref>, which was a very great
               pleasure. He will write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs.
                  C.</ref> It is a villainous wet morning. <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> is gone about our carriage, and I
               remain at home the while to make up my dispatches for England. And now God bless you.
               Considering how little time can be saved in such a place and during such a life,
               this is a very respectable letter. Tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw</ref> that I have
               seen the cats with tails like squirrels, one tabby, the other tortoiseshell, clearly
               a distinct variety produced by crossing the Persian and European breed. Love to all. </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1">RS</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>