<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2927</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4198</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2927. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 23 February 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2927.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the
                     Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 60&#8211;62.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2927" type="letter">
        <head>2927. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1817-02-23">23 February 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] <del>To</del>/ <del>C W Williams
                     Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P</del>./ <del>London</del>/ London {<del>Xxxxxx xxxxx xxxx</del>/ C Williams Esqr M.P./ Xxxxx
                  xx/ Great Marlow/ Free}<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks: FREE/ FE 26/ 1817; FREE/ 26 FE/ 1817; [partial] FE/ 2X/ 1817<lb />
                  MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the
                     Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 60&#8211;62.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The affidavit arrived on Saturday, &#8211; &amp; I must go to Cockermouth to swear to it, so that it cannot be returned till
               tomorrows post.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had learned that <title>Wat Tyler</title>, a radical play he had written
                  in 1794, had been published without his consent. His affidavit was part of his legal action to gain an injunction against this
                  publication.</note> The inclosed will tell you <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brothers</ref> opinion; he
               has more knowledge of the world than most men, &amp; I should willingly assent to his advice, were it not highly probable that the
               publishers will force me to come forward at last, by putting my name in the advertisement, as they did in a paragraph in the M
                  Chronicle.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was informed of the publication of <title>Wat Tyler</title> by a short
                  article in the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 12 February 1817.</note> Therefore I think it is better to act at once, &#8211; &amp;
               indeed in all cases the <del>straightforward</del> manliest course is the best. But it rather staggers me that both <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> incline to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> way of thinking. If you should alter yours, desire <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> by a note not to proceed. I think you will remain in the same mind, &amp; in that
               belief shall send up the affidavit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How much could I say to you upon the subject of your letter! Muirs &amp; Palmers cases did harm, because both parties
               were hardly used.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Muir (1765&#8211;1799; <title>DNB</title>) and Thomas Fysshe Palmer
                  (1747&#8211;1802; <title>DNB</title>) were radicals sentenced, by Scottish courts in 1793, to transportation to Australia. Palmer was a
                  Unitarian Minister, whose only crime was to order the printing of an address to parliament.</note> They had not deserved the
               punishment, &#8211; especially Palmer<del>s</del> &#8211; whose case was a flagrant act of injustice. Margarot was justly sentenced, -<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Maurice Margarot (1745&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>) was a delegate from the London Corresponding Society to
                  the Edinburgh Convention of the Friends of the People in Scotland in 1793. He was transported to Australia in 1794, only returning
                  in 1811.</note> but there was an appearance of wrong in not allowing some of his challenges. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WakefieldGilbert">Gilbert Wakefields</ref> book<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Gilbert Wakefield&#8217;s
                     <title>A Reply to Some Parts of the Bishop of Llandaff&#8217;s Address</title> (1798) led to a sentence of two years&#8217;
                  imprisonment.</note> was not addressed to the mob, &#8211; I think there is more danger <del>than</del> if transportation was made the
               punishment that it would prevent convictions, than that the power would be abused. But what else will stop the evil? &amp; if the evil
               be not stopt a <hi rend="ital">jacquerie</hi> is inevitable. Give the Press full play, &amp; nothing can prevent the Agrarians<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s name for the Society of Spencean Philanthropists (founded 1814), a group of
                  revolutionaries who supported the theories of Thomas Spence (1750&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>) that all land should be publicly
                  owned.</note> from raising the mob upon us. They will swallow up all the feebler vermin, as the Committee<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The House of Commons and House of Lords both established committees on 4 February 1817 to investigate popular unrest.
                  Their alarmist reports helped justify the new Treason Act and Seditious Meetings Act in 1817.</note> tells us they are doing; &#8211;
               &amp; as for stopping them by force of reason, &#8211; you might as well reason against a steam engine, or one of our mountain floods. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I groan over the cowardice of the ministry. Every concession will only provoke insult, <del>dem</del> contempt &amp;
               farther demands. But they must be supported, &#8211; the choice is between them &amp; Revolution; &#8211; &amp; therefore I was sorry that you had
               refused to be on the Finance Committee.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The House of Commons appointed a Select Committee in
                  February 1817 to examine how to reduce public expenditure. It began by examining sinecures and superfluous public offices.</note>
               Indeed this is no time for doing any thing which may increase their discredit.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If I were not too closely occupied I would by way of penance, gird up my loins, &amp; take the subject of Wat Tyler for
               an historical play, in which to put forth all the powers I could bring to bear upon the story. Plot is excused in such dramas, <del>so
                  that</del> {if} interest can be excited without one by the mere march of events. I meant to have done this in 1797 &#8211; but it was laid
               aside.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have bought the first vol. of the Rerum Hibernicarum Script. &amp; have taken a great fancy to O&#8217;Conor,
               notwithstanding the great O in his name.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles O&#8217;Conor (1764&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Rerum Hibernicarum Scriptores Veteres</title>, 4 vols (1814&#8211;1826), no. 2112 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.
                  O&#8217;Conor was a priest from a well-known family of Irish scholars. His book was an edition of some of the Irish manuscripts in the
                  library at Stowe, where he worked as chaplain to Mary, Marchioness of Buckinghamshire (d. 1812), the sister-in-law of Wynn&#8217;s uncle,
                  Lord Grenville.</note> Some of the parts which relate to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">your Uncle</ref> &amp; to his
               own situation are Stowe are exceedingly fine. I hope the work will proceed; &#8211; it is indeed a munificent example of wisely directed
               patronage.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The second vol. of Brazil<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols
                  (1810&#8211;1819).</note> is finished, &amp; you will receive it in a few days. I am busy upon the third, &#8211; &amp; such is the course of my
               life at present, that this employment seems like playing truant from closer calls. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> offers me 150&#163; for two articles in each number. I want this money from the next, &amp; shall earn it in the course of
                  <del>the</del> six weeks: the subjects are Mariners Tonga Islands (pray read the book)<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">William Mariner (1791&#8211;1853) lived in the Tonga islands from 1806 to 1810 after the local people attacked his ship and killed his
                  crewmates. His narrative was published by Murray in 1817, having been prepared for the press by the meteorologist John Martin
                  (1789&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of the Natives of the Tonga Islands, in the South Pacific Ocean, with an Original
                     Grammar and Vocabulary of their Language</title> (1817). Southey reviewed the book in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 17 (April
                  1817), 1&#8211;39.</note> &#8211; &amp; the Reports of the Committee.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Rise and Progress of Popular
                  Disaffection&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511&#8211;552. The books of which it was nominally a review included
                  the <title>Report of the Secret Committee of the House of Commons, Respecting Certain Meetings and Dangerous Combinations</title>
                  (1817), which investigated recent revolutionary outbreaks and reported on 19 February 1817.</note> I must write the latter part of
               this first, &#8211; &amp; leave the beginning till I see what is to be done, &#8211; the main part will be a <del>pic</del> sketch of the growth
               &amp; progress of political discontent in this country, &#8211; &amp; the means of abating it: I shall aim at a conciliating &amp; persuasive
               tone, &amp; avoid all personalities, which I endeavour <hi rend="ital">totis viribus</hi>
          <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;with
                  all one&#8217;s might&#8217;.</note> to attack that spirit of party which is the curse &amp; the opprobrium of England.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Wynn</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1817-02-23">23 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>