<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3218</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4489</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3218. Robert Southey to Chauncy Hare Townshend, 10 December 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3218" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3218.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850) .  Previously  published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 329&#8211;331.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3218" type="letter">
        <head>3218. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Hare Townshend</ref>,<date when="1818-12-10"> 10 December 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from
                  Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb /> Previously published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 329&#8211;331.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-12-10">Dec. 10. 1818.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Chauncey,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You made the best use of your misfortune at Kendal. The most
               completely comfortless hours in a man&#8217;s life (abstracted from all real calamity) are
               those which he spends alone at an inn, waiting for a chance in a stage-coach. Time
               thus spent is so thoroughly disagreeable that the act of getting into the coach, and
               resigning yourself to be jumbled for four-and-twenty or eight- and-forty hours, like
               a mass of inert matter, becomes a positive pleasure. I always prepare myself for such
               occasions with some closely-printed pocket volume, of pregnant matter, for which I
               should not be likely to afford leisure at other times. Erasmus&#8217; Colloquies<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Desiderius Erasmus (1466&#8211;1536),
                     <title>Colloquies</title> (1518).</note> stood me in good stead for more than
               one journey; Sir Thomas More&#8217;s Utopia<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir
                  Thomas More (1478&#8211;1535; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Utopia</title> (1516).</note>
               for another. When I was a school-boy I loved travelling, and enjoyed it, indeed, as
               long as I could say <hi rend="ital">omnia mea mecum</hi>;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;All that&#8217;s mine [I carry] with me&#8217;.</note> that is, as long as
               I could carry with me an undivided heart and mind, and had nothing to make me wish
               myself in any other place than where I was. The journey from London to Bristol at the
               holidays was one of the pleasures which I looked for at breaking up; and I used
               generally to travel by day rather than by night, that I might lose none of the
               expected enjoyments I wish I had kept a journal of all those journeys; for some of
               the company into which I have fallen might have furnished matter worthy of
               preservation. Once I travelled with the keeper of a crimping-house<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A place at which men were enticed, usually by
                  being plied with alcohol, to enlist in the army or navy.</note> at Charing Cross,
               who, meeting with an old acquaintance in the coach, told him his profession while I
               was supposed to be asleep in the corner. Once I formed an acquaintance with a young
               deaf and dumb man, and learnt to converse with him. Once I fell in with a man of a
               race now nearly extinct, &#8211; a village mathematician; a self-taught, iron-headed man,
               who, if he had been lucky enough to have been well educated and entered at Trinity
               Hall, might have been first wrangler,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  highest-scoring BA student in any year at Cambridge University.</note> and perhaps
               have gone as near towards doubling the cube<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">An ancient problem in geometry, often known as the &#8216;Delian problem&#8217;. The
                  non-existence of a solution was not finally demonstrated until 1837.</note> as any
               of the votaries of Mathesis.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  personification of mathematical learning. Southey hated mathematics and had no
                  talent for the subject.</note> (Pray write a sonnet to that said personage.)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Townshend did, indeed, write the sonnet &#8216;To
                  the Goddess of Mathematics&#8217;, which begins: &#8216;O Mathesis, I loathe thy very sight!&#8217;,
                     <title>The Weaver&#8217;s Boy, a Tale; and Other Poems</title> (London, 1825), p.
                  225.</note> This man was pleased with me, and (perhaps because I was flattered by
               perceiving it) I have a distinct recollection of his remarkable countenance after an
               interval of nearly thirty years. He laboured very hard to give me a love of his own
               favourite pursuit; and it is my own fault that I cannot now take the altitude of a
               church tower by the help of a cocked hat, as he taught me, or would have taught, if I
               could have retained such lessons.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is an act, not absolutely of heroic virtue, but of something like
               it, my writing to you this evening. Four successive evenings I have been prevented
               from carrying into effect the fixed purpose of so doing; first by the <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General&#8217;s</ref> dropping in to
               pass the last evening with me before his departure, then by letters which required
               reply without delay. And this afternoon, just before the bell rang for tea, a huge
               parcel was brought up stairs, containing twenty volumes of the Gospel Magazine;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Gospel Magazine</title>
                  (1766&#8211;present), an evangelical publication, mainly aimed at Anglicans. It was an
                  important source for Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and
                     Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> in which dunghill I am now about
               to rake for wheat, or for wild oats, if you like the metaphor better. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>