<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2745</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4016</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2745. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 25 March 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2745" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2745.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 3p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2745" type="letter">
        <head>2745. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-03-25">25 March 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>./ Exchequer<lb /> Endorsement: 25.
                  March 1816<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS; 3p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-03-25">25 March 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Laus Deo<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;God be praised&#8217;.</note> you have herewith the Amen of my
                  labours.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> The final copy of <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816), which
                  Bedford was to see through the press.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are all provoked about the prints, &#8211; that they should not be sent at once without waiting for the Letter Engravers
               work, &#8211; which however necessary for the public is not at all so for those who have been upon the ground.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was eager to see proof copies of the eight engraved pictures that were to illustrate <title>The Poet&#8217;s
                     Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816) and did not want to wait until the captions had been added to the images.</note> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Moon</ref> has been disappointed every day for this week past. But what is worse he has
               been very unwell with an influenza which is going off; &amp; with a cough which is keeping its ground to his great discomfort &amp; not
               less to mine. We cannot give him bark<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> Peruvian bark, from the cinchona tree, contained quinine,
                  and was widely used as a medicine.</note> while the cough continues, &#8211; &amp; he stands much in need of it. But I trust whenever the
               genial weather comes he will shine forth again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> to print fast, &amp; to send me the remaining clean
               sheets for as yet I have only the <hi rend="ital">first</hi>. And I want to fit in the notes. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GrenvilleLord">Lord Grenvilles</ref> speech upon the Slave Trade comes most opportunely this evening to be
               touched upon in the concluding note, &#8211; for I <hi rend="ital">hope</hi> he alludes in it to some provision for the abolition of slavery
               at a determinate time.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey did not allude in his notes to <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to
                     Waterloo</title> (1816) to the speech made in the House of Lords on 22 March 1816 by Lord Grenville, in which Grenville argued
                  for the full enforcement of existing laws prohibiting importation of slaves to the West Indies, and proposed a law forcing the
                  colonial authorities to register each existing slave and to submit their records to London.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall have at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> in the next Quarterly.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> No such article specifically attacking Brougham was published by Southey in the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title> in 1816.</note> His attack upon the Admiralty I suppose originated in personal animosity to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 13, 20 and 25 March 1816 Brougham
                  had, as part of the Whig campaign against government extravagance and corruption, attacked Croker, the Secretary of the Admiralty,
                  in parliament, after it was discovered that Croker&#8217;s wartime salary of &#163;4,000 per annum had been renewed in time of peace. Croker
                  defended himself on 13 March and was defended by other ministers on 20 March; on 25 March 1816 Brougham&#8217;s excessive rhetoric led to
                  a rallying of support for Croker, who survived the attack when the House voted.</note> By the by you had better recover those papers
               from the Times &amp; send them to the Courier, &#8211; &amp; I will put in a verse in the first chapter upon this subject.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s parodic attack on Jeffrey, the &#8216;Book of the Prophet Jehephary&#8217;, was, on the advice of his
                  friends, not published in his lifetime, neither in <title>The Times</title>, where Southey had asked Bedford to submit it, nor the
                     <title>Courier</title>. It appeared in John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4
                  vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 35&#8211;42.</note> It would be easy for me to secure their admission by sending them in my own name to <ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref>; &#8211; but I think they will be glad enough of them anonymously when the heat of
               the debates is a little over.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8220;Of yore, certainly instead of as before for the reason you assign.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816), Part Two, Book 3, &#8216;The Sacred Mountain&#8217;, stanza 10, lines 1&#8211;2; &#8216;full to the
                  brim/ Of her abominations as of yore&#8217;. &#8216;Of yore&#8217; replaced &#8216;before&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to all at home</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">And now instanter to the Lay of the Laureate.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey turned immediately
                     from <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816) to his next Laureate poem, <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen
                        Nuptiale</title> (1816), so that it could be published in time to celebrate the marriage of Charlotte, only child of the
                     Prince Regent, to Prince Leopold of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld (1790&#8211;1865; King of the Belgians 1831&#8211;1865) on 2 May 1816.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>