<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2878</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4149</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2878. Robert Southey to John Murray, 13 December
                  1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2878" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2878.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of
                  Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 4p.  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2878" type="letter">
        <head>2878. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1816-12-13">13 December
                  1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298 <lb /> Postmark: E/ 16 DE 16/ 1816 <lb /> Seal: black wax, with &#8216;S&#8217;, &#8216;In Labore Quies&#8217; motto below<lb />
                  Watermark: HAGAR &amp; HODGSON/ 1815<lb /> Endorsement: 1816 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 13/ Southey R<lb /> MS: National Library of
                  Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 4p. <lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-12-13">13 Dec. 1816.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> That my nature is tolerably open must I think have appeared from my correspondence with you, &#8211; &amp; the very letter
               which has given you pain is proof of it,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">See Robert Southey to John Murray, 17 November 1816,
                  Letter 2864.</note> &#8211; for the moment that I felt any dissatisfaction I expressed it plainly. &#8211; I thought the article in question
               worth its full price, judging thereof by the time &amp; thought which it had cost me, &amp; the effect which it produced, &#8211; for it was
               quoted in country papers &amp; in the Courier, where assuredly no personal considerations for me as the author could have the slightest
               influence, &#8211; &amp; by the <del>reports</del> opinions upon it given <del>xx</del> me by friends who are not accustomed to flatter.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Murray were in disagreement about remuneration for his contributions to the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>. In <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 537&#8211;574, Southey reviewed a series of
                  volumes by travellers in England, under the title &#8216;Works on England&#8217;. His review of &#8216;Ali Bey&#8217; Domingo Badia y Leblich (1766&#8211;1818),
                     <title>Travels of Ali Bey in Morocco, Tripoli, Cyprus, Egypt, Arabia, Syria, and Turkey, Between the Years 1803 and 1807</title>
                  (1816) also appeared in the<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 299&#8211;345. Southey expected to receive &#163;100 for each
                  article, but Murray only agreed to &#163;150 for the two. The <title>Courier</title>, 14 November 1816, had commended &#8216;Works on England&#8217;
                  calling it &#8216;a masterly consideration of the present state of the country&#8217; and suggested it should be published as a pamphlet. This
                  did not happen.</note> Let that matter pass.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> With regard to the Life of Wesley the case stands thus. I never had any conception of promising it to the Quarterly,
               but named it among other subjects, &amp; regretted what would still have been an insuperable objection, the want of any opportunity for
               introducing it.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray was also annoyed that Southey was writing for a new journal edited by
                  John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>): <title>The Correspondent; Consisting of Letters, Moral, Political, and Literary,
                     between Eminent Writers in France and England; and designed by presenting to each Nation a Faithful Picture of the Other, to
                     Enlighten both to their True Interests, promote a Mutual Good Understanding between them, and render Peace the Source of a Common
                     Prosperity</title>. Southey contributed a sketch of the life of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) to the first two
                  numbers (1 (1817), 26&#8211;48; and 2 (1817), 157&#8211;176). However, the <title>Correspondent</title> lasted only one further number. </note>
               This objection did not apply to Stoddarts work, &#8211; <del>xxx</del> I promised him a paper, purely from motives of personal regard,
               without any intention, &#8211; or possibility of regularly contributing, &#8211; but for the sake of assisting him in his outset.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>) was the editor of <title>The Times</title> until
                  dismissed, at the end of 1816, for the intemperate Toryism of his articles. </note> Stoddart is a man whom I have known for more
               than twenty years, &#8211; I disliked him greatly at one time, &amp; did him in my own mind much injustice upon insufficient grounds:<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John Rickman, 3 June 1803, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part
                     Two</title>, Letter 793; here Southey refers to Stoddart as &#8216;this unhappy Spider-brained metaphysician&#8217; and blames him for
                  provoking the excoriating review of Lamb&#8217;s <title>John Woodvil: a Tragedy</title> (1802) in <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 3
                  (April 1803), 90&#8211;96.</note> tho he never knew this, &amp; tho it did him no injury, still I was glad to make him some kind of
               compensation. And as the Editor of the Times throughout the Spanish War I consider him a man preeminently deserving, &#8211; for that
               newspaper &amp; the QR were the best allies of the Government. &#8211; It never occurred to me that you could feel wounded at my contributing
               a paper to his work, or that his work could come in competition with yours. When the British Review<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>British Review and London Critical Journal</title> (1811&#8211;1825).</note> was started I was applied to, &amp;
               refused at once to be concerned with it, as being engaged with you. The Correspondent is not a Review. In all likelihood I shall never
               write for it again if I do, it will only be a chance paper, &#8211; merely for the Editors sake.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There can never be a lack of subjects for the Q. For the present number I can do nothing more, &#8211; &amp; for this reason,
               the validity of which you will allow. How clearly I have foreseen the present fermentation of public opinion you know. Upon this
               momentous subject I have thought so much, &amp; feel so much that I have determined to write upon it <hi rend="ital">totis
                  viribus</hi>,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;With all my powers&#8217;.</note> &amp; without restraint. I shall therefore
               produce a volume of Observations upon the Moral &amp; Political State of England.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">This pamphlet
                  or book was not published; Southey did, though, write on &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October
                  1816), 225&#8211;278, and the &#8216;Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817),
                  511&#8211;552.</note> The first part will demolish the assertions &amp; schemes of the Reformers, &#8211; the second enter fully into the real
               evils of the country &amp; propose the remedies. I believe that I have some things to say which may produce great good. &#8211; &amp; I mean
               to affix my name to it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have begun this book &amp; am making progress in it. Have you any objection to my embodying in it such parts of the
               papers in the Review as belong to the subject, &amp; could be fitted in? &#8211; There are some things also in the Register<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808 to 1811</title> (1810&#8211;1813), for which Southey wrote the
                  historical section.</note> which I should incorporate, making of course a general acknowledgement in the prefatory Advertisement. &#8211;
               If I could say the same things more forcibly, &#8211; the trouble or expence of time would be no consideration, &#8211; but it would be vexatious
               &amp; injurious to say them worse merely for the sake of <del>saying</del> {putting} them in a different form. A considerable
               difference would necessarily be made, by rearrangement, correction &amp;c: &amp; the whole acquire weight &amp; force from coming in
               something like a systematic form. The fairest terms will be that you publish the book, &amp; allow me half the eventual profits: &#8211; I do
               not think it can fail of a considerable sale. Let me hear from you upon this point without delay. I {calculate upon a fair octavo
               volume, &#8211; the size of Pasleys,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles William Pasley (1780&#8211;186; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Essay on the Military Policy and Institutions of the British Empire</title> (1810) &#8211; a book that Southey greatly
                  admired.</note> &amp; I hope not less effective in its way.}</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> For the number after this there will be the Catacombs &#8211; a short paper for which I have collected a good many
               interesting memoranda.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris&#8217; appeared in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359&#8211;398.</note> And as Mariner is just published <del>that</del> the longer paper had better be
               upon his book &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BurneyJames">Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Burneys</ref>.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed John Martin (1789&#8211;1868; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Account of the Natives of the Tonga Islands,
                     in the South Pacific Ocean, with an Original Grammar and Vocabulary of their Language</title> (1817) in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 17 (April 1817), 1&#8211;39. This book told the story of the ship&#8217;s boy William Mariner (1791&#8211;1853) who lived in the
                  Tonga islands from 1806 to 1810 after the local people attacked his ship and killed his crewmates. Southey also discussed in the
                  same review Burney&#8217;s <title>A Chronological History of the Voyages and Discoveries in the South Sea or Pacific Ocean; Illustrated
                     with Charts and Plates</title> (1816).</note> There is George 3.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Aikin,
                     <title>Annals of the Reign of King George III</title> (1816) was not reviewed by Southey in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.
                  The book was no. 20 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> &#8211; there is Huntington the Sinner Saved<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">William Huntington (1745&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), a coalheaver turned Calvinist preacher who believed he would, on
                  Judgement Day, be revealed as a prophet. Huntington became a popular, and rich, preacher in London, despite being accused of
                  antinomianism. Southey&#8217;s review of <title>The Works of the Reverend William Huntington, S.S. Minister of the Gospel, at Providence
                     Chapel, Gray&#8217;s Inn Lane, completed to the close of the Year 1806</title> (1811) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24
                  (January 1821), 462&#8211;510.</note> (he shall come next but one) &#8211; &amp; I can give you a weighty paper upon the Jesuits, including a
               Life of Loyola.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not contribute an article on the Jesuits or their founder, Ignatius
                  Loyola (1491&#8211;1556).</note> There are some recent publications about the Jesuits which you had better send me, &#8211; I have a life
               written which requires only such alteration as may be made in transcribing it, &#8211; materials for the rest are at hand, &amp; I am master
               of the subject. Send me also that I may be reading for George 3, Woodfalls Junius, &#8211; the Anecdote of Lord Chatham, the Life of Pitt, &#8211;
               &amp; any other books that may occur to you upon the subject.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Sampson Woodfall
                  (1739&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Letters of Junius </title>(1772); John Almon (1737&#8211;1805; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Anecdotes of the Life of the Right Honourable William Pitt, Earl of Chatham</title> (1792) &#8211; an edition of 1810 was no. 580
                  in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; William Godwin, <title>The History of the Life of William Pitt, Earl of Chatham
                  </title>(1783).</note> I am inclined to think that this subject had better be divided into two papers &#8211; the first ending with the
               American War,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The American War of Independence (1775&#8211;1783).</note> &#8211; it is scarcely possible to
               comprize it in one.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must not conclude without reverting to the unpleasant nature of our last letters, &#8211; but it is only to say that on my
               mind it will leave no uncomfortable impression. And as to the affair of the Correspondent, I had not the most distant suspicion that it
               could in the slightest degree hurt you, or interfere with the Review. Stoddart communicated his plan to me when I was last in town, &#8211; I
               promised him something then for his first number, &amp; mentioning two or three subjects left him to chuse. &#8211; You offer very liberally,
               &amp; more than I can avail myself of. For two or perhaps three numbers in the year I may supply two articles each, &#8211; but hardly I
               think more than six in the year: &#8211; indeed the first month that I can fairly command I must give to the H. of the War,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; full half a volume is ready
               if the first chapter were finished. Pray procure for me Azanza &amp; O Farrills book,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Miguel
                  Jos&#233; de Azanza, Duke of Santa Fe (1746&#8211;1826), Minister for War 1793&#8211;1796, Viceroy of New Spain 1798&#8211;1800; and Gonzalo O&#8217;Farrill y
                  Herrera (1754&#8211;1831), Minister of War 1808&#8211;1813. They published <title>Memoria de D. Miguel Jos&#233; de Azanza y D. Gonzalo O&#8217;F&#225;rrill,
                     Sobre los Hechos que Justifican su Conducta Politica</title> (1815).</note> &#8211; which is the justification of the French party, I
               will certainly <hi rend="ital">bring</hi> the beginning to town in the spring, &#8211; communicate it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Frere</ref>, &amp; then go to press.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs as ever</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>