<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3151</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4422</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3151. Robert Southey to John Kenyon, 13 June 1818 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3151" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3151.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.232.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 305&#8211;306 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3151" type="letter">
        <head>3151. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#KenyonJohn">John Kenyon</ref>,<date when="1818-06-13"> 13 June 1818 </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Kenyon Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Aix la Chapelle<lb /> Stamped:
                  KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: F 18/ 230<lb /> Watermark: B.E. &amp; S. BATH 1814<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.232.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 305&#8211;306 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-06-13"> 13 June 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref>, which has this
               day arrived, enables me to thank you for Dobrizhoffer,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The account of the Jesuit missions in
                  Paraguay by Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title>
                  (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. He needed the book for his <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &amp; for the good old Huguenot Jean de Lery.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">By the time of his death,
                  Southey&#8217;s library contained two editions (1578 and 1585) of Jean de L&#233;ry (1536&#8211;1613), <title>Histoire d&#8217;un Voyage faict en la Terre
                     du Bresil</title>, nos 1709&#8211;1710 in the sale catalogue of his library. L&#233;ry had been part of the failed French colony in Brazil
                  and was later a Protestant Minister in France.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#EverettEdward">The American</ref> by whom the latter was sent to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brothers</ref>, has not yet made his appearance at the Lakes; &#8211; when he comes, I will
               provide him with an introduction to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, if he should not bring one
               from London; &amp; if he is particularly desirous of seeing live poets, he shall have credentials for <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>. I suppose an American enquires for them as naturally as you or I should do in
               America for a skunk or an opossum. They are becoming marvellously abundant in England, so that publications which twenty years ago
               would have attracted considerable attention, are now coming from the press in shoals, almost unnoticed. This makes it the more
               remarkable that America should be so utterly barren, &#8211; since their revolution they have not produced a single poet who has been heard
               of on this side of the Atlantic. Dwight &amp; Barlow<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), academic,
                  theologian and author of the first American epic, <title>The Conquest of Canaan</title> (1785); he served as a chaplain in the
                  American War of Independence 1777&#8211;1778. Joel Barlow (1754&#8211;1812) was the author of the American epic <title>Vision of
                     Columbus</title> (1787), revised as the <title>Columbiad</title> (1807). He was also a chaplain in the War of Independence and
                  later Consul at Algiers 1795&#8211;1797 and Minister Plenipotentiary to France 1811&#8211;1812. Barlow&#8217;s radical views and advocacy of
                  friendship with France earned him Southey&#8217;s disapproval.</note> both belong to the Revolution, &amp; well was it for the Americans,
               taking them into the account, that we could not say of them tam Marte quam Mercurio<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Proverbial,
                  meaning &#8216;As well qualified for diplomacy as for war&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very sorry that your friend Ritchie should have gone upon an adventure which has proved fatal to every one who has
               yet undertaken it, &amp; which I think the amateur geographizing &#8216;gentlemen of England who sit at home at ease&#8217; are altogether
               unjustifiable in pursuing at such a cost of valuable lives.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Ritchie (c 1788&#8211;1819;
                     <title>DNB</title>), a surgeon and naturalist, had been recruited by John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), the Second
                  Secretary of the Admiralty 1804&#8211;1806, 1807&#8211;1845, to be a member of an expedition to explore the course of the Niger and the location
                  of Timbuktu. Leaving in 1818, Ritchie died in the Sahara the following year. Southey had dined with Kenyon and Ritchie in Paris on
                  20 May 1817, on his continental tour. To illustrate his disapproval of the expedition, Southey quotes part of the opening line from
                  a popular ballad: &#8216;Ye gentlemen of England, who sit at home at ease/ How little do you think upon the dangers of the seas&#8217;.</note>
               The object is not tantamount, as it is in a voyage of discovery. In such voyages too men are only exposed to some additional risque in
               the way of their profession, &amp; the reward if they return safe is certain &amp; proportionate, &#8211; but here, &#8211; Mungo Park went upon
               his second expedition literally because he could not support his family after the first.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Mungo
                  Park (1771&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>), having narrowly survived his first expedition to the Niger river in 1797, went on a second
                  journey there in 1805, never to return.</note> &#8211; If however Ritchie should live to accomplish his object I am noways apprehensive
               that his reputation will be eclipsed by his intended rival Ali Bey,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Ali Bey al-Abbasi was the
                  name adopted by Domingo Bad&#237;a y Leblich (1766&#8211;1818), the Spanish explorer, during his travels in North Africa and Arabia. His
                  narrative appeared in England as <title>Travels of Ali Bey: in Morocco, Tripoli, Cyprus, Egypt, Arabia, Syria, and Turkey, Between
                     the years 1803 and 1807</title> (1816). Southey reviewed the book in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816),
                  299&#8211;345.</note> that solemn professor of humbug having made less use of his opportunities than any other traveller, always excepting
               Browne of Darfur.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">William George Browne (1768&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), the African explorer,
                  spent the years 1793&#8211;1796 in detention in Darfur, Sudan. On his return, he published <title>Travels in Africa, Egypt and Syria, from
                     the Years 1792 to 1798</title> (1799). He was killed in Iran during an expedition to Samarkand.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you go thro Cologne (as I suppose you will) do not fail to visit S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ursula &amp; the Eleven
               Thousand Virgins, whose relics form the most extraordinary sight that the Catholic superstition has to display.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The church of St Ursula in Cologne contains an enormous reliquary in which supposedly lie the bones of this
                  fourth-century British saint who, according to legend, was killed, with her eleven thousand virginal handmaids, on a pilgrimage to
                  Cologne, by the Huns besieging the city. The reliquary is extraordinary because, in addition to its size, it displays the bones
                  arranged in patterns and so as to form letters and words. Southey had seen the church on his continental tour of 1817.</note> You
               will also find the Three Kings in the same city<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A reliquary in Cologne Cathedral supposedly
                  contains the bones of the magi who visited the infant Christ in Bethlehem, <title>Matthew</title> 2: 1&#8211;12.</note> well worthy a
               visit to their magnificent shrine. &#8211; From thence to Mentz &amp; Frankfort you will see every where the havoc which the Revolution has
               made: &#8211; farther I cannot accompany your journey. We came to Frankfort from Heidelberg &amp; the Black Forest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> During the winter &amp; what should be the spring I have been closely employed, chiefly upon the history of Brazil
               &amp; a life of Wesley, which is in fact a history of Methodism.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) and <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> Both will
               be compleated about the fall of the leaf. &#8211; Summer came upon us suddenly, &amp; we have had four or five weeks of continual sunshine, &#8211;
               giving us the heat &amp; drought of a hot climate, without any of the compensations. Today for the first time, we are rejoicing in
                  <del>the</del> clouds &amp; rain, &amp; of these, we shall probably as usual have a full share before the season is over. &#8211; I do not
               know where <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General Peachy</ref> is, except that he is in motion; &#8211; his island is in
               its greatest beauty &amp; I do not believe that he has ever seen it at this season. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> has taken a house in Buckinghamshire for twelve months. A year or two hence perhaps, if we both live so long, we may
               talk of another expedition together,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Senhouse travelled to Europe together again in
                  1838, but only to France.</note> as far as Rome &amp; Naples, &amp; then I shall be content to chew the cud of recollection for the
               rest of my life. You do wisely to lay in a larger stock at a more convenient age.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Ladies<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>
                  and her sisters <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> all desire to be remembered</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs most truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>