<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2867</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4138</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2867. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 26 November 1816 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2867" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2867.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 297. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 218&#8211;221 [in part;
                  misdated 20 November 1816].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2867" type="letter">
        <head>2867. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>, <date when="1816-11-26">26 November 1816 </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 26 Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816<lb /> MS: Huntington Library, RS 297. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 218&#8211;221 [in part;
                  misdated 20 November 1816].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Under two covers lest <del>they</del> {it} should prove too heavy for
               one I inclose a communication for D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stoddart, for his new
               adventure, in which I wish him success, &#8211; good proof of <del>which</del>
                  {<del>this</del>} it is that I have spared him this precious time. It will take me
               yet another weeks half work to finish for him. I have long had an inkling for the
               subject, &#8211; which is a life of John Wesley.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In
                  1817 a new journal was launched, published by Longmans and edited by John Stoddart
                  (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>), who had in 1816 been dismissed from the
                  editorship of the <title>Times</title> for the intemperate Toryism of his
                  articles. It was entitled <title>The Correspondent; Consisting of Letters, Moral,
                     Political, and Literary, between Eminent Writers in France and England; and
                     designed by presenting to each Nation a Faithful Picture of the Other, to
                     Enlighten both to their True Interests, promote a Mutual Good Understanding
                     between them, and render Peace the Source of a Common Prosperity</title>.
                  Southey contributed a sketch of the life of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791;
                     <title>DNB</title>) to the first two numbers (1 (1817), 26&#8211;48; and 2 (1817),
                  157&#8211;176). However, the <title>Correspondent</title> lasted only one further
                  number. Stoddart became the editor of a new ministry-supported paper, <title>The
                     New Times</title> (1817&#8211;1828).</note> This done &#8211; forthwith to the Opus.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s intention resulted in the articles
                  &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816),
                  225&#8211;278, and &#8216;Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511&#8211;552, rather than the book on the &#8216;State
                  of the Nation&#8217; that he was planning.</note> It is clearly better that I should
               write <hi rend="ital">ex proprio motu</hi>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8217;Of my own accord&#8217;.</note> than <del>any</del> under any understanding with men
               in office, which would unavoidably in some degree shackle me. And whether they like
               it or not, the freedom of one part will give ten fold effect to the other.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> About the poor I am very anxious to be informed thoroughly, &#8211; &amp;
               very sensible how deficient I am in the right sort of knowledge upon this subject, &#8211;
               that is as to how the great evil is to be remedied, &#8211; that of the poor rates. My
               present views can reach no further than to the slow alterations &amp; preventatives
               of good instruction in youth, &amp; encouragement to frugality &amp; industry
               afterwards by means of hope. Concerning immediate alleviation I entirely agree with
               you in the great advantage of undertaking great public works, &#8211; &amp; stated it
               strongly some years ago in the first paper upon the Poor, which is in some respects
               better than the last, &#8211; &amp; which if it had wrought duly upon the men in power
               would have prevented all danger now.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                  first article on the poor was his &#8216;Inquiry into the Poor Laws&#8217;, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;56; the more recent article was &#8216;On the
                  Poor&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187&#8211;235. In his first
                  article Southey had written &#8216;No time, therefore, can be so proper for national
                  works, for making new naval stations and improving the old, for cutting roads,
                  draining fens, and recovering tracts of country by embankments from the sea&#8217;
                  (352).</note> The Anarchists felt its force, &amp; for that reason have been
               spitting their venom {at me} ever since, &#8211; I know this to be the case with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref> &amp; the Examiner, &#8211; as for
               his worthy coadjutor <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Sir Tarquin of
                  the Round Table</ref>, he has a reason which is proverbially valid for wishing to
               cut my throat.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The proverb runs &#8216;Save a thief
                  from the gallows, and he&#8217;ll be the first shall cut your throat&#8217;. Southey and
                  Coleridge considered themselves betrayed by William Hazlitt, having hosted him at
                  Greta Hall in 1803 and assisted him in escaping from the anger of the townsfolk
                  after he caused a furore in a Keswick inn by spanking a local woman when she
                  laughed at his advances. In the Arthurian legends, Sir Tarquin was a treacherous
                  knight who fought against his former friends. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My scheme is something of this kind,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Here Southey outlines his plan for his unwritten book on &#8216;The State
                  of the Nation&#8217;.</note> &#8211; but tho I am always long even to dilatoriness in planning
               whatever I write, the plan is always very much altered in the course of execution.
                  1<hi rend="sup">st</hi>. State in which the war has left us &#8211; political &amp;
               moral. 2. necessity of that war, &amp; Buonaparte<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821), Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814,
                  1815.</note> drawn to the life as the Perfect Emperor of the English friends of
               freedom. 3 Sketch of {the history of} anarchical opinions in this country from
               Charles 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> time<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles I
                  (1600&#8211;1649; King of England 1625&#8211;1649; <title>DNB</title>).</note>, &#8211; Wilkes<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wilkes (1727&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>):
                  radical journalist, politician and pornographer, whose exclusion from his seat in
                  parliament had led to a political crisis and much radical agitation in 1768&#8211;1771.
                  Southey would attack Wilkes in &#8216;Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217;,
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511&#8211;552 (530&#8211;531).</note>
               &amp; Junius<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The pseudonym of the author of a
                  series of letters to the <title>Public Advertiser</title>, 1769&#8211;1772, defending
                  liberty and attacking government corruption. Also attacked in the &#8216;Rise and
                  Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January
                  1817), 511&#8211;552 (530&#8211;531).</note> the root in modern times, &#8211; (here M. Simond
               agrees with me, who by the by married Wilkes&#8217;s niece,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis Simond (1767&#8211;1831), <title>Journal of a Tour and Residence in
                     Great Britain, During the Years 1810 and 1811 </title>(1815). Southey reviewed
                  this work in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 537&#8211;74. Simond had
                  married Wilkes&#8217;s niece, Frances (dates unknown).</note>) the first fruit was the
               American war, &#8211; the French Revolution the second; &#8211; this leads <del>xx</del> to 4. a
               view of the united reformers, i.e. the enemies of Government under their several
               classes, their mode of operations (here the press) &#8211; their various plans of reform,
               &amp; the sure consequences of each. I have old papers of yours which were of
               excellent use in the Register,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                     <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808&#8211;1811</title> (1810&#8211;1813), for which
                  Southey wrote the historical sections.</note> &amp; will come into use again, &#8211;
               heavy artillery for the grand battery.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All this will be well liked, &amp; if I looked for favour it would be
               prudent to stop here, but it is not for any such motive that I put myself in the
               front of the battle. And here I wish to begin upon an exposure of the evils which
               exist in our state of society, &amp; which it is the duty &amp; interest of
               Government as far as possible to mitigate &amp; remove. Some things should be got rid
               of as matters of scandal. To destroy influence in elections would be neither wise if
               it were possible, nor possible if it were wise; &#8211; but it is not fit that
                  <del>indi</del> men should sell <del>these</del> seats in parliament, {(i.e.
                  borough-mongers<del>)</del> x have no obligation to the voters who take their
               price per man as at Ilchester<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">At Ilchester
                  all resident householders could vote, but there were very few of them, as the town
                  had shrunk considerably since the Middle Ages. Elections were notoriously corrupt
                  and led to numerous petitions and inquiries. The price of a vote at this time was
                  apparently &#163;30. </note> to wit)} tho very fit that they should be bought. I would
               have these boroughs bought openly, like commissions in the army, &amp; the money
                  <del>appli</del> go to form a fund for public works either national or provincial.
               A scandal is got rid of, &amp; a good produced, &amp; the species of property which
               would be touched by it, is one which ought not to have existed, as having always been
               contrary to positive law.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Laws duly made by
                  Parliament.</note> &#8211; I think too that the few great sinecures which still exist
               should be given up (Lord Cambden for instance has had his quite long enough<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John Jeffreys Pratt, 1st Marquess Camden
                  (1759&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), long-serving politician and Teller of the Receipt
                  of the Exchequer 1780&#8211;1834. This office involved no duties but was alleged to
                  produce a profit of &#163;20,000&#8211;&#163;30,000 per annum during the wars against France.
                  Camden agreed to give up one third of these profits in 1812.</note>) &amp; applied
               during the lives of the present incumbents to some purpose of public splendour, &#8211;
               that they may give them up with a grace. I would also give members to the great towns
               which have none, <del>by such a xxx xx x xxxx</del> by restricting the voters by such
               qualifications as should as far as may be disqualify the mere mob. &#8211; I would lay no
               stress on these things, farther than as depriving the anarchists of the only topics
               which give a shadow of <del>reason</del> plausibility to their harangues.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The great evil is the state of the poor, which with our press
                  <del>&amp;</del> our means of communication &amp; the perfect knowledge which the
               lowest journeymen possess of the act of combining &amp; raising money (I might add of
               insurrectionary tactics) constantly exposes us to the horror of a Bellum
                  Servile,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">A war of the poor against the
                  rich.</note> &amp; sooner or later (if not remedied) must end in one. For there is
               a state of knowledge &amp; feeling (call it half knowledge if you will) in which the
               sort of poverty that exists among us will be no more to be borne than slavery would
               be at this time in any part of civilized Europe.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There are also great evils in the <del>xxxx</del> delays of law,
               which are surely capable of remedy (tho from Sir Samuel Romilly<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Samuel Romilly (1757&#8211;1818; <title>DNB</title>),
                  legal reformer, Whig Solicitor-General 1806&#8211;1807 and MP for Horsham 1807&#8211;1808,
                  Wareham 1808&#8211;1812, Arundel 1812&#8211;1818 and Westminster 1818.</note> Good Lord
               deliver us) &#8211; &amp; in the expence of criminal law: here in this place we have
               striking proof how it operates in ensuring impunity for <del>men who</del> notorious
               villains</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A greater still is the condition of women: &#8211; here we are upon your
               old ground, &#8211; &amp; passing from morals to religion I think I could show how a great
               comprehension is practicable, &#8211; that is how the Church might employ those who will
               else be enlisted against her. And if there be a mode by which the <del>cause of</del>
               tithes could be placed upon such a footing, or so commuted,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Tithes were the system whereby one tenth of the annual profits from
                  various occupations, but mainly agriculture, were paid to the upkeep of the Church
                  of England. Many tithes had passed to lay owners, though, and the system was
                  fantastically complex and litigious. Commutation would involve turning tithes into
                  cash payments.</note> as to get rid of that perpetual cause of litigation, &#8211; you
               are of all men most likely to point it out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One topic more, which is not introduced here in its proper place may
               conclude this long outline. All professions, trades &amp; means of getting a
               livelihood among us are overstocked. We must create another layer of customers at
               home by bettering the condition of the lower classes, &amp; giving them more wants
               with more means of gratifying them. We must extend establishments instead of
               diminishing them, &#8211; more clergyman, more colleges &#8211; more Courts of Law, &amp; lastly
               we must colonize upon the true principles of colonization, &#8211; &amp; cultivate every
               cultivable acre at home.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here is work enough cut out; &#8211; &amp; tho many of these topics cannot
               possibly be expected to produce any effect at present, yet an impression will be made
               &#8211; &amp; ultimately something may spring from them. I am much liked in one wide
               circle, &amp; am heartily abominated in another, &#8211; &amp; what between praise on one
               side &amp; abuse on the other the book will be sent abroad with a whirlwind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now after making up my dispatches I shall have a good half hour
               for Brazil.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> So God bless you &#8211; Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R.</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yrs most truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-11-26">26 Nov. 1816</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>