<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2919</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4190</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2919. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, [15 February
                  1817]</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2919" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2919.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 238&#8211;240 [in
                  part]. Dating note: Dating from endorsement.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2919" type="letter">
        <head>2919. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1817-02-15">[15 February
                  1817]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer <lb /> Endorsements: 15 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>
                  1817; 15 February 1817/ Paper hanger W.T. Murray/ the Great blank verse poem/ 1000
                  Gs<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously
                  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of
                     Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 238&#8211;240 [in
                  part].<lb /> Dating note: Dating from endorsement.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do you remember that twenty years {ago} a letter directed for me at
               your house was carried to a paper hangers of my name in Bedford Street,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John William Southey (dates unknown), a paper
                  hanger and stationer, whose shop in 1794&#8211;1798 was at 35 Bedford Street, Covent
                  Garden. He had gone bankrupt in 1809. It is possible that he was from Somerset and
                  a very distant relative of Southey&#8217;s.</note> &#8211; &amp; the man found me out &amp;
               put his card into my hand? Upon the strength of this acquaintance I have now a letter
               from this poor namesake; &#8211; soliciting charity, &amp; describing himself &amp; his
               family as in the very depth of human misery. This is not the only proof I have had of
               a strange opinion that I am overflowing with riches. &#8211; Poor wretched man what can I
               do for him! However I do not like to shut my ears &amp; my heart to a tale of this
               kind. Send him I pray you a two pound note in my name, &#8211; to N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 10
               Hercules Buildings, Lambeth; &#8211; your servant had better take it, for fear he should
               have been sent to the work house before this time. When I come to town I will seek
               about if any thing can be done for him. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I wrote to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> last night to consult him about Wat Tyler,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 14
                  February 1817, Letter 2918. In 1794 Southey sent James Ridgway (1755&#8211;1838) and
                  Henry Symonds (1741&#8211;1816), radical booksellers and then in Newgate prison, a copy
                  of his Jacobin drama <title>Wat Tyler</title>; see Robert Southey to Edith
                  Fricker, [c. 12 January 1795], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey.
                     Part One</title>, Letter 123. Ridgway and Symonds did not publish it and it
                  remained in manuscript until a pirated publication, designed to embarrass the now
                  anti-Jacobin Southey, appeared in 1817. Having taken advice from <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref>, Wynn and Turner, Southey
                  launched a suit in Chancery so as to gain an injunction suppressing the
                  publication.</note> &#8211; telling him all the circumstances &amp; desiring him, if it
               be best to procure an injunction, to send the letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, &amp; desire him to act
               for me. Three &amp; twenty years ago the MS was put into Ridgeways hands who promised
               to publish it then (anonymously unless I am very much mistaken) &#8211; &amp; from that
               time to this I never heard of it, &#8211; there was no other copy in existence except the
               original scrawl which is now lying up stairs in an old trunk full of papers. I wish
               the Attorney General<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir William Garrow
                  (1760&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>), Attorney-General 1813&#8211;1817, and thus responsible
                  for prosecutions of this nature.</note> would prosecute the publisher for
               sedition, &#8211; this I really should enjoy. Happy are they who have no worse sins of
               their youth to rise in judgement against them. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I inclose a draft for the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Docstor</ref> wherewith to
               pay for the forks,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey
                  had arranged the purchase of some silver forks for Southey.</note> &#8211; the residuum
               will be a supply for my immediate calls on my arrival.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Government are acting like themselves &#8211; could I say <del>xx</del> any
               thing more severe? They should have begun with vigour &amp; rigour, &#8211; &amp; <hi rend="ital">then</hi> when they had the victory have made their sacrifices ex
               propria motu,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Of one&#8217;s own
                  accord&#8217;.</note> &#8211; with a good grace. But they ought not, on any account to have
               touched the official salaries, &#8211; a thing unjust &amp; unwise, which instead of
               currying favour for them {with the rabble} will make them despised for their
                  pusillanimity.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Stewart, Viscount
                  Castlereagh (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), Foreign Secretary and Leader of the
                  House of Commons 1812&#8211;1822 had announced a series of reductions in public
                  expenditure, especially in the army and navy, on 7 February 1817. As part of this
                  programme, public servants (including Bedford and Southey) were urged to give up
                  the rise in their salaries caused by the abolition of income tax in 1816.
                  Castlereagh also announced a select committee would be appointed to examine public
                  expenditure.</note> I have neither pity nor patience for them. Was ever paper used
               like this last <del>xx xxx</del> article has been to please them! They have
               absolutely cut it down to their own exact measure, &#8211; every thing useful is
                  <del>xx</del> gone &amp; every thing original, &#8211; <del>every thing</del> whatever
               had most force in it was sure to be <del>xx</del> struck out.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey refers to the censorship of his article on current
                  affairs, &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October
                  1816), 225&#8211;278 (published 11 February 1817). </note> Of all the practical measures
               upon which I touched, one only has escaped, &amp; that because it comes in as if by
               accident, the hint about transporting for sedition.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had suggested in &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;,
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 268 that an appropriate
                  punishment for the radical Thomas Spence (1750&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>) when he
                  was convicted for seditious libel in 1801 would have been transportation, rather
                  than one year in prison.</note> &#8211; If we come out of this confusion without an
               utter overthrow it will be as we escaped the Gunpowder plot,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The plot by a group of English Catholics to blow up parliament
                  in 1605.</note> &#8211; not by any aid of human wisdom, &#8211; God knows we have no right to
               calculate upon miracles. The prospect is very dismal, &amp; it is provoking to think
               that nothing is wanting to secure us but foresight &amp; courage. &#8211; But of what use
               is railing, or advising or taking thoughts for such things. I am only a passenger, &#8211;
               the officers must look to the ship, &#8211; if she is lost then the fault rests with them.
               I have nothing to answer for, &amp; must take my share in the wreck with
               patience.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand
               Murray</ref> in his grand way offers me a thousand guineas for my intended poem
               in blank verse, &#8211; &amp; begs it may not be a line longer than Thomsons seasons!!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">James Thomson (1700&#8211;1748;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Seasons</title> (1730), the most popular blank
                  verse poem of the eighteenth century, ran to 5423 lines. Southey began, but did
                  not finish, a blank verse poem, entitled &#8216;Consolation&#8217; on the death of his son,
                  Herbert. Sections were published after his death as &#8216;Fragmentary Thoughts
                  Occasioned by his Son&#8217;s Death&#8217;, <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale
                     (Unfinished): With Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 93&#8211;95,
                  and &#8216;Additional Fragment, Occasioned by the Death of his Son&#8217;, <title>Poetical
                     Works of Robert Southey. Complete in One Volume</title> (London, 1850), p.
                  815.</note> &#8211; I rather think the poem will be a post-obit, &#8211; &amp; in that case
               twice that sum, at least, may be demanded for it. What the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Personages</ref> real feelings
               towards me may be I cannot tell, &#8211; but he is a happy fellow, living in the light of
               his own glory, &amp; as proud as a fly upon the Kings state carriage. The Review<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>
                  (1809&#8211;1967), established by Murray in March 1809.</note> is the greatest of all
               works, &amp; it is all his own creation. he prints 10,000, &amp; fifty times ten
               thousand read its contents in the East &amp; in the West. &#8211; &amp; he never seems to
               recollect that not one of all those readers ever think of the Bookseller. Joy be with
               him &amp; his Journal. I will treat you with his correspondence whenever you come to
                  <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &#8211; it is admirable in its
               kind, &amp; will make you alternately laugh &amp; swear. I am very far from disliking
               him, &#8211; vanity is the most pardonable of all faults, &#8211; &amp; most men have it in some
               form or other. I should be loth to part with what little is left of <del>the large
                  xxxxx xxxx xxxxxx</del> my share. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is really amusing to see how the Rascals attack me about the
                  Court,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Lay of the
                     Laureate</title> (1816) had reignited these charges, e.g. in the
                     <title>Examiner</title>, 445 (7 July 1816) and 446 (14 July 1816).</note> as if
               I were a regular courtier, punctual in attendance, perfect in flattery, &amp;
               enjoying all that favour for {the slightest portion of} which these very Rascals
               would sell their souls, &#8211; if they had any! Malice never aimed at a less vulnerable
               mark. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> has
                  just sent me this Resurrection of Sedition. &#8211; The verses are better than I
                  expected to find them, &#8211; which I think you will allow to be a cool philosophical
                     remark.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference to Southey&#8217;s
                     Jacobin drama of 1794, <title>Wat Tyler</title>, now first published in a
                     pirate edition.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>