<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3217</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4488</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3217. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 6 December
                  1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3217" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3217.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 173.
                  ALS; 4p..  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3217" type="letter">
        <head>3217. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1818-12-06">6 December
                  1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ DE 9/ 1818 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 9 DE 9/ 1818<lb /> MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 173.
                  ALS; 4p.<title>
              <lb />
            </title>Unpublished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenJames">Gooden</ref>. Some person has put
               into his hands <del>xxx</del> a book containing the Government correspondence with the Governors General of Brazil from 1614 to 1622, &#8211;
               the original papers, with the signatures of Philip<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Philip III (1578&#8211;1621; King of Spain and
                  Portugal 1598&#8211;1621).</note> &amp; his ministers. By his account they are not of much importance, &amp; yet he thinks I should have
               gleaned something from them had they been discovered in time. The owner asks <hi rend="ital">five</hi> guineas for the book, <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenJames">Gooden</ref> is not sure that I should think it worth <hi rend="ital">one</hi>; &#8211; more
               than one he would give himself, but not nearly what <del>xxx</del> is demanded. &#8211; If he purchases it I shall be able to get all the
               contents when I come to town, &#8211; it is never too late to correct &amp; amplify a work on which so much labour has been bestowed as this
                  history.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This manuscript was purchased by the publisher, Archibald Constable (1774&#8211;1827;
                     <title>DNB</title>), and Southey was able to make use of it for the second edition of the first volume of his <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1822).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He tells me also of two volumes of Alvaras<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Government decrees.</note> &amp;c
               with the title of Condi&#231;oens da Companhia de Pernambuco a Paraiba in the public library at Gottingen,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Gottingen State Library (founded 1734). It was one of the leading research libraries in Germany and as it was in
                  the State of Hanover, which shared a monarch with the United Kingdom, it might have been possible for Southey to borrow a book from
                  its collections.</note> which he has little doubt would be <hi rend="ital">lent</hi> me if I applied for it. If as I suppose they
               relate to Pombals Company,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebasti&#227;o Jos&#233; de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Marquess of Pombal
                  (1699&#8211;1782), effectively Prime Minister of Portugal 1750&#8211;1777. He established companies to monopolise Portuguese trade with Maranhao
                  and Para (1755) and Pernambuco and Paraiba (1756), <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp.
                  548&#8211;553.</note> this cannot be worth while, &#8211; for in that case they must be exclusively concerning commercial regulations.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On Friday last I finished my quarterly business, &#8211; two papers <del>xxx</del> insignificant in length &amp; of little
               value, except in as far as they may aid the object for which they were written, &#8211; the one to assist <del>the</del> in obtaining
               national encouragement for historical painting, &#8211; the other to resist the rascally exaction of the eleven copies for the public
               libraries, &amp; to express a sense of the injustice which refuses to authors a perpetual property in the work of their own hands.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Haydon&#8217;s <title>New Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities
                     they Offer for the Encouragement of Painting</title> (1818) was held over until <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23 (July 1820),
                  549&#8211;591. His article on the &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217; appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819),
                  196&#8211;219. All publishers had to submit eleven copies of every book to specified public and research libraries; and authors had
                  copyright in their works for 28 years after publication, or their lifetime, if longer.</note> I have yet another paper to finish,
               which however is not for this number, &amp; will soon be compleated, &#8211; upon the Catacombs of Paris.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris&#8217;,<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 359&#8211;398.</note> With this I
               take leave of the Review for two or three numbers, unless they press me about <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoxeWilliam">Coxes </ref>
          <del>xxx</del> Memoirs of Marlborough.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of William Coxe, <title>Memoirs of John
                     Duke of Marlborough, with his Original Correspondence; Collected from the Family Records at Blenheim, and Other Authentic
                     Sources. Illustrated with Portraits, Maps, and Military Plans</title> (1818-1819) appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23
                  (May 1820), 1&#8211;73.</note> And being thus clear of that impediment, &amp; left wholly to myself without any chance of <del>a
                  visitor</del> external interruption, I purpose not to take my hand from the Brazil till the word <hi rend="ital">finis</hi> shall be
               written. In two or three days I shall dispatch a portion of copy, which enters upon the Treaty of Limits &amp; the affair of the
                  Reductions.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapters 39, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III,
                  pp. 442&#8211;504, covering the Treaty of Madrid (1750), which altered the boundary between Spanish and Portuguese America, and the
                  subsequent War of the Seven Reductions (1756&#8211;1757), to remove seven Jesuit settlements transferred to Portuguese control.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> was with me last week, compleating the arrangements for his removal in
                  March.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s brother was moving from his farm at Warcop to Emerald Bank House, in the
                  Newlands valley near Keswick, on 25 March 1819.</note> He will <del>xxx</del> save about 40&#163; in rent &amp; taxes by the exchange,
               bettering every thing &#8211; except his land, which will yet be good enough. If the place suits him upon trial, I may very probably be able
               to purchase it with &#8211; the peninsular war, which I shall prosecute <hi rend="ital">totis viribus</hi>,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;With all my powers&#8217;.</note> immediately on my return from London in the spring.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) was much delayed. He did not purchase any property
                  with his brother.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> will be confined in February or March.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s son, Charles Cuthbert, was born on 24 February 1819.</note> She suffers much both in health &amp; spirits.
               &#8211; By that time I expect to finish both the Brazil &amp; Wesley, &amp; shall <del>start</del> {be} free from the press.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) and his <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise
                     and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820). </note> My journey will be one of business, &#8211; I shall have to work at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BunburySirHenryEdward">Sir H. Bunburys</ref> papers,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Bunbury, who was
                  Under-Secretary for War and the Colonies 1809&#8211;1816, had offered Southey sight of his papers concerning the Peninsular War.</note> &#8211;
               to collect from a correspondence in the hands of a <ref type="m" target="people.html#MoorEdwardMajor">Major Moor</ref>, (the Hindoo
               Pantheonist) in Suffolk,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Moor was the author of <title>The Hindu Pantheon</title>
                  (1810). He, like Bunbury, lived in Suffolk, and had offered Southey the use of papers connected to the Peninsular War &#8211; those of his
                  brother-in-law, Sir Augustus Simon Frazer (1776&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; to see what documents <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">Frere</ref> can supply me with, &amp; to get at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Walpoles correspondence
               in the foreign office.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810) was the British envoy to Portugal 1771&#8211;1800
                  and Southey wished to see his official correspondence, having been sent his private papers by John May. May hoped that Southey would
                  write a memoir of Walpole.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have resumed the long poem which I began four years ago &amp; having written the first book, <del>xxx</del> laid it
               aside, <hi rend="ital">more meo</hi>
          <note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;In my own manner&#8217;.</note> till a more convenient
                  season.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, a poem which remained unfinished and was published posthumously by
                  Longmans as a fragment in 1845; see <title>Oliver Newman: a New England Tale (Unfinished): with Other Poetical Remains</title>
                  (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;92. Only 1,000 copies were printed and sales were poor. </note> A second book is now added, &amp; I am in a
               fair way with the third, so that it will soon become <del>an object</del> of some consequence to proceed to its completion. The plan is
               pretty well matured, &amp; if it turn out as well as it promises &amp; I have good reason to expect, I may demand a large sum for it,
               with confidence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This has been the mildest season within the memory of man. the snow has only appeared once on the mountains, &amp; was
               presently dissolved. We gathered kidney beans on the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of Nov. &amp; should have had them till this time in
               abundance, had it not been for a gale of wind about a month ago which destroyed the blossoms. The annual poppies which were left to
               stand for seed, have pushed out diminutive leaves &amp; flowers from their dry stalks. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has lilacs in blossom, &amp; gardens which are better sheltered than ours have the appearance of Michaelmas rather than
               of December.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The boys will soon be coming home for the holydays &#8211; my love to them &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">their mother</ref>, &amp; to the Earl, &#8211; the Viscount, &#8211; the Dutchess &amp; my namesake the
                  Baron.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s nicknames for the Hills&#8217; children.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-12-06">6. Dec. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>