<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2942</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4213</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2942. Robert Southey to Humphrey Senhouse, 14
                  March 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2942" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2942.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Department of Rare
                  Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS;
                  3p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2942" type="letter">
        <head>2942. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>, <date when="1817-03-14">14
                  March 1817</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Humphrey Senhouse Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Netherhall/ Maryport<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Seal: black wax, design illegible<lb /> Watermark: B.E. &amp; S. BATH.1814<lb /> MS: Department of Rare
                  Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS;
                  3p.<lb /> Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-03-14">14. March. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Senhouse</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was about to have written to you, &amp; precisely to the purport of your letter. By the fifteenth of April I shall be
               ready to start<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">For the European tour that he and Southey were about to make in May&#8211;August
                  1817.</note> from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Warcop">Warcop</ref>; &#8211; fix the day according to your own convenience, let me
               know it, &amp; you shall find me &amp; my portmanteau, at the Wheat Sheaf, Warcop, kept by a certain Thomas Tinkler,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Tinkler (c. 1754&#8211;1824) of Brough; landlord of the Wheatsheaf Inn, Warcop.</note> &#8211; ready to step
               into the Mail.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The books which I have consulted seem to show that our better plan will be to go by way of Dijon, Lyons &amp; Mont
               Cenis to Turin, &#8211; from thence to Milan, &amp; back across the Simplon to Geneva. We shall thus see Piedmont &amp; Savoy as well as
               Switzerland, countries which may perhaps prove little inferior in beauty, &#8211; for tho we may miss the Lakes, we may find a more varied
               foliage, &amp; a richer cultivation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When I read in the Courier of the marauding expedition to Allonby,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Allonby is a
                  village on the Cumbrian coast. The <title>Courier</title>, 10 March 1817, had carried reports of events there on 4&#8211;5 March 1817.
                  Large crowds from Maryport had broken into a storehouse and carried off about twenty tons of flour, oatmeal and barley to prevent it
                  being shipped out of the country. </note> I could not helping wishing that these men of liberal opinions had visited some of the
               corn stacks at Tallantyre,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Tallantire Hall near Cockermouth, located about ten miles inland,
                  southeast of Allonby. William Browne (1780&#8211;1861) of Tallantire Hall was High Sheriff of Cumberland 1816&#8211;1817 and thus ultimately
                  responsible for law enforcement in the county. He was a supporter of the Whigs.</note> &#8211; where a practical lecture might perhaps
               produce a change of opinions. &#8211; I have a letter from town which says &#8220;Curwen again will be the ruin of any improvement in the Poor
               Laws. Such an ignorant &amp; long-tongued man to be chairman of a Committee, after having in two following years showed different
               degrees of palpable ignorance in the speech moving for such a Committee! Who will work in it under his name &amp; banner? Many Members
               are very eager, &amp; very well informed &#8211; but Curwen must ruin all.&#8221;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The quotation is from John
                  Rickman&#8217;s letter to Southey, 11 March 1817, Orlo Williams, <title>Lamb&#8217;s Friend the Census-Taker. Life and Letters of John
                     Rickman</title> (Boston and New York, 1912), p. 192. John Christian Curwen (1756&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), MP for Carlisle
                  1786&#8211;1790, 1791&#8211;1812, 1816&#8211;1820, MP for Cumberland 1820&#8211;1828, had moved for the appointment of a select committee to examine the
                  Poor Laws on 21 February 1817. It reported in July 1817 without producing any major reforms.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I shall leave this place for <ref type="m" target="places.html#Warcop">Warcop</ref> on the seventh of April, &#8211; by which
               time I shall have compleated a paper for the Quarterly upon the Reports of the Secret Committee, &#8211; the causes which have combined so
               many persons against the best &amp; mildest Government that the world has ever seen, &#8211; &amp; the consequences of that party spirit
               which is the peculiar disgrace, &#8211; &amp; one day or other will be the ruin of England. &#8211; Whether it be possible with so timid a ministry
               to save the country from a Yahoo insurrection, God only knows: &#8211; but <del>X</del> if I cannot succeed in persuading them that the
               boldest measures are the safest, I will at least endeavour to convince the sober part of the people of their danger.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January
                  1817), 511&#8211;552 (published 20 May 1817). The article reviewed, among other things, the <title>Report of the Secret Committee of the
                     House of Commons, Respecting Certain Meetings and Dangerous Combinations</title> (1817), which investigated recent revolutionary
                  outbreaks and reported on 19 February 1817. Jonathan Swift (1667&#8211;1745; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gulliver&#8217;s Travels</title>
                  (1726), Part 4 described a race of beings called the Yahoos, who were ignorant, coarse and incapable of reason. They closely
                  resembled human beings. Here Southey uses the term to refer to the mob. </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to Miss Wood<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Anne Wood (1782&#8211;1860), Senhouse&#8217;s cousin.</note>
               &amp; her sister. And give my love to Humphrey,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Humphrey Senhouse (1809&#8211;1834), Senhouse&#8217;s only
                  son.</note> &amp; tell him I will not fail to send him the next poem which I publish</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> who is just come up to her lessons, desires I will not
                  forget her love &#8220;to Miss Wood, &amp; Miss Fanny<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Anne Wood&#8217;s youngest sister, Frances
                     Wood (dates unknown).</note> &amp; all of them.&#8221;</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>