<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2876</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4147</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2876. Robert Southey to Josiah
                  Conder, 10 December 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2876" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2876.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Houghton Library, Harvard, fMS Eng 948. ALS; 4p.
                   .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2876" type="letter">
        <head>2876. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ConderJosiah">Josiah
                  Conder</ref>, <date when="1816-12-10">10 December 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Josiah Conder Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ St Paul&#8217;s Churchyard/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmarks: E/ 13 DE 13/ 1816; 13 DE 13/ 1816<lb /> Seal: [partial] black
                  wax, design illegible<lb /> MS: Houghton Library, Harvard, fMS Eng 948. ALS; 4p.
                  <lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-12-10">10 Dec. 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> For a long time I have delayed writing to you, in expectation that
               the Eclectics<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Copies of the <title>Eclectic
                     Review</title>, of which Conder was the editor.</note> would arrive, &#8211; but it
               so happens than an unusually long time has elapsed without my receiving any parcel
               from <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">
            <del>Wm Gifford</del>
          </ref>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, nor am I now likely to receive any for <del>time</del> some time,
               having sent him a reviewal of <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Kosters</ref> Travels, &amp; not meaning to do any thing more for his next
                  number.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henry Koster,
                     <title>Travels in Brazil</title> (1816) appeared in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 344&#8211;387.</note> In the last number you might
               recognize me upon Ali Bey, &amp; the Foreign Travellers, which latter was intended to
               be something very different, &amp; of more permanent value, &#8211; but the danger of
               insurrection or rebellion appeared to me to be drawing so near that I took that
               opportunity of speaking a word in season &amp; in place.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed &#8216;Ali Bey&#8217;, Domingo Badia y Leblich, (1766&#8211;1818),
                     <title>Travels of Ali Bey in Morocco, Tripoli, Cyprus, Egypt, Arabia, Syria,
                     and Turkey, Between the Years 1803 and 1807</title> (1816) in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 299&#8211;345. His review of &#8216;Works on England&#8217;, the
                  narratives of foreign travellers, which included a warning about the state of the
                  nation, appeared in the same issue, 537&#8211;574.</note> I hope the folly &amp; madness
               of these Watsons &amp; their crew<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference
                  to James Watson (c. 1766&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>) and his son James Watson (d.
                  1836), leaders of the group of revolutionaries who, on 2 December 1816, incited a
                  section of the public meeting at Spa Fields, London, to attack the Tower of London
                  and the Bank of England. </note> will not blind the eyes of the public to their
               real situation, &amp; make them overlook or despise the deep &amp; extensive
               disaffection which <del>in xxx</del> prevails. There is a dry rot in the mainbeams
               &amp; joists, &amp; if timely props be not applied the whole edifice will fall in
               ruins about our heads. The measure which I recommend, as the only effectual one, is
               that transportation be made the punishment for seditious libel. Any other is
               ridiculously inefficacious: &amp; unless some check be given to the licentiousness of
               the press, in a short time the question will be whether we shall have a
               mob-revolution or a dragoon government, &#8211; &amp; this question will be to be decided
               by arms.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is so much good in this country, in our public institutions
               &amp; private habits &amp; we possess such easy means of bettering the condition of
                  <del>mankind</del> {the people} at home &amp; extending the blessings of
               civilization &amp; Xtianity in distant parts of the globe, that I cannot think
               Providence will permit this light of the world to be extinguished And this is my best
               hope, for <del>xxxx xxxx speaking</del> there is little to be gathered from human
               prospects. On the one hand I see men without energy or decision at the helm,
               inactive, supine &amp; either ignorant of the danger or intimidated by it. The only
               man among them who has the courage for his station is Lord Castlereagh,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Stewart, Lord Castlereagh (1769&#8211;1822;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Foreign Secretary 1812&#8211;1822.</note> &#8211; &amp; this is his
               sole <del>merit</del> qualification, &#8211; all else is froth &amp; emptiness. On the
               other hand there is the Press battering the government in breach, &amp; a formidable
               alliance of Guilt &amp; Error, <del>xxxx xxxx</del> Poverty, Profligacy, Sophistry
               &amp; Enthusiasm.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is very likely that I may write at length upon the state of the
               country what I have thrown out at different times, &amp; under considerable
               restraint, has made some impression.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  intended to write a book on the &#8216;State of the Nation&#8217;, but this project was
                  abandoned.</note> And if I can but convey to others the same distinct perception
               which I have myself <del>xx</del> upon some momentous subjects, any labour would be
               well bestowed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Here we are out of the way of distress, or hear little of it. But
               this is not a poor country, because it is an agricultural one; &amp; agricultural
               countries suffer only from natural, not from political causes. It is true we must
               live upon bad bread &amp; bad potatoes till the next season, &amp; pay dearer for
               them, but this has been foreseen in time to prevent any serious consequences, &amp;
               the early sense of scarcity will prevent any thing like famine.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We talked of you on the Lord Mayors Day.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Saturday, 9 November 1816. This was the day on which the incoming
                  Lord Mayor of the City of London processed through the streets of London. On this
                  occasion the Lord Mayor was Matthew Wood (1768&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), MP for
                  the City of London 1817&#8211;1843, who had been re-elected for a second term. As part
                  of the procession the Lord Mayor was blessed by the Dean of London on the steps of
                  St Paul&#8217;s Cathedral; as Conder lived at 18 St Paul&#8217;s Churchyard he would have had
                  a good view of proceedings.</note> &#8211; The year which is now drawing to its close
               has produced more sensible &amp; lasting effects upon me than any former one. It has
               drawn a broad black line between the years which are gone &amp; those which may be
               before me.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s only son, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, had died on 17 April
                  1816.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am now taking up my Tale of Paraguay, to get it ready for spring
               publication, &#8211; a volume the size of the Pilgrimage,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo </title>(1816)
                  was published in a slim octavo edition of 232 pages.</note> with rather a larger
               proportion perhaps of notes, &#8211; &amp; the metre Spenser&#8217;s stanza.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was not
                  completed and published until 1825. It, too, was an octavo, of 217 pages,
                  including 63 pages of notes, and used the stanza form employed by Edmund Spenser
                  (1552&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>) in <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590&#8211;1596).
                  The 18 pages of &#8216;Preface&#8217; did not outweigh the 35 pages of &#8216;Notes&#8217; to <title>The
                     Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hughes would tell you that he saw me, &#8211; a long
               interval had elapsed since we had seen each other, not less I think than fifteen or
               sixteen years.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Hughes (1769&#8211;1833;
                     <title>DNB</title>), a Baptist minister, who in 1791&#8211;1796 worked as a teacher
                  and Minister at the Baptist Academy and Broadmead Baptist Church in Bristol.
                  During his time there he met Joseph Cottle and moved in literary circles. He took
                  up a post in Battersea, London in July 1796 and remained there until his death. He
                  was one of the Secretaries of the British and Foreign Bible Society (founded 1804)
                  and had visited Southey in the summer of 1816.</note> I was much interested with
               his colleague<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John Owen (1754&#8211;1824;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Anglican priest and Secretary of the British and Foreign
                  Bible Society. He had accompanied Hughes on his visit to Southey. Southey would
                  have found many aspects of Owen&#8217;s life fascinating &#8211; he had known John Wesley
                  (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>), of whom Southey was to publish a biography in
                  1820, and he had served as a chaplain in India 1783&#8211;1794 and with British forces
                  in the Peninsular War 1809&#8211;1812; he had also led British troops in prayer before
                  the Battle of Waterloo (18 June 1815).</note> both in his public delivery, &amp;
               in conversation. Campbell the traveller was also at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, but I was unluckily absent, &#8211;
               otherwise I should have been much gratified in seeing him &amp; his umbrella. I like
               his odd book, &amp; should willingly have conversed with him.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Campbell (1766&#8211;1840; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Travels in South Africa: Undertaken at the Request of the Missionary
                     Society </title>(1814). Campbell was an evangelist who was famed for walking
                  great distances and is pictured with his umbrella in the frontispiece of this
                  work.</note> Oh that we had a Colonial Board upon [MS torn] principles of
               colonization, &#8211; &amp; a missionary department <del>x</del> belonging to it.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">At this time colonial matters were divided
                  between a Board of Control with ultimate authority over India, the Secretary of
                  State for War and the Colonies and the Foreign Secretary. There was no &#8216;missionary
                  department&#8217; and missionaries had only been allowed to operate in India from
                  1813.</note> Might it not be effected with the disposable zeal which this age
               supplies. This &amp; the condition of women in England are two of the
                  <del>momen</del> important subjects which I shall enter upon, if I fulfill my
               present purpose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am anxious to hear how <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville</ref> is going on. Remember me to him
               &amp; to your brother<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">One of Conder&#8217;s three
                  brothers: Thomas (b. 1782), John (1783&#8211;1869) and Henry (b. 1797).</note> &#8211; &amp;
               remember <hi rend="ital">us</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Conder.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Joan Elizabeth Thomas (1786&#8211;1877), who wrote under the
                  name &#8216;Eliza Thomas&#8217;.</note> &#8211; I had nearly forgotten the very subject which made
               me resolve to write to you this day, &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BloomfieldRobert">Bloomfields</ref> subscription. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Tilbrooke</ref> has written to me about it.
               I cannot but think that the best plan in every respect is to publish a subscription
               edition of his works, &#8211; the pleasantest, the surest &amp; far the most productive
               plan. Tell him this, &#8211; tell me if it be adopted,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">It was not adopted and instead donations were solicited to help
                  Bloomfield, who suffered from failing eyesight and had been impoverished by the
                  bankruptcy of his publisher. </note> &#8211; &amp; if it be not (but I <hi rend="ital">strongly</hi> urge it) let me know where subscriptions may be paid. &amp; now God
               bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent1">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>