<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2691</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce3962</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2691. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 7 January 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2691" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2691.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2691" type="letter">
        <head>2691. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-01-07">7 January 1816</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster.<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: [illegible] <lb />Endorsement: 7 January 1816 <lb />MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25.
                  ALS; 4p. <lb />Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-01-07">7 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent3">&#8220;Here where the woods receding from the road,</l>
          <l rend="indent4">Have left on either hand an open space</l>
          <l rend="indent3">For fields &amp; gardens &amp; for mans abode, </l>
          <l rend="indent4">Stands Waterloo; a little lowly place</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Obscure till now when it hath risen to fame</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Usurping wrongfully the battles name.&#8221;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage
                        to Waterloo</title> (1816), Part One, Book 3, stanza 3.</note>
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p rend="indent1">Damnatus ero, vel fuero; damnatus eris, vel fueris,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;I&#8217;m damned, or shall have
                  been; you&#8217;re damned, or shall have been&#8217;.</note> &amp; as for any third person be he who he may, damnatus erit, vel fuerit<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;He&#8217;s damned, or shall have been&#8217;.</note> before I will alter that stanza, or call the field of
               battle in my verse by any other name than the Field of Fair Alliance.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"> In the published version
                  of <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816), Southey&#8217;s preference for &#8216;Belle Alliance&#8217; as the name of the battlefield
                  was altered. The last line of verse quoted here was changed to: &#8216;And given the victory its English name&#8217;.</note> The name of
               Waterloo was given it by the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Duke</ref> in the vilest spirit of meanness,
               that the Prussians might be deprived of their fair share of merit; an attempt was made to make me instrumental in this;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"> Through interpolations made by Croker into Southey&#8217;s article on the Battle of Waterloo (18 June 1815)
                  in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 13 (July 1815), 448&#8211;526; see Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 15 December 1815,
                     <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2682.</note> I will not diminish a tittle of the praise
               to which the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Duke</ref> is entitled, but by God I will call the battle as he ought to have called it, &amp; would have called it if he had a
               proper sense of justice, or a proper feeling of generosity. And you may as well attempt to move old <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> (which no person but the Butler<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> A mythological
                  hero of extraordinary powers, invented by Southey and Bedford as boys at Westminster school.</note> ever thought of doing, or could
               do) as to dissuade me from my purpose. Amen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The expression of walk the earth must not be altered.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> This phrase does not
                  appear in the published poem.</note> It is most decidedly preferable to any that can be substituted for it. As for the other
               alterations, <del>the</del> whether one word {stand} or the other be <del>xxxx</del> {<del>xxxx</del>} {inserted} is not worth the ink
               that would be used in making the substitution. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">To recur to my title, The battle will be always called the battle of Waterloo, <del>&amp; for</del> &amp; so it may be,
               in England: of Mount S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Jean in France, &amp; of {le} Belle Alliance in Germany.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> Mont St Jean is a ridge and hamlet near the battle, after which Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French
                  1804&#8211;1814, 1815) named the conflict; La Belle Alliance was the preference of the Prussian commander, Gebhard Leberecht von Blucher
                  (1742&#8211;1819).</note> My Poem will be called Southeys Pilgrimage, &#8211; this we are sure of, long titles are always thus shortened by
               common sense for common convenience, &amp; a title soon comes to signify nothing than the name of the thing designated: &#8211; for instance
               who affixes any meaning to As you like it, &#8211; or Much ado about nothing &#8211; or Twelfth Night, when he speaks of the plays so called? The
               hymn of victory I write as P. L. pro fiddleribus surleyoque <ref type="m" target="people.html#ParsonsWilliam">Sir Parsons</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey had composed three stanzas to fulfil his obligation as Poet Laureate to produce a &#8216;New
                  Year&#8217;s Ode&#8217;, which could be set to music and performed at Court &#8216;for the fiddling and surly&#8217; Sir William Parsons, Master of the
                  King&#8217;s Music. He hoped that these verses could be reused in the &#8216;Hymn of Victory&#8217; with which he intended to conclude <title>The
                     Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> &#8211; a hope that was not fulfilled.</note> The poem, which makes the book, is in my individual
               character. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">It is proceding well, this poem. I have now written 800 lines, &amp; if I hold <del>the</del> {my} purpose of adapting
               that Proem which you <del>saw</del> have seen, there will then be 60 more in readiness,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Southey had written, in March&#8211;June 1814, fifty stanzas celebrating the engagement of Princess Charlotte, only child of the Prince
                  Regent, to William, Hereditary Prince of Orange (1792&#8211;1849; King of the Netherlands 1840&#8211;1849). He had to abandon the poem when the
                  engagement was broken off, but he was able to reuse most of it, not in <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage</title> but in
                  his <title>Lay of the Laureate</title>. <title>Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816), which celebrated Charlotte&#8217;s marriage to Prince
                  Leopold of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld (1790&#8211;1865; King of the Belgians 1831&#8211;1865) on 2 May 1816.</note> &#8211; besides <del>the hym</del> as
               much of the hymn as {is} in your hands, &#8211; if that should be adopted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Perhaps it may be as well not to give a print of Ligny.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> An engraving of the
                  &#8216;Ruins of Ligny&#8217;, after a sketch by Nash, was published in <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (London, 1816), between
                  pp. 90&#8211;91.</note> I wish we had an interior view of Waterloo Church, &#8211; about which I have some stanzas, concerning the tablets
               there: but this there is no chance of finding.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (London, 1816), frontispiece [unpaginated], showed the exterior of &#8216;Waterloo
                  Church&#8217;, but there was no picture of the interior. The tablets in St Joseph, Waterloo were described in <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage
                     to Waterloo</title> (1816), Part One, Book 3, stanzas 6&#8211;7.</note> Do not however fail to beat up for sketches as you proposed.
               The sooner we get the drawings into the engravers<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> George Cooke (1781&#8211;1834), engraver.</note>
               hands the better. I am working almost exclusively at this poem, to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> great
               dismay: but done it must be without delay, &amp; I am at present in good humour with it, having read it yesterday evening consecutively
               &amp; aloud; I liked it myself, &amp; it fitted where it was tried on.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Lunus</ref> was born in Oct. 1806, he is now therefore in his tenth
               year.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Will you when I am out of your debt, or when you can without inconvenience make me farther in it, send us a stock of tea
               from Twinings<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Twinings tea room in The Strand, London (founded 1706).</note> in the
               following quantities</p>
        <p rend="indent3">24 pounds of black tea at 7/<hi rend="sup">s</hi>-</p>
        <p rend="indent3">2 D<hi rend="sup">o</hi> &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211; 10/<hi rend="sup">s</hi>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent3">9 &#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211;&#8211; green at 10/<hi rend="sup">s</hi> {If good at that price, otherwise not</p>
        <p rend="indent9">exceeding 12/<hi rend="sup">s</hi> &#8211;<hi rend="sup" />} </p>
        <p>The tea here is of higher price &amp; worse quality. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">And now I close my dispatches for the night, this being the third letter.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>