<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3073</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4344</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3073. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 31 January 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3073.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3073" type="letter">
        <head>3073. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1818-01-31">31 January 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re.</hi>/ Exchequer<lb /> Endorsement: 31
                     Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1818<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-01-31">31 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Better late than never. I have been looking for these books the two last carrier days,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A consignment of books Southey had bought in Milan in June 1817 had been located in the Customs House in London and
                  was on its way to Keswick by wagon.</note> &#8211; their delay however is not of that kind that maketh the heart sick.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Proverbs</title> 13: 12: &#8216;Hope deferred maketh the heart sick&#8217;.</note> You give me no tidings of
               the larger collection from Brussels. &#8211; I conclude therefore that they have not reached England (which is altogether unaccountable)
               &amp; must therefore cause enquiry to be made concerning them.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The books that Southey had bought
                  in Brussels on his continental tour in 1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> D&#8217;Ivernois<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Francois D&#8217;Ivernois (1757&#8211;1842), writer on economics and politics who
                  had been in exile in Britain 1792&#8211;1814.</note> was not in Geneva when I called at his house, &#8211; &amp; therefore conceiving the letter
               to be merely a line of introduction &#8211; I destroyed it. If it be necessary that I should explain this to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> tell me where to direct to him. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can your brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> tell me any thing of a scheme for
               establishing a colony somewhere in South America for which a certain Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Thomas Braum had obtained the sanction of
               Government in 1714 just before Q Anne died.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In the early eighteenth-century the British
                  government showed a persistent interest in acquiring trading bases in South America. They pressed hard for some suitable concessions
                  during the negotiations of the Treaty of Utrecht (1713), which was signed shortly before the death of Queen Anne (1665&#8211;1714; Queen
                  of Great Britain 1702&#8211;1714; <title>DNB</title>), and which brought Britain&#8217;s participation in the War of the Spanish Succession
                  (1701&#8211;1714) to a close. One of the many plans at this time to gain a base in South America was put forward by the merchant Thomas
                  Bowrey (d. 1713; <title>DNB</title>), who in 1711 suggested taking Valdivia in Chile and possibly also a port on the Atlantic coast.
                  This may be the source of the garbled report Southey had read in his Portuguese sources. The incident is mentioned in Southey&#8217;s
                     <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, p. 131.</note> Thus his name is spelt in the diplomatic
               correspondence of the Portugueze ministers at Utrecht,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s account of the Treaty of
                  Utrecht (1713), <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 132&#8211;143, draws on the correspondence of Luis
                  da Cunha (1662&#8211;1749), one of the two Portuguese representatives at the negotiations that led to the Treaty; &#8216;Cartas de Officios de
                  D. Luis da Cunha Embaixador Extr. a Plenopo. dos SS. S&#241;res Reis de Portugal D. Pedro II e D. Joaom V na Corte de Londres e na
                  Congresso de Utrecht&#8217;, no. 3832 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. His colleague, and the other Portuguese representative,
                  was Joao Gomes da Silva, 4th Conde de Tarouca (1671&#8211;1738). </note> who were much alarmed at the project, suspecting that the Isle of
                  S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Catharines<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Santa Catarina, an island just off the southern Brazilian
                  coast, (now the site of the city of Florianopolis).</note> was the point in view. It may be Brown or it may be Braham, &#8211; it would be
               some satisfaction only to rectify his name, &#8211; if it be upon the Admiralty books, &#8211; farther I suppose it would be hopeless to enquire,
                  <del>x</del> &#8211; or it may be <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> &#8211; which is the likeliest guess of
               all, &#8211; for Broom I think would probably have been rightly spelt. &#8211;It would delight you to see how I am getting on with the last volume
               of Brazil, which will be opus curiosissimum.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The most curious of books&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> has nearly finished his plates of the Caves, &#8211; &amp; very fine things
               they are; &#8211; wonderful specimens of ingenuity, &amp; I dare say a great deal better than if he had understood the process of aqua-tinta
               engraving better when he began, &#8211; for by blending this in some cases with the soft ground, &amp; heightening it with the graver in
               others he has produced all that could be desired, in a way that it would puzzle the mere mechanic to understand, &amp; with all the
               freedom &amp; originality of his genius, &#8211; which is of a very high order.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall&#8217;s collection
                  of engravings <title>Views of the Caves near Ingleton in Yorkshire</title> (London, 1818) combined several engraving techniques to
                  create effects of light and shade.</note> I know from him that his brother wishes much to be acquainted with you. &#8211; &amp; I quite
               long for him to see these plates, which he is very anxious about (for they are first attempts) &#8211; or at least that he should know how
               very good they are.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Westall (1765&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), William&#8217;s elder brother
                  and mentor, a popular artist whose drawings would be used to illustrate Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note>
               We shall now have justice done to this country. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> is about, as soon as
               the season will permit, to make some book-panoramas here in the manner of that from the Righi which I brought home.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall&#8217;s <title>Views of the Lake and of the Vale of Keswick</title> (1820), a book of coloured aquatints, was
                  indeed a great step forward in the reproduction of the Lake District landscape. Southey had brought home a copy of a panoramic view
                  from Mont Righi in Switzerland, possibly that produced by Johann-Jakob Scheurmann (1770&#8211;1844) in 1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When this money is payable,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s stipend as Poet Laureate.</note> I will
               beg you at your leisure to settle certain accounts due from me to Hyde,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Hyde (d. 1820) was
                  Southey&#8217;s London tailor.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Osiris</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>
          <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey owed Nash money for the purchase of
                  frames for the drawings Nash had made of the Southey family.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope the Pilgrimage will come in the box, &#8211; or with the books that are to be bound &amp; follow it, &amp; the Spanish
               MS. which you took to town for binding<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly the copy of <title>The Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to
                     Waterloo</title> (1816), no. 2693 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, described as &#8216;<hi rend="ital">LARGE PAPER, not
                     printed for sale: a Presentation Copy from G. C. Bedford, with his autograph</hi>&#8217;. It was accompanied by those of Southey&#8217;s
                  books bought in Milan 1817 that required binding and an unidentified Spanish manuscript.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are going on tolerably well here, &#8211; except <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Lovell</ref>, who has been much worse than usual this winter, &amp; is visibly much altered: &#8211; so that I look on with no pleasant
               anticipations. Nor <del>xx</del> are there any comfortable prospects for me in another near quarter. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> has now five children,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Hill Southey (b.
                  1811); Mary Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813&#8211;1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815&#8211;1864), Eleanor Thomasina Southey
                  (1816&#8211;1835). They were followed by Sarah Louise Southey (1818&#8211;1850); Nelson Castle Southey (1820&#8211;1834); Sophia Jane Southey
                  (1822&#8211;1859); and Thomas Castle Southey (1824&#8211;1896).</note> &#8211; &amp; is in a fair way of having as many more: &#8211; this is likely to
               weigh heavier &amp; heavier upon me every year while I live, &amp; when I am dead, or if my own resources should fail, &#8211; which they so
               easily may, depending upon health, eyesight, &#8211; &amp; success in the lottery of literature. &#8211; God knows what is to become of them. It is
               a little vexatious when I have overcome all my own difficulties to be <del>weighed down by</del> assailed by this corps de reserve.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Poor Hodge!<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Altered from &#8216;Hyde&#8217;. One of Bedford&#8217;s pets.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This Voluntary Contribution is indeed pityful. Even if it be meant for an example &#8211; it is good for nothing. There are
               fifty ways in which the same money could have done such good, &amp; purchased deserved commendation which would have ripened into
               popularity. <del>xxx</del> In this form, &#8211; it can only excite sarcasm, contempt, &amp; vexatious inquiry &#8211; if it end in vexation
                  alone.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The government had made provision in the Malt and Pension Duties Act (1817) for
                  holders of public office or pensions to donate part of their salary to public services, if they wished to do so, following the
                  example of the Prince Regent. In particular, government ministers gave up the increase in their salaries caused by the abolition of
                  income tax in 1816.</note> Well &#8211; well! These things are no concern of mine. I have more to do with John Wesley,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> &amp;
               the Zamucos &amp; the Moxos &amp; the Mbayas &amp; the Abipons {&amp; the Jesuits, &amp; the Miners}<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Subjects discussed in the third volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Lord Wellington</ref>,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">A reference
                  to Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bell</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, &amp; Bona Fidelia, &amp; Madame Bianchi &amp; Pulcheria.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                  cats.</note> What have I to do with Princes &amp; Politics? &#8211; The Acta Sanctorum<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had
                  bought this 53&#8211;volume compendium of hagiographies (1643&#8211;1794) in Brussels in 1817; he was eagerly awaiting its delivery to Keswick.
                  It became no. 207 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> are more to me than all the Acts of Parliament that will ever be
               made</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>