<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2947</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4218</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2947. Robert Southey to Robert
                  Banks Jenkinson, 2nd Earl of Liverpool, [written by
                  19 March 1817]</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2947.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Southey&#8217;s original MS is untraced;
                  the text is from a copy in an unidentified hand in Lord Liverpool&#8217;s papers,
                  British Library, Add MS 38367. TR; 4p .  Previously  published: C.D. Yonge, The
                     Life and Administration of Robert Banks Jenkinson, Second Earl of Liverpool,
                     K.G., 3 vols (London, 1838), II, pp. 298&#8211;299 [in part]. Dating
                  note: The letter survives only as a copy in an unidentified hand and the date
                  &#8216;March 19th 1817&#8217; may have been supplied by the transcriber. Southey&#8217;s original
                  letter might well have been written earlier, possibly prompted by Robert Owen&#8217;s
                  visit to Keswick in early February 1817; see also the similarities of phrasing in
                  Southey to Chauncy Hare Townshend, 16 February 1817, Letter 2921. </p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2947" type="letter">
        <head>2947. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Robert
                  Banks Jenkinson, 2nd Earl of Liverpool</ref>, <date when="1817-03-19">[written by
                  19 March 1817]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: Memorandum submitted
                  to Ld Liverpool by Robert Southey Esq<lb />MS: Southey&#8217;s original MS is untraced;
                  the text is from a copy in an unidentified hand in Lord Liverpool&#8217;s papers,
                  British Library, Add MS 38367. TR; 4p<lb /> Previously published: C.D. Yonge, <title>The
                     Life and Administration of Robert Banks Jenkinson, Second Earl of Liverpool,
                     K.G.</title>, 3 vols (London, 1838), II, pp. 298&#8211;299 [in part].<lb /> Dating
                  note: The letter survives only as a copy in an unidentified hand and the date
                  &#8216;March 19th 1817&#8217; may have been supplied by the transcriber. Southey&#8217;s original
                  letter might well have been written earlier, possibly prompted by Robert Owen&#8217;s
                  visit to Keswick in early February 1817; see also the similarities of phrasing in
                  Southey to Chauncy Hare Townshend, 16 February 1817, Letter 2921. </note>
        </head>
        <dateline>
          <date when="1817-03-19">March 19th, 1817</date>. </dateline>
        <p rend="indent1"> Feeling as I do upon the state of the country, I venture to offer for
               your private consideration some reflections which cannot be made publick, nor need I
               apologise for addressing you on the subject</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The danger must be looked fairly in the face. I am of course entirely
               ignorant of what farther measures may be had in view for checking the course of those
               opinions which the Press, by every imaginable means, is at this time disseminating
               throughout the remotest parts of England; even among these mountains. But I am
               certain that the great Body of the manufacturing populace are not merely discontented
               with the Government, but absolutely abhor it with a deadly hatred; &amp; that in the
               Metropolis this temper is so prevalent that if the fear of the Military were
               withdrawn, four &amp; twenty hours would not elapse before the tri-coloured flag
               would be planted upon Carlton House.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  London home of the Prince Regent. A tricoloured flag of red, white and green
                  horizontal stripes, inspired by the French revolutionary flag, had been much in
                  evidence at the Spa Fields meeting on 2 December 1816; a group of revolutionaries
                  had broken away from the main meeting and attempted to march on the Bank of
                  England and Tower of London.</note> You have passed Laws to prevent men from
               tampering with the soldiers;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Seduction of
                  Soldiers Act (1817).</note> but can such Laws be effectual? Or are they not
               altogether nugatory while such Manifestoes as those of <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoneWilliam">Hone</ref>, &amp; the <hi rend="ital">Examiner</hi>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The radical weekly paper,
                  the <title>Examiner</title>, edited by Leigh Hunt from 1808&#8211;1821.</note> &amp;<hi rend="sup">c.</hi> are daily &amp; weekly issued, fresh &amp; fresh, &amp; read
               aloud in every Ale House where the men are quartered, or where they meet together?
               Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Temple observes that when a people are generally
               discontented you may as well attempt to subdue pestilence by a military force, the
               military being as liable to one contagion as to the other.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir William Temple (1628&#8211;1699; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;An essay on
                  the original and nature of government&#8217;, <title>The Works of Sir William
                     Temple</title>, 4 vols (London, 1757), I, pp. 29&#8211;57 (p. 45): &#8216;the humour of the
                  people runs insensibly among the very soldiers, so as it seems much alike to keep
                  off by guards a general infection, or an universal sedition: for the distemper in
                  both kinds is contagious, and seizes upon the defenders themselves.&#8217;</note> I
               beseech you, consider what the consequences would be if these writers, instead of
               abusing the soldiers, were steadily to pursue the system of flattering them, &#8211; which
               they have more than once begun, but have wanted temper to pursue!<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">For instance, radicals particularly objected to
                  flogging in the Army: Cobbett had served two years in prison in 1810&#8211;1812 for
                  writing against the flogging of some militiamen at Ely.</note> You must curb the
               Press, or it will destroy the constitution of this country. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The question is, whether it be possible to keep off Revolution till
               the moral &amp; physical condition of the populace shall be so far improved that they
               will cease to desire one, &#8211; feeling that they have more to lose than to gain. &#8211; We
               must not be blind to the signs of these perilous times: The spirit of Jacobinism
               which influenced men in my sphere of life four &amp; twenty years ago (myself &amp;
               men like me among others) has disappeared from that Class &amp; sunk into the Rabble;
               &#8211; who would have torn me to pieces for holding those opinions then; &amp; would tear
               me to pieces for renouncing them now.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  had first made this point in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1809</title>,
                  2.1 (1811), 229.</note> &#8211; Concessions can only serve to hasten the catastrophe.
               Woe be to the garrison who hoist a white flag to an enemy that gives no quarter!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The main thing needful is to stop the seditious press. I did hope
               that the first measure upon the suspension of the Habeas Corpus Act<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Parliament voted to suspend habeas corpus on 28
                  February 1817, with effect from 4 March. This allowed imprisonment without trial;
                  the suspension was not lifted until 31 January 1818.</note> would have been to
               place the chief incendiary writers in safe custody, &#8211; a measure in which the sound
               part of the nation would bear you out. Doubtless it is far better to imprison them in
               consequence of the verdict of a jury; &#8211; but whilst prosecutions are going on against
               them, the mischief is going on also. If they are convicted, let their imprisonment be
               such as will prevent them from carrying on their Journals. But if Juries, either from
               fear or faction (as in Hooper&#8217;s case the other day) give their verdict in the very
               face of facts,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hooper (dates unknown),
                  one of the leaders of the attempted revolution following the Spa Fields meeting on
                  2 December 1816, had been charged with four others on 20 January 1817 with
                  stealing over &#163;200 of firearms during the insurrection on 2 December, in order to
                  arm the revolutionaries. He and three of his co-defendants were acquitted by the
                  jury. Hooper was then immediately re-arrested and charged with High Treason,
                  though his trial was not proceeded with once his co-defendant, James Watson
                  (1766&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>), was acquitted in June 1817.</note> I beseech you
               do not hesitate at using that vigour beyond the Law which the exigence requires,
               &amp; which your own personal safety requires as much as the vital Interests of the
               country. It is in vain to dissemble the nature of the contest. It is no struggle for
               place &amp; power. &#8220;<hi rend="ital">Turni de vit&#226; et sanguine certant</hi>.&#8221;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC),
                     <title>Aeneid</title>, Book 12, line 765; &#8216;for the life and blood of Turnus
                  they strive&#8217; i.e. the government is engaged in a war to the death.</note> Unless
               these men are silenced, &amp; unless the press is diligently watched &amp; curbed,
               the spirit which now exists will be kept alive it will spread in secret, after the
               present alarm has subsided. Upon the next Season of dearth or commercial
               Embarrassment, it will break out again, &#8211; and sooner or later we shall have all the
               horrors of a <hi rend="ital">Bellum Servile</hi>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A &#8216;servile war&#8217;; i.e. a war between the classes of society.</note>
               &#8211; No means can be effectual for checking the intolerable license of the Press, but
               that of making transportation the punishment for its abuse. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is of infinite importance to secure the attachment of the army; &#8211;
               not merely of the men whom you retain, but of those also whom in evil hour your
               poverty consents to disband. If the disbanded men should join the rioters there is
               always a possibility that their former comrades might be unwilling to act against
               them; &amp; and there are moments in which the defection of a single company may
               decide the fate of a kingdom. &#8211; So also with the Sailors. Is it too late to give them
               a medal for Algiers, &amp; even for Trafalgar?<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Two naval actions: the bombardment of Algiers by an Anglo-Dutch
                  fleet, 27 August 1816, and the British victory at Trafalgar, 21 October 1805.
                  Veterans of Trafalgar were presented with an unofficial medal, paid for by the
                  industrialist Matthew Boulton (1728&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>). There was no
                  general issue of medals for participation in the action at Algiers.</note> No man
               who wears one will ever be found in a mob against the Government which has thus
               distinguished him. But I would look to something more than this. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; There is a person now in town soliciting Ministers with his plans,
               &amp; regarded by them, no doubt, as a madman: - Owen of Lanark. <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Robert Owen (1771&#8211;1858; <title>DNB</title>), manager
                  and owner of the mills and model community at New Lanark in Scotland 1799&#8211;1825.
                  Owen embodied his ideas about settling the poor in agricultural communities in his
                     <title>Report to the Committee of the Association for the Relief of the
                     Manufacturing and Labouring Poor</title> (1817). Owen had discussed these
                  matters with Southey when he visited Keswick in August 1816 and early February
                  1817. </note>He is insane upon some points: But if you pare off the crazy parts of
               his scheme, I cannot but think that much which is useful &amp; practicable would
               remain; &amp; that he is, like my old friends <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>: Bell</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>, a great moral
               Steam-Engine, who might be put into action with wonderful effect. Is it not possible
               for Government to form an experimental establishment with some of its disbanded
               soldiers &amp; sailors, upon a tract of waste land, aiding them till they should be
               fairly settled, &amp; then giving them a life-hold interest in the ground upon an
               equitable rent? If the thing succeeded it might be extended: - Government would
               prevent men from becoming dangerous to itself, or burthensome to the community; - it
               would have them at its&#8217; call in time of need; - and a new &amp; unexceptionable
               source of Revenue would arise from such national lands. &#8211; I sincerely wish that Owen
               were encouraged to make his experiment in any parish which might be persuaded to try
               it.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>