<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2898</idno><idno type="nines">rce4169</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2898. Robert Southey to John
                  Murray, 14 January 1817</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2898.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>National Library of
                  Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 3p.  .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                     New Letters of Robert Southey, 2 vols (London and New York,
                  1965), II, pp. 147–149.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2898" type="letter"><head>2898. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John
                  Murray</ref>, <date when="1817-01-14">14 January 1817</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Watermark: R E &amp; S BATH
                  1814<lb/> Endorsement: 1817 Jan 14/ Southey Rob<lb/> MS: National Library of
                  Scotland, MS 42551. ALS; 3p. <lb/> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.),
                     <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York,
                  1965), II, pp. 147–149.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address><date when="1817-01-14">14 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1817</date></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> First I must return you <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southeys</ref> thanks
               for the almanack. The representation of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">this house</ref> is taken almost from the only point of view which fails to give
               any idea of its situation in a mountainous country.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The illustration of Greta Hall in the almanac sent by Murray has
                  not been traced.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref>, with
               a few trifling liberties such as he conceives a painter ought to take, has made one
               of the most beautiful drawings of it that I have ever seen. When I have more heart,
               as well as more leisure for the undertaking, I purpose going on with a
                  <del>desultory</del> poem in blank verse, as desultory in its subject as the Night
               Thoughts or the Task,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey began, but did
                  not finish, such a poem, entitled ‘Consolation’. Sections were published after his
                  death as ‘Fragmentary Thoughts Occasioned by his Son’s Death’, <title>Oliver
                     Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished): With Other Poetical Remains</title>
                  (London, 1845), pp. 93–95, and ‘Additional Fragment, Occasioned by the Death of
                  his Son’, <title>Poetical Works of Robert Southey. Complete in One Volume</title>
                  (London, 1850), p. 815. The models for this poem were two other works in blank
                  verse: Edward Young (1681–1765; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Night Thoughts</title>
                  (1742–1745) and William Cowper (1731–1800; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The
                     Task</title> (1785).</note> but in a more elevated strain than the latter,
               &amp; in a happier one than the former; – describing my own habits, views &amp;
               feelings, – what they have been, &amp; what they are. Whenever I bring this out
               (which if during my life will be the last of my poetical works) I will have it
               accompanied with views of the scenery incidentally described, &amp; among them one or
               two of this house – But this is looking far forwards &amp; leading <del>xx</del> me
               from my present business.</p><p rend="indent1"> The papers which you have sent me give me quite a new view of the
                  Spenceans<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">These papers were for Southey’s
                  article ‘Parliamentary Reform’ in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October
                  1816), 224–278 (published 11 February 1817). Murray had probably sent Southey,
                  Thomas Spence (1750–1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Constitution of Spensonia, a
                     Country in Fairy Land Situated between Utopia and Oceana</title> (1801) and
                     <title>The Important Trial of Thomas Spence</title> (1807), and Thomas Evans
                  (1766–1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Christian Policy, the Salvation of
                     Empire</title> (1816). The ‘Society of Spencean Philanthropists’ comprised a
                  number of small groups of radicals who met at various London public houses. Their
                  political ideas were modelled on the writings of Thomas Spence, the radical
                  journalist and campaigner for communal ownership of land. By this time they
                  contained a number of revolutionaries, who had attempted to lead part of the crowd
                  at the Spa Fields meeting on 2 December 1816 in storming the Bank of England and
                  the Tower of London.</note> so that I shall have something to alter in the
               subsequent proofs, – &amp; something to add at the end. Nothing can be farther from
               my intention than to write with party feeling. The outline of my projected book<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s planned book on the ‘State of the
                  Nation’, of which his <title>Quarterly Review</title> article was intended to be
                  the first part.</note> will show you this. The first part of the present article
               in the beginning – with certain alterations &amp; additions; – this chapter shows the
               necessity &amp; popularity of the war. then {2<hi rend="sup">dly</hi>} the causes of
               the distress. 3<hi rend="sup">dly</hi> the proposed remedies of Reform in Parliament
               &amp; Diminished Expenditure. 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. view of political parties in
               England with a sketch of the history of discontent in the country since the
               Reformation, – including also some mention of religious sects, as far they have a
               political bearing – 5. State of the Press &amp; necessity of checking its license: 6.
               Changes in society – growth of mendicity. agricultural poor. manufacturers. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Condition of women. 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Real Evils in
               Society which are remediable by Governments: <del>then I</del> among them I include
               the gross ignorance of the people, the ruinous expence &amp; heart-breaking delays of
               law – the state of our prisons, &amp; those <del>xx</del> modes of taxation which
               directly tend to produce <del>xxx</del> violations of the laws – &amp;c &amp;c. Some
               hints rather than plans for alleviating some of these evils I shall throw out, – such
               as Protestant nunneries, in which women may find {a} respectable &amp; comfortable
               retreat, without vows; asylums for every child who needs one; – &amp; whether it
               would <del>it</del> not be practicable &amp; advisable at this time for tracts of
               waste land to be at this time purchased by Government, &amp; the poor settled upon
               them in villages (money being advanced by Government for this purpose; to be borrowed
               upon the poor rates for such purpose) – these lands to be national property, &amp;
               when brought into cultivation to be leased like Church or College lands, &amp; thus
               contribute to the revenue. Perhaps I shall add this to the present article, but of
               course <del>in an</del> rather as a query as to the feasibility, than in any positive
               form of advice. This is certain that no relief is to be expected from employing the
               poor in manufactures; you only shift the burden, &amp; carry more goods to a market
               already overstocked; – but set them to <del>xx</del> agriculture, &amp; every man can
               at least provide for himself &amp; family, if he raises no surplus produce – Things
               cannot continue as they are. There is a <hi rend="ital">perilous</hi> spirit abroad,
               inflamed &amp; misdirected by journalists who are the worst of traitors; – whether we
               shall escape a more frightful revolution than the world has ever yet seen I will not
               venture to say, – &amp; perhaps in my secret heart I incline to apprehend the worst;
               – but it would not do to betray this apprehension, for that would contribute to bring
               the ruin on. At present the course to be pursued is plain. Individuals are doing all
               that can be done. I have procured some facts from Birmingham which I shall insert in
               the article.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Parliamentary Reform’,
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 274–275, on distress in
                  Birmingham and charitable efforts to relieve poverty in the city.</note>
               Government should force enterprize with public money, – but above all things it
               should stop these libels which aim at nothing less than a general overthrow, – their
               lives, – &amp; yours &amp; mine. Were I minister I would suspend the H Corpus
                  Act,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Habeas Corpus Act (1679)
                  effectively prevented detention without trial.</note> throw these fellows into
               prison – &amp; then I would call upon the great sinecurists to give up those
               emoluments which give occasion for just this exaggerated <del>xxx</del> disgust.</p><p rend="indent1"> You ask me why there was not more discussion in the review of <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Kosters</ref> book – chiefly, if not
               wholly, because it seemed to me one of those books which are best reviewed by
               abstracting it, with a running commentary.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had reviewed Koster’s <title>Travels in Brazil</title> (1816) in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 344–387. </note> In due
               time I will go thro the whole of the American states &amp; kingdoms for you; – Mexico
               will come first {on this subject Barrow (if he be the Reviewer of Humboldt) is very
               much mistaken, or very ill informed}<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John
                  Barrow (1764–1848; <title>DNB</title>), had, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>,
                  15 (July 1816), 440–468, reviewed Alexander von Humboldt (1769–1859),
                     <title>Researches Concerning the Institutions and Monuments of the Ancient
                     Inhabitants of America; with Descriptions and Views of Some of the Most
                     Striking Scenes in the Cordilleras</title> (1814). Southey might have taken
                  issue with a number of Barrow’s views, especially his prediction that the ongoing
                  revolution in Mexico would be successful (464).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> I inclose a letter of thanks to Mr R Wellesley.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Wellesley (1787–1831), son of Marquess
                  Wellesley, MP for a number of seats intermittently 1810–1826, Lord of the Treasury
                  1812 and Commissioner of Stamp Duties 1826–1831. He had worked in Spain 1808–1810
                  as his father’s assistant.</note> He has sent me some Debates of the Cortes, – I
               have the first 18 vol. &amp; then Ferdinands return cut off my supply.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Diario de las Discusiones y Actas de las Cortes,
                  1810–1813’, no. 3288 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. Southey had
                  eighteen volumes in a ‘Spanish binding’ and a nineteenth, unbound, volume –
                  presumably provided by Wellesley. Ferdinand VII (1784–1833; King of Spain 1808,
                  1813–1833) had abolished the Cortes and imprisoned its supporters in 1814, so
                  ending Southey’s supply of documents – particularly from Manuel de Abella.</note>
               What was more vexatious it deprived me of a complete set of Aragon Gazettes<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey owned twenty-four volumes of
                     <title>Gazetas</title> issued by the various juntas, no. 3472 in the sale
                  catalogue of his library.</note> which the Junta of that Kingdom had collected for
               me.</p><p rend="indent1"> Your Ledger is the best pole-star by which we can steer.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">That is, Murray’s sales records for the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> I address myself not to any party, –
               but to the good feelings of mankind. I aim at lessening human misery, &amp; bettering
               the condition of all the lower classes. Some persons may be offended, but I am
               perfectly sure that every reader <del>has</del> is honest himself will perceive that
               the writer is writing as he thinks</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs very truly</salute><signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p rend="indent1">The Correspondent<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                        <title>Correspondent</title> was a new, short-lived, journal devoted to
                     Anglo-French affairs and edited by John Stoddart (1773–1856;
                     <title>DNB</title>), who had been the editor of <title>The Times</title> until
                     dismissed at the end of 1816 for the intemperate Toryism of his articles.
                  </note> has far too much French politics, which it is impossible to render
                  interesting here. It wants relief, &amp; general matter. There is another fault
                  also; – the number is not large enough to allow room for finishing a subject, –
                  &amp; it is very injurious not to have every paper compleat as far as
                  possible.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>