<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3123</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4394</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3123. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 19 April 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3123" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3123.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p. .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3123" type="letter">
        <head>3123. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>,<date when="1818-04-19"> 19 April 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 22 AP 22/ 1818<lb /> Endorsements: 19 April 1818; p<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 19 April 1818/
                     rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 22<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The tincture<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wanted to numb Edith May&#8217;s toothache, the tincture contained the
                  herb pellitory, cloves, camphor and opium.</note> came safe, &amp; so did the razors, &#8211; &amp; I should have thanked you for both, if
               just at that time an influx of letters had not come in which put them out of mind &#8211; Verbeyst had the clearest instructions to direct
               the books <del>of</del> to Rothschilds,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had bought a consignment of books from
                  Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1849), a famous bookseller in Brussels, in 1817, but its arrival was greatly delayed. The banker
                  Nathan Mayer Rothschild (1777&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>) had been recruited to aid the books&#8217; passage to Britain.</note> &amp; to
               advise him when they were sent: &#8211; he could not misunderstand these orders, &#8211; yet it is possible that there may have been some neglect
               of this kind, because he lives at Brussels, &amp; the packages would be shipt from Ostend. If they could find their way to the
               custom-house without any demand being made for freight, &#8211; there I should suppose they would be, &#8211; but the first thing a Flemish Skipper
               would look for would of course be to have his bill paid. The best course is what you have taken. <ref type="m" target="people.html#VardonMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> V.</ref> will write to Brussels, &amp; from thence Col: Houlton<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant-Colonel John Houlton (1773&#8211;1839), a Somerset landowner, then living in Brussels to reduce his
                  expenditure, whilst he rebuilt Farleigh House and educated his thirteen children.</note> will write to the Commander at Ostend. &#8211;
               When you see the Acta (if that blessed day should ever come) you will not wonder how anxious I am to have them safe in my own
               possession, &#8211; for this book has been the great object of my ambition <del>xx</del> more than twenty years.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Acta Sanctorum</title> (1643&#8211;1794), a 53&#8211;volume compendium of hagiographies. It was no. 207 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> has acted very improperly, &amp; his conduct can only be explained by a
               supposition that he knew the author to be a man whose situation &amp; character entitled him to that kind of notice. His proper course
               should have been to have prosecuted Ridgeway, &#8211; for the act of circulating the letter would, I think, have been considered a
                  publication.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Canning had over-reacted to the circulation of an anonymous pamphlet that
                  attacked his speech in the House of Commons on 11 March 1818 on the Indemnity Act (1818). The pamphlet, <title>A Letter to the Right
                     Hon. George Canning</title>, was withdrawn the day after it was published, but circulated under blank covers by the radical
                  bookseller and printer James Ridgway (1745&#8211;1838). Canning&#8217;s response was to write, via Ridgway, on 10 April 1818, effectively
                  challenging the anonymous author to a duel. This letter became public on 12 April. Many thought the pamphlet to have been the work
                  of John Cam Hobhouse, Baron Broughton (1786&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), but no reply was received and a duel was avoided.</note> The
               Times is become a more mischievous paper than the M Chronicle, &#8211; the MC. is merely a thorough-paced opposition paper, &#8211; but the Editor
               of the Times would go the whole length of <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref>
          <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Times</title>, 14 April 1818, published almost all the suppressed pamphlet, <title>A Letter to the Right
                     Hon. George Canning</title> (1818), only leaving out the most offensive paragraph. The newspaper, under Thomas Barnes (1785&#8211;1841;
                     <title>DNB</title>), editor 1817&#8211;1841, was gradually moving away from support for the government, though it did not share the
                  radical agenda of figures like Cobbett. The <title>Morning Chronicle</title> (1769&#8211;1862) was a daily paper that supported the Whig
                  opposition.</note> &amp; Co. &amp; is the more dangerous, <del>but</del> because he wants to keep the respectable <del>xxx</del>part
               of his subscribers, whom an open avowal of his principles would disgust.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The 3 &#189; plan I have not troubled myself to understand, as it concerns not me.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">On
                  14 April 1818 the government issued a new annuity yielding 3&#189; percent to raise money to help pay for army and navy pensions; it did
                  not prove attractive to investors.</note> But (between ourselves) you will be glad to hear that I am likely to recover part of my
               loss with the Ballantynes; <del>who</del>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BallantyneJames"> the printer</ref> has sent me a bill payable in November next for the repurchase of
               my share in the Register, at the price it cost me &#8211; &#163; 209.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1810 Southey had been induced by
                  James and John Ballantyne and by their silent partner Walter Scott to take a 1/12th financial share in the publication to which they
                  invited him to contribute &#8211; the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. But he received none of the profits from the early
                  editions of the <title>Register</title>, was not paid for his final contribution, to the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                     1811</title> (1813), and feared his share in the <title>Register</title> had become worthless. The sum of &#163;209 repaid Southey&#8217;s
                  initial investment.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> All parties are to blame about the R Dukes. Ministers at first for asking too much: the H Commons afterwards for
               granting too little. I am afraid that some of the country Gentlemen voted with a view to the near Election not as it became them as
               Gentlemen, statesmen &amp; Englishmen.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">On 13 April the ministry presented to parliament the
                  Prince Regent&#8217;s request that it should make increased financial provision for several of his brothers, who were intending marriage.
                  This matter had become urgent with the death in 1817 of Princess Charlotte, the only legitimate heir in the succeeding generation.
                  Eventually, Adolphus Frederick, Duke of Cambridge (1774&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>) married Princess Augusta of Hesse-Cassel
                  (1797&#8211;1889; <title>DNB</title>) on 7 May 1818; Prince Edward, Duke of Kent (1767&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) married Victoria, Dowager
                  Princess of Leiningen (1786&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>) on 11 July 1818; and William Henry, Duke of Clarence (1765&#8211;1837; King of the
                  United Kingdom 1830&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>) married Princess Adelaide of Saxe-Meiningen (1792&#8211;1849; <title>DNB</title>) on the
                  same day. The government initially suggested that the Duke of Clarence&#8217;s annual income should increase from &#163;19,000 to &#163;40,000, as
                  he was second in line to succeed his brother, the Prince Regent; while the Dukes of Cambridge and Kent and Ernest Augustus, Duke of
                  Cumberland (1771&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>) &#8211; he had married in 1815 &#8211; should receive &#163;30,000. But in the face of concerted
                  opposition, the government retreated and offered to add only &#163;10,000 to the Duke of Clarence&#8217;s income and &#163;6,000 to that of his
                  brothers. On 15 April the House of Commons reduced the Duke of Clarence&#8217;s raise to &#163;6,000; on 16 April the Commons granted the Duke
                  of Cambridge a similar raise, but the Duke of Cumberland nothing. Finally, once his marriage was formally announced, the Duke of
                  Kent received an additional &#163;6,000 on 15 May. The Duke of Clarence initially declined the offer of another &#163;6,000 and this was seen
                  as a refusal to continue with his proposed marriage, but he relented and pressed ahead anyway.</note> Yet I think the D of Clarence
               has done wrong in breaking off the match; had it taken place &amp; had he gone on quietly &amp; prudently, upon the birth of a child,
               or any favourable opportunity, it would have been only to ask &amp; have. For this poverty of the Government, &amp; this petty fogging
               parsimony will neither of them last. The revenue must necessarily improve if peace continues, &#8211; &amp; the Saving Banks<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The first savings bank, which accepted and paid interest on small cash deposits, had been instituted by
                  Henry Duncan (1774&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>) in Ruthwell, Dumfriesshire in 1810 and the movement had spread rapidly.</note> in a
               very few years will add to the wealth of the state as well as of the country in a manner which perhaps few persons have contemplated.
               That class of persons who profit by this opportunity will rise a degree in society, they will acquire the wants &amp; feelings of the
               class which is now next above them, &amp; this will be felt in <del>xxx</del> indirect taxation. &#8211; I hardly expect that the Poor Law
               paper will do good in Parliament, &#8211; but it is possible that the Magistrates may act upon it, interpreting the existing laws in its
                  <del>favour</del> sense, &#8211; &amp; that the remedy is efficacious I have no doubt.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                  article (co-written with Rickman), &#8216;On the Poor Laws&#8217;, was published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308.
                  It urged that &#8216;no pauper shall have a right to insist on relief in any other form than as the magistrates, or parish-officers, shall
                  think his conduct and situation deserve&#8217; (307).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longimanus&#8217;s</ref> eldest daughter is engaged to the nephew &amp; partner of Strahan
               the printer,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Andrew Strahan (1749&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>) was MP for various constituencies
                  1796&#8211;1820 and ran a highly successful printing business. His nephew and co-heir was Andrew Spottiswoode (1787&#8211;1866), later himself
                  MP for Saltash 1826&#8211;1830, MP for Colchester 1830&#8211;1831. On 16 March 1819 he married Mary Longman (1801&#8211;1870), daughter of Thomas
                  Norton Longman.</note> &#8211; to whom therefore at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longimanus&#8217;s</ref> particular
                  <del>xxxx</del> request, the Life of Wesley is consigned. It will be a convenience to send the MS thro your hands, &#8211; &amp; if you
               like to see the chapters in a more readable state the <hi rend="ital">clean sheets</hi> may be sent me when I want them thro the same
               channel. It will be an exceedingly curious book, &#8211; of more value in displaying the human mind, &#8211; than all the metaphysical
               disquisitions that have ever been written.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise
                     and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820). It was indeed printed by Strahan and Spottiswoode&#8217;s firm.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Mag: Rot</ref>:</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1818-04-19"> 19 April. 1818. </date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>