<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3040</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4311</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3040. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn,
                  20 November 1817 </title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3040" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3040.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 78&#8211;80.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3040" type="letter">
        <head>3040. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>,<date when="1817-11-20">
                  20 November 1817 </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ CW Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Llangedwin/ near/
                  Oswestry<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 78&#8211;80.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Since <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> left me after his fraction of a visit I
               have with very little interruption kept close to my desk; having Heaven knows, heavy arrears of business upon my hands. I have composed
               a paper for the Quarterly upon Lope de Vega, with some translations, &amp; a good deal of curious matter, tho perhaps it may have cost
               me more time than it is worth.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed Lord Holland, <title>Some Account of the Lives
                     and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title> (1817) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (October
                  1817), 1&#8211;46.</note> This, however, goes to Mammon&#8217;s account. There is nothing else of mine in the number. I am thoroughly disgusted
               &#8211; as I daresay you are also, with the review of Lady Morgans book;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Morgan ( bap.
                  1783&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), <title>France</title> (1817) was savagely reviewed in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 17 (April
                  1817), 260&#8211;286, probably by John Wilson Croker and William Gifford.</note> I would rather have cut off my right hand than have
               written any thing so unmanly &amp; so disgraceful; &#8211; &amp; yet there are people who impute it to me, &#8211; perhaps as much from stupidity
               as malice. This is the evil of reviewing, &#8211; but the evil must be taken with the good in this, as in all things. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am preparing to write upon the Report of the Poor Committee, &amp; have prepared myself for it by good counsel.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of the Report of the House of Commons Select Committee to consider the Poor Laws (1817)
                  in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308, was actually written mostly by John Rickman.</note> The Report is
               exceedingly able, &#8211; so also is Davison&#8217;s pamphlett,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Davison (1774&#8211;1834;
                  <title>DNB</title>), clergyman and theologian. His <title>Considerations on the Poor Laws</title> (1817) was an influential tract
                  against the existing poor laws.</note> tho the scheme with which he concludes is very objectionable. He would abolish the poor rates
               at the end of ten years, &#8211; giving notice now, &amp; making the abolition all at once. There is I think great reason to apprehend that
               whatever is done for getting rid of this cancer will be made a handle by the <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbetts</ref>, Hunts,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), radical
                  politician.</note> &amp;c &#8211; &amp; <del>it will</del> perhaps it will not be done without some partial riots; &#8211; but to do it <hi rend="ital">at once</hi>, would ensure a general insurrection. A better plan is to limit the assessment &amp; lessen it gradually,
               every year a tenth less than the last for ten years; this would leave at the end of that time about one third of the present
               assessment; &#8211; &amp; then the fitness of a farther reduction might be considered. But I have a good deal to say upon this subject, &amp;
               I hope to good effect. What a triumph it will be if the country can be eased of this burthen, &#8211; which otherwise must crush it! </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We were, like everybody else, much shocked at the death of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WalesCharlottePrincess">the Princess</ref>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Princess Charlotte, the only child of the Prince Regent, died on 6
                  November 1817 after giving birth to a still-born son the previous day.</note> &amp; the more so because of the temper in which we
               were found by the intelligence. It so happened that our newspaper did not arrive that day. When I went down to tea, young <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> in the gaiety of her heart was expressing her impatience <del>xx xxxx</del> {to
               know the event} in the most playful &amp; fantastic way, &amp; indulging in this the more because of the quiet &amp; thoughtful mood in
               which I came from my books. While I was smiling at her extravagance, &amp; the rest of the family were laughing, <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> came in, &#8211; who was then lodging in the town. He asked if we had
               heard the news, &amp; began to relate it in a lower tone &amp; more deliberate manner than usual: we did not however apprehend the
               worst, &#8211; his voice faltered in a slight degree when he came to it, &#8211; &amp; poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> was instantly in tears. &#8211; There is a great deal of disgusting stuff in the Courier upon this occasion.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Many national newspapers, including the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, the <title>Morning
                     Post</title>, <title>The Times</title>, the <title>Courier</title> and the <title>Sun</title> contained detailed reports of
                  Princess Charlotte&#8217;s death and the medical care she received, going far beyond the material in official dispatches.</note> It will
               not surprize me if we should hear ere long of a divorce, &#8211; in which case obsolete laws will be more talked of than they are in the
               abominable case of <del>xx</del> Thorntons.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A rumoured divorce between the Prince Regent and the
                  Princess of Wales, Caroline of Brunswick (1768&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>). Such proceedings were very difficult and would require
                  either: an annulment of the marriage under the Church of England&#8217;s canon law; or the Prince to sue his wife&#8217;s alleged lover for
                  &#8216;criminal conversation&#8217;, followed by a trial in an ecclesiastical court and finally a private Act of Parliament if the Prince wished
                  to marry again. The latter proceeding was certainly as arcane as that concerning Abraham Thornton (d. c. 1860). On 8 August 1817 he
                  was found &#8216;not guilty&#8217; by a jury at Warwick Assizes of the rape and murder of Mary Ashford on 27 May 1817. Her brother, William
                  Ashford (d. 1867), launched a &#8216;criminal appeal&#8217; (a medieval form of private prosecution) against Thornton, which was heard in London
                  at the Court of King&#8217;s Bench on 17 November. Thornton pleaded &#8216;not guilty&#8217; again and challenged his accuser, William Ashford, to
                  trial by combat. A lengthy legal argument followed, but the Court found that the case against Thornton was not so overwhelming that
                  he could be denied the right to trial by combat. As Ashford declined to fight him, Thornton was finally acquitted on 20 April 1818.
                  The case led to the abolition in 1819 of both trial by combat and criminal appeals.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In thinking over this unlucky event with a view to writing any thing upon the subject, I have almost resolved upon
               writing something <del>in xxxxxx xxxxx</del> of which the notion is taken from Boethius.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Anicius
                  Manlius Severinus Boethius (c. 480&#8211;525), <title>De Consolatione Philosophiae</title>, a dialogue between the author and the
                  character of Lady Philosophy, consisting of both prose and verse. Southey&#8217;s idea eventually became <title>Sir Thomas More: or,
                     Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> Instead of his Philosophia I should introduce Sir
               Thomas More,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas More (1478&#8211;1535; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1529&#8211;1532 and
                  humanist scholar, executed for opposing the Church of England&#8217;s break with the Papacy.</note> &amp; make the occasion serve to
               introduce a view of the present circumstances of society with the impending changes, as compared with the time of the Reformation. If I
               do this I shall not do it hastily, &#8211; but I am disposed to like the plan, as one in which some points of weighty consideration might be
               brought forward with much propriety. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Both my poems<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825) and the unfinished
                  &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;. A fragment of the latter was published posthumously; see <title>Oliver Newman: a New England Tale (Unfinished):
                     with Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;92.</note> have stood still. Whenever I go on with them you shall have
               them as they proceed. In poetry I have long perceived that disuse induces disinclination; &amp; if I live to finish these, it is very
               little likely that I shall ever begin another. My chief business at present is the last volume of Brazil,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &#8211; when that is compleated I shall have a great work off my
               hands, &amp; lose a great pleasure. The insurrection in Pernambuco<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">An attempted revolution in
                  the north-eastern Brazilian province of Pernambuco in 1817.</note> has deprived me of one source of information. I was in
               communication with P. Joam Ribeiro, the Priest who killed himself. <note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Joam Ribeiro Pessoa de Melo
                  Montenegro (1766&#8211;1817), a priest who was a member of the provisional government set up by the revolutionaries in Pernambuco, 8
                  March&#8211;18 May 1817. He committed suicide in the town of Paulista after the defeat of the revolutionary forces and the fall of Recife,
                  the provincial capital.</note> He was one of the ablest men in Brazil, &amp; of an excellent heart, but the pestilence of the age
               had infected him. Living in the midst of gross idolatry &amp; knowing no other Christianity than the mummery in which he was a
               performer, he became an Atheist &amp; having once engaged in Revolution would have gone on thro all its excesses. There was an
               intention of setting fire to the city, &amp; butchering the royalists who were in confinement. Orders had been given to this effect &#8211;
               but <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> succeeded in making Joam Ribeiro feel what infamy this would bring upon
               him, &#8211; &amp; this was the argument by which he was moved from his purpose. <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref>
               has sent over details of the whole business. The two Brazilians with whom he was most intimate were Ribeiro &amp; the Vicar of
                  Hamaraca,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Pedro de Sousa Tenorio (1779&#8211;1817), Vicar of Vila Velha in Itamaraca.</note> who
               was shot at Bahia, having been secretary to the Revolutionary Government.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The man who has suffered <del>at the</del> for having been the head of this conspiracy at Lisbon<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Gomes Freire de Andrade (1757&#8211;1817), Portuguese general. He served in the Russian army in the
                  Russo-Turkish war of 1787&#8211;1792. After the French invasion in 1807 he was a leading figure in the Lusitanian Legion, which served as
                  part of the French Army 1808&#8211;1814. He was one of twelve people executed on 18 October 1817 for taking part in a conspiracy against
                  the Portuguese monarchy.</note> is the representative of that Gomes Freyre who figures toward the end of my last volume.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), II, pp. 616&#8211;631 describes the suppression
                  of the Beckman Revolt in Maranhao in 1685 by Gomes Freire de Andrade, Conde de Bobadela (1636&#8211;1702), Governor of Maranhao
                  1684&#8211;1687.</note> His grandfather (of the same name)<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Gomes Freire de Andrade, Conde de
                  Bobadela (1685&#8211;1763), Governor and Captain-General of Rio de Janeiro 1733&#8211;1763. He commanded the Portuguese and Spanish troops that
                  defeated the Guarani troops in the Guarani war (or War of the Seven Reductions) in 1754&#8211;1756. Southey strongly sympathised with the
                  Guarani, who refused to move from their lands when they were shifted from Spanish to Portuguese control by the Treaty of Madrid
                  (1750). This Gomes Freire was the nephew of Gomes Freire (1636&#8211;1702); but he was not the grandfather of Gomes Freire
                  (1757&#8211;1817).</note> was the chief instrument in the wicked affair of the Seven Reductions, &amp; I dare say the Jesuits will appeal
               to the disgrace &amp; destruction of the old &amp; honourable family as a striking proof that the sins of the fathers are visited upon
               the sons. When I was first at Lisbon<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had first visited Lisbon in 1795&#8211;1796.</note> I
               saw Gomes Freyre review his own regiment: he had served in the Russian army, &amp; had the reputation of being an excellent officer but
               of revolutionary principles. After the decided part which he took in favour of the French, he ought never to have been suffered to
               return to Portugal, &#8211; for if there was one traitor upon that occasion who deserved death more than another this was the man. &#8211; It
                  <del>xxxx xxxx</del> is a mournful thing to see this blot upon a good name.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have spoken to <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> about the sketch of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lowtherestate">Lowther</ref>, &#8211; &amp; he will send it thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> when you are both in town.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you my dear Wynn </salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS. </signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-11-20">20 Nov. 1817.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>