<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3112</idno><idno type="nines">rce4383</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3112. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 5 April [1818] </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3112.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Huntington Library, RS 339. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey,
                  6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 298–299 [in part]. Dating note: Year from
                  endorsement.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3112" type="letter"><head>3112. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>,<date when="1818-04-05"> 5 April [1818] </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS/ 5 April 1818 <lb/>
                  MS: Huntington Library, RS 339. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles
                  Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>,
                  6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV, pp. 298–299 [in part].<lb/> Dating note: Year from
                  endorsement.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear R.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I apprehended, – as you know, some such demurral on the part of the
                  feeble.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. that the manuscript of ‘On the
                  Poor Laws’, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259–308, would be
                  watered down before publication (on 9 June 1818).</note> They are I believe the
               only persons who when engaged in mortal combat, were {ever} afraid of provoking their
               enemys, or striking them too hard. As for <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Asmodeus</ref> he has, I verily believe, a
               disinterested love of mutilating whatever comes before him.</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> wrote me a brief note the
               other day wherein without any mention of this paper, he said that he never desired to
               see another article upon either politics or religion in the Review, – because they
               are “certain of offending a great mass of people!” – I replied to this at some length
               &amp; in a way which for a little while would impress the Magnus Homo.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Great Man’: Southey’s sarcastic nickname for Murray.
                  For Southey’s reply to John Murray, 3 April 1818, see Letter 3110.</note> But he
               of course quasi <del>Br</del> Cormorant, &amp; quasi Scotchman has no other object in
               view than the sale of his journal, &amp; because Mackintosh<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir James Mackintosh (1765–1832; <title>DNB</title>), the Whig
                  writer and lawyer, MP for Nairn 1813–1818, MP for Knaresborough 1818–1832.</note>
               &amp; a few other Ops<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Whig political
                  opposition.</note> praise a number which does them no harm, he fancies because
               they are pleased, that the rest of his readers must be pleased too. – This is the
               mere impression of the moment, – but that the Review will ever proceed in a bold,
               upright &amp; straight forward course is not to be expected.</p><p rend="indent1"> I suppose <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> will be consulted on this case,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. on the editing of ‘On the Poor Laws’.</note> – for he is on
               familiar terms with <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>.
               But that they will make a mess of it between them I dare say! –</p><p rend="indent1"> I have a chance letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref>. He says <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> has fallen one third in
                  sale,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Cobbett’s <title>Political
                     Register</title> (1802–1835), the best-selling weekly paper among labouring
                  class readers. Cobbett had fled to America in 1817 to avoid arrest, but continued
                  to edit his paper.</note> &amp; all such publications are declining, but the
               Anarchists are as active as ever &amp; new opportunities will occur for bringing
               their venom into life. “These wretches are effecting their purposes by libelling, –
               they are driving off the ground every man that can oppose them they are conquering by
               scandal, &amp; Ministers wish as much as others to keep out of the way. Unless this
               spirit of scandal is put down, unless the licentiousness of the Press be restrained,
               certainly it will effect a Revolution, – restrained I mean by new laws &amp; new
               regulations. It is altogether, as at present practised a <hi rend="ital">new
                  thing</hi>, not older than the French Revolution. I can perceive every one
               shrinking from it, – you, me, <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref>, Street.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas George
                  Street (dates unknown) was the editor and part-owner of the
                  <title>Courier</title>, the pro-government paper to which Coleridge contributed
                  and to which Southey subscribed.</note> Every one about the Press dreads <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbets</ref> scandal, &amp; thus
               when a man throws off all considerations of character, he has all others in his
               power. Even the Ministry too, &amp; their friends, I think, shrink from those who
               fight their battles, when covered with filth in the fray.”</p><p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#StuartDaniel">Stuart</ref> is wrong in two points.
               This sort of scandal is certainly as old as Junius &amp; Wilkes,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Junius, the pseudonym of the author of a series of
                  letters to the <title>Public Advertiser</title>, 1769–1772, defending liberty and
                  attacking government corruption; and John Wilkes (1727–1797; <title>DNB</title>),
                  radical journalist, politician and pornographer, whose exclusion from his seat in
                  parliament had led to a prolonged political crisis in 1768–1772. Southey attacked
                  Junius and Wilkes in ‘Rise and Progress of Popular Disaffection’, <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 16 (January 1817), 511–552 (530–531).</note> – perhaps much
               older. – And he mistakes my feeling upon the subject &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref>, who (<hi rend="ital">inter nos</hi>)<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">‘between ourselves’.</note> is at this very time preparing a heavy
               battery against <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">In the form of the
                  anonymous pamphlet, <title>Two Addresses to the Freeholders of Westmorland</title> (1818), first distributed c. 8 April
                  1818.</note> –</p><p rend="indent1"> It is time that Espriella was actually on his travels; – he may speak
               as plain as old Tom <del>Truth</del> Tell-truth.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The fictional traveller of <title>Letters from England: By Don
                     Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title> (1807). Southey did not publish a second
                  instalment of this work. ‘Tom Tell-Truth’ was the title of a ballad from the
                  1680s: ‘All that you will not believe me, disprove me if you can;/ You by my story
                  will perceive, I am an honest man’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> And now that this note may not be made up wholly of uncomfortable
               things, – you will be glad to hear that the Irish Scriptores are not laid aside as we
               apprehended they would be. The second volume (<ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> tells me) waits only for a sheet or
               two to be published, &amp; at the same time there will be a catalogue by O Connor of
               the Stowe MSS.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles O’Conor (1764–1828;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rerum Hibernicarum Scriptores Veteres</title>, 4
                  vols (1814–1826), no. 2112 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This was an
                  edition of some of the manuscripts in the library at Stowe. O’Conor was the
                  chaplain of Mary, Marchioness of Buckinghamshire (d. 1812). Her husband, George
                  Nugent-Temple-Grenville, 1st Marquess of Buckingham (1753–1813;
                  <title>DNB</title>), provided financial support for the project. O’Conor also
                  edited <title>Bibliotheca MS. Stowensis. A Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts in
                     the Stowe Library</title> (1818–1819).</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the Bankruptcy Report.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The Select Committee on the Bankrupt Laws reported in 1817 and
                  produced three further Reports in 1818.</note> A well-directed cross examination
               might have got out more roguery from <hi rend="ital">one</hi> of the Witnesses
                  <del>than ap</del> as his occasional practise, than appeared from his voluntary
               statement: – Pray send me the report about the Church<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">On 16 March 1818, Nicholas Vansittart (1766–1851;
                     <title>DNB</title>), Chancellor of the Exchequer 1812–1823, drew attention to
                  statistics collected on the deficiency of Church of England places of worship and
                  proposed £1,000,000 be spent on constructing new churches. This proposal was
                  embodied in the Church Building Act (1818).</note></p><closer><signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1818-04-05">5 April</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>