<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2934</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4205</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2934. Robert Southey to Horatio Gates Spafford, 5 March 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2934" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2934.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>LWS Collection, Morristown National Historical Park. ALS; 4p. (c).
                  .  Previously  published: Belles-Lettres Repository, and Monthly Magazine, 2 (1820), 454&#8211;455; Julian P. Lloyd, &#8216;Horatio
                  Gates Spafford: Inventor, Author, Promoter of Democracy&#8217;, Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society, 51
                  (October 1941), 335 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2934" type="letter">
        <head>2934. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SpaffordHoratioGates">Horatio Gates Spafford</ref>, <date when="1817-03-05">5 March 1817</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Horatio Gates Spafford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Albany/ United States
                  of America<lb /> Stamped: [partial] KESWICK<lb /> MS: LWS Collection, Morristown National Historical Park. ALS; 4p. (c).<lb />
                  Previously published: <title>Belles-Lettres Repository, and Monthly Magazine</title>, 2 (1820), 454&#8211;455; Julian P. Lloyd, &#8216;Horatio
                  Gates Spafford: Inventor, Author, Promoter of Democracy&#8217;, <title>Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society</title>, 51
                  (October 1941), 335 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName>
              <placeName>Cumberland,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-03-05">5 March. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your letter &amp; your Gazetteer<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Spafford&#8217;s <title>A Gazetteer of the State of
                     New-York</title> (1813), no. 2573 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> came yesterday to my hands in a parcel from
               my Publishers Mess<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>. I thank you sincerely for both; &#8211; the book I shall find useful, &amp;
               it would not be easy for me to express how much I have been affected as well as gratified by your letter. With that wide ocean between
               us, you &amp; I are in sympathy with each other. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In awakening my feelings you have also strongly excited my curiosity. There is an oak, or rather the shell of what was
               once a stately one, upon the estate of Monk-hall,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Just to the north of Keswick, a former pele
                  tower, defended by a moat, Monk&#8217;s Hall was in Southey&#8217;s day a farmhouse.</note> within my view, &#8211; about a quarter of a mile distant
               on the other side of the river Greta. Is this your family tree?<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Spafford&#8217;s letter to Southey
                  concerned the pseudonymous novel he had just published, <title>The Mother-in-Law, or Memoirs of Madam de Morville, by M. Ann
                     Burlingham</title> (1817). The novel was presented as the memoirs of a woman who was born in Keswick and died there on 17 October
                  1814, aged seventy-six; her memoirs being then edited and presented to the public by her daughter. The central character was buried
                  beside her father and husband, at the site of a willow tree, which her father had planted. Southey&#8217;s reply strengthens the idea that
                  Spafford&#8217;s novel was based on real events and people.</note> &#8211; When the estate belonged to Sir Michael Fleming,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Michael le Fleming, 4th Baronet (1748&#8211;1806). The le Flemings had their main residence at Rydal Hall,
                  Grasmere, and were thus neighbours of Wordsworth.</note> about twelve years ago, he sold the timber upon it to the person who rented
               the farm, an old man of the name of Slack,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given
                  here.</note> &amp; this old oak, which all artists have admired, was marked <del>by</del> for the axe, &amp; purchased with the
               rest. But tho Slack had paid for it he did {not} chuse to destroy the tree. He said to me, &#8220;It was there long before my time, &amp; I
               would not be <del>xx</del> the man who should cut it down.&#8221; &#8211; I have respected the old man ever since. He has left the farm, but the
               Oak is yet standing. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There <hi rend="ital">was</hi> within my view a yew tree, likewise of great age &amp; beauty. The town of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> consists chiefly of one long street: &amp; this yew stood behind some houses, which have
               been erected not above twenty years: other buildings have since been built behind them, &#8211; &amp; to make room for these the
                  <del>xx</del> yew to my great regret was destroyed. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is yet a third tree to which your history may peradventure relate. &#8211; It is a Weymouth {pine}<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A large pine tree, native to eastern North America.</note> upon the top of a little hill called
                  Cockshot,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Near Friar&#8217;s Crag on the shore of Derwentwater.</note> &#8211; the hill is covered with
               wood, &#8211; but this pine is manifestly half a century older than all the rest, &amp; stands a conspicuous object above them all. &#8211; If this
               should be your tree, &#8211; I have a deeper feeling connected with it even than yours. I had an <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">only son</ref>, of whom it has pleased God to bereave me; &#8211; he was my pupil &amp; I was his
               playfellow; <del>xxxx xx father</del> I loved him with all my heart &amp; with all my soul &amp; with all my strength, &#8211; for he was in
               intellect &amp; in disposition every thing I could desire, &amp; in acquirements I verily believe superior to every boy of his age. He
               was the constant companion of my walks; &amp; our last walk was to that Pine Tree. It was not a happy one, &#8211; for the symptoms of that
               disease which proved mortal had appeared sufficiently to disquiet me greatly. But he chose that point for his walk, &amp; enjoyd
                  <del>for</del> upon the summit something of his habitual cheerfulness. And I well remember that he touched the Tree, &amp; remarked
               that it must have been planted before the surrounding wood. It is full in view from the window of my study, &#8211; but I have never since
               ventured to the spot. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell me if either of these <del>are</del> {may be} the memorial to which you allude; &#8211; or direct me to it if you can,
               that if it be still standing, I may use my endeavours to prevent it from being ever cut down.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell me also how I may direct some of my recent publications to you. My publishers can probably inclose them in a
               package to New York, if you will inform me to whose care they may be addressed. I would fain keep up this intercourse with you, &#8211; &amp;
               if you can enable me to ascertain your Tree I will have a drawing made of it &amp; send you. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A ferocious attack was made upon me by some person at New York upon the false supposition that I had written in abuse
               of the Americans.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">James Kirke Paulding&#8217;s (1778&#8211;1860) <title>The United States and England: being
                     a Reply to the Criticism on Inchiquin&#8217;s Letters, contained in The Quarterly Review, for January, 1814</title> (1815) had accused
                  Southey of writing an article that was highly critical of the United States of America &#8211; the review of Charles Jared Ingersoll
                  (1782&#8211;1862), <title>Inchiquen, the Jesuit&#8217;s Letters</title> (1810) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 10 (January 1814), 494&#8211;530.
                  Paulding was mistaken &#8211; the review had been authored by John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>). Southey had defended himself in
                  the pages of the <title>Courier</title>; see Robert Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 16 June 1815, <title>The
                     Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2616. </note> Very different are my feelings toward America. My
               inheritance indeed &#8211; is there as well as in England. Wherever the English language prevails there I hope that <del>for those who</del>
               my bread shall be found after many days, &#8211; upon the waters of the Hudson as well as of the Thames, &#8211; &amp; of <hi rend="ital">our</hi>
               Derwentwater. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Gazetteer will be <hi rend="ital">useful</hi> to me; &#8211; for I have begun a poem of considerable length of which the
               scene lies in Connecticut, &amp; the time in Philips War.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, set in New England
                  during King Philip&#8217;s (Metacom&#8217;s) war 1675&#8211;1676, and left incomplete at Southey&#8217;s death. </note> Your state is near enough for the
               natural images of one country to be applicable to the other. My feelings towards America will be seen in the poem. </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> And now Sir God bless you.</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Your obliged friend</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>