<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3019</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4290</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3019. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 26 August 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3019" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3019.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3019" type="letter">
        <head>3019. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1817-08-26">26 August 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/
                  London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 30 AU 30/ 1817<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have no right to abuse you for not writing &#8220;by waggon&#8221; upon the direction of the box of books, because I myself was
               guilty of the same omission at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>: the waggon goes from the same inn as the
               coach, &amp; the people there according to the usual roguery in their vocation have sent both by the most expensive mode of conveyance
               &#8211; so I have paid 1&#163; <del>000</del> for the box from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> &amp; &#163;1&#8211;7- for that
               which you dispatched. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> On my return I found some letters of compliment, some of abuse, &amp; one which is entitled to a distinguished place
               among my curiosities. It is from a gentleman signing himself N. T. P. who describes himself as being in the middle class of society,
               &amp; wanting nothing &#8211; except a wife: Being in suit of one with the expectation of all other parties &amp; in good hope of winning the
               Lady a Rival had stept in with a copy of verses, &amp; by this means, the Lady &#8216;being passionately fond of the Muses&#8221; &#8211; outstript him
               in her affections. He therefore thinking that if he could produce better verses he should sans doubt win the prize, intreats that I
               will favour him with an acrostick upon the word Rebecca, &amp; if I should be unable to include in seven lines all the ideas which he
               has suggested &#8211; Rankin may be added &#8211; the place of her abode, (as he chuses to say, thinking thus stupidly to disguise her name).<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Rebecca Rankin (1795&#8211;1871), eldest daughter of William Rankin (c. 1769&#8211;1833), a prominent farmer
                  in Bocking, Essex. On 30 October 1817 she married Charles Stock (1781&#8211;1835), a &#8216;gentleman&#8217; who later became a coal merchant. The
                  identity of &#8216;N.T.P.&#8217; is a mystery.</note> This would look very like a hoax if there had not been a twenty shilling bill inclosed &#8216;to
               defray postage,&#8217; an ingenious &amp; delicate mode of paying me for the expected verses, which were to be addressed to him at Rochford
               Essex. I have written him word that his twenty shillings has been expended on giving four poor old women a flannel petticoat each, &#8211;
               &amp; instead of the acrostick have given him a rap over the knuckles in prose. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The General</ref> had neither seen the Flying Tree,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Peachy had completed a continental tour shortly before Southey. On his tour of 1817, Southey reached Alpnach in
                  Switzerland on 11 July 1817. There he saw the eight-miles long &#8216;Slide of Alpnach&#8217;, erected to convey logged spruce trees from the
                  mountain-side to the lake below. The trough, a feat of engineering supported on a timber frame over several ravines, was so angled
                  as to transport the tree trunks from forest to shore in no more than six minutes.</note> nor the Fair Elizabeth<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">On 7 July 1817 Southey had reached Unterseen in Switzerland. There he met Elisabetha Grossmann
                  (1795&#8211;1858), a shopkeeper&#8217;s wife who had gained some fame with visitors from rowing them on the local lake. She was known as &#8216;La
                  Belle Bateliere&#8217; or the &#8216;beautiful Elizabeth of Brientz&#8217;. Southey compared her to Mary Robinson (1778&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), the
                  &#8216;Maid of Buttermere&#8217;, another local beauty.</note> nor the Eleven Thousand Virgins.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  church of St Ursula in Cologne contains an enormous reliquary in which supposedly lie the bones of this fourth-century British saint
                  who, according to legend, was killed, with her eleven thousand virginal handmaids, on a pilgrimage to Cologne, by the Huns besieging
                  the city. The reliquary is extraordinary because, in addition to its size, it displays the bones arranged in patterns and so as to
                  form letters and words. Southey visited Cologne on the return leg of his tour of 1817.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you should be near Chancery Lane shortly, I wish you would call on <ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref>, &amp; purchase for me Clarendons Hist. of the Rebell &amp; the Cromwelliana,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon (1609&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in
                     England</title> (1816); James Caulfield (1764&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Cromwelliana; a Chronological Detail of Events in
                     Which Oliver Cromwell Was Engaged, From the Year 1642 to His Death in 1658</title> (1810), no. 708 in the sale catalogue of
                  Southey&#8217;s library.</note> which he will let me <del>half xx</del> have much below the selling price. Do you pay for them &#8211; which
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> will settle with you, &amp; let him transmit them thro
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, &#8211; together with <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> poems<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor&#8217;s <title>Idyllia Nova
                     Quinque Heroum atque Herodium</title> (1815).</note> if he can find this latter book. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am busy upon the mines of Brazil.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapter 32, <title>History of
                  Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 40&#8211;85.</note> The weather here has been very bad, &amp; is still as chearless
               as possible. All here tolerably well. I do not think that I have been handsomely used about the purchase of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">the house</ref>; &#8211; &amp; therefore place no great confidence in Fishers large language of his
               willingness to do every thing for making it comfortable &amp;c. &#8211; He seems a good natured &amp; very weak man; exceedingly ambitious of
               being noticed by me.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall had been sold in June 1817 and bought by Isaac Fisher (c.
                  1773&#8211;1819), a member of a Borrowdale farming family and a gold and silversmith in Cockspur Street, London.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let me hear how Ham<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s infant son Robert, born on 1 June
                  1817.</note> is going on I hope Richmond air agrees with him, &amp; that his new Nurse may agree with him. The travellers by this
               time, or before this time are at Paris. Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-08-26">26 Aug. 1817.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I have a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref>, in consequence of which I have
                  been obliged to &#8211; write to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">Bishop of London</ref>
            <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Since 1633 the Bishop of London had been responsible for appointing overseas chaplains in areas where there were
                     no bishops.</note> about appointing a chaplain for Pernambuco. The <del>xx</del> resolution of the English was sent to me,
                  instead of being transcribed officially. However I have taken care to excuse myself from any <del>xxxt</del> suspicion of having
                  willingly obtruded myself.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>