<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2819</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4090</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2819. Robert Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 2 July 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2819" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2819.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 30&#8211;32.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2819" type="letter">
        <head>2819. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1816-07-02">2 July 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Acton/ near/
                  Wrexham<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4812D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood
                  Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 30&#8211;32.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1816-07-02">Tuesday 2 July. 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do not imagine that any circumstances would ever render me indifferent to any thing which concerned your
                  happiness.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s only son, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, had died on 17 April 1816. Wynn&#8217;s first son to survive infancy, Henry Watkin Williams Wynn (1816&#8211;1832), was born
                  on 29 June 1816.</note> My state of mind as it regards my own loss is what it should be, &amp; admits of no repining thought or
               feeling: least of all occasions would any such feeling occur upon the present, &#8211; an event of which I have so truly wished to hear.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope to see you here. If I leave home this year it must be for a longer journey than to Wales. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> I think must lose <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">his
                  mother</ref> ere long, &#8211; she is not in immediate danger, but she may be so at any moment, &#8211; that she should recover is nearly
               impossible, &amp; any day <del>may</del> the disorder may assume a fatal character. Whenever this event happens, if it be possible for
               me to get from home I should wish to go with <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> for five or six
               weeks to the continent, &#8211; the best thing for him, &#8211; &amp; which would be wholesome for me also. During my last trip I kept a minute
                  journal,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Finally published as <title>Journal of a Tour in the Netherlands in the Autumn of
                     1815</title> (1902).</note> &amp; were I to go thro the rest of the Netherlands the knowledge which I have acquired from books,
               &amp; which I have the means of obtaining in that country, would enable me to make a volume that should do me no discredit; &amp; would
               pay the expences of my journey.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> As to the mention of the Catholic Question, the character of the poem rendered it indispensible.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816). It celebrated the marriage of
                  Princess Charlotte, only child of the Prince Regent, to Prince Leopold of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld (1790&#8211;1865; King of the Belgians
                  1831&#8211;1865) on 2 May 1816. <title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816), &#8216;The Dream&#8217;, stanzas 40&#8211;57, contained a
                  lengthy lecture to the royal couple from the &#8216;Angel of the English Church&#8217; on the need to uphold the privileges of the Church of
                  England, especially against the &#8216;inveterate malice&#8217; of the Catholic Church (the &#8216;Harlot old&#8217;; stanza 52, line 2).</note> The
               Sovereign of this country has no more imperative duty than that of preserving the institutions of the country. That the Roman
               Catholicks will ever succeed in building up their own Church here I do not believe, &#8211; but they may go a great way in assisting to pull
               our church down, &#8211; &amp; a church <del>xxxx</del> which is undermined, which is battered in breach, &#8211; &amp; which has the dry rot to
               boot, is in a bad way for durability. That you will carry the question <del>for</del> I take for granted, &#8211; from the total want of
               activity in your opponents.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn favoured the removal of civil disabilities from Roman Catholics
                  and the attempt to do so was a staple opposition measure; but the Catholic Relief Bill failed again in 1816.</note> You would not
               carry it if most of the men who sit upon the wool sacks were not as soft as the wool which they sit on.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Lord Chancellor, who presided over the House of Lords, as well as being a senior judge and a cabinet minister,
                  sat on a woolsack while acting as Speaker of the House of Lords. The occupant of this office in 1816 was John Scott, 1st Earl of
                  Eldon (1751&#8211;1838; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1801&#8211;1806, 1807&#8211;1827, a notorious reactionary and opponent of Catholic
                  Emancipation, so Southey may be using &#8216;the men who sit upon the wool sacks&#8217; as a general term for the House of Lords.</note> The
               next demand which the Catholicks make is for a Catholick Establishment in Ireland, &#8211; &amp; upon this quarrel (into which every Paddy
               Rampant will enter as into a crusade) you will have a civil war; &#8211; &amp; if it {be} delayed till the Bourbons feel safe upon their
               throne, you will find far more danger from a Bourbon <del>xxx</del> fomenting a Catholick Rebellion, &#8211; than ever you did from a
               Directory instigating a republican one.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The five-man Directory which governed France in
                  1795&#8211;1799 had supported the Irish rising of 1798.</note> &#8211; The question will not however be easily carried, &#8211; this business in the
               South of France has opened the eyes of the Dissenters, &amp; you may probably calculate upon some act of folly in the Irish.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The conflicts between supporters and opponents of the French Revolution in 1815&#8211;1816 included clashes
                  between Protestants and Catholics in the South of France, where there was a significant Calvinist minority. This produced many
                  protests from English Nonconformists, including Southey&#8217;s friend John Prior Estlin in his <title>On Persecution: A Discourse. To
                     which are added Extracts from the Report of the Persecution of the French Protestants, by C. Perrot</title> (1816).</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> is so connected with <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> that the Quarterly will probably be enlisted on that side, &#8211; in that case I shall most likely publish a pamphlett
               upon the subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tho I cannot come to you at present (my fellow traveller <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>, who
               made the drawings for me<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Nash produced seven of the eight drawings for <title>The Poet&#8217;s
                     Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> is just arrived) &#8211; at some future time I hope to go over Madocs ground,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn lived at Llangedwin in North Wales; and much of <title>Madoc</title> (1805), Part One was set in
                  this part of the country. Southey did not fulfil his intention.</note> that I may improve the poem by interweaving local
               descriptions. My race as a poet is nearly run &#8211; if I finish what I have begun, it is <del>likely xx</del> little likely that I shall
               ever begin any thing more. Solve senescentem.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65&#8211;8 BC),
                     <title>Epistles</title>, Book 1, Epistle 1, lines 8&#8211;9: &#8216;Put your aged, broken horse out to pasture&#8217;.</note> The hours which I
               might be able to spare for such pursuits in declining life would be better employed in correcting my former poems than in attempting
               any thing more.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have received M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rochejaquelein for the next number,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Amable Guillaume Prosper Brugiere, Baron de Barante (1782&#8211;1866), <title>M&#233;moires de Madame la Marquise de la Roche Jacquelein,
                  &#233;crits par elle-m&#234;me</title> (1815), reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 1&#8211;69.</note> &amp;
               written a paper upon bettering the condition of the Poor.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article on &#8216;On the Poor&#8217;
                  was published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187&#8211;235.</note> I am about to take Pinckards shallow book for
               a text, &amp; write upon the West Indies.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">George Pinckard (1768&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>),
                     <title>Notes on the West Indies</title> (1806). A second edition was published in 1816. Southey possessed both editions, nos
                  2243&#8211;2244 in the sale catalogue of his library. He did not review this book as Murray refused to accept a pro-abolitionist article
                  for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> &#8211; My mind is reconciled to remaining here, &#8211; &amp; having worn out the first
               inclination of flying from the spot, in all likelihood I shall never remove from it. I am perfectly at ease respecting the future
               circumstances of my family, &#8211;&#8211;&#8211; were I to be removed immediately there would be a provision for them, &amp; if I live some few years it
               will be in my power to save money. All things considered I have been singularly fortunate; &#8211; nor <del>can</del> shall I ever be
               unmindful how much this has been owing to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear Wynn. present my congratulations to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnMary">your wife</ref>,
               &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Most affectionately yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>