<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3148</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4419</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3148. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 7 June 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3148.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS
                  48123D. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                     Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London,
                  1856), III, pp. 90&#8211;92.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3148" type="letter">
        <head>3148. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1818-06-07">7 June 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> M.P./ Whitehall/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmark: FREE/ 10 JU 10/ 1818<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS
                  48123D. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.),
                     <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London,
                  1856), III, pp. 90&#8211;92.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-06-07"> 7 June. 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you for D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> O Connors letter, &amp; am
               very glad he can derive any pleasure from the expression of the high value which I
               set upon his labours, &#8211; such labours having very little to remunerate them except the
               gratification <del>by</del> which the employment itself affords.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The work Southey admired was Charles O&#8217;Conor
                  (1764&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rerum Hibernicarum Scriptores
                     Veteres</title>, 4 vols (1814&#8211;1826), no. 2112 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library. This was an edition of some of the manuscripts in the library at Stowe.
                  O&#8217;Conor was the chaplain of Mary, Marchioness of Buckinghamshire (d. 1812). Her
                  husband, George Nugent-Temple-Grenville, 1st Marquess of Buckingham (1753&#8211;1813;
                     <title>DNB</title>), provided financial support for the project.</note> Thank
               you also for the Reports of the Copy-right Committee. The part of this business which
               most concerns me is the term of years, which the booksellers seem <del>xxx</del>
               willing to give up. Now in my case a prolongation of the term is of much more
               consequence than the eleven copies, &#8211; for my books make their way slowly,
                  <del>they</del> have a steady sale, &amp; there will be a greater demand for them
               in the first three or four years after my death than there ever has been, or will be,
                  <del>during</del> in the same length of time <del>which I x</del> during my life.
               But <del>xx</del> the greater number of them will then have become common property.
               And the only means I can <del>see of</del> perceive of securing any advantage from
               them to my children, is, by never publishing a single <del>xxxx</del> improvement in
               any of them as long as I live, but reserving all corrections <del>&amp;</del> alterations &amp; additions for a posthumous edition.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was asking Wynn for the Report of the House of Commons
                  Select Committee on the Copyright Acts (1818). He wrote on the &#8216;Inquiry into the
                  Copyright Act&#8217;, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 196&#8211;219.
                  Southey disliked the law that required publishers to deliver 11 copies of all
                  works to &#8216;copyright&#8217; libraries, describing it as &#8216;downright robbery&#8217;; see Southey
                  to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, [c. 13 April 1813], <title>The Collected Letters
                     of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2246. But he was even more
                  concerned about the position under the Copyright Act of 1814 that an author (or
                  his heirs) only retained rights in his work for 28 years after publication, or his
                  life if longer. Alterations to published works made them into new editions subject
                  to copyright, so if these were reserved until after Southey&#8217;s death this would
                  prolong his family&#8217;s rights in his work.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I read <ref type="m" target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lambes</ref> death in
               the newspaper,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lamb had died on 13 May
                  1818.</note> &amp; thought more of him, poor fellow, in consequence, than I had
               done for the last four &amp; twenty years. &#8211; Do you remember Bean<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Bean (c. 1774&#8211;1813). The eldest son of an
                  apothecary at Camberwell Green; he was educated at Westminster School with Southey
                  and became an Army surgeon in various regiments in the West Indies and then in
                  India. When his ship foundered on the way from Java to Bombay he was murdered by
                  some of the crew.</note> who was in the remove with me? he had a good strong head
               &amp; an excellent heart. Two or three years ago I called at his brothers<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Edward Bean (dates unknown), who
                  continued to run the family apothecary business in Camberwell.</note> to enquire
               for him, &amp; learnt that he was soon expected home from India, to settle in England
               upon the money which he had saved as an Army Surgeon, &amp; the half pay, to which
               from length of service he was entitled. &#8211; Just about that time he was murdered by
               some Malay boatmen for the regimental money which he was carrying to one of the E
               Indian islands. Tis a melancholy thing when we have got more than half way over
               Mirzas bridge<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Bridge of Human Life, as
                  described in Joseph Addison (1672&#8211;1719; <title>DNB</title>) &#8216;The Vision of Mirza&#8217;,
                  first published in <title>The Spectator</title>, 159 (1 September 1711).</note> to
               look about us, &amp; see how many of those who set out with us on the passage have
               fallen short by the way. I should have had real pleasure in meeting again with Bean,
               &#8211; all that was good in him was of the permanent kind, he had travelled widely, &amp;
               would have come home with an extensive knowledge of men &amp; things. Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#LambThomasDavis">Lambe</ref> on the contrary <del>xxx xx
                  xxxxx</del>
          <del>for want of</del> had become a mere idle <del>man</del> {heir} of fortune, &amp;
               not having <del>ha</del> {his} estates to manage while <ref type="m" target="people.html#LambThomasPhillipps">his father</ref> lived had not even
               that occupation to keep him from frivolities. He was an old man at thirty, &amp; that
               too being of a family in which it is degeneracy to die at an age short of
               fourscore.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Scarcely a week passes in which I do not dream of Westminster, so
               strong a hold have those years upon the mind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You franked me a letter some time ago from <ref type="m" target="people.html#CraufurdCharlesGeneral">General Craufurd</ref> which has led to a correspondence with him. He
               has sent me some observations upon the Spanish war, &#8211; &amp; among my Inscriptions
                  <del>I</del> there was an epitaph for his brother which I was glad to communicate
               to him.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Major-General Robert Craufurd
                  (1764&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), commander of the Light Division in the British
                  army in the Peninsular War. Craufurd was mortally wounded leading his troops into
                  a breach in the city walls at the siege of Ciudad Rodrigo in January 1812.
                  Southey&#8217;s inscription &#8216;For the Walls of Ciudad Rodrigo&#8217; praises Craufurd; it was
                  not published until Southey&#8217;s <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London,
                  1837&#8211;1838), III, pp. 150&#8211;151. </note> I have written no poetry for many months,
               nor shall I have leisure for any this year, unless a much stronger inclination should
               arise for it, that I ever <del>xxxx</del> expect to feel. Before I set out for London
               in November I must bring forth the last volume of Brazil, &amp; the life of
                  Wesley.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was preparing the final
                  volume of his <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819) and his
                     <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>
                  (1820).</note> Of the former about a third is printed, of Wesley the sixth sheet
               (in octavo) is lying on my table.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I may tell you that the office of Librarian to the Advocates
                  Library<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Advocates Library, founded
                  in 1689, is the library of the Faculty of Advocates (the Scottish equivalent of
                  barristers) in Edinburgh and was at this time a copyright library. Alexander
                  Manners, the incumbent, had tendered his resignation as Librarian on 10 April
                  1818. His successor, David Irving (1778&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), was not
                  appointed until 1820.</note> at Edinburgh was offered me the other day, &#8211; 400&#163; a
               year, with the prospect of an increase, &amp; the labour of forming a catalogue. &#8211;
               Few persons would dislike such labour less, &#8211; but I am better employed. I do not love
               great cities. I will not remove farther from my friends (being already too far from
               them) &#8211; &amp; having, God be thanked, <del>nor wants xxxx</del> no <del>anxieties as
                  far</del> pecuniary anxieties, I am contented where I am &amp; as I am, &#8211; wanting
               nothing, &amp; wishing nothing. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I hope you are all ere this well thro the hooping cough, &#8211; this &amp;
               the measles are among the things to which I look &amp; fear.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear Wynn</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p> Let me give you a specimen of the electioneering temper in
                  Westmoreland. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> daughter<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Dorothy &#8216;Dora&#8217; Wordsworth
                     (1804&#8211;1847).</note> (about 13 years old) was walking in Kendal with a yellow
                  ribband, &#8211; one woman struck her a smart blow across the lips, &amp; another pushed
                  her out of the street into a shop, saying at the same time <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref> for never, A knife in his heart, &amp; a fork in his
                     liver.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">At the general election in
                     June 1818 the Lowther family&#8217;s dominance of the Westmorland constituency was
                     contested for the first time since 1774, by Henry Brougham. Canvassing and
                     campaigning were marked by a great deal of disorder, especially in Kendal. The
                     Lowther colours were yellow, while Brougham&#8217;s colours were blue.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>