<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3225</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4496</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3225. Robert Southey to John May,
                  28 December 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3225" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3225.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University
                  of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Ramos (ed.),
                     The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838 (Austin,
                  Texas, 1976), pp. 170&#8211;173.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3225" type="letter">
        <head>3225. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,
                  <date when="1818-12-28">28 December 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletion and readdress in
                  another hand] To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ <del>Richmond</del>/
                     <del>Surry</del> 4 Tavistock Street/ Bedford Square<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/
                  298<lb /> Postmarks: E/ 31 DE 31/ 1818; 10 o&#8217;Clock/ DE. 31/ 1818; [partial] 10
                  o&#8217;Clock/ DE. 31/ 1818 F<lb /> Watermark: B. E. &amp; S. Bath 1814<lb /> Endorsement:
                     N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 203 1818/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> December/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
            <lb /> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University
                  of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.),
                     <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin,
                  Texas, 1976), pp. 170&#8211;173.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-12-28">28 Dec. 1818</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was truly glad to be assured by your last letter of what I had
               before suspected, that John had been more sinned against than sinning.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">May&#8217;s son John (1802&#8211;1879) had been expelled from
                  Eton for his part in &#8216;Palk&#8217;s Rebellion&#8217; on 3&#8211;4 November 1818.</note> Indeed by
               what I have since learnt it appears that the Master<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John Keate (1773&#8211;1852), clergyman and headmaster of Eton
                  1809&#8211;1834. One of the causes of the rebellion was his insistence that boys should
                  be in their boarding houses one hour earlier, at 5pm. </note> acted at the
               beginning with great imprudence. If, as has been stated, he ordered the boys to be
               locked up an hour earlier than usual, because some of them employed their time
               improperly, it was assuredly an act of injustice towards all the others; &amp; any
               person who knows what boys at a public school are, might have anticipated the
               consequences. In reality one of the best things belonging to public schools is that
               they generate that kind of spirit, which is liable to explode upon such occasions,
               but which gives a master who knows how to direct it, the best hold upon his boys. In
               my time at Westminster if any offence had been committed by some unknown person
                  <del>xxx</del> {whom} it was thought necessary to discover &amp; punish nothing
               more was necessary than to send one of the Monitors round to the different forms,
               &amp; ask who had done the thing, &#8211; &amp; immediately the offender stood up &amp;
               avowed himself. The Master behaved injudiciously at first, &amp; his conduct towards
               John has been abominably unjust. How easily might it have happened that such a
               punishment might ruin a boys fairest prospects; &#8211; for instance if instead of having a
               good &amp; affectionate father his fortune depended upon the will of some relation
               who without enquiring into the merits of the case <del>xxx</del> might think it {a}
               sufficient reason for discarding him, because he had been expelled from school.
               Public expulsion is {for this reason} too severe a punishment for any thing except
               some heinous moral offence, &#8211; But boys are so tractable when they are treated justly,
               &amp; generously &amp; kindly, that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> says it is almost always the Masters
               fault if they <del>xxx</del> require punishment at all.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are very well satisfied with the result of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartleys</ref>
                  examination.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Hartley Coleridge had just
                  graduated from Merton College, Oxford with a Second Class Honours degree. His
                  examiners had disagreed profoundly about his merits, with some wishing to award
                  him a First and some a Fourth.</note> Considering the disadvantages which he has
               had in a north-country school &amp; an inefficient Tutor,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Hartley Coleridge had attended a school in Ambleside 1808&#8211;1815,
                  run by John Dawes, the local clergyman. John Lightfoot (1784&#8211;1863), Principal of
                  the Postmasters and Tutor at Merton College, Oxford was felt by Southey to have
                  provided Hartley Coleridge with little help in his studies.</note> it is almost as
               honourable for him to have taken <del>xxx</del> a second class as for one who has
               been regularly bred to obtain the first place. About his future prospects I am
               <del>xxx</del> by no means hopeful. There is far too much of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">his father</ref> in his
               disposition. He has neither the strength nor the richness of his mind, &#8211; but he has
               the same subtlety in finding reasons to justify his own habits &amp; inclinations, &#8211;
               &amp; a perverse love of paradox which never brings forth good fruits. &#8211; If his
               prospects at Oxford should altogether fail, I believe it would be in my power to send
               him out as Chaplain to Pernambuco, &#8211; (a house, &amp; 400&#163; a year) an appointment
               every way desirable for a young man.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry
                  Koster, on behalf of the expatriate community in Pernambuco, had asked Southey&#8217;s
                  help in finding a chaplain, but it was proving difficult to produce a suitable
                  candidate.</note> &#8211; His brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref>
               is doing well, &amp; I am in good hope that <del>xxx</del> {<del>xxx</del>} {a} way
               to Cambridge begins to open for him;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Coleridge finally entered St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge in
                  1820.</note> One of his schoolfellows (the eldest son of poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharles">Charles Lloyd</ref>
          <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Grosvenor Lloyd (1800&#8211;1850).</note>) much
               to the delight of his father &amp; mother has pressed upon him from his own abundant
               salary (in <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharlesSnr">his
               grandfathers</ref> bank) 30&#163; a year towards his college expenses.
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>
               &amp; an unknown friend of Wordsworths &amp; myself &#8211; undertake for 10&#163; each. When he
               leaves his present situation,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent
                  Coleridge lived with the Hopwood family, well-connected Lancashire landowners, at
                  Summerhill, near Ulverston 1817&#8211;1819. Robert Gregge Hopwood (1773&#8211;1854) had
                  married in 1805 Cecilia Elizabeth Byng (1770&#8211;1854), daughter of John Byng, 5th
                  Viscount Torrington (1743&#8211;1813). Derwent Coleridge was tutor to the Hopwoods&#8217;
                  sons: Edward (1807&#8211;1891); Frank (1810&#8211;1890); and Hervey (1811&#8211;1881).</note> at the
               close of the ensuing year, he will have sixty or seventy pounds of his own. And I
               have put him in a way of helping himself rather more effectually, I have set him upon
               translating my old friend Dobrizhoffer de Abiponibus, which <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will print, &amp; give him half
               the eventual profits. He has plenty of time for this task. I will oversee it for him,
               &amp; review the book as soon as it appears, so as to give it the best chance for a
               sale, &#8211; which indeed I should hope my little Tale of Paraguay (taken from
               Dobrizhoffer) will almost secure.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  account of the Jesuit missions in Paraguay by Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791),
                     <title>Historia de Abiponibus, Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae
                     Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, was
                  a book of which he was especially fond. Derwent made little headway with the
                  translation and so Sara Coleridge completed it, and her <title>Account of the
                     Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> was published by Murray in
                  1822. Southey reviewed it positively in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26
                  (January 1822), 277&#8211;323. Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825) was
                  based on Dobrizhoffer&#8217;s narrative.</note> It is in three octavo volumes, &amp; his
               probable share of profits may be estimated at <del>xxx</del> about 200&#163;. He is not a
               little pleased with the prospect of thus working his own way. The book is a
               delightful one, tho it will lose something in translation, &#8211; for there is a
               liveliness &amp; originality in the old Jesuits Latin which cannot be transfused. &#8211;
               Two of the volumes he has with him, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">his
               sister</ref> is helping him here at home with the third,
               &#8211; <del>xxx</del> to which she is fully competent.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is in all points of view satisfactory. &#8211; I suppose it will make
               me accelerate my poem, that it may be published before the story appears in prose. It
               is very well that I should have some such motive to spur me on, &#8211; the less time we
               have to spare the more careful should we be not to let that <del>old</del> notorious
               old thief Procrastination run away with any of it. What little poetry I have written
               of late has been in Oliver Newman, &#8211; &amp; this I am going on with at a snails pace
               without laying it aside.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s New
                  England epic, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, was never completed and the fragment was published
                  posthumously in <title>Oliver Newman: a New England Tale (Unfinished): with Other
                     Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;92. </note> &#8211; I shall probably
               ere long take up the other in good earnest &amp; go thro with it at a heat. &#8211; But my
               main business at present is with Brazil, where my long labours are drawing toward
               their close. By the time this reaches you I shall have finished the war of the Seven
                  Reductions.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Under the Treaty of
                  Madrid (1750), Spanish land east of the River Uruguay was ceded to Portugal. The
                  Jesuits were ordered to dismantle seven of their Reductions and re-build them west
                  of the river. The Guarani inhabitants of the Reductions resisted these measures
                  and were defeated by a joint Spanish-Portuguese force in the Guarani War of
                  1756&#8211;1757. These matters were covered in Chapter 39, <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 442&#8211;504.</note> the next
               chapter contains the Expulsion of the Jesuits.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The Jesuits were expelled from Brazil in 1759 and then from
                  Spanish America in 1767: Chapters 40 and 42, <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3
                  vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 505&#8211;547, 603&#8211;617.</note> Two more will compleat
               this very laborious undertaking. This is being very near the end, &#8211; &amp; a winning
               horse does not push with more spirit for the goal when he has it full in view than I
               hasten forward toward the conclusion of a book.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s schedule was as usual optimistic. The excessive length of the
                  concluding chapter delayed completion; see <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3
                  vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 696&#8211;879.</note> The life of Wesley will not be
               much behind hand.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The
                     Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism </title>(1820).</note>
               They are printing the notes to the first volume, &amp; a quarter part of the second
               is ready for the press. &#8211; The Peninsular War<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). Southey
                  already had much of the material to hand from his accounts of the war in the
                     <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808&#8211;1811</title> (1810&#8211;1813).</note>
               will seem a mere trifle to me in comparison with the Brazil, &#8211; indeed I do not expect
               that the three volumes will take up so much time in composition as one of the others
               for in the great bulk of the work I make no second copy, &#8211; whereas every syllable of
               the Brazil has been transcribed, &amp; the materials which have been collected &amp;
               not used are of no inconsiderable bulk.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is a long while since I have heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, &#8211; but if any thing
               had been amiss <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> no doubt would have
               informed me. In his last letter he spoke of himself as relieved from his rheumatism
               but very feeble. Winter I fear will bring back the one complaint, &amp; the other is
               not likely to be lessened by any favourable change. I cannot turn my thought that way
               without perceiving many anxieties in store, &#8211; <del>xx</del> yet there is so much
               promise about the three elder boys, as greatly to lessen the apprehensions concerning
               them. The prospect of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother Toms</ref>
               family gives me a much sadder concern. He has already six, &#8211; &amp; they come as fast
               as they can come four of them are girls.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey&#8217;s rapidly growing family: Margaret Hill Southey (b. 1811); Mary
                  Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813&#8211;1828); Herbert Castle Southey
                  (1815&#8211;1864); Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816&#8211;1835); Sarah Louise Southey
                  (1818&#8211;1850). They were later joined by: Nelson Castle Southey (1820&#8211;1834); Sophia
                  Jane Southey (1822&#8211;1859) and Thomas Castle Southey (1824&#8211;1896).</note> It is
               utterly impossible that he can make the slightest provision for them, &#8211; &amp; they
               are almost as much dependant upon my life as upon his. &#8211; Our writers &amp;
               speculative politicians seem never to touch upon the real evils of our state of
               society; &#8211; the great &amp; growing one is the increase of the educated class
                  <del>xx</del> in a ratio out of all proportion to the room for it. If it does not
               become a part of our system of policy to provide remedies or at least alleviations
               for this <del>xx</del> it is scarcely possible that two generations more should pass
               way without a root &amp; branch revolution, &#8211; were there no other causes tending
               toward such a catastrophe. Schemes of colonization upon a scheme which we have no
               statesmen bold enough to contemplate, ought not to be delayed. Another thing needful
               is some sort of establishment for educated women, which should have the advantages of
               the Convent without its vows &amp; its superstition. More than twenty years ago <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> &amp; I thought of pressing this upon the
               public attention.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 17 January 1800, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part
                     Two</title>, Letter 479.</note> And it will be the first subject which I shall
               take up for the Q Review,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  advocated the idea in a review of Thomas Dudley Fosbrooke (1770&#8211;1842;
                     <title>DNB</title>), <title>British Monachism; or, Manners and Customs of the
                     Monks and Nuns of England</title> (1817) in the <title>Quarterly
                  Review</title>, 22 (July 1819), 59&#8211;102 (90&#8211;102). </note> I am sure it is
               practicable &amp; sure that it would be one of the greatest blessings that could be
               conferred upon this country could we succeed in carrying it into effect. But I am at
               the end of my paper &#8211; God bless you my dear friend. Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; your daughters<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">May&#8217;s daughters, Mary Charlotte (b. 1804),
                  Susanna Louisa (1805&#8211;1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note> &amp; believe me
               most affectionately yours</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>