<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2814</idno><idno type="nines">rce4085</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2814. Robert Southey to Mary Matilda Betham, 24 June
                  [1816]</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2814.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14107. ALS; 2p. .  Previously 
                  published: Ernest Betham (ed.), A House of Letters: Being Excerpts from the Correspondence of Miss Charlotte Jerningham (the
                     Honble. Lady Bedingfield), Lady Jerningham, Coleridge, Lamb, Southey, Bernard and Lucy Barton, and others, with Matilda Betham;
                     and from Diaries and Various Sources; and a Chapter upon Landor’s Quarrel with Charles Betham at Llanthony (London,
                  1905), pp. 168–169.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2814" type="letter"><head>2814. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BethamMatilda">Mary Matilda Betham</ref>, <date when="1816-06-24">24 June
                  [1816]</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Beinecke Library, Osborn MSS File ‘S’, Folder 14107. ALS; 2p.<lb/> Previously
                  published: Ernest Betham (ed.), <title>A House of Letters: Being Excerpts from the Correspondence of Miss Charlotte Jerningham (the
                     Honble. Lady Bedingfield), Lady Jerningham, Coleridge, Lamb, Southey, Bernard and Lucy Barton, and others, with Matilda Betham;
                     and from Diaries and Various Sources; and a Chapter upon Landor’s Quarrel with Charles Betham at Llanthony</title> (London,
                  1905), pp. 168–169.</note></head><opener><salute>My dear Miss Betham</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> I ought long since to have written to you, – &amp; thanked you for your verses.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Matilda Betham had sent Southey her poem, ‘On the Death of Herbert Southey, addressed to his Father’. The lines were published in
                  her <title>Vignettes in Verse</title> (London, 1818), pp. 64–67.</note> I felt them as you would wish me to feel them, but I have
               not yet ventured to put them into <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref> hand, &amp; perhaps she had better not
               see them till they appear in print, – when Time shall have blunted the edge of pain, believe me I thank you sincerely for them, nor
               could you have gratified me more. They bear your stamp – the stamp of the lawful mint of the Muses.</p><p rend="indent1"> There needs no apology about the Lay of Marie, – rather there does need one – but it is on my part; <del>&amp;</del>
               you will easily excuse me for not having sooner executed my intention.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Betham’s <title>The Lay
                     of Marie: a Poem</title> (1816). Southey did not review it for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. A presentation copy was no.
                  278 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> I will certainly write an account of it for the number after this which is
               now far advanced in the press, – but I cannot answer for its insertion: – that must depend upon the Editor.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), published on 11 August 1816.</note> My influence &amp; efforts
               shall not be wanting; – &amp; as I have some influence with one other Review I will lose no time in recommending it there.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably the <title>Eclectic Review</title>; if so, it did not review the poem.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> That stanza in my Lay which made you sorry, will make others angry, – but the occasion required it.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Lay of the Laureate. Carmen Nuptiale</title> (1816), ‘The Dream’, stanza 53, attacking the
                  Catholics and Dissenters as allied opponents of the Anglican church: ‘The stern sectarian in unnatural league/ Joins her to war
                  against their hated foe;/ Error and Faction aid the bold intrigue,/ And the dark Atheist seeks her overthrow,/ While giant Zeal in
                  arms against her stands,/ Barks with an hundred mouths, and lifts an hundred hands’. </note> I cannot forgive the Dissenters for
               leaguing with the Catholicks against the Church, – the original cause of dissent being that the Church retained so many Popish
               ceremonies. They have no common principle, but that of hatred to the Establishment &amp; a union formed upon that principle is
               abominable. But Church &amp; State will both be overthrown before this generation pass away, unless the Government awakens to a sense
               of its danger. – I suppose I shall be called a Methodist for the poems &amp; for the Pilgrimage.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Poet’s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> – with just as much propriety as I have formerly been called an
               Atheist.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">Love from all. God bless you.</salute><signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1816-06-24">24 June. </date><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick.</ref></placeName></address></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>