<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3175</idno><idno type="nines">rce4446</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3175. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 1 August 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3175.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p.
               .  Not previously published.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3175" type="letter"><head>3175. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>,<date when="1818-08-01"> 1 August 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G C Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi><lb/> Endorsements: 1 August 2<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 1818; 1
                  August 2<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 1818 <hi rend="sup">d<lb/></hi>MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head><opener><salute> My dear G.</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> The first part of this Tender Epistle which you now receive is to be
               followed by a pleasant digest of the various slanders uttered &amp; afterwards eaten
               by <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>, in his
               public character.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was transmitting
                  a draft of the first part of an attack on Brougham. Southey’s intended pamphlet
                  was provoked by a speech made by Brougham in the course of the general election of
                  1818. As the <title>Courier</title> reported on 4 July, Brougham, campaigning for
                  the parliamentary seat of Westmorland against the candidates favoured by
                  Wordsworth’s patron, the Earl of Lonsdale, spoke at the hustings at Appleby on 30
                  June, attacking Southey and Wordsworth. Southey was dissuaded from publishing the
                  retort that he discusses here. Part of it finally appeared as a ‘Postscript’ to
                  the second edition of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (London, 1821), pp.
                  45–53.</note> I have received two rich cases from <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrokerJohnWilson">Croker</ref>, &amp; have other collectors at work for me. </p><p rend="indent1"> I wrote to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> concerning it some ten days ago, &amp; desired he would send me
               the Parl: Debates from the time when <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> came in
               for Winchelsea in the last Parliament.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham was returned as the MP for Winchelsea 1815–1830. </note> But they
               are not come. The middle part of the letter of course cannot be put together till
               these materials are before me. But I have got on with the concluding part where <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Gog</ref> &amp; the ER.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeffrey and the <title>Edinburgh Review</title> (1802–1929),
                  the main Whig quarterly journal, to which Brougham was a contributor.</note> come
               in for their share. </p><p rend="indent1"> The beginning need not go to the Press till the whole is ready, – for
               there is no hurry, – tho I shall not make any unnecessary delay. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> thinks I am writing in exculpation of myself.
               But you will see that being called upon flatly to contradict a gross &amp;
                  <del>offensive</del> insolent slander, I take advantage of that occasion to give
               this fellow a thorough dressing, – &amp; this will certainly be of some use here,
               where the pamphlet will be conned with curiosity by <del>xx</del> all my neighbours. </p><p rend="indent1"> I have asked <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to let <ref type="m" target="people.html#PopleWilliam">Pople</ref> print it. The documents
               in proof of the <del>historical</del> slanders (MacKerrel<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert M’Kerrell (1761–1841), a textile merchant and
                  manufacturer in Paisley, had on 28 May 1812, given evidence to the House of
                  Commons committee enquiring into the Orders in Council system, which enforced a
                  trade blockade on territories controlled by France. The Whig opposition were
                  campaigning for its repeal, on the grounds that it harmed British manufacturing.
                  Brougham denounced M’Kerrell (though not by name) in the House of Commons on 16
                  June 1812, claiming he had told the committee that textile workers were overpaid
                  and ‘oatmeal and water were good enough for Englishmen.’ M’Kerrell denied he had
                  said this and published an acrimonious exchange of letters between himself and
                  Brougham in <title>The Times</title> of 20 July 1812.</note> &amp;c) will go in an
               appendix. And I shall have a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>. – What a dose it will be for this paltry scoundrel, –
               &amp; I am sure that when you {shall} have read marked &amp; inwardly digested the
               extracts with which the letter begins, you will agree with me that it is impossible
               to treat him with more severity than he deserves. </p><p rend="indent1"> Do not wait for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, – put Bourke<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                  friend of Bedford’s whose visit would prevent Bedford’s travelling on holiday to
                  the Lakes.</note> off &amp; set off with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Mag: Rot</ref> for the mountains
               as soon as you can.</p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1818-08-01"> Aug. 1.</date></p><p> Ask <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to
                  send me a <hi rend="ital">navy-list</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The annual list published by the Royal Navy of all its officers, their
                     ranks and their ships.</note><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> being
                  here, &amp; hungry for one.</p><p> The Hydians<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s
                     new clothes, sent from his London tailor Hyde (d. 1820).</note> are
                  arrived.</p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>