<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3032</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4303</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3032. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 29 October 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3032.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p. .  Previously 
                  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert Southey, 2
                  vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 175&#8211;177.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3032" type="letter">
        <head>3032. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1817-10-29">29 October 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
                  Postmark: E/ 1 NO 1/ 1817<lb /> Endorsement: 29 Octb<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1817.
                     Rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Nov<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                  1817<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously
                  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2
                  vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 175&#8211;177.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline> Wednesday <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-10-29"> 29 Oct. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> You are a vile fellow Grosvenor, &#8211; &amp; really made me uneasy by
               your silence, &#8211; for I could not help thinking you were ill. I have been hard at work
               since you departed, &amp; have got thro (as you may perhaps have seen) a paper for
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Lord Holland, <title>Some Account
                     of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de
                     Castro</title> (1817), which appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 18
                  (October 1817), 1&#8211;46.</note> which, quoad<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;In respect of&#8217;.</note> the trouble it cost, will not be overpaid by any thing
               which may be given for it in the form of sweet remuneration. Since this was
               dispatched I have been recreating myself alternately with Brazilian history<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title>
                  (1810&#8211;1819).</note> &#8211; &amp; the introduction to the peninsular war;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>
                  (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; in this {latter} I have done with the moral picture of Spain
               &amp; Portugal, &amp; shall probably have compleated that of France before this will
               reach you. the chapter is to conclude with England &amp; in this part I shall draw
               for posterity the true picture of an English opposition. As soon as this is done
               (&amp; I shall not lay it aside, till it be done) it goes to press without delay: &#8211;
               when I am once under weigh, stop me who can, &#8211; I can answer for myself.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey here describes what became <title>History of
                     the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 3&#8211;61. Those
                  opposed to the war with France were denounced at pp. 55&#8211;57.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Some time ago <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> desired that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref> might be sent up to
               him, &#8211; preparations have been made accordingly, &amp; I was desirous that he should
               go, in hopes that the father when he felt the weight upon his own shoulders might
               bestir himself: <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">C.</ref> is
               fortunate in making friends &amp; noways delicate in soliciting favours from them: on
               this occasion there was great cause for any assistance which he could obtain. Today
               however his wife has received a letter from M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gillman,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Gillman (1779&#8211;1860), with her husband James
                  (1782&#8211;1839), had taken Coleridge into their house in Highgate in 1816; he would
                  continue living there, under their supervision, until his death.</note> saying
               that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  C</ref> is not well enough at present to receive his son; &#8211; that his illness is
               chiefly occasioned by his having engaged to write the introduction to the New
                  Cyclopeadia<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge had undertaken to
                  edit a new <title>Encyclopedia Metropolitana</title> with Thomas Curtis
                  (1787&#8211;1859), a Baptist minister and partner in the publishing firm Gale, Curtis
                  and Fenner. The publishers, in return for making Coleridge an advance of &#163;300,
                  required him to live at Camberwell, where Curtis could supervise his work. </note>
               which he now repents of having undertaken, finding it cannot be done in time &amp;c
               &amp;c &#8211; The truth is that instead of taking his son, he had laid a plan for
               quartering himself here also: &#8211; to this as you may well suppose I have just &amp;
               insuperable objections, it may suffice to mention one, &#8211; I know that he is
               exceedingly in debt, &amp; I know also that to pay off the debts which he must needs
               have paid before he could leave the Gillmans, he was endeavouring to obtain money
               from Curtis (of the Cyclopaedia) &#8211; upon condition of engaging <hi rend="ital">totis
                  viribus</hi>
          <note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;With all his might&#8217;.</note>
               in <del>the</del> his service: his coming here would have been a breach of those
               conditions (in reality the money would have been obtained upon false pretences,)
               &amp; he would have been arrested in consequence. Whenever he is arrested, which
               sooner or later he must be, it had better take place any where else than here.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Without affecting any love for <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">Derwent</ref>, I feel much compassion for
               him: it is a truly pitiable situation; for his father not only does nothing for him,
               but stands in the way of having any thing done, because there is not that claim upon
               his relations to bestir themselves, which there would be if he were an orphan. I can
               contribute nothing toward placing him at college, if such a scheme were set on foot,
               because there are <del>nearer</del> much nearer claims<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s four daughters and any future children he might have, as
                  well as the family of Southey&#8217;s brother, Tom Southey.</note> which take from me
               all I can spare <del>x</del> which <del>x</del> are likely to grow heavier, &amp;
               which will continue as long as I live. I wish it were as certain that my own means
               would increase in equal proportion. &#8211; By the bye you may purchase for me a
                  sixteenth:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The British State operated a
                  national lottery from 1694 to 1826. The tickets were sold by brokers, who issued
                  shares in tickets, such as the one sixteenth that Southey proposed to buy.</note>
               &#8211; let lotteries be as bad as they may, this is a loss which I cannot feel, &#8211; &amp;
                  <del>xx xxxx</del> there is a possibility of very essential advantage from it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Have you heard nothing of my books? I am uneasy about the box from
                  Milan,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Books that Southey had bought on
                  his continental tour in 1817.</note> &#8211; &amp; wish those from Brussels were
               arrived, because the season is now coming on when the voyage <del>xx of</del> {has}
               more risque than should be mine without necessity.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> is visiting <ref type="m" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Senhouse</ref> at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> is downstairs, with <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> &amp;
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#CrothersMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Crothers</ref> &amp; the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Senhora</ref>. The snow is on the fells, &#8211; but the country still beautiful, &#8211;
               indeed I have never seen grander effects than what <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw</ref> called upon me to look at this
               afternoon.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murrays</ref>
               letter has not yet arrived, &#8211; it will probably come with the Q.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Southey was probably
                  expecting proofs of his review of Lord Holland&#8217;s <title>Some Account of the Lives
                     and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and Guillen de Castro</title>, but
                  it was held over until the next issue.</note> proofs, of which I am in daily
               expectation. You are perfectly right in your opinion upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffreys</ref> essay.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeffrey&#8217;s essay on &#8216;Beauty&#8217; appeared in the Supplement to the
                  fourth edition of the <title>Encyclopaedia Britannica</title> (1816).</note>
               Whether it deserve criticism is <del>xxxx</del> {a} question for others, not for me,
               &#8211; this I am certain that <del>&amp;</del> no essay upon beauty can be worth my
               reading: &#8211; upon such subjects I have never bestowed a thought, nor ever shall: [MS
               missing] is enough for me to know when things are <del>sublime</del> beautiful, or
               sublime, just as I know whether things are sweet, or sour, &#8211; <del>xx</del> without
               enquiring or caring <hi rend="ital">why</hi> they are so. But if the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> will let me take <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> Biographia for a
                  text,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not review Coleridge&#8217;s
                     <title>Biographia Literaria</title> (1817) in the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>.</note> &amp; under that text, make a direct personal attack
               upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Hazlitt</ref>, I will give these
               {scoundrels} a <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">Williamsmithiad</ref>
               which shall answer his purpose effectually as well as mine.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge&#8217;s recent publications, and his change of political
                  opinion, had been attacked by Jeffrey and Hazlitt just as Southey&#8217;s had, hence
                  Southey&#8217;s wish to retaliate on his behalf with another such publication as
                     <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M. P.</title>, published by Murray at
                  the end of April 1817.</note> There are no usages of parliament to stand in my
               way, &#8211; &amp; may this right hand forget its cunning,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Psalms</title> 137: 5.</note> if it does not do me justice
               &amp; inflict due punishment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> God bless you. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">your brother</ref>, &amp; lay your plans for
               bringing him with you next year to the Lakes</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1"> The kitten is named Pulcheria. If Narses<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Cats belonging to Southey and Bedford. Both Pulcheria (c.
                     398&#8211;453; Empress 450&#8211;453) and Narses (c. 478&#8211;566/574), a leading general, were
                     central figures in the early Byzantine Empire.</note> understood the fitness of
                  his own name, he would admire this also. She is daughter to Madame Bianchi, &amp;
                  granddaughter to Bona Fidelia; niece to the late Catalani, &amp; related in many
                  ways to Lord Nelson &#8211; deceased.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>