<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2909</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4180</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2909. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 29 January 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2909.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d.
                  47. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey, 4 vols
                  (London, 1856), III, pp. 56&#8211;58.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2909" type="letter">
        <head>2909. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1817-01-29">29 January 1817</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
                  Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: E/ 1 FE 1/ 1817<lb /> Endorsement: 29 January 1817<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d.
                  47. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols
                  (London, 1856), III, pp. 56&#8211;58.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1817-01-29">29 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1817</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am neither surprized nor sorry at what you tell me of the <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Prose-gelders</ref> intentions. The more he cuts out from the Review, the more he leaves fresh for the Book,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 225&#8211;278
                  (published 11 February 1817), which he at this stage intended to form part of a book on the &#8216;State of the Nation&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; it
               is better that the strongest things should appear where they will be accompanied with free language respecting the Anti-Jacobines &amp;
               the Noddles &amp; the great Sinecures, than where there are forbidden topics, &amp; I seem rather, to the reader, as a Partizan, than
               as in truth I am, &amp; ought to appear. I have desired <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to send me the paper
               as soon as it is printed, &#8211; but for fear he should not send it in <del>xx</del> its genuine state, do you secure for me the manuscript.
               We may be quite sure that the boldest &amp; best parts are those which will be omitted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My letters to you are such pure <hi rend="ital">Meipseads</hi>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Me-myself-Is&#8217;.</note> that I have seldom room or leisure for any but personal concerns, &amp; therefore it is that you have heard
               nothing from me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Townsend</ref>, &#8211; who is however as far as it is
               possible to judge by his verses &amp; his letters a <del>xxxx</del> highly interesting youth. His poetry is of uncommon promise, &#8211;
               &amp; it is a great pleasure to me to hear from him, &#8211; tho&#8217; I can ill afford time for my part of the correspondence, &#8211; being indeed too
               old as well as too busy for the epistolary mood. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I knew you would be delighted with the drawing of the two girls,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sketches of
                  Southey&#8217;s family by Edward Nash.</note> yet there is one here of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>
               sitting on a mountain side, which I think is more beautiful, &#8211; &amp; is indeed, according to my perception, the perfect ideal of
               innocence. And the three younger ones<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s younger daughters, Bertha, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>.</note> over my
               chimney are so delightfully grouped that it is worth while to come to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> for the
               sake of seeing the picture. My blank verse poem<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey began, but did not finish, a poem,
                  entitled &#8216;Consolation&#8217; on the death of his son, Herbert. Sections were published after his death as &#8216;Fragmentary Thoughts Occasioned
                  by his Son&#8217;s Death&#8217;, <title>Oliver Newman: A New-England Tale (Unfinished): With Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845), pp.
                  93&#8211;95, and &#8216;Additional Fragment, Occasioned by the Death of his Son&#8217;, <title>Poetical Works of Robert Southey. Complete in One
                     Volume</title> (London, 1850), p. 815.</note> will probably not be printed while I live, &#8211; these drawings should one day be
               engraved to accompany it, &#8211; &amp; that view which <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> has made of the Church may
               come in for the frontispiece with my tombstone in the foreground.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We are very much attached to <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>. The childrens eyes sparkle with
               delight when they talk of him. I want him to take a six weeks run on the continent with me when I come to town, &amp; then return with
               me to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. &#8211; The Torso is an excellent thing, &#8211; by the bye this rich book is in
               such forwardness that if you will only come down this summer &amp; spur me on, we will have it ready for publication by Christmas.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to Southey&#8217;s unfinished comic novel, <title>The Doctor</title>
                  (1834&#8211;1847).</note> Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref> is no caprice of Natures &#8211; his deformity is the
               effect of an accident when he was twelve years old. One of his portraits of me is more like the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Docstor</ref>. When I come to town I must contrive to have you meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> (the younger) &#8211; a man much to my liking, who I hope will take up his abode at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My book sleeps till the <del>xxxx</del> Review <del>comes</del> arrives,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  awaited the return of the manuscript of his article &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816),
                  225&#8211;278 (published 11 February 1817). See note 1 above for his wish to rework parts of it into a book on the &#8216;State of the
                  Nation&#8217;.</note> meantime I am busy upon the Morte Arthur (which bringeth sweet remuneration)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Byrth, Lyf, and Actes of Kyng Arthur</title> was published in two volumes by Longman in 1817.</note> &amp; upon the third volume of Brazil,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819) was published in 1817 and
                  the third in 1819.</note> which bringeth something sweeter still, in the great pleasure which I take in it. On Tuesday next I go
               with <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Shedaw</ref>
               &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref>
               for a week, &#8211; <del>by the</del> when I return it will be with fresh appetite for Liber the Book,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The book of comic materials that Southey had, since their schooldays, dreamed of writing with Bedford. The
                  collaboration never bore fruit in a jointly-authored book, but did lead to Southey&#8217;s <title>The Doctor </title>(1834&#8211;1847). &#8216;Liber&#8217;
                  literally means in Latin &#8216;the free one&#8217;.</note> which may properly be called <hi rend="ital">Liber</hi>, for free it shall be <hi rend="ital">as sure as</hi> I&#8217;m a Dutchman.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In other words, the book would not be
                  free.</note> My brother Mynheers have sent me no notification of this undeserved honour,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">According to the <title>Courier</title>, 2 January 1817, Southey had been appointed an Associate of the Second Class of the Royal
                  Institute of Science, Literature and the Fine Arts of the Netherlands (founded 1808). The Institute&#8217;s headquarters are the
                  Trippenhuis in Amsterdam.</note> &#8211; &amp; of course it appeareth not in my title pages till such notification be duly received. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have written a chapter concerning the Pantaloons<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">This appeared as
                  Interchapter XX of <title>The Doctor</title> (London, 1848), p. 489.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">And now God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">Let your portrait be fitly framed,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">The portrait Southey had commissioned Nash
                     to make of Bedford.</note> &amp; it may come down in the same package with the frame for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref> drawing.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">Stoddart is dismissed from the Times. Walter believing that neither the Ministry nor the Opposition will be able to
                  stand, but that Hunt is to be Lord of the Ascendant!<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856;
                        <title>DNB</title>) was editor of <title>The Times</title> until dismissed by its proprietor John Walter (1776&#8211;1847;
                        <title>DNB</title>), at the end of 1816, for the intemperate Toryism of his articles. Stoddart blamed the decision on Walter&#8217;s
                     supposed belief that radical reformers led by Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>) would take power. Later in
                     1817, Stoddart became the first editor of the ministry-supported <title>The New Times</title> (1817&#8211;1828).</note> &#8211; Walter must
                  be a blockhead as well as a knave. But with such blockheads &amp; such cowards in office I fear there will be work for the Light
                  Horse Volunteers.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The Light Horse Volunteers of London and Westminster, a volunteer unit to
                     which many merchants and bankers belonged. It was commanded by Charles Herries (1745&#8211;1819), father of Southey&#8217;s correspondent,
                     John Charles Herries. Grosvenor Bedford was a member.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>