<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2892</idno><idno type="nines">rce4163</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">2892. Robert Southey to John May,
                  1–3 January [1817] </title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2892.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Harry Ransom Humanities Research
                  Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles
                  Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838
                  (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 153–155.</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="2892" type="letter"><head>2892. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,
                  <date when="1817-01-03">1–3 January [1817] </date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surry<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/> Postmarks:
                  E/ 6 JA 6/ 1817; 10 o’Clock/ JA. 6/ 1817 F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi><lb/> Watermark:
                  1813<lb/> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 192 1817/ Robert Southey/ Keswick
                     1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> January/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi><lb/> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research
                  Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles
                  Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797–1838</title>
                  (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 153–155.</note></head><opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address><date when="1817-01-01">1 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1817.</date></dateline><salute>My dear friend</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> Your last letter gave me great &amp; most unexpected concern<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John May’s financial position had been
                  precarious since he had suffered heavy losses in the Brazil trade. His letters to
                  Southey may have referred to continued conflicts with his partner and younger
                  brother William Henry May (1785–1849).</note> – I had indeed {believed} you were
               sailing in a quiet sea, in no danger of shoals or tempests. – By what principle, – or
               what strange want of principle is it, that mercantile men so often for the sake of
               the shortest reprieve from bankruptcy involve their nearest friends &amp; connections
               with them! – I write to you in a frame of mind which you will easily conceive,
               looking back upon the year which has just closed, &amp; reflecting on the trials with
               which we have both been visited during its course. Your loss I would fain hope may
               not prove <del>so xx</del> altogether so great as you apprehend, – &amp; I would hope
               also that some prize in the lottery of life, full of chances as it is, may one day or
               other replace it. Even at the worst, it leaves you heart-whole: – it will be long
               before I shall find myself so,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s son,
                  Herbert, had died on 17 April 1816.</note> – &amp; if life had no duties, I should
               be very far from desiring its continuance for the sake of any enjoyments which it can
               possibly have in store. I have the same sort of feeling that a man who is fondly
               attached to his family has when absent from them, – as if I were on a journey, –
               &amp; yearn perhaps more than I ought to do to be at home &amp; at rest. – Yet what
               abundant cause have I for thankfulness; possessing as I do so many blessings that I
               should think no man could possibly be happier, – if I had not been so much happier
               myself! – Do not think that I give way to such feelings – far less that I encourage
               them, – or am <del>indeed</del> weak enough to repine: – what is lost in possession
               is given me in hope.</p><p rend="indent1"> I am now in my forty third year: – both my parents<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">Margaret</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">Robert Southey Snr</ref>.</note> died in their
               fiftieth. Should my lease be continued to that term there is a fair prospect of
               leaving my family well provided for, – &amp; let it fall when it may, a decent
               provision is secured. Before this object was attained, great natural chearfulness
               saved me from any anxiety on this score, &amp; there happily exists no cause for
               anxiety when I have no longer the same preservative. My house is in order, &amp;
               whenever the summons may come I am ready to depart. Dearly as I love these
                  children,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s daughters, Edith May,
                     <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref>.</note> my presence is by no
               means so necessary to them as it was to him who is gone. He drew in his intellectual
               life from me, – &amp; a large portion of mine is departed with him. It is best as it
               is, – for he is gone in the perfection of his nature, – &amp; mine will not be the
               worse for the chastening which it has undergone.</p><p rend="indent1"> Hitherto the lapse of time only makes me feel the depth of the wound.
               It will not be always thus. A few years (if they are in store for me) will alter the
               nature of my regret, – I shall then be sensible how different a being <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref> were he living would be from the
               Herbert whom I have lost: – &amp; the voices &amp; circumstances which now so
               forcibly recall him will have lost their power. – Too much of this. – But holydays
               are mournful days to persons in our situation, – &amp; the strong forefeeling which I
               have always experienced of such possibilities has always made me dislike the
               observance of particular days. Your <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">God-daughter</ref> is the only child whose
               birthday I have not contrived to forget, – &amp; hers has been remembered from the
               accident of its being May day.</p><p rend="indent1"> She – God be thanked, is in high health, growing fat as well as fast,
               – &amp; with such <del>xx</del> a countenance of intelligence &amp; innocent
               chearfulness – that I might truly call her the delight of my eyes. When <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Nash</ref> returns to town
               you must go with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Doctor</ref> one morning &amp; see the picture which he has made of her &amp; her
               cousin <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara
                  Coleridge</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Nash’s sketch of the two
                  girls, made at Keswick in 1816.</note> The others also are well, &amp; as happy as
               skylarks in a fine day. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref>
               does not recover her spirits, – we take care not to depress each other, – but I can
               read thoughts which are not permitted to find utterance. Towards the end of the month
               we purpose paying a weeks visit at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> – a house twenty miles from hence near the town of Maryport: –
               your <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">God-daughter</ref> goes with
               us. The change of air &amp; the exercise will do her mother some good I trust, –
               &amp; for myself a little shaking of the solids is very needful, – for I have been
               but once out of the house since the first of November, – except to Church. The
               weather has been <del>xx xx</del> a fair pretext, if not a just cause for this
               seclusion. Never was there such a succession of storms, sometimes with snow,
               sometimes with rain. The floods have been higher than I ever before saw them, – tho
               this is the fourteenth year of my residence at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>!</p><p rend="indent1"> I expect <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother
               Tom</ref>, whose <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">wife</ref> is in the straw, – so he comes to pass his state of
               batchelorship with me. His present home is about forty miles from hence.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Southey’s third daughter and fifth child,
                  Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816–1835) was born on 24 December 1816, at Warcop
                  Hall, where he rented a farm.</note> Whether I shall ever have sufficient interest
               to get him promoted is very doubtful, – however what I have shall be exerted.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey was promoted to Captain in the Royal
                  Navy in 1811, but was never given command of a ship.</note> Civil things are said
               of me by men in power, &amp; as no man has ever stood forward more conscienciously in
               behalf of their measures, – upon the great scale, – they could in no way so properly
               acknowledge their sense of what I have done, as by giving him that rank to which his
               old services most fully &amp; honourably entitle him.</p><p rend="indent1"> What you tell me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> &amp; his parishioners does
               not surprize me.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill was Rector of
                  Streatham.</note> They behaved exceedingly ill when first he went among them,
               &amp; he was not accustomed to be treated thus, – living as you <del>had</del> know
               he had done among his Lisbon flock. It is moreover a parish in which it would be very
               difficult to feel as a Clergyman would wish to do, – the [MS torn] is of so
               fluctuating a kind, – &amp; that kind also – far from being a pleasant one. A man
               fancies himself rich enough to have his country house, – he betters it, fits it up
               expensively, gets into the gazette in a year or two, – &amp; is followed by another
               person <del>xx</del> running the same career, &amp; <del>xx</del> hastening to the
               same end. There is a great deal of this in the immediate vicinity of London. Moreover
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncles</ref> habits, which
               were always quiet &amp; not inclined to much activity, are become more so, from
               years, &amp; from matrimony, – which has very probably accelerated the work of time
               upon his constitution. I hope to see him early in the spring, – at which time it is
               my full purpose to visit London.</p><p rend="indent1"> Pray let me hear your affairs: – in which you know how deep an
               interest I must needs take. – Ere long I hope to send a portion of my Paraguay
                  Tale.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s poem <title>A Tale of
                     Paraguay</title> was not published until 1825. </note> Remember me most kindly
               to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref>
               &amp; your daughters.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Charlotte (b.
                  1804), Susanna Louisa (1805–1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note>
                  Johnny<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">May’s son John (1802–1879) had
                  entered Eton School in September 1815 and his conduct was causing some concern. He
                  was expelled following his part in ‘Palk’s Rebellion’ of 3–4 November 1818.</note>
               should have been at Westminster instead of Eton, &amp; you might then have had him
               for a companion during your evenings in town. I have always thought the best possible
               education that of a Westminster <hi rend="ital">home-boarder</hi>.</p><p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref>, whom I <del>xxxxx xxx xxx</del> {shall always be} glad to
               see here, – or any where else. – <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">Hartley</ref> will soon be returning to
               Oxford. Of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">the father</ref>
               we know nothing.</p><closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear friend</salute><salute rend="indent2"> yrs most affectionately</salute><signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1817-01-03">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 3.</date></p></postscript><postscript><p> Should the Correspondent fall in your way, you will find <del>it</del> in it a
                  life of Wesley of my writing.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">In advance
                     of the full-scale biography of John Wesley (1703–1791; <title>DNB</title>) that
                     he published in 1820, Southey contributed ‘On the Life of John Wesley, Founder
                     of the English Methodists’ to Longmans’ new venture, <title>The
                        Correspondent</title>, 1–2 (1817), 26–48, 157–176.</note></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>