<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3088</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4359</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3088. Robert Southey to Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn, 8 March 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3088.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3088" type="letter">
        <head>3088. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles
                  Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1818-03-08">8 March 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ C W Williams Wynn
                     Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi> MP/ London<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark:
                  FREE/ 11 MR 11/ 1818<lb /> MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry your Bill was lost,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">On 24 June 1817 Wynn had moved an Election Laws amendment bill, designed to
                  make a number of reforms to the conduct of elections. It was rejected by the House
                  of Lords. When he reintroduced it in 1818 it was defeated in the House of Commons
                  on 2 March by 51 votes to 44. One reason for its defeat was opposition from some
                  Whigs, who usually supported electoral reforms, but were annoyed that the
                  Grenvillite group, headed by Wynn in the Commons, had formally separated from
                  their Whig allies. Southey presumably did not know that one of the Bill&#8217;s keenest
                  supporters was Brougham, who hoped that its clause to remove the provision that
                  freeholders had to demonstrate their land was assessed for land tax would help his
                  election campaign in Westmorland.</note> &#8211; and a little vexed, &#8211; because with so
               little zeal on the part of those who approved it, it might have been carried. This
               however is one of those reforms which is sure to be effected, if you persevere in
               bringing it forward. Our neighbours in Westmorland are already enjoying in rehearsal
               the blessings of a contested election.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                  general election was imminent, though the House of Commons was not dissolved until
                  10 June 1818. It was already clear, though, that there would be a contest in
                  Westmorland, which was dominated by the Lowther family, who were supporters of the
                  government &#8211; the two sitting MPs were the brothers Henry Lowther (1790&#8211;1867), MP
                  for Westmorland 1812&#8211;1867 and William, Viscount Lowther (1787&#8211;1872), later 2nd
                  Earl of Lonsdale and MP for Cockermouth 1808&#8211;1813, MP for Westmorland 1813&#8211;1831
                  and 1832&#8211;1841. So complete was the Lowthers&#8217; dominance that the last contested
                  election in Westmorland was in 1774. However, in January 1818, a committee of
                  Whigs and smaller landowners had brought forward Henry Brougham to challenge the
                  Lowthers &#8211; Brougham&#8217;s family home was Brougham Hall near Penrith and he could
                  plausibly be presented as a local candidate.</note> One of the best men in the
               county has been nearly killed by the <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> mob &amp;
               spits blood in consequence of the injury which he received.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The election canvas produced a good deal of violence,
                  especially in Kendal. Southey may be referring to the injuries received on 21
                  February 1818 by John Fleming (c. 1769&#8211;1835) of Rayrigg Hall, Rector of Bootle
                  1814&#8211;1835. </note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham&#8217;s</ref> probability of success arises from a cause
               which has <del>xxx</del> been widely operating over the whole of the kingdom,
                  <del>&amp; ought to have been foreseen &amp; proceeded against</del> the great
               multiplication of <del>xxxx</del> freeholders by the enclosures, &#8211; forty shilling
                  voters,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Only owners of land worth 40
                  shillings per annum were entitled to vote in county elections.</note> &#8211; good part
               of whom are in that hopeful state that they would vote for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoneWilliam">Hone</ref> or <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref> against
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>, for the same reason which will make them
               vote for <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> against <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lowther</ref>. I am out of the circle of these petty politics,
               &amp; should regard them with perfect indifference, if every symptom of the times did
               not indicate the same disease. <del>Xxx</del> Nevertheless I think the aspects on the
               whole are improving.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Is the publication of the Irish historians to be continued? &#8211; If it
               be not, &#8211; I shall look upon the death of the M. of Buckingham as the greatest loss
               that has been sustained in our times.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles O&#8217;Conor (1764&#8211;1828; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Rerum Hibernicarum
                     Scriptores Veteres</title>, 4 vols (1814&#8211;1826), no. 2112 in the sale catalogue
                  of Southey&#8217;s library. This was an edition of some of the manuscripts in the
                  library at Stowe. O&#8217;Conor was the chaplain of Mary, Marchioness of Buckinghamshire
                  (d. 1812). Her husband, George Nugent-Temple-Grenville, 1st Marquess of Buckingham
                  (1753&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), provided financial support for the
                  project.</note> If it were compleated as it is begun, it would vie with any
               undertaking of the kind. Ill as I can spare the time, &amp; unfit as I am in many
               respects for the task, I am strongly inclined to give some account of it in the Q.
                  Review,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">No review appeared in the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> merely for the sake of calling the
               public attention to a work of such importance, &amp; which is <del>xx</del> sure to
               be neglected without some such help: for this is the state of literature among us, &#8211;
               &amp; a vile state it is. &#8211; If you were Minister (&#8211; <del>xx</del> I would give up the
               Catholic question<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn was in favour of
                  full political rights for Catholics; Southey was opposed.</note> for the sake of
               seeing you one &#8211;) I should be laying plans before you for national collections of
               this kind, &amp; other works, which never can be performed without public assistance:
               in these things we are behind hand even with the Spaniards &amp; Portugueze.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You would be amused to see my table overlaid with Methodism &amp;
               Moravianism. I am going thro the whole set of the Arminian Magazine.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Arminian Magazine </title>(1778&#8211;1797),
                  a monthly magazine edited by John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) until his
                  death and continued as the <title>Methodist Magazine</title> (1798&#8211;1822) and the
                     <title>Wesleyan Methodist Magazine</title> (1822&#8211;1969).</note> This Life of
                  Wesley<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Life of Wesley; and
                     the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title> (1820).</note> is a more <hi rend="ital">operose</hi> business than one who is not acquainted with my habits
               would suppose. &#8211; I am given to works of supererogation, &amp; could do nothing to my
               own satisfaction if I did not take twice as much labour as any other person would
               bestow upon it. In this case it will be well bestowed, &#8211; I am treating of a curious
               part of history just at the right time, &#8211; &amp; in as fair a temper as it could be
               possible to bring to such a subject. The materials are very copious &amp; very
               curious, &#8211; &amp; the plan so arranged as to relieve that monotony which you might
               perhaps apprehend.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had a letter lately from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BunburySirHenryEdward">Sir H. Bunbury</ref>,
               inviting me to Suffolk to look over his papers about the war.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Bunbury had been Under-Secretary of State for War and the
                  Colonies 1809&#8211;1816.</note> &#8211;&#8211;This invitation I must accept, &#8211; not as a matter of
               inclination, but of duty in my vocation; &#8211; so most probably if he can receive me at
               the fall of the leaf, I shall then move from home. His materials <del>xxx</del> will
               relate to the latter years of the war, I wait <del>only</del> for a French book which
               contains the details &amp; official papers concerning the Imperial system of
                  education.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Baptist Germain Fabry
                  (1770&#8211;1821), <title>Le Ge&#769;nie de la Re&#769;volution Conside&#769;re&#769; dans l&#8217;Education ou
                     Me&#769;moires pour Servir a l&#8217;Histoire de l&#8217;Instruction Publique, Depuis 1789
                     jusqu&#8217;a&#768; Nos Jours</title> (1817&#8211;1818).</note> When this comes I shall finish
               the introductory chapter &amp; go to press. The introduction describes the moral
               &amp; political state of the Peninsula France &amp; England.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols
                  (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 3&#8211;62.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I see no person during the winter except my own family, &amp; for
               weeks together do not stir beyond my own garden; the kitchen clock is not more
               regular in its movements than my life, &amp; scarcely more monotonous, &#8211; yet time
               never appeared to glide so swiftly. I have often said that live as long as we may,
               the first twenty years of life are the longest half. There are indications enough
               that I am on the downhill road, &#8211; an unwillingness to exertion of any kind is one &#8211; I
               fear that a decay of sight is another; &#8211; as yet however it only regards distant
               objects, &#8211; what is near I see as distinctly as ever.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you my dear Wynn</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p> K[MS torn] <date when="1818-03-08">8 March. 1818.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>