<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2877</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4148</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2877. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 13 December 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2877" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2877.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS;
                  8p. .  Previously  published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), New Letters of Robert
                     Southey, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 144&#8211;146 [text does
                  not include the ode &#8216;Europe had suffered&#8217;]. Note on MS: the letter included
                  an enclosure, the ode &#8216;Europe had suffered&#8217;.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2877" type="letter">
        <head>2877. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1816-12-13">13 December 1816</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb /> Endorsements: 13 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  1816; 13 Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816./ with proposed Ode for 1817; Proposed Ode
                  for 1817; Enclosed in ltr from R.S. of 13. Dec<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816.
                  Proposed Ode for 1817.<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 25. ALS;
                  8p.<lb /> Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert
                     Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 144&#8211;146 [text does
                  not include the ode &#8216;Europe had suffered&#8217;].<lb /> Note on MS: the letter included
                  an enclosure, the ode &#8216;Europe had suffered&#8217;.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> First here is some doggrel for the <ref type="m" target="people.html#ParsonsWilliam">Mus. Doc</ref>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Parsons, as Master of the King&#8217;s Music, was obliged to set the Poet
                  Laureate&#8217;s New Year&#8217;s Ode to music, for performance at Court, though this event
                  had been suspended since 1810. The poem Southey enclosed was his first draft of
                  the New Year&#8217;s Ode for 1817.</note> &#8211; which I pray you convey to him, &#8211; unless you
               like to write better doggrel yourself &amp; substitute it. It cost me just what it is
               worth; &#8211; the time which was required for writing it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Secondly thank you for what you have done concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnowlesHerbert">Herbert Knowles</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 20 November 1816, Letter
                  2866.</note> I shall make no scruple of calling upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref> for his five pounds, he having more
               than as many thousands a year, &#8211; a single man, &amp; living so little in one place,
               that he can scarcely be said to have an establishment. And if I should come to you
               for five more, &#8211; which I will not if I can help it because you have calls enough, &#8211;
               why you will not grumble. I shall write by this same post to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">Rogers</ref> who is rich, &amp; generous in a
               princely degree.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thirdly. I have a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, who is very sore: &amp; so he
               deserves to be. But he is sore also about the Correspondent without any cause, &#8211; for
               in the first place, this journal is no rival of his, not being a review, &#8211; &amp; in
               the next place I never dreamt of doing more than giving it a lift.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 18 November
                  and 29 November 1816 (Letters 2865 and 2868), concerning what he felt to be
                  underpayment by Murray for articles in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. Murray
                  was also annoyed that Southey was contributing an article to a new journal edited
                  by John Stoddart (1773&#8211;1856; <title>DNB</title>): <title>The Correspondent;
                     Consisting of Letters, Moral, Political, and Literary, between Eminent Writers
                     in France and England; and designed by presenting to each Nation a Faithful
                     Picture of the Other, to Enlighten both to their True Interests, promote a
                     Mutual Good Understanding between them, and render Peace the Source of a Common
                     Prosperity</title>. Southey&#8217;s sketch of the life of John Wesley (1703&#8211;1791;
                     <title>DNB</title>) appeared in the first two numbers (1 (1817), 26&#8211;48; and 2
                  (1817), 157&#8211;176). The <title>Correspondent</title> lasted only one further number.
               </note> You do Stoddart wrong. A fellow by name Barnes, quondam coadjutor to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Hunt</ref> in the Examiner, has got into
               the Times, &amp; puts in all the poison there, greatly to Stoddarts discomfort, &#8211; who
               I believe would get out of it, if he could find any other means of employing himself
               so well for the public &amp; himself.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John
                  Walter (1776&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), the proprietor of <title>The
                  Times</title>, had been, since 1815, employing Thomas Barnes (1785&#8211;1841;
                     <title>DNB</title>) to tone down the intemperate Toryism of the leading
                  articles written by Stoddart, the paper&#8217;s editor. After Stoddart was dismissed, at
                  the end of 1816, Barnes became editor from 1817&#8211;1841. He had previously
                  contributed articles to Hunt&#8217;s papers, the <title>Examiner</title> and <title>The
                     Reflector</title>. </note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Sir Tarquin</ref>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Hazlitt had, early in 1817, republished a number of
                  his essays for the<title> Examiner</title> in a book with the Arthurian title
                     <title>The Round Table</title>. These included his critical &#8216;Observations&#8217; on
                  Wordsworth&#8217;s 1814 poem <title>The Excursion</title>. In the Arthurian legends, Sir
                  Tarquin was a treacherous knight who fought against his former friends. Southey
                  and Coleridge considered themselves betrayed by Hazlitt, having hosted him at
                  Greta Hall in 1803 and assisted him in escaping from the anger of the townsfolk
                  after he caused a furore in a Keswick inn by spanking a local woman when she
                  laughed at his advances. Hazlitt had married Sarah Stoddart (1774&#8211;1843) in 1808;
                  he and his brother-in-law were on very poor terms.</note> has married his sister,
               &#8211; a worthy couple, &#8211; they quarrel, fight, make it up over the gin bottle, &amp; get
               drunk together. {Stoddart <hi rend="ital">paid</hi> him for a paper for his first
               number, &amp; the said <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Tarquin</ref> has postponed the paper sine die, as might have been expected.}</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Quarterly &#8211; I write to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Grand Murray</ref> concerning the Opus.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">This pamphlet or book on the &#8216;State of the Nation&#8217; was
                  not published; Southey did, though, write on &#8216;Parliamentary Reform&#8217; in
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (October 1816), 225&#8211;278, and the &#8216;Rise and
                  Progress of Popular Disaffection&#8217; in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 16 (January
                  1817), 511&#8211;552.</note> The Opus will be more compleat if I embody in it some
               things from the Review &amp; some from the Register,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had written on contemporary events in the <title>Edinburgh
                     Annual Register, for 1808 to 1811</title> (1810&#8211;1813).</note> &#8211; &amp; for the
               former his persuasion is <del>x</del> necessary. In this case he must be sole
               publisher, upon my usual terms of half profit. I have a great deal to say, &amp;
               shall make a noise in the world.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The instance of folly which you tell me is stupendous. Gracious God
               are there men so little sensible that there is some <hi rend="ital">truth</hi> in
               Jacobinism, &#8211; that <del>the</del> inequality, in the degree in which it exists is a
               real &amp; grievous evil, &#8211; &amp; that the Bank is tempting enough to a mob with
               empty pockets!<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A large pro-reform public
                  meeting was held at Spa Fields, London, on 2 December 1816, addressed by veteran
                  radical Henry &#8216;Orator&#8217; Hunt (1773&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>). Some of the crowd,
                  breaking away from the meeting and moving to attack the Tower of London and Bank
                  of England, were confronted by troops at the Royal Exchange. </note> &#8211; If nothing
               of more worth than such noodle heads as these were at stake, it would be of very
               little consequence which way the game went: &#8211; I shall make them stare with my book.
               &#8220;Very odd this &#8211; some of this is very true, &#8211; strange that we should not have thought
               of it, &#8211; a singular man this M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> S. &#8211; a little visionary in some
               things, &#8211; but then his principles are excellent.&#8221; This thing they will say of the man
               who says Spend spend &amp; God will send,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">An
                  old proverb, dating at least to the 16th century.</note> &#8211; &amp; takes the Bull, &#8211;
               the mad Bull by the horns for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What mystery can there be in Christabel;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Coleridge had, after eighteen years, published &#8216;Christabel&#8217; in
                  1816, in a volume entitled <title>Christabel: Kubla Khan, A Vision; The Pains of
                     Sleep</title>.</note> &#8211; more than in any other story which is left half-told??
               &#8211; half-telling has <del>xxxx</del> excited <del>that</del> {great} interest for
                  <del>Chaucer</del> the Squires Tale,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In
                  Geoffrey Chaucer (c. 1343&#8211;1400; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Canterbury
                     Tales</title> the Squire&#8217;s Tale is interrupted by the Franklin, who proceeds to
                  tell his own tale. </note> which to my mind <del>o</del> is one of the least
               promising in Chaucer. The Christabel is very beautiful, &#8211; &amp; you wonder how it
               would be explained.</p>
        <p rend="center"> ___</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How have you misunderstood me about <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>? he offered me 100 &#163; for an article
               upon Foreign Travellers. He sent me 105 &#163; for that article &amp; for Ali Bey; &#8211; both
               being specified in the draft.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">In
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 537&#8211;574, Southey reviewed a
                  series of works by travellers in England, under the title &#8216;Works on England&#8217;. His
                  review of &#8216;Ali Bey&#8217; Domingo Badia y Leblich (1766&#8211;1818), <title>Travels of Ali Bey
                     in Morocco, Tripoli, Cyprus, Egypt, Arabia, Syria, and Turkey, Between the
                     Years 1803 and 1807</title> (1816) also appeared in <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 15 (July 1816), 299&#8211;345. </note> On my remonstrance he sent 45
               &#163; more, making 100 for one; 50 for the other. I am no hard bargainer, but I did not
               chuse to be treated thus. He is very sore, offers largely &amp; talks about <hi rend="ital">friendship</hi>. He is a bookseller, &#8211; aye every inch a bookseller,
               &amp; as such I like him well. And writing to him upon business I write <hi rend="ital">more meo</hi>
          <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;In my own
                  style&#8217;.</note> without reserve, but as for the friendship of the concern &#8211;
               pardonnez moi Monsieur! I am very willing to write for his money, &#8211; to engage with
               him as a publisher; &#8211; &amp; when it lies in my way to be of any use to him. But my
               friendships are not made of such materials &#8211; nor with such men.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The young ones having learnt from the Courier that there is a book of
               juvenile calibre about the Lioness &amp; the Exeter Mail, are clamorous for it.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">On the night of 20 October 1816 one of the
                  horses pulling the mail coach from Exeter to London was attacked by a lioness
                  which had escaped from a menagerie. The passengers took fright; the horse was
                  injured; and the lioness was captured. The unlikely incident became the subject of
                  prints, newspaper reports and the children&#8217;s book, <title>The Blue Caravan; or,
                     the Salisbury Lioness. A Poem for the Nursery</title> (1816). It had been
                  advertised in the <title>Courier</title>, 6 December 1816. Southey requests a copy
                  of it here. </note> &#8211; When you see it in a shop window buy it I pray you, &amp;
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> will frank it
               down</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Vale Vale<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;Farewell,
                     farewell&#8217;.</note> &#8211;</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">
            <date when="1816-12-13">13 Dec. 1816.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="center">1</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center">Europe had suffered </l>
            <l rend="center">Too long in Algiers</l>
            <l rend="center">The cries of the captives</l>
            <l rend="center">Their wrongs &amp; their tears: &#8211;</l>
            <l rend="center">Too long had she let</l>
            <l rend="center">Your marauders go free,</l>
            <l rend="center">Tunis &amp; Tripoly,</l>
            <l rend="center">Pests of the Sea</l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="center">2</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center">Till the Queen of the Ocean</l>
            <l rend="center">Aroused by fresh wrong</l>
            <l rend="center">Awakened the wrath</l>
            <l rend="center">Which had slumbered too long,</l>
            <l rend="center">Then did the voice of war</l>
            <l rend="center">Speak from the deck&#8217;s mouth</l>
            <l rend="center">Liberty! Liberty! </l>
            <l rend="center">England &amp; Exmouth.</l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="center">3</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center">The flag of the Dutchman</l>
            <l rend="center">Waved there on the wind</l>
            <l rend="center">That day in its triumph</l>
            <l rend="center">With the Red Cross combin&#8217;d</l>
            <l rend="center">In faith, &amp; in freedom</l>
            <l rend="center">And valour allied,</l>
            <l rend="center">Oh never may Fortune</l>
            <l rend="center">Their friendship divide!</l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="center">4</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center">Hoist the banner of joy</l>
            <l rend="center">On the rock of Gibralter!</l>
            <l rend="center">Let Spain sing thanksgiving</l>
            <l rend="center">And light up the altar</l>
            <l rend="center">And vows of deliverance</l>
            <l rend="center">Be rendered in Rome</l>
            <l rend="center">For England hath sent them</l>
            <l rend="center">Their prisoners home.</l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="center">5</p>
          <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="center">Mothers of Italy</l>
            <l rend="center">Lift up your voice!</l>
            <l rend="center">Daughters of Sicily</l>
            <l rend="center">Sing &amp; rejoice!</l>
            <l rend="center">Sing the praises of England</l>
            <l rend="center">The free &amp; the brave;</l>
            <l rend="center">For England hath broken</l>
            <l rend="center">The chains of the slave.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">On 27 August 1816, in an attempt to put an end to piracy in the
                        Mediterranean and to the enslavement of captured Europeans, an Anglo-Dutch
                        fleet under the command of Admiral Edward Pellew, 1st Viscount Exmouth
                        (1757&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>) bombarded the port of Algiers. The action
                        caused the Dey of Algiers to release about 1200 slaves and to sign of a
                        treaty undertaking to end the practice. </note>
            </l>
          </lg>
          <p rend="center">______</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>