<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2830</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4101</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2830. Robert Southey to Chauncy Hare Townshend, 17 August 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2830.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850) .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 193&#8211;195.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2830" type="letter">
        <head>2830. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy Hare Townshend</ref>, <date when="1816-08-17">17 August 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and
                     Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850)<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.),
                     <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 193&#8211;195.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-08-17">August 17. 1816.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute rend="indent0"> My dear Chauncey,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was from home for a few days&#8217; absence when your letter arrived. I have seen too many instances of unjust
               prepossession to be surprised at them now. Much of my early life was embittered by them when I was about your age; and in later years I
               have been disinherited by two uncles in succession, for no other assignable or possible reason than the caprice of weak minds and
               misgoverned tempers.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey, and his surviving brothers, had not benefitted from the Wills of
                  two wealthy, paternal uncles: <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref> (d. 1806) and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southey</ref> (d. 1811).</note> In this manner was I deprived of a good property,
               which the ordinary course of law would have given me. These things never robbed me of a moment&#8217;s tranquillity, &#8211; never in the slightest
               degree affected my feelings and spirits, nor ever mingled with my dreams. There is little merit in regarding such things with such
               philosophy. I suffered no loss, no diminution of any one enjoyment, and should have despised myself if anything so merely external and
               extraneous could have disturbed me. It is not in the heel, but in the heart, that I am vulnerable; and in the heart I have now been
               wounded: how deeply.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s son, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">Herbert</ref>, had died on 17 April 1816.</note> He only who sees the heart can tell.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Whenever you come I shall rejoice to see you. Do not, however, wind up your expectations too high. In many things I
               may, in some things I must, disappoint the ideal which you have formed. No man has ever written more faithfully from his heart; but my
               manners have not the same habitual unreserve as my pen. A disgust at the professions of friendship and feeling and sentiment in those
               who have neither the one nor the other, has, perhaps, insensibly led me to an opposite extreme; and in wishing rather <hi rend="ital">esse quam videri</hi>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;To be, rather than seem [to be]&#8217;.</note> I may sometimes have
               appeared what I am not. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I would not have you look on to the University with repugnance or dread.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Townshend entered Trinity Hall, Cambridge in 1816, graduating with a B.A. in 1821.</note> My college years were the least
               beneficial and the least happy of my life; but this was owing to public and private circumstances, utterly unlike those in which you
               will be placed. The comfort of being domesticated with persons whom you love, you will miss and feel the want of. In other respects,
               the change will bring with it its advantages. To enter at college, is taking a degree in life, and graduating as a man. I am not sure
               that there would be either schools or universities in a Utopia of my creation; in the world as it is, both are so highly useful, that
               the man who has not been at a public school and at college feels his deficiency as long as he lives. You renew old acquaintances at
               college; you confirm early intimacies. Probably, also, you form new friendships at an age when they are formed with more judgment, and
               are therefore likely to endure. And one who has been baptized in the springs of Helicon,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A
                  mountain in Greece, reputed to be the home of the Muses; the reference is to Townshend&#8217;s ambitions as a poet.</note> is in no danger
               of falling into vice, in a place where vice appears in the most disgusting form.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">There is a paper of mine in the last Quarterly, upon the means of bettering the condition of the poor. You will be
               interested by a story which it contains of an old woman upon Exmoor.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> &#8216;On the Poor&#8217;, published
                  in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 15 (April 1816), 187&#8211;235. The story of a 76 year-old woman who lived alone, after the death
                  of her &#8216;idiot&#8217;, illegitimate daughter, in a hovel on Exmoor, her miserable condition and &#8216;vehement grief&#8217; exacerbated by her lack of
                  religious faith, is related at 231&#8211;232. </note> In <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref>
               blank-verse it would go to every heart. Have you read The Excursion? and have you read the collection of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref> other poems, in two octavo volumes?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Wordsworth&#8217;s <title>The Excursion</title> (1814), and <title>Poems: Including Lyrical Ballads, and the Miscellaneous Pieces
                     of the Author; with Additional Poems, a new Preface, and a Supplementary Essay</title> (1815).</note> If you have not, there is a
               great pleasure in store for you. I am no blind admirer of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>, and
               can see where he has chosen subjects which are unworthy in themselves, and where the strength of his imagination and of his feeling is
               directed upon inadequate objects. Notwithstanding these faults, and their frequent occurrence, it is by the side of Milton<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>).</note> that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> will have his station awarded him by posterity. God bless you!</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3"> R.S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>