<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3030</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4301</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3030. Robert Southey to John May,
                  13 October 1817</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3030" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3030.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Harry Ransom Humanities
                  Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published:
                  Charles Ramos (ed.), The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                     1797&#8211;1838 (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 159&#8211;162; Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 278&#8211;282 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3030" type="letter">
        <head>3030. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>,
                  <date when="1817-10-13">13 October 1817</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Richmond/ Surrey<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmarks:
                  E/ 16 OC 16/ 1817; [partial ]o&#8217;Clock/ OC/16/ 1817 F.N.<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />
                  Watermark: B. E. &amp; S. Bath 1814<lb /> Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 196
                  1817/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> October/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Nov.<lb /> MS: Harry Ransom Humanities
                  Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published:
                  Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May:
                     1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 159&#8211;162; Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 278&#8211;282 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The notion of writing again that letter which the rascal Louis
               destroyed at Geneva,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suspected the
                  letter that he had written to John May from Geneva on 4 June 1817 had been
                  destroyed by his guide, Louis Clerc, to whom he it gave it to post, so that Clerc
                  could keep the postage money.</note> has I verily believe repeatedly prevented me
               from beginning one in the natural order of things. I can place myself at Thebes or at
               Athens in my vocation, &#8211; dive into Padalon<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Padalon is the world of the dead in Southey&#8217;s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>
                  (1810).</note> or scale Mount Calasay,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  residence of Seeva in <title>The Curse of Kehama</title>.</note> &#8211; but to remember
               what I then wrote, farther than the journal which you have seen might remind me of
               the facts, is beyond my power. Let us see however what can be done, with as little
               repetition as possible of what you have taken the trouble to decypher.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In speaking of Paris I probably might have remarked what an
               out-of-door life is led by the inhabitants, &amp; how prodigiously busy those people
               are who have nothing to do. There is more stir &amp; bustle than in London, &amp; of
               a very different character; <del>xx</del> in London they bear the <del>xxx</del>
               stamp of business, &#8211; you see that the crowds who pass by you in Cheapside have some
               thing to do something to think of; &#8211; &amp; in Paris you see as clearly that
               restlessness &amp; dissipation bring people into the street, because they have
               nothing to do at home. Nothing is more frequent in the suburbs than inscriptions at
               public gardens &amp; hotels to this purport <hi rend="ital">Ici on fait des
                  noces</hi>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Weddings performed
                  here&#8217;.</note> This is as common as &#8216;funerals performed&#8217; in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I should think France decidedly inferiour to England in beauty of
               country: yet I did not find the scenery altogether so uninteresting as I had been
               taught to expect. Picardy has much historical interest to an Englishman, &amp;
               perhaps the recollection of great events sometimes made me enjoy scenes which might
               also have been insipid. For I thought of Commines,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Philippe de Commines (1447&#8211;1511), a diplomat in the courts of
                  Burgundy and France. His <title>M&#233;moires</title>, first published in 1524,
                  detailed the major historical events in which he had played a part. Southey
                  possessed an English translation of 1674 (no. 701 in the sale catalogue of his
                  library).</note> of the struggle between Burgundy &amp; France, &#8211; &amp; in tracts
               where there was little more than earth &amp; sky to be seen I remembered that that
               same earth had been trodden by our countrymen before the battles of Cressy &amp;
                  Agincourt<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">At the battles of Cr&#233;cy (26
                  August 1346) and Agincourt (25 October 1415) the English won notable victories
                  over the French. </note> &amp; that that same sky had seen their victory. The
               towns also have many interesting antiquities, where an antiquarian <del>xxx</del>
               artist would find enough to employ him. The rivers have a magnitude &amp; majesty to
               be found in few English streams: on the other hand there is a want of wood, or of
               variety of wood; &#8211; poplars give a sameness to the scene &amp; a sort of sickly
               colouring, very different from the deep foliage of our oaks &amp; elms. &#8211; The very
               general custom of housing the cattle is unfavourable to the appearance of the
               country; <del>you xxx xx</del> there is a want of life &amp; motion &amp; sound. I
               believe also that there are fewer birds than in England &#8211; I scarcely remember to have
               seen a crow, or a bird of prey. The most beautiful part of France which we saw
               (except the Jura country which has a Swiss character) was French Flanders, &#8211; which is
               indeed exceedingly beautiful. The country from Lisle to St Omers may vie with the
                  <del>xx</del> richest parts of England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> John Audry<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry
                  (1766&#8211;1844), solicitor in Reybridge and husband of Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither
                  (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife, Catherine.</note> was much
               disappointed with the South of France, &#8211; perhaps this was because he entered it from
               Switzerland &amp; Savoy, &#8211; but the features as he described them were naturally
               unfavourable. The country upon the Loire has been much extolled. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> told me it had the same fault
               which I had observed in other parts, a pale &amp; monotonous colouring from the
               poplars, which was not relieved by vineyards, &amp; in summer by the <del>xxx</del>
               sands which the river then left bare.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We came upon a fine country as we approached Besan&#231;on, &#8211; the air of
               the Jura mountains seemed congenial to <del>my xxxx</del> me, &amp; if I did not look
               upon the people with some partiality because they were mountaineers, they were a
               better race in many respects than the <del>xx</del> natives of Burgundy &amp;
               Champagne. Were I to visit Switzerland again I should wish to see more of the Jura. I
               do not think that a traveller can <del>xx</del> enter Switzerland in any better
               direction than by way of Pontarlier &amp; Neuchatel. If the wine of this latter
               territory could reach England I should think it would have a great sale, for it has
               the flavour of Burgundy &amp; the body of Port.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The quality of Neuchatel&#8217;s red wines (grown from the pinot noir
                  grape, as are many wines from Burgundy) were much commented on by travellers in
                  the early nineteenth century. Wine duties were not reduced until 1825.</note> If
               the duties are lowered (as I understand they are likely to be) it will find its way
               here by the Rhine.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We amused ourselves sometimes with talking of the great good to be
               effected by a Missionary Society for instructing the French &amp; the other rational
               nations in certain acts &amp; decencies of life with which they are unacquainted. As
               they would have much to learn even in cookery. Sir W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Curtis<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir William Curtis (1752&#8211;1829;
                     <title>DNB</title>), MP for the City of London 1790&#8211;1818 and 1820&#8211;1826, where
                  he was a prominent figure as an Alderman 1785&#8211;1829. His large girth and reputed
                  appetite at City functions made him the subject of many cartoons. </note> was to
               be Patron of the proposed society. We should have something to learn from them in
               return, on this art, but it would be doing them a signal service to instruct them in
               roasting &amp; boiling, &#8211; texts upon which the Missionary should be charged
               frequently to dwell, he should preach also upon pastry, &amp; lecture upon Apple
               dumplins. He should convert them to the use of carpets, &amp; expound water closets
               earnestly exhorting the unclean generation to profit by his discourse. If the general
               use of tea could be introduced also <del>xxx</del> it might prove a general benefit.
               A French breakfast has neither the comfort, nor the domestic character of an English
               one, &#8211; he gets it better at Restaurateurs or an hotel than at home. But domestic
               habits are what are wanting in France, &amp; if it were the fashion to drink tea,
               they would be very much promoted by it. In Morocco tea is rapidly superseding the use
               of coffee, &#8211; I do not know why it <del>xxx</del> is so little liked upon the
               continent of Europe, when among us it has become one of the first necessaries of
               life. &#8211; We tried it sometimes, but scarcely ever with success, &amp; it is curious
               enough that we never on any occasion met with cream, except at one Chalet in
               Switzerland which is famous for it: neither in France, Switzerland, Italy Germany or
               the Netherlands, rich in dairies as all these countries are, do the inhabitants
               appear ever to use it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Perhaps I described the Lakes of Neuchatel &amp; Geneva in my lost
               letter, &amp; the abominable odour of the great city of Calvinism:<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The established church in Geneva, the Protestant
                  Church of Geneva, followed the doctrines of the French theologian, Jean Calvin
                  (1509&#8211;1564), who was long resident in the city.</note> but this you have seen in
               my journal. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your god
                  daughter</ref> is making the extracts from it, &amp; I shall find means of
                  <del>sen</del> conveying them in a frank. Since my return we have had much
               company, &amp; in consequence I have been led into much idleness. Winter is now
               setting in, altho the weather continues fine; the days are shortening fast, long
               evenings will confine me to my desk, &amp; the retirement which this place affords
               during the dark season is such that I am in no danger of being disturbed. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present I am finishing a paper upon Lope de Vega for the next
                  Quarterly,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In the <title>Quarterly
                     Review</title>, 18 (October 1817), 1&#8211;46, Southey reviewed Lord Holland,
                     <title>Some Account of the Lives and Writings of Lope Felix de Vega Carpio, and
                     Guillen de Castro</title> (1817).</note> &amp; preparing the first chapter of
               the Peninsular war for the press.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                     <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (1823&#8211;1832).</note> An
               influenza has gone thro the house, I had it slightly, the children with more or less
               violence. at present, thank God, all are well. The season cannot be finer, tho the
               cold is a little premature. &#8211; The sale of <ref type="m" target="places.html#GretaHall">the property</ref>
          <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Greta Hall, of which Southey was the tenant, was sold in June 1817
                  to Isaac Fisher (c. 1773&#8211;1819), a member of a Borrowdale farming family and a gold
                  and silversmith in Cockspur Street, London. However, legal complications arising
                  from the previous landlord&#8217;s debts had halted the purchase. The injunction
                  halting the sale had been granted by John Scott, 1st Earl of Eldon (1751-1838;
                  <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1801-1806, 1807-1827.</note> is stopped by an injunction
               from the Chancellor, &amp; I have been plagued in various ways about the rent, &amp;
               certain annuities which are charged upon the estate. After much consideration &amp;
               conciliation I have paid the former to the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WoodSara">mortgagee</ref>, &amp; I have since been
               distrained upon for annuities in advance of the next half year. When the business
               will be settled nobody knows. &#8211; I have heard nothing of my books from abroad:<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Books purchased during Southey&#8217;s visit to the
                  continent in May&#8211;August 1817.</note> but hope that <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will learn something
               concerning them, on his return to town. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; your daughters<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Charlotte (b. 1804), Susanna Louisa (1805&#8211;1885) and Charlotte
                  Livius (b. 1812).</note> &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1817-10-13"> 13 Oct. 1817</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>