<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title><title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title><author><name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name></author><editor>Lynda Pratt</editor><sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Neil Fraistat</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>General Editor, </resp><name>Steven E. Jones</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Technical Editor</resp><name>Laura Mandell</name></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2013-05-27</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3187</idno><idno type="nines">rce4458</idno><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><availability status="restricted"><p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p><p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p><p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list><item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item><item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item></list></p><p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><biblStruct><analytic><title type="main" level="a">3187. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 6 September 1818</title><author role="primary"><persName><forename>Robert</forename><surname>Southey</surname></persName></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title><title level="s">Electronic Editions</title><imprint><publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher><pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace><date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date><biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3187.html</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), Life
                     and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV,
                  pp. 310–311 [in part].</p><p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p><p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p><p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><quotation><p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="none"><p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p><p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p><p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p></hyphenation><normalization method="markup"><p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p><p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p></normalization><normalization><p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p><p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p><p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p></normalization></editorialDecl><classDecl><taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g"><bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl><category xml:id="g1"><catDesc>Architecture</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g2"><catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g3"><catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g4"><catDesc>Collection</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g5"><catDesc>Criticism</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g7"><catDesc>Letters</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g6"><catDesc>Drama</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g8"><catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g9"><catDesc>Politics</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g10"><catDesc>Folklore</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g11"><catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g12"><catDesc>Fiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g13"><catDesc>History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g14"><catDesc>Leisure</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g15"><catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g16"><catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g17"><catDesc>Humor</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g18"><catDesc>Education</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g19"><catDesc>Music</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g20"><catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g21"><catDesc>Paratext</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g22"><catDesc>Perodical</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g23"><catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g24"><catDesc>Photograph</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g25"><catDesc>Citation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g26"><catDesc>Family Life</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g27"><catDesc>Poetry</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g28"><catDesc>Religion</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g29"><catDesc>Review</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g30"><catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g31"><catDesc>Translation</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g32"><catDesc>Travel</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g33"><catDesc>Book History</catDesc></category><category xml:id="g34"><catDesc>Law</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml"><category xml:id="people"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc></category></taxonomy><taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml"><category xml:id="places"><catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc></category></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27"/><catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html"/><catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html"/></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1"><label>Changed by</label><name>David Rettenmaier</name><list><item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item></list></change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div n="3187" type="letter"><head>3187. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1818-09-06">6 September 1818</date><note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
                  Postmark: E/ 9 SE 9/ 1818<lb/> Endorsements: 6 Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1818; 6
                     Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1818<lb/> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47.
                  ALS; 4p.<lb/> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life
                     and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849–1850), IV,
                  pp. 310–311 [in part].</note></head><opener><salute> My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener><p rend="indent1"> If you had written to me in extenuation as you term it, I should have
               been as nearly angry with you, as any thing could make me: – for how could I possibly
               attribute any thing which you had said to any motive but the right one, – or
               wherefore should I be more displeased with you for not liking <del>the</del> my
               intended epistle,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had sent Bedford
                  a draft of the first part of his pamphlet criticising Brougham. As the
                     <title>Courier</title> reported on 4 July, Brougham, campaigning for the
                  parliamentary seat of Westmorland against the candidates favoured by Wordsworth’s
                  patron the Earl of Lonsdale, had spoken at the hustings at Appleby on 30 June,
                  attacking both Southey and Wordsworth. Southey was dissuaded from publishing the
                  retort that he discusses here. Part of it finally appeared as a ‘Postscript’ to
                  the second edition of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (London, 1821), pp.
                  45–53.</note><del>xx</del> more than you were with me for not liking your Dalinatian or Damnation
               wine: the roughness of the one did not <del>ple</del> suit my palate, nor the
               asperity of the other your taste. And what of that? I dare say you think quite as
               favourably of your wine as before, &amp; I am not a whit the less satisfied with my
               style objurgatory. But let that pass. </p><p rend="indent1"> I hope you have bought <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref> views of the Caves.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall’s collection of engravings <title>Views of the Caves near Ingleton in
                     Yorkshire</title> (London, 1818) combined several engraving techniques to
                  create effects of light and shade.</note> When you come into this country next you
               must see the<del>xx</del> Cave country, &amp; I will go with you. &amp; D Manuel
               Alvarez Espriella shall be of the party, &amp; keep a journal.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not produce a sequel to his
                     <title>Letters from England: By Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title>
                  (1807).</note> So bear this in mind &amp; consider it as an engagement. </p><p rend="indent1"> In the midst of daily &amp; almost hourly interruptions I am getting
               on with Brazil in such a way as to be tolerably well contented with the quantum of my
                  labours.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>History of
                     Brazil</title> (1810–1819).</note> But I can hardly call a single hour my own.
               Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#LloydCharles">Lloyd</ref> is in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &amp; I hope the better for being
               here, &amp; for feeling himself treated exactly as he used to be, with no reference
               to his malady, – over which he has a perfect controul. It is a pitiable &amp; strange
               derangement, – for his intellect was never clearer, nor his conversation more
               interesting, or <del>xxxxxx</del> {more} discriminating &amp; acute, at any time of
               his life. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General</ref> too is arrived, &amp; the Beaumonts<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady Beaumont</ref>.</note> are
               here, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref> is coming. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> brought <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Ld Lowther</ref> here two
               days ago to pass the evening. And not a week passes without sundry Lakers each with
               his Letter. By the by your Frenchman<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> has given me the go by. He was at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Lowtherestate">Lowther</ref> some weeks ago, &amp;
               said he was coming here, – but non est inventus.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘He is not found’.</note></p><p rend="indent1"> Roderic is going to press for a fifth edition.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths </title>(1814). The 5th
               edition appeared in 1818.</note> When I see the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Long
                  Men</ref> I shall talk to them about the prudence of trying one of my
               poems in a cheap form, close printing without the notes, so as to sell for three or
               four shillings, &amp; find its way into all country shops. I do not think it would in
               any degree interfere with the sale of the other edition, – but I believe that a great
               many would sell among persons who cannot or will not afford 16/<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.
               &amp; that we should not only gain by this sale, but indirectly by the good effect of
               popularizing my writings.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">This plan was not
                  realized.</note> Kehama<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The 4th edition
                  of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810) also appeared in 1818.</note> also is
               in the press – for the fourth time, but the editions have been smaller than those of
               Roderick. Of Roderick the editions were <del>1</del> 500, 1500, 2000, 2000. Of Kehama
               only 2500 in all. I do not wonder at the difference, – it is as it ought to be, &amp;
               yet Kehama is the greater work, &amp; that by which I shall be known as a creative
               poet.</p><p rend="indent1"> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Maximus Murray</ref> had left much
               of his greatness in Albemarle Street, – notwithstanding he came in his own carriage.
               He brought with him a brother Bibliopole – <ref type="m" target="people.html#BlackwoodWilliam">Blackwood</ref> of Edinburgh,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray had taken a stake in the <title>Edinburgh Monthly Magazine</title>,
                  which had started publication on 1 April 1817 and was run by William Blackwood.
                  The seventh number was retitled <title>Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</title>
                  (1817–1980).</note> – they were full of his (<ref type="m" target="people.html#BlackwoodWilliam">Blackwoods</ref>) Magazine, in which <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has engaged; – I let them talk &amp; throw
               out their hooks, gave them a dinner, &amp; set them off well pleased with their
               entertainment; in which no hospitality had been wanting, &amp; nothing had been said
               to put them out of humour with themselves &amp; their own projects.</p><p rend="indent1"> I have just purchased <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> B
                  Jonson.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Gifford’s <title>The
                     Works of Ben Jonson ...: With Notes Critical and Explanatory, and a
                     Biographical Memoir</title> (1816), no. 1529 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s
                  library: an edition of the works of the dramatist and poet, Ben Jonson (1572–1637;
                     <title>DNB</title>).</note> He supposes that the Laureate continues to receive
               his tierce<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">An early modern measure of
                  volume, equal to forty-two gallons. This perquisite was converted into an
                  additional annual payment of £27 by Southey’s predecessor, Henry James Pye
                  (1745–1813; <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate 1790–1813. Gifford, <title>The
                     Works of Ben Jonson</title>, 9 vols (London, 1816), I, pp. cliv–clv, stated
                  that Jonson received ‘a tierce of Canary, (Jonson’s favourite wine,) which has
                  been continued to his successors, and of which the first glass should, in
                  gratitude, be offered by them to the poet’s memory’.</note> of Spanish Canary,
               &amp; recommends him yearly to drink to old Ben in the first glass. Tell him if he
               will get me reinstated in my proper rights, I will drink to Ben Jonson not once a
               year, but once a day, &amp; to him also. – By the manner of which he speaks of
               Sidneys Arcadia<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Philip Sidney
                  (1554–1586; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Countess of Pembroke’s Arcadia</title>
                  (1590) was a favourite work of Southey’s. Gifford, <title>The Works of Ben
                     Jonson</title>, 9 vols (London, 1816), I, p. cxxii, reported the idea that
                  Sidney had intended to transpose the action of Arcadia to the Court of King
                  Arthur.</note> I conclude that either he has never read the book, or has totally
               forgotten it. </p><p rend="indent1"> So you are to have a Palace Yard Meeting tomorrow<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Public meetings often occurred in Palace Yard,
                  outside Westminster Hall. The meeting on 7 September 1818 was a radical gathering,
                  urging the people ‘to take into consideration the propriety of making a public
                  declaration of their rights’.</note>; – so few weeks have elapsed since Hunt<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry ‘Orator’ Hunt (1773–1835;
                     <title>DNB</title>), the radical reformer, was the main speaker at the Palace
                  Yard meeting.</note> was beaten &amp; blackguarded in the face of the mob, till
               his own miscreants hooted at him, – &amp; yet you see he is in full feather
                  again.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Hunt had been a radical
                  candidate for the Westminster constituency in the 1818 general election. However,
                  he received only 84 votes and found himself jeered and jostled by the Westminster
                  mob, which feared his candidature would split the anti-government vote and lead to
                  the defeat of the Whig candidates, Sir Francis Burdett and Sir Samuel Romilly
                  (1757–1818; <title>DNB</title>).</note> This fellow ought to be tried for
               sedition, – he would certainly be found guilty, <del>xxxx</del> for the jury as yet
               would be nothing worse than <ref type="m" target="people.html#Burdett">Burdettite</ref>,
               &amp; therefore disposed to give him his deserts. And during the time of his
               confinement he should be restricted to prison diet, kept from all intercourse with
               visitors – &amp; left to amuse himself with the Bible, the Prayer Book,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Book of Common Prayer</title> (1662)
                  detailing daily forms of worship in Anglican Churches.</note> &amp; Drelincourt
               upon death<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Drelincourt
                  (1595–1669), <title>The Christian’s Defense against the Fears of Death</title>
                  (1651).</note> – or the Whole Duty of Man<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">An anonymous devotional work of 1658.</note> for his whole Library. At the
               end of two years he would come out cured. </p><p rend="indent1"><del>Do you not let xx</del> Have you paid the worthy Israelite to whom I am indebted
               so much on the score of civility, that part of the debt which consists in a money
               account for freight, &amp; cartage?<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had enlisted the Jewish banker Nathan Mayer Rothschild (1777–1836;
                     <title>DNB</title>) to assist in the transit of the books he had bought in
                  Brussels in 1817. </note> – </p><closer><salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute><signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer><postscript><p><date when="1818-09-06">Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 6. 1818.</date></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>