<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2870</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4141</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2870. Robert Southey to William Wilberforce, 30
                  November 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.2870" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2870.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Not previously published.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2870" type="letter">
        <head>2870. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">William Wilberforce</ref>, <date when="1816-11-30">30
                  November 1816</date>
          </head><p>Address: [deletion and readdress in another hand] To/ W<hi rend="sup">m</hi>
                  Wilberforce Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi> M. P./ near/ <del>London</del>/ Hastings <lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb /> Postmark: FREE/ 3 DE
                  3/ 1816<lb /> Endorsement: Poet Southey/ Character of/ Portuguese<lb /> MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-11-30">30 Nov. 1816</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Henry Koster</ref> sailed on the 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of this month from Liverpool
               for Pernambuco, whither he is gone to establish a house of business. He will I have no doubt employ himself well upon the voyage, for
               he is indefatigable in what he undertakes, &amp; has the business of the Portugueze slave trade at heart. He has had some
               correspondence with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey
                  had recommended to Wilberforce that the African Institution should support Henry Koster in preparing a Portuguese translation of
                  Thomas Clarkson, <title>History of the Rise, Progress, and Accomplishment of the Abolition of the African Slave-Trade by the British
                     Parliament</title> (1808).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Bad as appearances may be, &amp; shocking as the conduct of the Portugueze slave captains is, I think Brazil will be
               the first country in which decisive measures will be taken for the abolition of slavery.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Despite
                  Southey&#8217;s hopes, the slave trade remained legal in Brazil until 1850 and slavery was not abolished until 1888.</note> Two classes of
               men are agreed upon this point, &#8211; the Liberales who conduct journals here in England, &#8211; &amp; influence all in Brazil who read,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In particular, the liberal <title>Correio Braziliense</title> (1808&#8211;1822), no. 3203 in the sale
                  catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, was anti-slave trade.</note> &amp; the priests whose influence extends over every body else. One
               great obstacle is the pride of the Portugueze. As we {are} the least national of any people under heaven, (for an English party, if it
               suited any party purpose would take up the cause of the Devil himself against their own country) &#8211; the Portugueze are the most so,
               &amp; whatever may be their principles, they unite instantly to resent the very shadow of a national offence. Hence it is that they who
               desire the abolition cannot brook the suspicion that it should be forced upon them, or demanded from their weakness. I wish you read
               their journals, &#8211; it is scarcely credible to what an excess this national sensibility is carried by them. &#8211; Pride &amp; weakness
               naturally produce suspicion, &amp; they have the vice of supposing that in all our efforts for the suppression of the abominable
               traffic there is some interested motive at the bottom. The two things needful are to undeceive them upon this point, which <ref type="m" target="people.html#KosterHenry">Koster</ref> will make his chief object, &#8211; &amp; to treat them with as much respect as
               possible; &#8211; &amp; indeed much respect is due to them; they have been a great people, &amp; a great people they must again become, for
               the finest part of the new world is their indefeasible portion. Instead of reproaching them directly for not following the example of
               England &amp; France in the abolition, I would <del>prai</del> extol them for having <del>xxx</del> set the example by destroying the
               Indian slave trade,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">That is, the trade in indigenous American peoples in Brazil, largely ended
                  during the eighteenth century (though it had been illegal since 1537).</note> &amp; represent what they have yet to do as the just
               &amp; legitimate consequences of the principles upon which they then acted.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Surely Spain cannot carry on the trade for herself;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spanish slave trade was
                  abolished in 1820, following a Treaty with Britain in 1817.</note> &#8211; she has no colonies in a state to require much importation of
               negroes, &#8211; the main<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The mainland parts of the Spanish Empire, bordering on the Caribbean. Most
                  of these areas were in revolt and had declared their independence.</note> is too disturbed, their part of S Domingo<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Today, the Dominican Republic, on the island of Hispaniola, the western part of which is occupied by
                  Haiti.</note> too poor, &#8211; &amp; Cuba far from flourishing. The root of the evil is in our own islands, &#8211; I cannot think of them
               without indignation. &#8211; The Registry Bill would reach it if its observance were honestly enforced, &#8211; but tho honesty grows plentifully
               in our English gardens, it <del>is not</del> does not flourish in the plantations,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Wilberforce
                  had proposed a Registry Bill in 1815 to set up a register of all slaves in the British West Indies. It had been virulently opposed
                  by the planters and they continued their opposition in 1816&#8211;1817. From 1817 onwards the West Indian colonies began passing their own
                  local Registration Acts, though these were largely ineffective.</note> &amp; in my judgement nothing will ever cut up the slave
               trade by the roots but fixing a time for the abolition of slavery itself.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Slavery in British
                  colonies was not abolished until 1833.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Pope<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Pius VII (1742&#8211;1823; Pope 1800&#8211;1823); in a letter of 20 September 1814
                  he had forbidden Catholics from arguing that the slave trade could be lawful. The Society of Jesus (restored by the Pope in 1814)
                  had long opposed the enslavement of indigenous peoples in South America.</note> &amp; the Jesuits would be the best allies</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I thank you much for your intention of procuring me a copy of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bowdlers works<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bowdler (1783&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Select Pieces in Verse and Prose</title> (1816),
                  no. 330 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; which I shall be very glad to possess: &#8211; they may come to me either
               thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> or <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref>, from
               whom I am continually receiving parcels.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am not without hopes of seeing you sometime in the early spring, when if my too numerous employments will allow me I
               may probably visit London. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Francis<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Clement Robert Francis (1792&#8211;1829),
                  clergyman, Fellow of Caius College, Cambridge and nephew of Southey&#8217;s friend, James Burney. Francis graduated in 1817. As
                  mathematics formed the major part of the B.A. degree at Cambridge, this may well have been the &#8216;science&#8217; he was studying of which
                  Southey disapproved.</note> gave me some hopes that you might pass a summer in this delightful country. I saw but little of him
               unfortunately because he took up his abode at a distance, &amp; I have no other means of conveyance than those which were given to
               Father Adam.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Walking &#8211; the only mode of transport available to Adam in
                  <title>Genesis</title>.</note> It is needless to say that I was much pleased with &amp; interested in him. But I was sorry
                  <del>him</del> to see him sacrificing his time to a science for which he has no predilection, &amp; which never can be of any
               service to those who dislike it.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> very truly &amp; respectfully yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>