<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3185</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4456</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3185. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 1 September 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3185" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3185.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Huntington Library, RS 351. ALS; 4p.
                  .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters
                     of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 95&#8211;96.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3185" type="letter">
        <head>3185. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>,<date when="1818-09-01"> 1 September 1818</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>
            <lb /> MS: Huntington Library, RS 351. ALS; 4p.<lb />
                  Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters
                     of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 95&#8211;96.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have just read thro Clarendons Hist: of the Rebellion,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A new edition, printed by Pople, of Edward Hyde,
                  1st Earl of Clarendon (1609&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the
                     Rebellion and Civil Wars in England</title> (1816).</note> &amp; the result has
               been rather to strengthen my hope in the conservative principles of society. If any
               thing could induce me to wish the Whigs in power, it would be their certain
               interference with the press, &amp; the probability of their undoing the mischief
               which <ref type="m" target="people.html#FoxCharlesJames">Fox</ref> did
               by making the Jury in cases of libel judges of the law as well as of the fact.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Libel Act of 1792, sponsored by Fox,
                  gave juries the chief responsibility to decide if a publication was libellous,
                  rather than leaving the matter mainly to the judge.</note> &#8211; <del>xx</del> Yet
               there has been as much fault in the manner of enforcing the laws, as in the law
               itself. So much time has been suffered to elapse between the commission of the
               offence &amp; the trial (as in <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoneWilliam">Hones</ref> case<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hone
                  was prosecuted in three separate trials on 18&#8211;20 December 1817 on the grounds that
                  his radical satires, which parodied the Church of England&#8217;s litany and the
                  Athanasian Creed, constituted blasphemous libel. The ex-officio information that
                  led to the trials had been filed as early as April 1817, though. Hone was
                  acquitted, following a notably &#8216;theatrical defence&#8217; mounted by himself, which
                  effectively mocked the judge, prosecuting counsel, and government.</note>) that
               the culprit has had full leisure to get up a theatrical defence, &amp; the public
                  <del>has</del> feeling of indignation has been <del>palli</del> worn out &amp;
               subsided into indifference.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your note about the Jerboa. I had made the same guess,
               but suppressed because of the difficulty of explaining how the Jerboa should get
               there, &#8211; being neither known in Europe nor in America, nor in those parts of Africa
               from whence any ship at any time had ever touched upon the Island.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The jerboa is a desert rodent from North Africa
                  and Asia. In <title>History of Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, p.
                  303, Southey discussed the island of Fernam de Noronha, off the Brazilian coast,
                  and the plague of rats that caused its Dutch settlers to abandon it in the 1630s.
                  In a note he speculated that the rats were actually jerboas.</note> However as
               your first thought coincided with mine I have mentioned the likelihood &amp; the
               difficulty. You see I am getting on well, &amp; with matter which will be almost as
               new to the Portugueze themselves as to the English. This chapter will be a very
               curious one: &amp; the following one relates to the Equestrian tribes.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Chapters 37&#8211;38 of the <title>History of
                     Brazil</title>, 3 vols (London, 1810&#8211;1819), III, pp. 299&#8211;441.</note> It is a
               great pleasure to perceive the end of so long a work fairly in view.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Can you send me the third Police &#8211; the Prison &#8211; &amp; the Endowed
               School Reports.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Select Committee on
                  the State of the Police of the Metropolis issued its third report in 1818 (printed
                  5 June 1818); the first and second Reports of the Select Committee State on the
                  State of the Prisons within the City of London and the Borough of Southwark
                  appeared in 1818; the Committee on the Education of the Lower Orders made five
                  reports on schools in 1818.</note> &#8211; I am about to write upon the
               Copy-right-question in the next Q.R., &#8211; &amp; also (taking the New Churches for a
               text), to put together my Collectanea concerning the disposal of the dead.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s article on the &#8216;Inquiry into the
                  Copyright Act&#8217; appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819),
                  196&#8211;219. Southey discussed new churches in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 23
                  (July 1820), 549&#8211;591, in a review of (among other things) Haydon&#8217;s <title>New
                     Churches, Considered with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the
                     Encouragement of Painting</title> (1818), and cemeteries in &#8216;Cemeteries and
                  Catacombs of Paris&#8217;, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819),
                  359&#8211;398.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1818-09-01"> 1 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.
                  1818.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1"> My brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> is coming at Lady Day<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">25 March 1819. Lady Day was a traditional day on which to
                     begin tenancies.</note> [MS torn] reside within an hours walk of me, &#8211; in the
                  vale of Newlands, &#8211; a very sweet place &#8211; where he takes 30 acres of land.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <ref type="m" target="places.html#EmeraldBank">Emerald Bank House</ref>.</note> This removal is in all respects
                  desirable for him &amp; for me, &amp; will at least double the quantum of my
                  yearly exercise.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>