<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2848</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4119</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2848. Robert Southey to John
                  Rickman, 2 October 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2848.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>.  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 213&#8211;215 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2848" type="letter">
        <head>2848. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John
                  Rickman</ref>, <date when="1816-10-02">2 October 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>.<lb /> Endorsement: 2 Oct<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1816<lb /> MS:
                  Huntington Library, RS 295. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert
                  Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols
                  (London, 1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 213&#8211;215 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1816-10-02">2 Oct. 1816.</date>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear R.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have received no further communications from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, &#8211; which is
               very well, as I must finish some few things &amp; rid my hands of them before I set
               seriously to work in the good cause.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford had conveyed to Southey the ministerial suggestion that he should
                  edit a pro-government journal.</note> Meantime the subject occupies my mind in all
               intervals of employment. Thank you for the papers: &#8211; when we talk these things over
               it will be found that you &amp; I shall not differ upon any material subject;
               concerning the extent &amp; nature of existing evils my estimates may perhaps be
               modified by your knowledge, &#8211; &amp; you will perhaps agree with me that Government
               will gain strength by correcting as far as possible acknowledged evils, &#8211; instead of
               letting the Anarchists have the advantage of enlisting good feelings on their side. &#8211;
               I shall take a wide range, &amp; I feel just now as if it were in my power to produce
               a work which, whatever might be its immediate effect, should be referred to hereafter
               as a faithful estimate of these times.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was contemplating a book on the &#8216;State of the Nation&#8217; &#8211; it was not
                  written.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#DavyHumphry">Davy</ref> was here last week
               &amp; told me a valuable fact. A friend of his who applying <del>xxxx</del>
               philosophical knowledge to practical purposes has turned manufacturer at
                  Clithero,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">James Thomson (1779&#8211;1850),
                  industrial chemist and co-owner of the Primrose Works, a calico factory near
                  Clitheroe, Lancashire. Thomson had, with Southey and Coleridge, been one of those
                  to inhale nitrous oxide under Davy&#8217;s supervision at the Bristol Pneumatic
                  Institution in 1799.</note> went abroad immediately after the peace, &#8211; not to seek
               for orders, but to examine with his own eyes the state of the manufacturers on the
               continent. He returned with a conviction that it was necessary to <del>reduce his
                  own</del> draw in; reduced his produce in time, &amp; in consequence is doing well
               while his neighbours are breaking all around. &#8211; Certain it is that manufactures, as
               depending upon machinery, advanced very rapidly on the continent during the last war:
               &#8211; no prohibitions &amp; no penalties however severe <hi rend="ital">can</hi> prevent
               machinery &amp; workmen from finding their way abroad; &#8211; <del>xxxx</del> to this we
               must make up our mind, &#8211; &amp; it is better that it should be so. &#8211; A little time
               sets these things to rights.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I incline to think that there will come a time when public
                  <del>opin</del> opinion will no more tolerate the extreme of poverty as existing
               in a large class of the community, than it now tolerates slavery in Europe. Meantime
               it is perfectly clear that the more we can improve the condition of the lower classes
               the greater number of customers we procure for the home market, &#8211; &amp; that if we
               can make people pay taxes &#8211; instead of claiming poor rates the wealth as well as the
               security of the State is increased. The poor rates <del>x</del> are a momentous
               subject, <del>in which</del> {&amp;} I have long believed you were the only man who
               could grapple with it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The fruits of
                  Rickman&#8217;s analysis appeared in &#8216;On the Poor Laws&#8217;,<title> Quarterly
                  Review</title>, 18 (January 1818), 259&#8211;308.</note> I see, or think I see
                  <del>x</del> palliations &amp; alterations, &#8211; in providing the labourers with
               garden &amp; grass land, &#8211; in establishing saving banks, in national education, &#8211;
                  <del>&amp;</del> in affording all possible facilities &amp; encouragement for
               emigration, &#8211; &amp; in colonizing at home upon our waste lands.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The state of the Church is another important question, &#8211; assailed as
               it is on all sides. I think it would be possible to take in the Methodists as a sort
               of Cossacks, &#8211; or certainly to employ those persons henceforward in aid of the
               establishment, who if not thus employed will swell the numbers of the Methodists
               &amp; act against them. There are no differences of doctrine in the way: it is but to
               let the licence<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Under the Toleration Act
                  (1689), Nonconformist Ministers had to obtain a license to preach from the local
                  magistrate and to have their names recorded by the Quarter Sessions. The only
                  legal requirement to obtain a license at this time was to swear the oaths of
                  allegiance and supremacy, which acknowledged the monarch as the lawful sovereign
                  and supreme head of the Church of England. </note> come from the Clergyman <del>as
                  x</del> instead of the Magistrate, &#8211; to invent some such name as Coadjutor for
               those who have &#8220;a call,&#8221; &#8211; let them catechise the children, conv<hi rend="ital">a</hi>rt the women, &#8211; reclaim the reprobates, &#8211; &amp; meet on week days or at
               extra hours on Sundays in the church to exhort &amp; sing psalms. &#8211; A little
               condescension, &#8211; a little pay &amp; a little flattery would do some good, &amp;
               prevent much mischief.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am now going to sit an hour with Lord Darnley<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Bligh, 4th Earl of Darnley (1767&#8211;1831;
                     <title>DNB</title>), a Whig peer whose seat was at Cobham Hall in Kent. </note>
               at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumonts</ref>, &#8211; &amp; shall turn the conversation
               upon the conduct of the <del>xx</del>
          <hi rend="ital"> Ultra-Whigs</hi> at Maidstone,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Maidstone was a particularly venal and hotly-contested borough. One of its
                  Whig MPs in 1806&#8211;1812 and 1818&#8211;1820 was George Longman (1773&#8211;1822), a wholesale
                  stationer and brother of Thomas Longman. In August 1816 the Whigs had adopted Sir
                  Robert Wilson (1777&#8211;1849; <title>DNB</title>) as a candidate, though he ultimately did not stand and
                  instead became MP for Southwark 1818&#8211;1831. Wilson had played a notable role in the
                  Peninsular War as commander of the Loyal Lusitanian Legion, but he fell out badly
                  with Wellington and became a radical. In April 1816 he was sentenced to three
                  months imprisonment in France for aiding the escape from prison of the Bonapartist
                  politician, Antoine-Marie Chamans de Lavalette (1769&#8211;1830).</note> &#8211; that by
               extracting some{thing} <del>xxxxxxxx xxxxxxxx</del> from the said [MS torn] of
               Ultra-Whiggish propensities I may derive <del>xxxxx</del> compensation for the
               sacrifice of precious time to civility.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> By nature I am a poet, &#8211; by deliberate choice an historian, &#8211; &amp; a
               political writer I know not how, &#8211; <del>rather</del> by accident, &#8211; or the course of
               events. Yet I think I can do something toward awakening the country, &amp; that I can
               obtain the confidence of well disposed minds by writing earnestly &amp; sincerely
               upon things in which all persons are concerned. &#8211; You mistake for <hi rend="ital">liberality</hi> what arose from <hi rend="ital">policy</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">prudence</hi>. Were I to accept a good birth, what <del>was</del> {is} held out
               to me &#8211; it would very much counteract the impression that I am aiming to
                  <del>xxxx</del> produce. Instead of attempting to answer my arguments &amp;
               accusations, the Anarch would become the assailants &amp; attack me as one who had
               sold himself. This I am willing enough to despise, &#8211; were it not for the mischief
               that it might do. Hereafter I should not refuse the remuneration to which I might
               feel entitled, &#8211; if it were offered in a form that I could accept.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>