<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.2738</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4009</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">2738. Robert Southey to Walter
                  Scott, 17 March 1816</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.2738.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>National Library
                  of Scotland, MS 3887. ALS; 4p. .  Previously  published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), Life &amp; Correspondence of Robert Southey, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 152&#8211;154 [in part].</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="2738" type="letter">
        <head>2738. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter
                  Scott</ref>, <date when="1816-03-17">17 March 1816</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Scott Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Abbotsford/ near/ Melrose<lb /> Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
                  Endorsement: Southey/ 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> &#8211; March<lb /> MS: National Library
                  of Scotland, MS 3887. ALS; 4p.<lb /> Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey
                  (ed.), <title>Life &amp; Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London,
                  1849&#8211;1850), IV, pp. 152&#8211;154 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1816-03-17">March 17.1816.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Scott,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have a debt upon my conscience, which has been too long unpaid. You
               left me a letter of introduction to the Dutchess of Richmond,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"> Charlotte Lennox, Duchess of Richmond (1768&#8211;1842;
                     <title>DNB</title>). The Duchess lived in Brussels from 1814 to 1818; the ball
                  she held on 15 June 1815, on the eve of the Battle of Quatre Bras, was attended by
                  most of the British officers.</note> which I was graceless enough to make no use
               of, &#8211; &amp; still more gracelessly I have never yet thanked you for it. As for the
               first part of the offence my stay at Brussels was not very long,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey was in Brussels between 28 September&#8211;3
                  October 1815. He saw Alexander I (1777&#8211;1825; Tsar of Russia 1801&#8211;1825) from the
                  crowd, but spent more time at the shop of Jean-Baptiste Ver Beyst (1770&#8211;1829), the
                  famous Brussels bookseller.</note> I had a great deal to see there, moreover, I
               got among the old books; &amp; having a sort of instinct which makes me as much as
               possible get out of the way of drawing-rooms, because I have an awkward feeling of
               being in the way when in them, I was much more at my ease <del>at</del> {when}
               looking at Emperors &amp; Princes in the crowd, than I should have been in the room
               with them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> How I should have rejoiced if we had met at Waterloo! This feeling I
               had &amp; expressed upon the ground. You have pictured it with your characteristic
               force &amp; animation. My poem<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The
                     Poet&#8217;s Pilgrimage to Waterloo</title> (1816).</note> will reach you in a few
               weeks: &#8211; it is so different in its kind, that however kindly malice may be disposed,
               it will not be possible to institute a comparison with yours.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Field of Waterloo; a Poem</title> (1815).</note> I
               take a different point of time &amp; a wider range, leaving the battle untouched,
               &amp; describing the field only such as it was when I surveyed it; the poem extends
               to some length; it is in two parts of four cantos each; the first comprehends the
               journey; the second consists of political matter allegorically drest, after the
               manner of our old worthies.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My route included the <del>xxxx</del> {three} scenes of action, for I
               went to les Quatre Bras &amp; to Ligny,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Les Quatre Bras, Belgium, was a strategic crossroads at which French and Allied
                  armies fought on 16 June 1815; on the same day at nearby Ligny, Napoleon&#8217;s forces
                  defeated the Prussian army. The Battle of Waterloo occurred two days later.</note>
               &#8211; a spot where you first begin to exchange the scenery of Brabant for something
               bolder. This ground became more interesting when we afterwards fell in with some
               wounded Prussian officers at Aix la Chapelle<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"> Present-day Aachen, Germany. Southey was delayed there 10&#8211;17 October 1815,
                  by the illness of his daughter, Edith May.</note> who had been in the field, &#8211; one
               of them the very Aid de Camp who had the pleasure of lying beside Blucher when he was
               ridden over.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors"> At Ligny, Gebhard Leberecht
                  von Bl&#252;cher (1742&#8211;1819), Field Marshal in command of the Prussian army, was
                  trapped under his horse and ridden over by cavalry. The Prussian officer who
                  Southey met was Ferdinand Augustus Leopold Francis von Dresky (dates unknown), who
                  commanded the 2nd Regiment of Silesian infantry at Ligny.</note> I wish you had
               been with me when we drank the Belle Alliance between England &amp; Prussia with all
               the glee that good wine, good spirits &amp; good fellowship could impart.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Mountaineer as I am, the cultivated scenery of Flanders delighted me,
               I have seen no town so interesting as Bruges, &#8211; no country in a state so perfect as
               to its possible production of what is beautiful &amp; useful, as the environs of that
               city &amp; the Pays de Waes.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors"> This area
                  comprises part of the modern provinces of East Flanders in Belgium and
                  Zeeland.</note> Of single objects, the finest which I saw were the market-places
               at Brussels &amp; at Ypres, &amp; the Town house at Louvain; &#8211; the most
               extraordinary, as well as the most curious, the cathedral at Aix la Chapelle, which
               is perhaps, &#8211; the most curious Church in existence; &#8211;<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"> Present-day Aachen Cathedral is &#8216;curious&#8217; because its
                  architecture exhibits a mixture of styles, reflecting its function as the
                  coronation site of Holy Roman Emperors and a focus for pilgrimages.</note> the
               most impressive were the Quarries of Maestricht. I found a good deal of political
               discontent particularly in the Liege country<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors"> The formerly independent Prince-Bishopric of Liege had been incorporated in
                  the United Kingdom of the Netherlands in 1815.</note> &#8211; a general sense of
               insecurity, &#8211; a very prevalent belief that England had let Buonaparte loose from
                  Elba,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors"> On 26 February 1815 Napoleon
                  Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815) escaped from
                  imprisonment on the Isle of Elba, returning to France to begin the &#8216;Hundred Days&#8217;
                  of rule that ended at Waterloo.</note> which I endeavoured in vain to combat, &#8211;
               &amp; a very proper degree of disappointment &amp; indignation that he had not been
               put to death as he deserved, &#8211; a feeling in which I heartily concurred. I saw nothing
               more of France than the miserable country between Boulogne &amp; Calais.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Did I ever thank you for the Lord of the Isles?<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors"> Scott&#8217;s narrative romance <title>The Lord of the
                     Isles</title> (1815).</note> There are pictures in it which are not surpassed
               in any of your poems, &amp; in the first part especially a mixture of originality
               &amp; animation &amp; beauty which is seldom found. &#8211; I wished the Lord himself had
               been more worthy of the good fortune which you bestowed upon him. The laurel<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors"> The Poet Laureateship, which was given
                  Southey after Scott turned the role down in 1813.</note> which it has pleased you,
               rather than any other person, to bestow upon me, has taken me in for much dogged work
               in rhyme; otherwise, I am inclined to think that my service to the Muses has been
               long enough, &amp; that I should perhaps have claimed my discharge: the ardour of
               youth is gone by; however I may have fallen short of my own aspirations my best is
               done, &amp; I ought to prefer those employments which require the matured faculties
               &amp; collected <del>xx</del> stores of declining life. You will receive the
               long-delayed conclusion of my Brazilian history<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors"> Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> in the
               course of the summer, &#8211; it has much curious matter respecting savage life, a full
               account of the Jesuit establishments,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"> The
                  &#8216;Reductions&#8217; &#8211; village colonies &#8211; into which Jesuit missionaries gathered some
                  Indian groups.</note> &amp; a war in Pernambuco<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors"> The struggle between the Dutch Republic and Portugal to
                  control Brazil in 1624&#8211;1661.</note> which will be much to your liking.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottMargaretCharlotte">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  Scott</ref> &amp; your daughter,<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
                  Charlotte Sophia Scott (1799&#8211;1837), who married John Gibson Lockhart in
                  1820.</note> who is now old enough <del>for these</del> to be entitled to these
               courtesies &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">my dear Scott</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">yours very affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>