<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 5: 1816-1821</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <author>
          <name>Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</name>
        </author>
        <editor>Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>General Editor, </resp>
          <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
          <name>Laura Mandell</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-05-27</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3203</idno>
        <idno type="nines">rce4474</idno>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
        <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
        <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any
												manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting,
												teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the
												author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law.
												Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication in any medium
												requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance notification of Romantic
												Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
												<address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
              <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
              <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
														permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
														ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers.
												It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available
												elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual
												basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one generally available to all Internet users.
												Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions
												of use.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title type="main" level="a">3203. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 26 October 1818</title>
            <author role="primary">
              <persName>
                <forename>Robert</forename>
                <surname>Southey</surname>
              </persName>
            </author>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/letterEEd.26.3203" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Five</title>
            <title level="s">Electronic Editions</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of
														Maryland</publisher>
              <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
              <date when="2015-12-17">December 17, 2015</date>
              <biblScope type="URL">http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters/Part_Five/HTML/letterEEd.26.3203.html</biblScope>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <p>Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. AL; 4p.
                  .  Previously  published: John Wood Warter (ed.), Selections from the Letters
                     of Robert Southey, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
               102&#8211;105.</p>
        <p>These letters were edited with the assistance of Carol Bolton, Tim Fulford and Ian Packer</p>
        <p>For permission to publish the text of MSS in their possession, the editor wishes to thank the Beinecke Rare
											Books and Manuscript Library, Yale University; Berg Collection of English and American Literature, The New
											York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations; the Bodleian Library Oxford University; the
											British Library; Boston Public Library; the Syndics of Cambridge University Library; the Syndics of the
											Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge; Haverford College, Connecticut; the Historical Society of Pennsylvania; the
											Hornby Library, Liverpool Libraries and Information Services; the Houghton Library, Harvard University;
											the John Rylands Library, Manchester; the Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas; Luton
											Museum (Bedfordshire County Council); Massachusetts Historical Society; McGill University Library; the
											National Library of Scotland; the Newberry Library, Chicago; the New York Public Library (Pforzheimer
											Collections); the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York; the Public Record Offices of Bedford, Suffolk (Bury
											St Edmunds) and Northumberland, the Master and Fellows of Trinity College, Cambridge; the Society of
											Antiquaries of Newcastle upon Tyne; the Trustees of the William Salt Library, Stafford, the Wisbech and
											Fenland Museum; the University of Virginia Library.</p>
        <p>A research grant from the British Academy made much of the archival work possible, as did support from the
											English Department of Nottingham Trent University.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for &#8220;," for &#8221;, ' for &#8216;, and ' for &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard.</p>
          <p>Dashes have been rendered as a variable number of hyphens to give a more exact rendering of their
												length.</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Southey's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the content recorded
												in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p>&#163; has been used for &#163;, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity
												decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E" xml:id="g">
          <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
												http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
												2009-02-26</bibl>
          <category xml:id="g1">
            <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g2">
            <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g3">
            <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g4">
            <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g5">
            <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g7">
            <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g6">
            <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g8">
            <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g9">
            <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g10">
            <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g11">
            <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g12">
            <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g13">
            <catDesc>History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g14">
            <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g15">
            <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g16">
            <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g17">
            <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g18">
            <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g19">
            <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g20">
            <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g21">
            <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g22">
            <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g23">
            <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g24">
            <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g25">
            <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g26">
            <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g27">
            <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g28">
            <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g29">
            <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g30">
            <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g31">
            <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g32">
            <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g33">
            <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="g34">
            <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/people.xml">
          <category xml:id="people">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Biographies</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy corresp="http://www.rc.umd.edu/southey_letters/places.xml">
          <category xml:id="places">
            <catDesc>Southey Letters: Places</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#g7 #g27" />
        <catRef scheme="#people" target="./people.html" />
        <catRef scheme="#places" target="./places.html" />
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#LM" when="2015-12-17" n="1">
        <label>Changed by</label>
        <name>David Rettenmaier</name>
        <list>
          <item>Ran transforms for proofing Southey Part 5</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3203" type="letter">
        <head>3203. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1818-10-26">26 October 1818</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: 26 Octo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 1818<lb /> MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 47. AL; 4p.<lb />
                  Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters
                     of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp.
               102&#8211;105.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1818-10-26">26. Oct. 1818.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I certainly shall not quarrel with just Nemesis<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, the spirit of divine
                  retribution.</note> &amp; the other aweful Powers of Vengeance for any punishment
               which they may have inflicted upon two persons who thought proper to go to Oswestry
               &amp; the country of the Welsh Barbarians when they might have come to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> where they would have had fine weather,
               &amp; rare society to boot.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford and
                  his brother Harry had gone to Wales on holiday, rather than to Keswick.</note> &#8211; I
               dare say you still smell like <del>xxxxx</del> Jacob when he personated his brother
               Esau, unless indeed there be a filthy odour of leeks to overpower the
                  <del>xxxxx</del> hircine savour which you must have brought away with you.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Genesis</title> 27, Jacob tricked
                  his blind father Isaac into thinking he was his favoured brother Esau, &#8216;a hairy
                  man&#8217;, by covering his smooth arms in goatskin. Goat herding was common in Wales in
                  Southey&#8217;s day.</note> Faugh! &#8211; You miserable man, to give up Derwent, &amp; <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>, &amp; Saddleback (over which
               noble mountain I have walked this very day) &#8211; &amp; Was-water whither I would have
               gone with you, ye wretches, &#8211; &amp; Crummock<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A lake to the southwest of Keswick.</note> &amp; Borrodale, &amp; <ref type="m" target="places.html#Ullswater">Ulswater</ref> &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c
               &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c. for rain &amp; lumbago &amp;
               an Oswestry parsonage! You might have laid in a stock of health for seven years upon
               these blessed mountains, where there would have been nothing between you &amp;
               Heaven. <del>And</del> {But} you must go to Wales forsooth, &#8211; or to the Welsh border,
               which is worse, &#8211; as if you had been a couple of sheep-stealers, &amp; so would keep
               company with Taffy, or like rats were unable to resist a bait of Toasted Cheese.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> So much by way of condolence. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Now for myself. You will conclude that I am in tolerable health when
               you hear that I was on foot from half past ten this morning till six this evening,
               without resting (more than a few minutes <del>&amp;</del> occasionally on a stone) or
               any other food than a single apple. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General</ref> was my foot
               companion &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TownshendChauncyHare">Chauncy
                  Townsend</ref> was with us on horseback, for he poor fellow, has not
               strength for such undertakings. He has been with me nearly a month, &amp; enjoys
               himself just as could be wished. I have been out a good deal with him, tho less than
               if he had been a good pedestrian: &amp; probably I may be the better for it. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You will have seen my two papers in the last QR.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">In the<title> Quarterly Review</title>, 19 (April
                  1818), 1&#8211;54, Southey reviewed <title>Memoirs, Illustrative of the Life and
                     Writings of John Evelyn</title> (1818); his essay, &#8216;On the Means of Improving
                  the People&#8217; appeared in the same issue (79&#8211;118).</note> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Megistos</ref> thought proper when he
               sent me 150 &#163; for them to remind me that such prices could not be afforded unless the
               articles produced a <hi rend="ital">decided impression</hi>; to observe that the <hi rend="ital">latter part</hi> of Evelyn had been approved, &amp; to offer some
               hints respecting the arrangement of such reviewals in future. I dare say my answer
               would astonish him.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John
                  Murray, 7 October 1818, Letter 3201.</note> It was written in thorough good
               humour, &amp; without expressing the slightest resentment at such impertinence &#8211;in
               truth I understand his <hi rend="ital">humour</hi> too well to <del>xxx</del> feel
               any thing <del>but</del> {except} amusement at it. But I told him that tho his prices
               were very liberal, it was never the less very plain that I was employing myself less
               profitably (of which I gave him convincing proofs) &amp; less worthily (which he will
               not very easily comprehend) {in writing for them} than in pursuing my own greater
               avocations, &#8211; &amp; that therefore he must admit it to be a matter of prudence on my
               part, when I {should} have executed the papers in hand to become only an occasional
               contributor to the QR instead of a regular assistant, &amp; that at long intervals. &#8211;
               He is chewing the cud upon this, &amp; I shall adhere to my purpose. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Therefore when I have finished what I have in hand for him for this
               next number,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">One of three articles for the
                     <title>Quarterly Review</title> on which Southey worked in late 1818: a review,
                  published in 23 (July 1820), 549&#8211;591, of Haydon&#8217;s <title>New Churches, Considered
                     with Respect to the Opportunities they Offer for the Encouragement of
                     Painting</title> (1818); an article, &#8216;Inquiry into the Copyright Act&#8217;, 21
                  (January 1819), 196&#8211;219; or an article &#8216;Cemeteries and Catacombs of Paris&#8217; which
                  appeared in 21 (April 1819), 359&#8211;398.</note> instead of supplying any thing for
               the following one, I shall compleat my Tale of Paraguay, which with the help of some
               drawings from <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref>, will bring me
               about 300 &#163; by an edition of 2000.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> was not published until 1825, by which
                  time Nash was dead. The illustrations were two engravings after drawings by
                  Richard Westall (1765&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>). Published in an edition of 1,500,
                  it sold poorly and realised Southey less than &#163;80 in profits in the first year.
                  There was no second edition.</note> Then I shall go to my long planned tale of
               Oliver Newman, &amp; for this I will demand a price of the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmen</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217; remained unfinished and was published
                  posthumously by Longman as a fragment in 1845; see <title>Oliver Newman: a New
                     England Tale (Unfinished): with Other Poetical Remains</title> (London, 1845),
                  pp. 1&#8211;92. Only 1,000 copies of the volume were printed and sales were poor.</note>
               By the time that I reach the age of fifty, if I should live so long, it is fit &amp;
               proper that I should have realized enough to emancipate myself from all the
                  <del>xx</del> drudgery of <del>xx</del> literature, &#8211; that is to say &#8211; from all
               such writing as is performed merely for the sake of bread.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Herewith I send you Ballantynes<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Either <ref type="m" target="people.html#BallantyneJames">James</ref> or <ref type="m" target="people.html#BallantyneJohn">John Ballantyne</ref>.</note> promissory note, &#8211; a lucky recovery of money
               which I had given up for lost. Tho I am still a loser to the amount of as much more.
               But this is the purchase money of my share in that Register for which I did such good
               yeomans service.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1810 Southey had
                  been induced by the Ballantynes and by their silent partner Walter Scott to take a
                  1/12th financial share (valued at &#163;209) in the publication to which they invited
                  him to contribute &#8211; the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. Southey wrote
                  the historical sections in the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for
                     1808&#8211;1811</title> (1810&#8211;1813). But he received none of the profits from these
                  editions, was not paid for his final contribution, to the <title>Edinburgh Annual
                     Register, for 1811</title> (1813), and feared his share in the
                     <title>Register</title> had become worthless.</note> Do you put it into proper
               hands to negociate it, &amp; when you have the proceeds add to them from my next
               payment as much as may suffice to <del>xxxxxx buy</del> buy in 300 &#163; in the 3 per
                  cents.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Government stock, yielding a
                  return of 3% per annum.</note> I have 100 already there, &amp; shall then be worth
               12 &#163; per annum. My incomings this year are considerably less than the last. &#8211; Kehama
               &amp; Roderick are reprinting, &amp; will hardly pay their expences next year: but I
               may look to Wesley for something, &#8211; tho it will be little in proportion to the time
               &amp; labour bestowed upon this work.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The fourth edition of <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810) was printed
                  in 1818, along with the fourth edition of <title>Roderick, the Last of the
                     Goths</title> (1814). Southey&#8217;s <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and
                     Progress of Methodism</title> appeared in 1820.</note> &#8211; My expences meantime
               are heavily increased by <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Toms</ref> increasing family<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey had been promoted to Captain in the Royal Navy in 1811, but was
                  never given command of a ship. His attempts at farming were proving unsuccessful.
                  His family consisted of: Margaret Hill Southey (b. 1811); Mary Hill Southey (b.
                  1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813&#8211;1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815&#8211;1864) and
                  Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816&#8211;1835). They were followed by Sarah Louise Southey
                  (1818&#8211;1850); Nelson Castle Southey (1820&#8211;1834); Sophia Jane Southey (1822&#8211;1859)
                  and Thomas Castle Southey (1824&#8211;1896).</note> &amp; growing wants: &#8211; <del>this is
                  an evil to which</del> there indeed a dismal prospect is before me; &#8211; for in case
               of his death a larger family than my own will be cast upon my hands, &amp; if he
               should lose his wife, whose life is far from being a good one, he will lose with her
               60 &#163; a year, which would inevitably fall upon me. The only set off against this, is
               the hope that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Osiris</ref> may get on in his profession, &amp; be enabled to do
               what he would have all the will <del>xx</del> in the world to perform in bearing his
               share of the burthen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These cares do not sit heavily upon me, &#8211; except indeed that my death
               (a much more likely event than his own) would leave <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> to bear the whole
               penalty of his rash marriage. A circumstance of a very different nature affects me
               much more in my heart of hearts. After an interval of more than six years I am
                  <del>in the</del> likely to become again a father;<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Cuthbert Southey was born on 24 February 1819. He was
                  Southey&#8217;s last child to be born and the first since Isabel, who was born on 2
                  November 1812.</note> &#8211; &amp; you may well imagine what feelings this must
               occasion, after the grievous loss which we have sustained in those years, &#8211; a loss
               which I shall never wholly overcome: &#8211; this prospect indeed only makes me feel more
               deeply how irreparable it is.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s
                  son, Herbert, had died on 17 April 1816.</note> For setting aside the myriad or
               million chances against my having such another son as that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHerbert">incomparable boy</ref>, &#8211; it
               is but too certain that I should neither have life nor heart ever again to perform my
               duty by another in the same manner. </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This will prevent me from leaving home till Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>.
               or March. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Ediths</ref>
               spirits are as you may suppose very much affected, &amp; she suffers very much in her
               bodily health.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>