<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
				<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
				<author>
					<name>Mary Shelley (1797-1851)</name>
				</author>
				<editor>Stuart Curran</editor>
				<sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Neil Fraistat</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Steven E. Jones</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor, </resp>
					<name>Carl Stahmer</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Technical Editor</resp>
					<name>Laura Mandell</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="edition">frank27.pop</idno>
				<publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
				<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
				<date when="2009-04-01">May 1, 2009</date>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated in any manner without
						authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by
						the Copyright Act of 1976, as amended.</p>
					<p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be
						shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement,
						redistribution or republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and advance
						notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:&gt;
						<address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
					</p>
					<p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
							<item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written permission from Romantic
								Circles.</item>
							<item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current ones.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
					<p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our
						interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make
						corrections and additions to our edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
						generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject
						to our conditions of use.</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a">STUDY AIDS : IN POPULAR CULTURE</title>
						<author>
							<persName>Curran, Stuart</persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main">Frankenstein</title>
						<title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
						<editor>Curran, Stuart</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
							<pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
							<date>2009-05-01</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “," for ”, ' for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
					<p>Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy xml:id="g" corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
					<bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
						http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on 2009-02-26</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Education</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Law</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<catRef target="#g12 #g16" scheme="#genre"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change n="3" when="2009-05-01" who="#LM">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="LM">Laura Mandell</name>
				<list>
					<item>XSLT Transforming into TEI, RDF</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="2" when="2009-05-01" who="#DR">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="DR">David Rettenmaier</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change n="1" when="2009-05-01" who="#MQ">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name xml:id="MQ">Mike Quilligan</name>
				<list>
					<item>XHTML Encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<head>STUDY AIDS : IN POPULAR CULTURE</head>
			<div type="appPopA">
				<list>
					<item>
						<ref target="1">abbott</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="2">young</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="3">bride</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="4">clive</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="5">comedy</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="6">cushing</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="7">fatefrank</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="8">filmlist</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="9">fisher</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="10">frank10</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="11">frank27</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="12">frank31</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="13">frank94</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="14">ghost</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="15">hammer</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="16">karloff</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="17">laemmle</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="18">lifesoul</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="19">lit</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="20">manmonster</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="21">mostro</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="22">movies</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="23">pierce</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="24">plays</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="25">pop</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="26">rocky</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="27">son</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="28">strick</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="29">whale</ref>
					</item>
					<item>
						<ref target="30">wolfman</ref>
					</item>
				</list>
			</div>
			<div type="appPopB">
				<list>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Abbott and Costello Meet Frankenstein (1948) </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Universal's last film to include all its classic monsters: Frankenstein's Monster (Glenn Strange), Dracula (Bela Lugosi),
							the Wolf Man (Lon Chaney, Jr.), and the Invisible Man (voice of Vincent Price). Directed by Charles Barton.</p>
						<p> Dracula and a mad scientist—for the first time, played by a woman (Lenore Aubert)—try to transplant Lou Costello's brain
							into the Frankenstein Monster; it's up to the Wolf Man to foil their plot.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Young Frankenstein</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>This movie of 1974, one of the most successful parodies of the horror film genre, was co-written by director Mel Brooks and
							star Gene Wilder, who plays a brain surgeon and descendant of Victor Frankenstein, Frederick Frankenstein (pronounced
							Frahnkensteen). It draws on the entire tradition of Frankenstein movies, but especially on the first three Universal
							movies starring Karloff: Frankenstein (1931), The Bride of Frankenstein (1935), and The Son of Frankenstein (1939).</p>
						<p> Frankenstein, a brain surgeon who scoffs at the activities of his famous ancestor, travels to Transylvania, and there
							discovers the secret of creating life. Brooks used Kenneth Strickfaden's original electrical equipment from the 1931
							Universal Frankenstein. The cast included Wilder, Peter Boyle (the Monster), Marty Feldman (Igor, pronounced Eye-gor),
							Madeline Kahn (as Elizabeth), Cloris Leachman, Terri Garr (in one of her first major roles), and Kenneth Mars.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">The Bride of Frankenstein (1935) </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Universal Studios announced a sequel to their phenomenally successful Frankenstein (1931), to be called The Return of
							Frankenstein, in 1933; but only in 1935 did Whale, Clive, and Karloff reunite, along with Valerie Hobson, Elsa Lanchester,
							Una O'Connor, and Ernest Thesiger, for The Bride of Frankenstein. Lanchester appears both at the beginning of the film,
							where she plays Mary Shelley, and at the end, where she plays the Monster's mate.</p>
						<p> Co-writer John L. Balderston originally created the screenplay as a satire, but while some satirical elements remain, much
							of the movie is in the same tradition as its predecessor.</p>
						<p> The film opens with a discussion between Lord Byron, Percy Bysshe Shelley, and Mary Shelley. When Byron complains about
							the ending of her original novel (making reference to the movie of 1931), Mary Shelley continues the tale. The Monster, we
							discover, was not killed in the fire at the mill that ended the first movie; he survived, and continued to wreak havoc
							among the villagers. A blind man befriends him and teaches him the rudiments of language. He is captured by local
							peasants, however, and taken into custody.</p>
						<p> The evil Doctor Pretorius, whose own experiments with creating life have produced a collection of six-inch people in glass
							jars, persuades Henry Frankenstein to collaborate in the creation of a mate for the Monster. In a scene strongly
							reminiscent of the creation scene in the 1931 movie, Frankenstein and Pretorius bring the Bride to life; when she sees the
							Monster, however, she spurns him, and he destroys the castle and its laboratory. As with its precursor, Universal edited
							the film at the last minute to give it a happy conclusion in which Frankenstein and Elizabeth escape.</p>
						<p>The Bride was the first of Universal's films in which the Monster speaks—a decision that Karloff regretted, feeling the
							muteness lent the Creature dignity.</p>
						<p> Universal produced a sequel, The Son of Frankenstein, which appeared in 1939.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Colin Clive </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Colin Clive, 1900-1937, British actor.</p>
						<p>After working with him in Journey's End (1930), James Whale chose Clive to play Henry Frankenstein [sic] with Boris
							Karloff's Monster in Universal's 1931 Frankenstein. He repeated the role in The Bride of Frankenstein (1935), but died (of
							tuberculosis, hastened by a drinking problem) before the third Universal movie, The Son of Frankenstein (1939). </p>
						<p> Clive's films include: </p>
						<list type="simple">
							<item>Journey's End (1930) </item>
							<item>The Stronger Sex (1931) </item>
							<item>Frankenstein (1931) </item>
							<item>Lily Christine (1932) </item>
							<item>Looking Forward (1933) </item>
							<item>Christopher Strong (1933) </item>
							<item>One More River (1934) </item>
							<item>The Key (1934) </item>
							<item>The Right to Live (1935) </item>
							<item>The Man Who Broke the Bank at Monte Carlo (1935) </item>
							<item>Mad Love (1935) </item>
							<item>Jane Eyre (1935) </item>
							<item>The Girl from Tenth Avenue (1935) </item>
							<item>Clive of India (1935) </item>
							<item>The Bride of Frankenstein (1935) </item>
							<item>The Widow from Monte Carlo (1936) </item>
							<item>The Woman I Love (1937) </item>
							<item>History Is Made at Night (1937)</item>
						</list>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Comic Adaptations of Frankenstein</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p> In 1934 The Inventors (directed by Al Christie) portrayed Colonel Lemuel Q. Stoopnagle's creation of Stoopenstein, who
							later goes out of control. The Monster makes an appearance in the musical comedy Hellzapoppin' (1941).</p>
						<p> Joseph Kesselring made Karloff's distinctive appearance a central part of his Broadway version of Arsenic and Old Lace,
							although Frank Capra was unable to convince Karloff to take the role in the 1941 film version (released 1944).</p>
						<p> In 1948, Bud Abbott and Lou Costello took on the Wolfman, Dracula, the Invisible Man, and Frankenstein's Monster in Abbott
							and Costello Meet Frankenstein, featuring Glenn Strange as the Creature. (Karloff, by this time seeking to escape the role
							that made him famous, agreed to pose for publicity photos "as long as I don't have to see the movie.")</p>
						<p> Other comic adaptations include: </p>
						<list type="simple">
							<item>The Bowery Boys Meet the Monsters (1954). </item>
							<item>Young Frankenstein (1974). </item>
							<item>The Rocky Horror Picture Show (1975) features Tim Curry as the alien transvestite, Doctor Frank N. Furter, who
								creates the Arian Rocky. </item>
							<item>Tim Burton's Frankenweenie (1984) </item>
							<item>The black comedy Frankenhooker (1990), directed by Frank Henenlotter.</item>
						</list>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Peter Cushing</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p> A number of minor movie roles in the 1940s (including Osric in Laurence Olivier's 1947 Hamlet) brought Cushing to the
							attention of the management of Hammer Films.</p>
						<p> Cushing appeared in a string of Hammer productions, including The Revenge of Frankenstein (1958), The Evil of Frankenstein
							(1964), Frankenstein Created Woman (1966), Frankenstein Must Be Destroyed (1969), and Frankenstein and the Monster from
							Hell (1973).</p>
						<p> Post-Hammer credits include Star Wars (1977).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Presumption; or, the Fate of Frankenstein </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Richard Brinsley Peake's dramatic adaptation of Mary Shelley's novel, Presumption; or, the Fate of Frankenstein, premiered
							at the English Opera House in July 1823. It was the first of many dramatic and film adaptations, and was quite popular in
							its day, running for 37 performances. The success of the play inspired copy-cat burlesque versions in other theatres. </p>
						<p> Peake was a popular and prolific dramatist, producing his first play in 1818 and continuing to write until his death. For
							many years he was employed by the English Opera House. Few of his works are remembered now, but in addition to
							Presumption, he wrote a large number of successful melodramas and farces, including the Gothic melodrama The Bottle Imp
							(1823) and The Evil Eye (1831). </p>
						<p>A electronic edition of Presumption has been published at Romantic Circles. </p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">A List of Movies Based on Frankenstein, 1910-2005</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Since a complete list of films based directly or indirectly on Frankenstein would run into the thousands, it's convenient
							to exclude films with only a tangential relationship to the original novel: those, for instance, with only a mad
							scientist, a raising-from-the-dead theme, or a Creature cameo. This chronological list includes most of the major feature
							films between 1910 and 2005 based on Shelley's novel. </p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Terence Fisher </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Terence Fisher, 1904-1980, British film director.</p>
						<p>Fisher directed such offerings as Stolen Face (1952) and Spaceways (1953) for Hammer Films before being offered The Curse
							of Frankenstein (1957), in which he worked with Peter Cushing. Later projects included Dracula (1958), The Revenge of
							Frankenstein (1958, again with Cushing), The Mummy (1959), The Man Who Could Cheat Death (1959), and The Brides of Dracula
							(1960). The Phantom of the Opera (1962) was a commercial failure, and Hammer dropped Fisher for a time, but he returned to
							direct Frankenstein Must Be Destroyed (1969).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Frankenstein, 1910 </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Directed by J. Searle Dawley, starring Augustus Phillips (Frankenstein), Charles Stanton Ogle (the Creature), Mary Fuller.
							Edison Film Company.</p>
						<p> In this silent short, the first film version of Frankenstein, Frankenstein creates the Creature from a vat of chemicals in
							an early use of movie special effects. Edison's version was more faithful to the original story than many subsequent
							adaptations. The movie's original run went from 16 March to 31 March, 1910.</p>
						<p> Only one print of the Edison film is known to survive, and is not readily available. Edison's Frankenstein (1990), a
							recent short film, uses stills to reconstruct the original.</p>
						<p> The next significant Frankenstein movie, and the first feature-length version, was Life Without Soul (1915).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Frankenstein, 1927</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Peggy Webling's 1927 stage adaptation of the novel was the basis for the most famous Frankenstein movie of all,
							Frankenstein (1931), directed by James Whale, starring Boris Karloff and Colin Clive. The play's success on its original
							run in 1927 was continued in a 1930 revival, which first brought it to the attention of Universal Pictures.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Frankenstein, 1931</term>
						<p>This, the most famous film version of the novel, stars Boris Karloff as the Monster and Colin Clive as Henry Frankenstein
							[sic], with Mae Clarke (Elizabeth), John Boles, Dwight Frye (Frankenstein's hunchback assistant, Fritz), and Edward Van
							Sloan. Universal Studios and producer Carl Laemmle, following on the success of their Dracula (based on Bram Stoker's
							novel) the year before, chose director James Whale to bring Mary Shelley's novel to the screen.</p>
						<p> The film was based on Peggy Webling's 1927 stage adaptation, with a screenplay by Robert Florey, Richard Schayer, and
							Garrett Fort. Two well-known actors—Bela Lugosi and John Carradine—turned down the role of the Creature, unhappy that it
							had no lines. Whale brought in a relative unknown, Boris Karloff, whose career was newly launched with the success of the
							picture.</p>
						<p> The film's budget was $262,000, of which $10,000 was spent on special effects—an exorbitant amount at the time. Karloff
							made famous the makeup of Jack Pierce. Kenneth Strickfaden's fantastic electrical equipment is also among the most
							memorable features of the film.</p>
						<p> Universal in fact filmed two endings, and in the end chose to release the one with the happy conclusion. The movie was
							hastily filmed: production began on 24 August 1931, and the movie opened on 4 November of that year. Frankenstein was an
							immediate sensation; drawing over one million dollars in its first run—more than twice the take of Dracula (1930)—it
							became one of Universal's most successful productions ever. Universal therefore featured Karloff as the Creature in two
							more Universal films, The Bride of Frankenstein (1935) and The Son of Frankenstein (1939).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Mary Shelley's Frankenstein</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Francis Ford Coppola produced and Kenneth Branagh directed and starred in this 1994 adaptation of the novel, a companion to
							Coppola's Bram Stoker's Dracula (1992), featuring Robert De Niro as the Creature. Though advertised as the most faithful
							film adaptation of Mary Shelley's novel, Branagh's film nonetheless featured significant discrepancies from the book, as
							well as homages to previous films, in turning a reconstructed and resurrected Elizabeth into the "Bride of Frankenstein."
						</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">The Ghost of Frankenstein</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>The fourth Universal Frankenstein movie, following the original Frankenstein (1931), The Bride of Frankenstein (1935), and
							The Son of Frankenstein(1942). It was the first Universal movie not to star Boris Karloff as the Monster, substituting a
							less successful Lon Chaney, Jr.</p>
						<p> The movie was directed by Erle C. Kenton, and the cast includes Bela Lugosi (Ygor), Sir Cedric Hardwicke (Ludwig
							Frankenstein), Ralph Bellamy, Lionel Atwill (Dr. Bohmer), and Evelyn Ankers.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Hammer Films </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Hammer Films, a British studio, produced a series of Frankenstein movies second in importance only to the Universal series
							initiated by Frankenstein (1931).</p>
						<p>The Curse of Frankenstein (1957), the first Frankenstein offering from Hammer Films, was directed by Terence Fisher and
							starred Peter Cushing as Baron Victor Frankenstein and Christopher Lee as the Monster. The Curse of Frankenstein grossed
							$7,000,000, more than any other British film of comparable production costs.</p>
						<p> Fisher and Cushing worked together for Hammer in the next year in The Revenge of Frankenstein; Cushing appeared again
							(without Fisher's direction) in The Evil of Frankenstein (1964), and (once again with Fisher) in Frankenstein Created
							Woman (1966), Frankenstein Must Be Destroyed (1969), and Frankenstein and the Monster from Hell (1973).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Boris Karloff </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Boris Karloff, 1887-1969, British actor.</p>
						<p> Karloff was born William Henry Pratt. In 1909 he traveled from his native England to Canada and thence to America, where
							he began getting small stage and film roles; his new stage name combined the surname of distant relations with "Boris,"
							which he claims to have pulled "out of the air." In the teens he had become a popular stage villain, but by the late
							twenties and (especially) early in the Depression, Karloff's money had run out, and he was forced to support himself by
							driving a truck.</p>
						<p> A series of small film parts—Criminal Code (1930), Five Star Final (1931), The Mad Genius (1931)—brought him to the
							attention of James Whale, who had been hired by Universal Studios to produce a film version of Frankenstein. Both Bela
							Lugosi and John Carradine had turned down the role for its lack of dialogue, but Karloff accepted. This was the deciding
							moment in his career, and throughout the thirties and forties Karloff was a widely sought actor.</p>
						<p> Four years after the huge success of the first movie, Karloff reprised his role as the Monster in The Bride of
							Frankenstein (1935) and The Son of Frankenstein (1939), but after this latter vowed never again to appear in the role. As
							he later recalled: </p> There was not much left in the Monster to be developed. We had reached his limits. I saw that from
						here on, he would become rather an oafish prop, so to speak, in the last act of something like that, without any great
						stature. </item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Carl Laemmle </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Carl Laemmle Jr., 1908-79, American producer and son of Carl Laemmle, founder of Universal Pictures.</p>
						<p> Laemmle produced nearly eighty films between 1926 and 1938, but his most famous is the 1931 version of Frankenstein,
							directed by James Whale and starring Boris Karloff.</p>
						<p> Laemmele's films include: </p>
						<list type="simple">
							<item>Lonesome (1928) </item>
							<item>Broadway (1929) </item>
							<item>College Love (1929) </item>
							<item>A Lady Surrenders (1930) </item>
							<item>The Cat Creeps (1930) </item>
							<item>All Quiet on the Western Front (1930) </item>
							<item>Waterloo Bridge (1931) </item>
							<item>Strictly Dishonorable (1931) </item>
							<item>The Spirit of Notre Dame (1931) </item>
							<item>Many a Alip (1931) </item>
							<item>The Iron Man (1931) </item>
							<item>Frankenstein (1931) </item>
							<item>East of Borneo (1931) </item>
							<item>Dracula (1931) </item>
							<item>Bad Sister (1931) </item>
							<item>Tom Brown of Culver (1932) </item>
							<item>Texas Bad Man (1932) </item>
							<item>Scandal for Sale (1932) </item>
							<item>Rider of Death Valley (1932) </item>
							<item>Once in a Lifetime (1932) </item>
							<item>The Old Dark House (1932) </item>
							<item>Night World (1932) </item>
							<item>My Pal, the King (1932) </item>
							<item>Murders in the Rue Morgue (1932) </item>
							<item>The Mummy (1932) </item>
							<item>The Impatient Maiden (1932) </item>
							<item>The Cohens and Kellys in Hollywood (1932) </item>
							<item>Air Mail (1932) </item>
							<item>Saturday's Millions (1933) </item>
							<item>The Kiss before the Mirror (1933) </item>
							<item>The Invisible Man (1933) </item>
							<item>Hidden Gold (1933) </item>
							<item>Counsellor-at-Law (1933) </item>
							<item>Love Birds (1934) </item>
							<item>Gift of Gab (1934) </item>
							<item>The Black Cat (1934) </item>
							<item>Beloved (1934) </item>
							<item>Remember Last Night? (1935) </item>
							<item>Night Life of the Gods (1935) </item>
							<item>The Man who Reclaimed His Head (1935) </item>
							<item>The Bride of Frankenstein (1935) </item>
							<item>Show Boat (1936)</item>
						</list>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Life Without Soul </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>This silent movie, the second film version of the novel (after Edison's Frankenstein, 1910), appeared in 1915, and was the
							first feature-length adaptation of Shelley's story.</p>
						<p>Life Without Soul was directed by Joseph W. Smiley, and stars Percy Darrell Standing as "the Brute Man" and William A.
							Cohill as Dr. William Frawley. After the Creature kills Frawley's sister, he pursues it across Europe; at the conclusion,
							Frawley shoots the Monster immediately before dying of exhaustion.</p>
						<p>Life Without Soul was later remade as Il Mostro di Frankenstein (1920).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Literary References to Frankenstein </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Frankenstein became very popular, particularly after Richard Brinsley Peake's dramatic adaptation in 1823. Throughout the
							nineteenth century, references to the novel appear in a great many novels and poems, sometimes in serious allusions,
							sometimes in facetious references. The following list is far from exhaustive. </p>
						<list type="simple">
							<item>Alexander Anderson, "Frankenstein"</item>
							<item>Alexander Anderson, "City and Village"</item>
							<item>Alexander Anderson, "The Engine"</item>
							<item>Samuel Egerton Brydges, The Lake of Geneva, Book II</item>
							<item>Robert Williams Buchanan, "The Voyage of Magellan"</item>
							<item>Elizabeth Gaskell, Mary Barton, chapter XV</item>
							<item>Henry Ellison, "The New Prometheus"</item>
							<item>Sebastian Evans, "Jones and Calypso"</item>
							<item>Thomas Hood, "Ode to the Great Unknown"</item>
							<item>Thomas Hood, "Ode to Joseph Grimaldi, Senior"</item>
							<item>Henry Luttrell, Crockford-House, Canto II</item>
							<item>Herman Charles Merivale, "The Storm"</item>
							<item>Robert Montgomery, The Age Reviewed, Part II</item>
							<item>Thomas Moore, "Enigma"</item>
							<item>Winthrop Mackworth Praed, "My Partner"</item>
						</list>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Demon of Switzerland and The Man and the Monster </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Henry M. Milner adapted Mary Shelley's novel for the stage twice. The first time was in 1823, and the play was entitled
							Frankenstein, or the Demon of Switzerland. It was produced at the Cobourg Theatre within a month after Richard Brinsley
							Peake's dramatic adaptation, Presumption; or, the Fate of Frankenstein, premiered at the English Opera House. A second
							adaptation of Milner appeared in 1826. It was called Frankenstein; or, The Man and the Monster and it drew upon Shelley's
							novel and a French adaptation by Jean-Toussaint Merle and Béraud Antony entitled Le Monstre et le magicien (1826).</p>
						<p>Little is known of Milner beyond what is suggested by his publications. He was apparently a very successful playwright; his
							works included a great many melodramas and popular tragedies, including Barmecide; or, The Fatal Offspring (1818), The
							Philosopher: A Tragedy in Five Acts (1819), Twelve Precisely! or, A Night at Dover: An Interlude in One Act (1821), The
							Hertfordshire Tragedy; or, The Victims of Gaming: A Serious Drama in Two Acts (Founded upon Recent Melancholy Facts)
							(1824), The Death-Fetch; or, The Fatal Warning: A Romantic Melo Drama in Two Acts (Founded on a Well-Known Superstition)
							(1826), The Hut of the Red Mountain; or, Thirty Years of a Gambler's Life: A Drama, in Three Acts (1827, also known as The
							Gambler's Fate), Lucius Catiline, the Roman Traitor: A Drama, in Three Acts (1827), Masaniello, or, The Dumb Girl of
							Portici: A Musical Drama, in Three Acts (1829), Mazeppa: A Romantic Drama in Three Acts: Dramatised from Lord Byron's Poem
							(1831), and Gustavus the Third; or, The Masked Ball! A Romantic Drama, in Three Acts (1833).</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Il Mostro di Frankenstein</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>The third silent film adaptation of the novel appeared in 1920, and was based on Joseph Smiley's Life Without Soul (1915).
							The Monster was played by Umberto Guarracino, Frankenstein by Luciano Albertini.</p>
						<p> No prints of the film are known to exist today. </p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Movies of Frankenstein</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>The century-long success of the stage adaptations of Frankenstein made it a natural choice for filmmakers. The list of
							movies based, however indirectly, on Mary Shelley's novel stretches into the hundreds.</p>
						<p> The first film treatment of the novel was a seven-minute silent short from the Edison Film Company, entitled simply
							Frankenstein (1910). It was followed by a number of silent movies, including Life Without Soul (1915) and Il Mostro di
							Frankenstein (1920).</p>
						<p> But the silents were merely preludes to the explosion of cinematic Frankensteins. The tremendous success of the 1931
							Frankenstein, directed by James Whale and starring Boris Karloff and Colin Clive, spawned a host of successors: Stephen
							Jones, in The Illustrated Frankenstein Movie Guide, counts over four hundred film adaptations of the novel.</p>
						<p> The hundreds of B-movie adaptations include Universal's Ghost of Frankenstein (1942) and Frankenstein Meets the Wolf Man
							(1943), as well as I Was a Teenage Frankenstein (1957), Frankenstein Conquers the World (1964; a Japanese horror film in
							which a young man eats Frankenstein's radioactive heart and grows to fifty feet), and Jesse James Meets Frankenstein's
							Daughter (1965).</p>
						<p> In 1957, Terence Fisher directed the first Frankenstein adaptation for Hammer Films, The Curse of Frankenstein, starring
							Peter Cushing; it was followed by a long string of successful movie versions.</p>
						<p> The "original" movie lent itself not only to further adaptations but to radical mutations of genre. A long tradition of
							comic films began immediately after the Universal film's opening in 1931 and continued through Abbott and Costello Meet
							Frankenstein (1948) and Young Frankenstein (1974). Maniac (1934), also released under the title Sex Maniac, was the first
							explicitly erotic adaptation, and stands in a line including House on Bare Mountain (1962), The Curious Dr. Humpp (1967),
							Fanny Hill Meets Dr. Erotico (1967), Hollow-My-Weanie, Dr. Frankenstein (1969), Dr. Penetration (1986), and Sex Scientist
							(1993, featuring Dr. Spankingtime's creation of a nymphomaniac). Woody Allen combined the comic and pornographic
							traditions in Everything You Wanted to Know About Sex (But Were Afraid to Ask) (1972), in which the mad sexologist Dr.
							Bernardo creates a fifty-foot killer breast.</p>
						<p> The "Blaxploitation" fad of the early 1970s brought about Blackenstein (1972), in which Dr. Stein's DNA experimentation on
							a Vietnam veteran results in an intestine-eating monster sporting a square afro.</p>
						<p> Recent years have seen a steady stream of adaptations, including the cable television Frankenstein (1992; directed by
							David Wickes, starring Patrick Bergen as Frankenstein and Randy Quaid as the Monster) and Mary Shelley's Frankenstein
							(1994; directed by Kenneth Branagh).</p>
						<p> Rhino Video's Frankenstein: A Cinematic Scrapbook (1990) includes the trailers of dozens of movies based on Frankenstein,
							including all the Universal and Hammer films.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Jack Pierce </term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Jack Pierce, 1889-1968, chief makeup artist for Universal Studios from 1926 to 1947.</p>
						<p> Pierce and Karloff worked together three hours a day for three weeks to create a prototype of the Monster's appearance.
							Although his creation, with its green skin, flat head, and electrodes in the neck, has entered popular consciousness as
							the definitive Creature, the image remains the property of Universal.</p>
						<p> Here Pierce explains his choice of the most visually distinctive feature of his Monster's appearance, the flattened head:
						</p> I did three months of research in anatomy, surgery, criminology, ancient and modern burial customs, and electrodynamics.
						My anatomical studies taught me that there are six ways a surgeon can cut the skull in order to take out or put in a brain. I
						figured that Frankenstein, who was a scientist but no practising surgeon, would take the simplest surgical way. He would cut
						the top of the skull off straight across like a pot lid, hinge it, pop the brain in, and then clamp it on tight. That's the
						reason I decided to make the Monster's head square and flat like a shoe box and dig that big scar across his forehead with the
						metal clamps holding it together. <p> The familiar green skin of the Creature in the Universal films (in the novel, the
							Creature's skin is yellow [1818:I:4:2]) was chosen because it suggested pallor when filmed in black and white.</p>
						<p> Pierce created all the classic horror makeup jobs for Universal for two decades, but he was finally dropped for being too
							old-fashioned for the studio in 1947. Thereafter he found piecework, including the makeup for the television series Mr. Ed
							(1960-66). Pierce's films include: </p>
						<list type="simple">
							<item>Masquerade (1929) </item>
							<item>Waterloo Bridge (1931) </item>
							<item>Frankenstein (1931) </item>
							<item>Dracula (1931) </item>
							<item>White Zombie (1932) </item>
							<item>The Old Dark House (1932) </item>
							<item>The Mummy (1932) </item>
							<item>They Just Had to Get Married (1933) </item>
							<item>The Invisible Man (1933) </item>
							<item>The Black Cat (1934) </item>
							<item>Werewolf of London (1935) </item>
							<item>The Raven (1935) </item>
							<item>Diamond Jim (1935) </item>
							<item>The Bride of Frankenstein (1935) </item>
							<item>Next Time We Love (1936) </item>
							<item>The Invisible Ray (1936) </item>
							<item>The Road Back (1937) </item>
							<item>Night Key (1937) </item>
							<item>Tower of London (1939) </item>
							<item>Son of Frankenstein (1939) </item>
							<item>The Wolf Man (1941) </item>
							<item>Night Monster (1942) </item>
							<item>Phantom of the Opera (1943) </item>
							<item>Frankenstein Meets the Wolf Man (1943) </item>
							<item>House of Frankenstein (1944) </item>
							<item>Magnificent Doll (1946) </item>
							<item>The Killers (1946) </item>
							<item>Dressed to Kill (1946) </item>
							<item>I'll Be Yours (1947) </item>
							<item>Joan of Arc (1948) </item>
							<item>Master Minds (1949) </item>
							<item>The Black Book (1949) </item>
							<item>The Big Cat (1949) </item>
							<item>The Curse of Frankenstein (1957) </item>
							<item>The Devil's Hand (1961) </item>
							<item>Beauty and the Beast (1963) </item>
						</list>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Plays of Frankenstein</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Frankenstein is best known today through the many films based on the novel, although the most famous movie Frankenstein
							came after more than a century of popular stage adaptations. As early as 1823, Frankenstein had been adapted for the
							stage: Richard Brinsley Peake's Presumption; or, the Fate of Frankenstein appeared on the stage only five years after Mary
							Shelley's novel was published. In response to its success, William Godwin published the second edition of Frankenstein in
							the same year. </p>
						<p> Peake's adaptation was not, however, the last. Steven Earl Forry, the best authority on this dramatic history, has
							catalogued nearly one hundred dramatic adaptations between 1821 and 1986. He writes in "Dramatizations of Frankenstein,
							1821-1986: A Comprehensive List": </p> Pre-Karloffian dramatizations played an important role in disseminating popular
						conceptions—and misconceptions—of Mary Shelley's novel, from the incipient gothic melodramas such as Peake's Presumption,
						Henry M. Milner's The Demon of Switzerland and The Man and the Monster (1826), and Merle and Antony's Le Monstre et le
						magicien (1826) to their burlesque counterparts—Humgumption; or, Dr. Frankenstein and the Hobgoblin of Hoxton, Presumption and
						the Blue Demon, and Frankin-Steam; or, The Modern Promise to Pay—through political burlesque in the form of William and Robert
						Brough's Frankenstein; or, The Model Man (1849), the musical comedy of Richard Butler and Henry Chance Newton's Frankenstein;
						or, The Vampires Victim (1887), the farce of Paul Dickey and Charles Goddard's The Last Laugh (1915), and finally Peggy
						Webling's drawing room melodrama Frankenstein: An Adventure in the Macabre (1927). (65) </item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Frankenstein in Popular Culture</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>The popularity of Mary Shelley's novel and its various adaptions can be matched by few works of literature. As early as
							1823, when Richard Brinsley Peake's Presumption was staged, and especially since the famous Universal Frankenstein
							starring Boris Karloff, Frankenstein has spawned many thousands of spin-offs, ranging from sombre meditations on the
							dangers of science to kitschy cult movies about cross-dressing aliens. And with it comes the image, endlessly reproduced
							in everything from horror movies to breakfast cereals, of a green-skinned, flat-headed, groaning, lumbering giant with
							bolts in his neck—a far cry from Mary Shelley's articulate Creature. </p>
						<list type="simple">
							<item>Literature</item>
							<item>Plays</item>
							<item>Movies</item>
						</list>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">The Rocky Horror Picture Show</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Richard O'Brien's stage musical, The Rocky Horror Show, was adapted for the screen in 1975. The movie was directed by Jim
							Sharman, and starred Tim Curry (Dr. Frank N. Furter), Susan Sarandon (Janet Majors), Barry Bostwick (Brad Majors), Richard
							O'Brien (Riff Raff), Peter Hinwood (Rocky), Charles Gray (narrator), Patricia Quinn, Nell Campbell, and Meat Loaf. Brad
							and Janet Majors, whose car has broken down, search for a phone at a mansion. There they discover Dr. Frank N. Furter, the
							"Sweet Transvestite from Transsexual Transylvania," and his creation, Rocky.</p>
						<p> The film did poorly at the box office on its first release, but soon became a cult favorite, with regular midnight
							showings featuring audience participation.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">The Son of Frankenstein (1939)</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>The third Universal Frankenstein movie, following the original Frankenstein (1931) and The Bride of Frankenstein (1935).
							Basil Rathbone plays Baron Wolf von Frankenstein, son of the "Henry" Frankenstein of the original movie; he returns to his
							father's castle and resurrects the monster, played (for the last time) by Boris Karloff.</p>
						<p> The movie was directed by Rowland V. Lee, and starred (along with Rathbone and Karloff) Bela Lugosi (as Igor, in the first
							appearance of that character), Lionel Atwill (as the one-armed Inspector Krogh), Josephine Hutchinson, and Donnie Dunagan.
							It was originally scheduled to be Universal's first Technicolor production, but objections to the appearance of Karloff's
							makeup in color caused the film to be shot in black and white.</p>
						<p> Universal announced a sequel, After Frankenstein, but it was never made.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Kenneth Strickfaden</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>Strickfaden, along with Frank Grove and Raymond Lindsay, created and operated the fantastic electronic equipment that fills
							Henry Frankenstein's laboratory in the Whale-Karloff version of Frankenstein (1931).</p>
						<p> Mel Brooks and Gene Wilder used much of Strickfaden's original equipment from the 1931 Frankenstein in Young
						Frankenstein.</p>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">James Whale</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>James Whale, 1893-1957, English film director.</p>
						<p> Whale had already produced several acclaimed adaptations of plays—R. C. Sherriff's Journey's End (1930), Robert Emmett
							Sherwood's Waterloo Bridge (1931)—before he was chosen by Carl Laemmle to direct Universal's film version of Frankenstein
							in 1931. Whale, impressed with his work in The Criminal Code (1931), chose Boris Karloff to play the part of the Monster.</p>
						<p> Whale, Karloff, and Colin Clive worked together four years later in The Bride of Frankenstein (1935), although Whale did
							not work on the third Universal movie, Son of Frankenstein (1939).</p>
						<p> Whale's films include: </p>
						<list type="simple">
							<item>Journey's End (1930) </item>
							<item>Hell's Angels (1930) </item>
							<item>Waterloo Bridge (1931) </item>
							<item>Frankenstein (1931) </item>
							<item>The Old Dark House (1932) </item>
							<item>The Impatient Maiden (1932) </item>
							<item>The Kiss before the Mirror (1933) </item>
							<item>The Invisible Man (1933) </item>
							<item>One More River (1934) </item>
							<item>By Candlelight (1934) </item>
							<item>Remember Last Night? (1935) </item>
							<item>The Bride Of Frankenstein (1935) </item>
							<item>Show Boat (1936) </item>
							<item>The Road Back (1937) </item>
							<item>The Great Garrick (1937) </item>
							<item>Wives Under Suspicion (1938) </item>
							<item>Sinners in Paradise (1938) </item>
							<item>Port Of Seven Seas (1938) </item>
							<item>The Man in the Iron Mask (1939) </item>
							<item>Green Hell (1940) </item>
							<item>They Dare Not Love (1941) </item>
							<item>Hello Out There (1949) </item>
						</list>
					</item>
					<item>
						<term rend="bold">Frankenstein Meets the Wolf Man (1943)</term>
						<p> </p>
						<p>The fifth Universal Frankenstein movie, following The Ghost of Frankenstein (1943), and one of the first to try to combine
							the monstrous elements of Universal's previous films. It was followed by others in the same vein, including The House of
							Frankenstein (1944, featuring Frankenstein's monster, the Wolf Man, Dracula, the Hunchback, and a Mad Doctor). In this
							movie, Lawrence Talbot, the Wolf Man, is accidentally resurrected by grave robbers; he travels to Transylvania to seek for
							a cure for his condition in Frankenstein's journals. While there, he encounters the Monster; after a battle, the two are
							swept away in the flooding caused by a burst dam.</p>
						<p> The cast includes Bela Lugosi (as the Monster, a role he turned down for the 1931 Frankenstein), Lon Chaney, Jr. (the Wolf
							Man), Lionel Atwill (the mayor), Maria Ouspenskaya (Maleva), Dennis Hoey (police investigator), and Ilona Massey (Elsa,
							Frankenstein's daughter). Roy William Neill directed.</p>
					</item>
				</list>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
