<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">
                    <emph>The Banks of Wye</emph>
                </title>
                <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name>
                </author>
                <editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor, </resp>
                    <name>Neil Fraistat</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor, </resp>
                    <name>Steven E. Jones</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>General Editor, </resp>
                    <name>Carl Stahmer</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Technical Editor</resp>
                    <name>Laura Mandell</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <idno type="edition">About</idno>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, http://www.rc.umd.edu, University of Maryland</publisher>
                <pubPlace>College Park, MD</pubPlace>
                <date when="2010-10-10">October 10, 2010</date>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p rend="noCount">Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, reproduced or disseminated
                        in any manner without authorization unless it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news
                        reporting, teaching, and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as
                        amended.</p>
                    <p rend="noCount">Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic Circles are copyrighted
                        by the author/editor and may be shared only in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S.
                        copyright law. Except as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or
                        republication in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author/editors and
                        advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests for authorization should be forwarded
                        to Romantic Circles:&gt;
                        <address><addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine><addrLine>c/o Professor Neil Fraistat</addrLine><addrLine>Department of English</addrLine><addrLine>University of Maryland</addrLine><addrLine>College Park, MD 20742</addrLine><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></p>
                    <p rend="noCount">By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following conditions: <list>
                        <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial purpose without prior written
                            permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                        <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any forms other than their current
                            ones.</item>
                    </list></p>
                    <p rend="noCount">Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order to mount them on their
                        own servers. It is not in our interest or that of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of
                        our holdings available elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text to be the only one
                        generally available to all Internet users. Institutions can, of course, make a link to the
                        copies at Romantic Circles, subject to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Tim Fulford</author>
                        <title>About This Edition</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title type="main">Robert Bloomfield - <emph>The Banks of the Wye</emph></title>
                        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
                        <author>
                            <name>Robert Bloomfield (1766–1823)</name>
                        </author>
                        <editor>Tim Fulford</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>University of Maryland</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p rend="noCount">All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for "," for ", ' for ', and ' for
                        '.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p rend="noCount">Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
                    <p rend="noCount">Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p rend="noCount">Dashes have been rendered as —</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p rend="noCount">Bloomfield's spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p rend="noCount">Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as such, the
                        content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p rend="noCount">&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p rend="noCount">£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
                    <p rend="noCount">All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have been encoded in
                        HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="g"
                    corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E">
                    <bibl>NINES categories for Genre and Material Form at
                        http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E on
                        2009-02-26</bibl>
                    <category xml:id="g1">
                        <catDesc>Architecture</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g2">
                        <catDesc>Artifacts</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g3">
                        <catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g4">
                        <catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g5">
                        <catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g7">
                        <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g6">
                        <catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g8">
                        <catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g9">
                        <catDesc>Politics</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g10">
                        <catDesc>Folklore</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g11">
                        <catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g12">
                        <catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g13">
                        <catDesc>History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g14">
                        <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g15">
                        <catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g16">
                        <catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g17">
                        <catDesc>Humor</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g18">
                        <catDesc>Education</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g19">
                        <catDesc>Music</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g20">
                        <catDesc>nonfiction</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g21">
                        <catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g22">
                        <catDesc>Perodical</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g23">
                        <catDesc>Philosphy</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g24">
                        <catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g25">
                        <catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g26">
                        <catDesc>Family Life</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g27">
                        <catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g28">
                        <catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g29">
                        <catDesc>Review</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g30">
                        <catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g31">
                        <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g32">
                        <catDesc>Travel</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g33">
                        <catDesc>Book History</catDesc>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="g34">
                        <catDesc>Law</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category">
                    <category xml:id="people">
                        <catDesc>Romantic Circles people: Bloomfield Banks of the Wye</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy corresp="people.xml/category">
                    <category xml:id="places">
                        <catDesc>Romantic Circles places: Bloomfield Banks of the Wye</catDesc>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef target="#g5 #g21" scheme="#genre"/>
                <catRef target="#EEd.25.names" scheme="#people"/>
                <catRef target="#EEd.25.places" scheme="#places"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="1" when="2011-01-21" who="#JW">
                <label>Changed by</label>
                <name xml:id="JW">Jason Whittaker</name>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI Encoding, first pass, all files</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
        
            <div type="paratext">
                <head>About this edition</head>
            
                <p rend="noCount">This edition presents a rare surviving example of the kind of multimedia production that arose from one of the new cultural activities of the late eighteenth century—the picturesque and antiquarian tour. It comprises a facsimile of the manuscript sketch- and scrap-book that Robert Bloomfield made after his 1807 tour of the Wye, an annotated transcription of the prose tour-journal that he incorporated into his scrap book, and a collated and annotated text of the poetic versions of the tour that were published (as <title level="m">The Banks of Wye</title>) in 1811, 1813, and 1823. Also included are reproductions of the engravings that illustrated the 1811 and 1813 publications, deleted or unadopted passages from the manuscript of the poem, and a selection of reviews from journals of the time. The whole represents a visually and verbally rich response to the fashionable tour of the Wye. Bloomfield’s manuscript sketch- and scrap-book is an example of the newly popular fashion for on-the-spot sketching. Full of self-penned images of views and ruins, it is a fine example of the visual culture that the English gentry began to produce and to value, a homemade book to pass around in drawing rooms before turning either to the latest set of engravings published by Mr Turner or to the poetic tour — <title level="m">The Banks of Wye</title> — that Bloomfield himself issued in print. Bloomfield, indeed, hoped to issue not just the poetic tour but also the ‘whole triple-page’d Journal, Drawings, prose, and rhime’. Cost prohibited such a publication at the time: only now, with this composite edition of poem, prose, scrap- and sketch-book, can we see the multimedia response to the Wye that was then accessible only to the intimate friends among whom the manuscript circulated.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paratext">
                <head>Format</head>
            
                <p rend="noCount">In preparing this edition I have followed the format of <ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/editions/bloomfield_letters">the edition of Bloomfield’s letters that I produced for Romantic Circles</ref> in collaboration with Lynda Pratt. The texts of the poem and the prose journal are fully annotated, with hyperlinks taking readers to documents identifying the people and the places mentioned therein. Facsimile reproductions of the pages of the manuscript journal are accessible both via hyperlinks from the transcription of the journal and from the List of Figures to be found in the Contextual Materials section of the site. A Bibliography, a List of Manuscripts, and a document containing unpublished drafts of the poem, transcribed from manuscript, are also to be found in the Contextual Materials section. A selection of contemporary reviews is also included there.</p>
            
            <p rend="noCount">Bloomfield 's original spelling, and mis-spelling, grammar and punctuation has been retained. Deletions are indicated by striking through the deleted word or phrase, but without any attempt to indicate the heaviness of the deletion. Throughout the text, 'x' is used to indicate an illegible character: e.g. 'he xxid'. Underlining is indicated by italics: e.g. '<emph>he said</emph>'. Editorial &lt;...&gt; are used to indicate an authorial insertion of text above or below the line.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="paratext">
                <head>People</head>
                
                <p rend="noCount">Tim Fulford is a Professor of English at De Montfort University. He has published several monographs and articles in which Bloomfield features, including <title level="m">Literature, Science and Exploration in the Romantic Era: Bodies of Knowledge</title> (2004). He edited <title level="m">Thalaba the Destroyer</title>, vol. 3 of <title level="m">Robert Southey: Poetical Works, 1793-1810</title> (2004) and is co-general editor, with Lynda Pratt, of the forthcoming <title level="m">Robert Southey: Later Poetical Works, 1811-1838</title>. Pratt and Fulford's edition <title level="m"><ref target="http://romantic.arhu.umd.edu/editions/southey_letters">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey</ref></title> is also online at Romantic Circles.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="paratext">
                    <head>Credits, Awards and Copyright</head>
                
                <p rend="noCount">For their invaluable assistance, I thank Kerri Andrews, Frances Banks, Carol Bolton, Averill Buchanan, Tim Burke, Julia S. Carlson, Neil Chambers, Rachel Crawford , Neil Fraistat, John Goodridge, Bruce Graver, Dafydd Johnston, Steve Jones, Suzanne Matheson, Tilar J. Mazzeo, Ian Packer, Lynda Pratt, Tami Spector, Sam Ward, Simon White, Hugh and Angela Underhill, Jason Whitaker. For permission to reproduce the MSS in its possession, I thank the British Library: the images remain copyright The British Library Board: ADD 28267 f1-f59.</p>
                
                <p rend="noCount">The Paul Mellon Centre for the Study of British Art and the Scouloudi Foundation kindly gave grants in support of illustrations costs.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="paratext">
                    <head>Contact</head>
                
                <p rend="noCount">The editor welcomes comments and corrections. Please contact:</p>
                
                <p rend="noCount">Tim Fulford: <ref target="mailto:timfulford@tiscali.co.uk">timfulford@tiscali.co.uk</ref></p>
                
                
                </div>
                <div type="paratext">
                    <head>About the Design</head>
                
                    <p rend="noCount">This electronic edition was TEI-encoded by Jason Whitaker in liaison with Laura Mandell and her team at Miami University of Ohio, and with the assistance of David Rettenmaier at the University of Maryland. The image associated with this edition was designed by Michael Quilligan at the University of Maryland, and includes elements from illustrations from this volume. Mandell transformed the TEI files into HTML by using modified versions of the transforms provided by the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml">TEI</ref>. The HTML pages do not use frames but rather make extensive use of tables and stylesheets for layout and presentation. The site works best when viewed with browsers later than Mozilla Firefox v. 3, Netscape 4.0, Internet Explorer 4.0, or comparable browsers; earlier browsers may not display everything properly.</p>
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
