<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">3778Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3778" type="letter"><head>3778. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-01-06">6 January 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               Endorsement: 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Jan.<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> 1822./ with Lr. on L Byron/ to the Courier.; 6 Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> 1822<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.<lb/>
               Note on MS: The original enclosure, Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776, is no longer with the letter to Bedford because the latter forwarded it to the newspaper, where it appeared on 11 January 1822.</note></head>
            
            
          <opener><salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">If you have read <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> note,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In the ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two Foscari’, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: ‘I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey’s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.’ Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May–August 1817. The ‘calumnies’ Byron believed Southey to have later spread were rumours that Byron and Shelley had engaged in a ‘League of Incest’ during their residence in Switzerland in 1816.</note> you will rather admire the temper in which I have answered it, than think any thing which I have said is too severe.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776. The letter appeared in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822.</note> He has literally blackguarded me. But this <hi rend="ital">Avenger of Abel</hi><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Genesis</title> 4: 1–16, Abel was murdered by his brother, Cain. Southey probably means that Byron had tried to justify Cain by writing <title>Cain, A Mystery</title>, but the poem was so disreputable it had instead avenged Abel.</note> will find me the ugliest customer he <del>ever</del> has ever ventured to deal with. If he compels me to return to the attack <hi rend="ital">tant mieux</hi>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘it is a good thing’.</note> I will lay him on the dissecting table, read a lecture upon morbid anatomy, &#38; demonstrate upon the living subject. I am as compleatly master of my temper, as his temper is master of him.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I saw the passage in a Whig-Radical paper published at Kendal, – no doubt all the provincial papers of that party will publish it.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Westmorland Advertiser and Kendal Chronicle</title>, 29 December 1821. Byron’s criticism of Southey in his ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two Foscari’ had been widely published in opposition newspapers, including the <title>Morning Chronicle</title>, 19 December 1821, and the <title>Examiner</title>, 726 (23 December 1821), 810.</note> Before this reply of mine appears in the other Kendal paper; I shall desire them to insert the attack, &#38; the passage from my Preface.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey got his wish. On 12 January 1822 the <title>Westmorland Gazette</title> (‘the other Kendal paper’) printed both Southey’s denunciation of ‘the Satanic School’ of modern poetry from <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), ‘Preface’, pp. xvii–xxii; and an extract from Byron’s attack on Southey in the ‘Appendix’ to the ‘Two Foscari’. Southey’s response to the latter, his letter to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776, was then printed in the <title>Westmorland Gazette</title>, 19 January 1822.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Some good passages have been struck out from the first draught of this reply, for the sake of keeping close to the subject. They may serve for after use. In one of them I had wiped my friends Jeremy the Merry Bentham,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Jeremy Bentham (1748–1832; <title>DNB</title>), philosopher and social reformer. In one of his drafts of the letter to the <title>Courier</title>, now Huntington MS 6655, Southey had commented: ‘The egregious &#38; incomparable Jeremy,&#60;ever Jeremy the Merry-Bentham&#62; equipped in full motley, has shaken his bells at me, erected his ancient cockscomb, and crowed in <title><del>triumphant</del></title> &#60;exultant&#62; defiance. Sir Tarquin the Table-Talker still slavers out his malevolence as freely as if he were quite certain I should never publish a tale in illustration of the old proverb <title><del>Save a Thief from the gallows</del></title> &#60;which tells me what he <title><del>xxx</del></title> xxxx criminal xxxx justice may expect for his reward>’. (See Appendix 3.)</note> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HazlittWilliam">Sir Tarquin the Table-Talker</ref>. All in good time. – You will like what is said of <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821) in <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 35 (July 1821), 422–436, had accused Southey of ‘a puny spite at those who dissent from his present creed in politics, and of a lamentable soreness at the success of those who have laughed at his affectations, or eclipsed, by their superior talents, his former fame as a poet’ (422). Southey responded by accusing Jeffrey, the <title>Edinburgh Review</title>’s editor, and author of this article, of ‘pitiful malevolence’; Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I shall now amuse myself with writing an answer to a challenge in case he should send me one, – which I should like well.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron asked his friend Douglas Kinnaird (1788–1830; <title>DNB</title>) to deliver a challenge to Southey on 7 February 1822. Wisely, Kinnaird did not carry out this instruction.</note> I had one ready for <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> at the last election.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Henry Peter Brougham, [c. July 1818], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Appendix 2. On 30 June 1818, during his general election campaign, Brougham had criticised Southey from the hustings at Appleby. Southey debated at length whether to make a public riposte to him – but in the end did not. He also fantasised about what he would do should he receive a challenge to a duel from Brougham. His jokey response to this possibility is published in Appendix 2.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">  No praise which has reached my ears ever pleased me half so much as an expression of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Piozzi’s in a letter, after she had read my tender Epistle to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SmithWilliam">Wm Smith</ref>, – it was this – Oh how I delight to see him <hi rend="ital">trample</hi> upon his enemies.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Hester Thrale Piozzi (1741–1821; <title>DNB</title>) to Reynold Davies (1752–1820), 29 April 1817, <title>The Piozzi Letters: Correspondence of Hester Lynch Piozzi (formerly Mrs Thrale)</title>, eds Edward A. Bloom and Lillian D. Bloom, 6 vols (Cranbury NJ and London, 1989–2002), VI, p. 87. This was Hester Piozzi’s response to Southey’s <title>A Letter to William Smith, Esq., M.P</title>. (1817). Southey had been shown her letter on his trip to London that year; see Southey to Thomas Southey, 5 May 1817, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 2986.</note> – Poor old Lady, had she been alive now, she would have seen me trample upon the Avenger of Abel in better style than S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> George does upon the dragon in the crown piece.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The reverse of the silver crown coin (worth five shillings) had, since 1818, carried an engraving of St George defeating the dragon, designed by Benedetto Pistrucci (1783–1855; <title>DNB</title>).</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I am very anxious to hear of your own official affairs. –</p>
           <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
              <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
            
            <postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1822-01-06">6 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822</date></p>
               <lb/>
            
               <p rend="indent1"> This inclosure<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The enclosure was Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776.</note> I fear will lose two days in reaching you, by following <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">R.</ref> into the country.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey here acknowledges that his letter would take longer than usual to reach Bedford because it was being sent to him via Rickman (see Letter 3779).</note></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
