<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
            <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
            <title level="a">3781. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 January 1822</title>
            <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
    
            <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
               <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Director</resp>
               <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp> Editor</resp>
               <name />
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
               <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2024-04-08</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
               University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                  reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                  it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                  and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                  amended.</p>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                  Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                  accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                  as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                  in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                  editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                  for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
               <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                  conditions: 
                  <list>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                        purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                     <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                        forms other than their current ones.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                  to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                  of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                  elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                  edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                  to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                  can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                  to our conditions of use.</p>
            </availability>
            <idno type="edition">3781Southey</idno>
            <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" type="main">3781. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 12 January 1822</title>
                  <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3781Southey"/>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" />
                  <title level="s" />
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                        University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <quotation>
               <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                  " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
               <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                  except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
               <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                  have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
               <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
               <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
               <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                  has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
            </normalization>
            <normalization>
               <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
               <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
               <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                  etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
         <tagsDecl>
            <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
               font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
            <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
         </tagsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
            <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
            <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
            <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
               <term subtype="tags" />
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name />
            <date />
            <list>
               <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
            </list>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3781" type="letter"><head>3781. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, 
            <date when="1822-01-12">12 January 1822</date></head>
           
            <p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb/>
               Endorsements: 12 Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>. 1822; 12. Jan<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>. 1822<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</p>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I was very glad to receive your long letter &#38; well pleased with all its contents, as well knowing that in one part you had rather expressed a transitory feeling than a settled one. There is a great deal of sterling friendship in the world, &#38; you are one of the last persons who should doubt it. You have so much of it yourself, that you would not only turn in your bed to serve me, but will, I dare say, save my corn-factor Joey Lock<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Locke (dates unknown), Southey’s shoemaker in London. Southey punningly refers to him as a ‘corn factor’, literally a trader in grain, but in this case a maker of corns on Southey’s feet.</note> the trouble of sending me a <del>bill the second</del> second bill for <del>the cxxx</del> his good works; – &#38; also prevent the like danger, (if it still exists) from Willis, on the score of the Stewardship.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been persuaded by his uncle, Herbert Hill, to share the role of Steward (i.e. bear part of the expenses) for the annual meeting of Westminster School ex-pupils in London. This took place at Willis’s Rooms in King Street, St James’s, in 1821.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">There is, (I repeat it), a great deal of sterling friendship in the world. It is very true that as men get higher in this world they are less able to act from feeling &#38; inclination. They are involved in party obligations. &#38; political considerations must of necessity predominate over personal ones. This is the case officially with all men, – &#38; in his honour, who I suppose is now to be <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Right-Honour</ref>,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had joined the Cabinet as President of the Board of Control and was admitted to the Privy Council on 17 January 1822, making him a ‘Right Honourable’.</note> there is more than this, arising from what <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">a Doxtor</ref> would call his idiosyncrasy. He who every morning of his life has been doing something else when he ought to have been dressing himself, will in like manner be doing some thing else when he might be serving those for whom he has the sincerest regard. But upon the specific subject of your wishes, (to which however I see there is an end, by your letter of today) I should really think the surest &#38; easiest way of serving <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> would be by endeavouring to secure his promotion in his own office, where he has the strongest claims, &#38; where he is master of the business.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Bedford had been a Clerk in the Admiralty since 1804. He was a Second Class Clerk 1816–1826, rising to First Class Clerk 1826–1844.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I shall look for you without fail next summer, &#38; lay out my plans accordingly in full assurance of your coming. Now I pray you, bring <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> with you – Do not either of you, think of any difficulties in the way, but make up your minds to it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">My Aunt Mary</ref>, who is old enough to be <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Ps</ref> mother took a longer journey last year. You do not know how much pleasure it would give <del>me</del> &#60;us&#62; to have her under this roof. – &#38; I say this for <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">my Governess</ref> as well as myself. Give my love to her, – &#38; <del>let me have a xxxxxxx</del> let no persuasions on your part be wanting to make her undertake the journey.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you<lb/>
           <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            
            <postscript><p rend="indent1">The Courier comes regularly to me. I cannot guess who wrote the letter signed Vindex.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A letter headed ‘Lord Byron and Mr. Southey’ and signed by ‘Vindex’ had appeared in the <title>Courier</title> on 9 January 1822. It defended Southey against Byron’s attack in the ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two Foscari’, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, where Byron had cautioned: ‘I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey’s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.’ Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May–August 1817. The ‘calumnies’ Byron believed Southey to have later spread were rumours that Byron and Shelley had engaged in a ‘League of Incest’ during their residence in Switzerland in 1816. For the argument that ‘Vindex’ was William Wordsworth, see Nicholas Joukovsky, ‘Wordsworth’s Lost Article on Byron and Southey’, <title>Review of English Studies</title>, 45 (November 1994), 496–516.</note> My own tender Epistle<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776. The letter appeared in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822.</note> looks well</p>
               <lb/>
               <p rend="indent0"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-01-12">12 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1822</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
