<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3787. Robert Southey to Bartholomew Frere, 27 January 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-10</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3787Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3787. Robert Southey to Bartholomew Frere, 27 January 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3787Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-10">April 10, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3787" type="letter">
        <head>3787. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Bartholomew Frere</ref>, <date when="1822-01-27">27 January 1822</date>
          </head>
        <p>Address: [in pencil in another hand] To Bartholomew Frere Esq. / 74 Saville Row<lb />
               Postmark: 2 o&#8217;Clock/ 30 JA/ 1822<lb />
               Watermark: [partial] 1819<lb />
               MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-01-27">27 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">You have indeed rendered me an essential service.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Frere was providing Southey with advice and materials for his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> I should have done ample justice to <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymple</ref> as to his conduct in Portugal; &amp; made honourable amends to him for the vehemence with which, twelve years ago I expressed a feeling, right in its principle, but injurious in its direction.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 365&#8211;378, had declared the Convention of Cintra (1808), which Dalrymple had negotiated with the defeated French forces in Portugal, to be &#8216;scandalous&#8217; (366). Southey&#8217;s treatment of the matter in <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 566&#8211;594, was much more circumspect, pointing out the Convention&#8217;s military advantages, but declaring it contained &#8216;some political errors&#8217; (577).</note> I have Lord Burghershs book, &amp; also Col. Jones&#8217;s;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Fane, 11th Earl of Westmorland (1784&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoir of the Early Campaigns of the Duke of Wellington: in Portugal and Spain. By an Officer Employed in his Army</title> (1820). Fane was known by the courtesy title Lord Burghersh until 1841. Sir John Thomas Jones, 1st Baronet (1783&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Account of the War in Spain, Portugal, and the South of France, from 1808 to 1814 Inclusive. In Two Volumes</title> (1821). An earlier one-volume edition had appeared in 1818.</note> &amp; I perceive a consequence of the Convention of Cintra which has not (I believe) yet been pointed out: &#8211; that Elvas (if not Almeida), would certainly have held out till the dispersion of the Spanish armies, &amp; that a movement of the French to relieve it, which would of course have been made, would have drawn them to Portugal in that direction, at the time when we only waited for their approach, to abandon Lisbon. Severer terms ought to have been imposed; but we did not then understand how to treat with the French; &#8211; neither indeed did we learn it even when we had learnt to beat them thoroughly. You will very soon see in what manner this transaction is treated; I hope &amp; think you will find it in accord with your own feelings; &#8211; but if it appears erroneous or unjust in any point, only let me know, &amp; I will reconsider it. For the chance of some such suggestions I shall always detain the proof sheet till the third post, instead of the second, as heretofore.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">It is with regard to the former part of <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hews</ref> conduct that you have served me now, by enabling me to remedy an act of omission, &#8211; which must not be called a sin, because it was involuntary. To the best of my recollection, <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hews</ref> offer of papers was not transmitted to me; &#8211; if it were, I could only have returned the answer which I have uniformly made in such cases, &#8211; that I should be truly thankful for the communication. &#8211; Concerning all the operations of Casta&#241;os,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">General Francisco Javier Castanos, 1st Duke of Bail&#233;n (1758&#8211;1852), and victor at the Battle of Bail&#233;n, 16&#8211;19 July1808.</note> I felt a want of information, &amp; knew not where to obtain it. It did not occur to me to apply to <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew</ref>, because I thought that if he had any papers which he wished me to see, he would have offered them; &#8211; that he has done this I did not know, &amp; was conscious that I had no right to ask it at his hands. If he will favour me with them now, I will rewrite that part of the chapter;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Battle of Bail&#233;n was the first great success of Spanish forces in the Peninsular War. Southey dealt with the matter in his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 382&#8211;386. On pp. 389&#8211;390, Southey inserted material concerning Dalrymple&#8217;s role in the attempts of Spanish commanders to change the terms of surrender of the French army.</note> as in justice I am bound to do. &#8211; I will attend also to Gen. Whittinghams remarks,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant General Sir Samuel Ford Whittingham (1772&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), British soldier who served with Spanish forces in the Peninsular War 1808&#8211;1813.</note> &#8211; for which, &amp; for the <hi rend="ital">Parte Historica</hi>
          <note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;historical part&#8217;.</note> I am greatly obliged. I am now well provided with materials concerning the operations on that coast, the late <ref type="m" target="people.html#HolroydJohnBaker">Lord Sheffield</ref> supplied me with some from Sir H Clintons<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">General Sir William Henry Clinton (1769&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), commander of the 1st Division in Spain 1812&#8211;1813 and commander-in-chief of British forces in eastern Spain 1813&#8211;1814. Clinton was the Earl of Sheffield&#8217;s son-in-law; see Southey to [John Baker Holroyd, 1st Earl of Sheffield], 8 May 1817, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 2990.</note> papers, &#8211; &amp; I am promised others from Lord W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Bentinck.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord William Henry Cavendish-Bentinck (1774&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), who served in Spain before commanding British troops in Sicily 1811&#8211;1815; see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 15 October 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3735.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I received O Donnells narrative, &amp; will return it as soon as it is done with. Is this the O Donnell who became Conde de Bisbal?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Enrique Jose O&#8217;Donnell y Anatar (1769&#8211;1834), Spanish General, created Conde de La Bisbal in 1810. The &#8216;narrative&#8217; that Southey was reading was O&#8217;Donnell&#8217;s journal.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Gen: Whittingham can probably tell me whether the Spanish official history of the war, has proceeded beyond the first volume, &#8211; or been put a stop to by this miserable Revolution,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A military revolt in 1820 had overthrown royal absolutism in Spain and restored the Constitution of 1812.</note> &#8211; miserable it may well be called, &#8211; for in such a state of things one knows not what to wish, where there is nothing but what is evil in prospect. The first volume is exceedingly good, &#8211; tho I have only seen it in a French translation.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Histoire de la Guerre de l&#8217;Espagne contre Napoleon Buonaparte, Par une Commission d&#8217;Officiers de Toutes Armes Etablie a Madrid, Aupres de S. Ex. Le Ministre de la Guerre; Traduite de l&#8217;Espanol, Avec Notes et Eclaircissemens</title> (1818).</note> &#8211; Marshal S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cyr<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Laurent de Gouvion Saint-Cyr (1764&#8211;1830), <title>Journal des Operations de l&#8217;Armee de Catalogne, en 1808 et 1809</title> (1821).</note> has published a good account of his short command in Catalonia. But in general the French books concerning this war are as rascally as their conduct in it</p>
        <p rend="indent0"> [MS missing; inserted in pencil in another hand in the left-hand margin is the following]</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent0">&lt;farewell my dear Sir<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent0">&amp; believe me<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent0"> Very thankfully<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent0"> &amp; truly yours<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent0">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">To Bartholomew Frere, Esq.&gt;</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>