<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3789" type="letter"><head>3789. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#YorkRichard">Richard York</ref>, <date when="1822-01-28">28 January 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Richard York Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Wighill Park/ near/ Tadcaster<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb/>
               MS: Borthwick Institute for Archives, University of York. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-01-28">28 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I have to thank you for a brace of Pheasants, which reached me this day, &#38; for your obliging note. It is very gratifying to me that my letter in the Courier appears to have been felt as it was intended.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">In the ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two Foscari’, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: ‘I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey’s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.’ Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May–August 1817. The ‘calumnies’ Byron believed Southey to have later spread were rumours that Byron and Shelley had engaged in a ‘League of Incest’ during their residence in Switzerland in 1816. Southey had responded by writing to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776. His letter was published in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822.</note> Had it not been for the sake of again pointing out in strong terms the abominable tendency &#38; purpose of <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byrons</ref> writings, I should no more have thought of noticing his coarse &#38; insolent charges against me, than of replying to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HoneWilliam">Hone</ref> or <ref type="m" target="people.html#CobbettWilliam">Cobbett</ref>. He has sent over for publication viler things than have yet appeared<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Vision of Judgment</title> (1822), a parody of Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), was first published in the <title>Liberal</title>, 1 (October 1822), 3–39; and <title>Heaven and Earth; a Mystery</title> in the <title>Liberal</title>, 2 (January 1823), 165–206. Murray had declined to publish them.</note> &#38; such as no bookseller will venture to touch, unless he be one of the <hi rend="ital">ames damnées</hi><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘damned souls’.</note> of the trade. It is however well that he should deal avowedly in poison; for the circulation of those works in which he has covertly administered it with so much success, will certainly be impeded now.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  If I should at any time be in your neighbourhood, I shall have great pleasure in paying my respects to you at Wighill Park<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The home of the York family, near Tadcaster, Yorkshire.</note></p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">I have the honour to remain</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3"> Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent4">Your obliged &#38; obedient servant</salute>
         <signed rend="indent5">   Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
