<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">3797Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3797" type="letter"><head>3797. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1822-02-09">9 February 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Miss Bowles/ Buckland/ near Lymington/ Hampshire<lb/>
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 23 To Miss Caroline Bowles<lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 24–26.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1822-02-09">9 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822.</date></dateline></opener>
            
           <p rend="indent0"> Thank you for your little volume.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822).</note> I received it yesterday evening. It was with pleasure that I saw it advertised, &#38; with more pleasure that I saw it turn up among the contents of a heavy parcel. Have I perused it with pleasure? both with as much pleasure &#38; as much pain as you have wished to excite. And whether most to find fault with you for chusing such deeply tragic subjects, or to praise you for the manner in which you have treated them I know not.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">For the execution, it is not too much to say that you have become such a poetess as I believed &#38; hoped from the first. You have the ear &#38; the eye &#38; the heart of poetry, – &#38; you have them in perfection. Had this volume appeared thirty years ago, England would have rung from side to side with its praises. And gay as the flower market now is, take my word for it it will flourish when all the annuals of the season have faded.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> William &#38; Jean<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘William and Jean’, <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), pp. 103–124.</note> would to my judgement, have <del>been</del> made two poems with advantage. – The picture which is, like all your pictures, true, &#38; finely coloured by itself; – but it is too chearful, too happy, for the tale which follows<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Conte à Mon Chien’, <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), pp. 125–147.</note> – Your tragedy is always in the right tone, having with it the true &#38; only balm. Yet it is too painful. I feel it to be so, &#38; in this respect I may judge of others by myself. We are less able to bear these emotions as we advance in years. Youth courts them, because youth has happiness as well as health &#38; spirits in excess. But at my time of life, tranquillity is the treasure of &#60;the&#62; mind, – &#38; if it must be broken, more willingly would I have it done by comedy or farce that makes the sides ache, than by any thing which <del>xxx</del> excites a heartache for imaginary distress, – especially with such possible &#38; actual scenes as that of your Editha,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Editha: a Dramatic Sketch’, <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), pp. [187]–222.</note> – perhaps the more painful to me because I have <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">a daughter</ref> of that name.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Give me I intreat you, a picture in summer &#38; sunshine, – a tale that in its progress &#38; termination shall answer to the wishes of the reader. Make the creatures of your imagination as happy as you would make them if they were real beings whose fortunes depended upon your will. Your poem will then be read again &#38; again with delight. You will please more readers, &#38; please them more. It is a road to popular favour which has not been tried in this country, &#38; it is a sure one. Goethe &#38; Voss have found it so in Germany. And I speak sincerely when I <del>say that</del> express my belief that you can produce as fine a poem as the Herman &#38; Dorothea, or the Luise.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Heinrich Voss (1751–1826), <title>Luise</title> (1783) and Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749–1832), <title>Hermann and Dorothea</title> (1797).</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> It is better for yourself too to dwell upon happier themes. You have no such exuberance of health &#38; spirits that you can afford with impunity to shed so many tears as these poems must have cost you.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I must not forget to mention the Sea of Life,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Sea of Life’, <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), pp. 83–102.</note> – which is throughout in a fine tone both of feeling &#38; versification. At P. 95 you should have written ‘<hi rend="ital">ignes fatui</hi>’, – but marsh-fires would <del>xxx</del> &#60;be&#62; better, if the word marshes did not occur in the next line.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘led astray/ By <hi rend="ital">igni fatui</hi> from the beaten way,/ They founder in the marshes of despair’: <title>The Widow’s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (London, 1822), p. 94. <hi rend="ital">Ignis</hi> fatuus, the meterological phenomenon popularly known as will-o-the-wisp, phosphorescent light seen over marshy ground at night.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> And now let me ask <hi rend="ital">how</hi> you are? That you are in the sure way to reputation, &#38; that of no mean degree, or transitory kind you must yourself know; – &#38; that feeling will encourage you in a favourite pursuit. I think you are right in withholding your name. There is an advantage in exciting curiosity, – &#38; sometimes a comfort in privacy which one is not sensible of till it is lost.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I shall send you my Book of the Church<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> as soon as it is published – you will go with it in feeling, &#38; find in it, I think, something that will interest you. But do not wait for it to let me hear from you, for it will not be ready in less than three or four months. – I am fastened to my desk by many employments, but well both in myself, &#38; in my family (God be thanked) – &#38; no ways disturbed by such enemies as <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In the ‘Appendix’ to ‘The Two Foscari’, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: ‘I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey’s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.’ Southey had visited Switzerland in his continental tour of May–August 1817. The ‘calumnies’ Byron believed Southey to have later spread were rumours that Byron and Shelley had engaged in a ‘League of Incest’ during their residence in Switzerland in 1816. Southey had responded by writing to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776. His letter was published in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822.</note></p>
            <closer>  <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">   Yrs faithfully</salute>
            <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
