<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3800. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 13 February 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3800Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3800. Robert Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 13 February 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3800Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3800" type="letter">
        <head>3800. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-02-13">13 February 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer<lb />
               Endorsement: 13. Feb<hi rend="sup">ry</hi>. 1822.<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-01-13">13 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi> 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Say for me how much obliged I am to General Hawker.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Major-General Samuel Hawker (1763&#8211;1838), who had served in the Peninsular War  between 1808 and 1811 as commander of the 14th Light Dragoons and made a number of sketches in Spain.</note> Whenever I come to town it will be a great gratification to me to see his sketches, if he will favour me with a sight of them. At present it will be quite sufficient if he will point out for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref> choice such views as are connected with any prominent events or circumstances of the war.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall wished to use Hawker&#8217;s sketches to assist with his <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). The <title>Views</title> could be detached and inserted in the appropriate place in the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> The hints to which the note alludes would be highly useful to me: &amp; I should be truly thankful to him for any circumstances which he can communicate concerning the movements of the army.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You would have heard from me sooner if I had not been deeply engaged in peninsular business. I am carrying on a brisk correspondence with <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Barth. Frere</ref> upon this subject, obtaining that sort of information which official papers do not communicate, from him, &amp; thro him, from <del>xx</del> Sir S. Whittingham.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant General Sir Samuel Ford Whittingham (1772&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), British soldier who served with Spanish forces in the Peninsular War 1808&#8211;1813.</note> And I have also a box of papers from <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymple</ref>, which will it make it necessary for me to insert a few pages <del>previous to</del> concerning the affairs in Andalusia &amp; the capture of Duponts army.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Pierre Dupont de l&#8217;Etang (1765&#8211;1840), French general. His defeat at the Battle of Bail&#233;n, 16&#8211;19 July1808, was the first great success of Spanish forces in the Peninsular War. Southey dealt with the matter in his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 382&#8211;386. On pp. 389&#8211;390, Southey inserted some material concerning Dalrymple&#8217;s role in the attempts of Spanish commanders to change the terms of surrender of the French army.</note> I should wish you now to let me have the clean sheets, which may come in three or four franks from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Right Honour</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Most heartily do I wish that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Rt Honour</ref> had it in his own power to do all that you deserve for <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref>,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Bedford had been a Clerk in the Admiralty since 1804. He was a Second Class Clerk 1816&#8211;1826, rising to First Class Clerk 1826&#8211;1844.</note> &#8211; I am sure there would be no delay in doing it. There is a heavy price paid for power, in the vexation of not being able to befriend those who deserve it, &amp; the annoyance of perpetual solicitations from those whose impudence is their strongest claim. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Our friend</ref> will provide for Welshmen by the dozen, by sending them to India, &#8211; some of whom peradventure (in profound secrecy be it said) had they left &lt;here&gt; to follow their <del>natural</del> national &amp; natural instinct for forbidden mutton, might have been provided for at the public expense in a different but as distant a part of the world.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suggests that Wynn, as President of the Board of Control, with ultimate control over the East India Company, would be able to provide posts for many Welshmen in India; but if these men remained at home and followed their &#8216;instinct&#8217; for stealing sheep they would be transported to Australia.</note> Will &lt;he&gt; be able to obtain a stall for <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref>?<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Canons of English cathedrals are assigned a special stall for use during services. These appointments are made by the Crown (i.e. in practice by the Prime Minister) and some were at this time very lucrative. Elmsley did not become a Canon, but he was offered the Bishopric of Calcutta (he declined). In 1823 Elmsley became Camden Professor of Ancient History and Principal of St Alban Hall, Oxford.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I must explain to you about <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> volume<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor&#8217;s <title>Idyllia Heroica Decem Phaleuciorum Unum Partim jam Primo Partim Iterum atq Tertio Edit Savagius Landor</title> (1820), no. 1598 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> concerning which you have escaped all trouble. It was in a frankable shape, &#8211; &amp; I had no other means of franking it than under cover to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, &#8211; the trouble which it would have given you would have been only that of leaving it at <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> door. But you were at Oxford when it arrived &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> very kindly sent it to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>. I give you <del>xx</del> much trouble in your factotumship for me, &amp; I should be very sorry if you were to think I ever did it when it could be avoided.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> said something to me about a paper on the State of the Country.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> I could with hearty good will advise or defend bolder measures than this ministry have courage to think of: &#8211; &amp; as you know, should not be deterred from the task by any apprehension of the ruffian-like attacks which it would draw on. But I do not think I could write to any purpose in the QR. where I should be restricted from the Cath: question.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Quarterly Review</title> was neutral on Catholic Emancipation; Southey was determinedly opposed.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &amp; I (if I do not mistake his opinions) differing upon that momentous point. &#8211; &amp; when other topics must be <del>xx</del> managed with a view rather to avoid offence, than to point out the right &amp; only measures of honour &amp; security.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I believe I shall dedicate my history to Lord Sidmouth,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), Prime Minister 1801&#8211;1804, Home Secretary 1812&#8211;1822. He had resigned the latter post on 17 January 1822. Southey dedicated his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) to George IV rather than to Sidmouth.</note> now that he is now no longer in office.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you <lb/>
          RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>