<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3801. Robert Southey to David Laing, 20 February 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3801Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3801. Robert Southey to David Laing, 20 February 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3801Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3801" type="letter">
        <head>3801. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LaingDavid">David Laing</ref>, <date when="1822-02-20">20 February 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ David Laing Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Edinburgh<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: FEB/ X 21 N/ 1822<lb />
               MS: Edinburgh University Library, Special Collections, The Laing Collection. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Previously published: Geoffrey Bullough, &#8216;Southey and David Laing&#8217;, <title>Times Literary Supplement</title>, 1681 (19 April 1934), 282 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-02-20">20 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">The Quaker books<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">David Laing had offered to loan Southey books to help with his projected, but unrealised, life of George Fox (1624&#8211;1690; <title>DNB</title>), founder of Quakerism.</note> have arrived safely, &#8211; I thank you for their use, &amp; shall be more glad to thank you personally when you call for them on your road. You must give me a day, that I may show you some of the beauties with which this place is surrounded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I was glad to see the Latin edition of Croesius, having only an English translation;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Gerard Croese (1642&#8211;1710), <title>Historia Quakeriana</title> (1695), no. 767 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It was translated as <title>The General History of the Quakers</title> (1696), no. 393 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> of Barclay also I had only the English apology,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Barclay (1648&#8211;1690; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Apology for the True Christian Divinity</title> (1678), no. 174 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The book was originally published in Latin in Amsterdam in 1676.</note> &amp; an account of his Life &amp; Writings published in 1802.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Gurney Bevan (1753&#8211;1814; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Short Account of the Life and Writings of Robert Barclay</title> (1802), no. 343 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> The adoption of Hac Ebn Yokdan by the Quakers<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Ibn Tufail (c. 1105&#8211;1185), <title>Hayy ibn Yaqzan</title> (early twelfth century), is an allegorical tale in which a boy who grows up alone on a desert island attains great wisdom purely from studying nature, and deduces his own system of beliefs, including monotheism and vegetarianism. The book was translated into Latin as <title>Philosophus Autodidactus</title> (1671) and English as <title>The Improvement of Human Reason</title> (1708). It was mentioned in Robert Barclay&#8217;s <title>An Apology for the True Christian Divinity</title> (London, 1678), p. 134, as proof that a person could attain &#8216;a profound knowledge of God&#8217; by &#8216;a conjunction of the mind of man with the Supreme Intellect&#8217;.</note> is a curious fact with which I was not previously acquainted; Quaker Missionaries of this temper would make converts in Persia, &amp; in Hindostan, &#8211; wherever mysticism &amp; naturalism are to be found. Barclay seems to me to have saved the Quakers, &#8211; before this time they hardly knew what they believed; &amp; as upon principle they spoke &amp; wrote without thinking, they often in pure absence of thought uttered expressions from which the worst consequences deduced by their adversaries were fairly inferred, &#8211; fairly as respected the words, but wrongfully as respected men in their state of mind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Tell me if a letter to Cambridge will be of use to you. I have a friend there &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">a fellow of Peter House</ref>, who I am sure will be very glad to render you any facilities, &amp; show you any attentions in his power, &#8211; &amp; I can frank you the letter by sending it six hundred miles round.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. by sending the letter to London, to be franked by one of Southey&#8217;s friends in government service, such as John Rickman, or Grosvenor Charles Bedford, who would then send the letter on to Laing in Edinburgh.</note> What a state of society does it imply, when this only occasions a delay of three or four days!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am glad you like Kehama,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (1810).</note> which both as regards the structure of the verse &amp; of the story, is the most original of my poems. But my career as a poet is almost at an end. If I compleat two poems which have been been several years in hand,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825); and his unfinished epic, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, set in New England. A fragment was published posthumously in <title>Oliver Newman: a New-England Tale (Unfinished): with Other Poetical Remains by the Late Robert Southey</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;90.</note> it is not likely that I shall ever begin another. <hi rend="ital">Solve senescentem</hi> &amp;c.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A contraction of &#8216;solve senescentem mature sanus equum&#8217;, meaning &#8216;a wise person would put his aged, broken horse out to pasture&#8217;, Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65&#8211;8 BC), <title>Epistles</title> (20 BC), Book 1, Epistle 1, lines 8&#8211;9.</note>
        </p>
        <p>
          Fare well my dear Sir<lb/>
            &amp; believe me yours faithfully<lb/>
           Robert Southey
        </p>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">What you say of the hexameter
            <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">David Laing had criticised Southey&#8217;s use of hexameters in <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> 
            was <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> objection to it twenty years ago, &#8211; that the beginning of the line was not sufficiently metrical, &#8211; the end of it too much so. &#8211; Yet in his judgement as well as mine, the practicability of naturalizing this metre is proved by the experiment. I shall like to show you the scene which is faithfully described in the first page, &#8211; from the window of this room.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), pp. 1&#8211;2; stanza 1, lines 1&#8211;21 of the poem described the view from Southey&#8217;s window.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>