<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3810Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3810" type="letter">
        <head>3810. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-03-02">2 March 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsements: R.S. 2 March. 1822.; 2 March. 1822<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 2p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I did not know Gen. H.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Major-General Samuel Hawker (1763&#8211;1838), who had served in the Peninsular War between 1808 and 1811 as commander of the 14th Light Dragoons and made a number of sketches in Spain.</note> was in France, or, of course, I should never have thought of asking him to select sketches which were to be copied in England. All I can now say &lt;is&gt; that I am much obliged both to him &amp; to your friend for their kind intentions, &#8211; &amp; very sorry that <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref> should be disappointed.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall wished to use Hawker&#8217;s sketches for <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These pictures could be detached from the publication so as to be at their appropriate places in the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am grieved at the uncomfortable tone of your letter: &amp; just now am in no condition to answer it, having a sick house, &amp; being myself by no means well. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> has a bilious fever upon him, which is not called alarming, but is quite sufficient to make me very uneasy, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my eldest daughter</ref> is far from well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I care not how the clean sheets are sent me<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823).</note> &#8211; Only <del>that as</del> I have told <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> I had desired you to send them under his cover, &#8211; &amp; it is better you should so do than seem to shun him. This is not a healthy feeling, &amp; I wish most earnestly that you would shake it off. A month among the mountains would be of infinite use to you, in putting your spirits &amp; feelings to rights. As for retiring into a hollow tree it was done by an English Saint who for so doing was named Simon Stok.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">St Simon Stock (13th century), English saint and early Prior-General of the Carmelite Order. One tradition about him states that as a boy he retired to live as a hermit in the hollow trunk of an oak tree.</note> But I would neither have you turn Stock or Stone<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A common phrase, meaning wood or stone. It derives ultimately from <title>Jeremiah</title> 2: 27.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">His Right Honour</ref> is now on a &#8220;bed of roses&#8221;.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Christopher Marlowe (1564&#8211;1593; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;The Passionate Shepherd to his Love&#8217; (1599), line 9. Wynn had joined the Cabinet as President of the Board of Control.</note> The only difference it will make between him &amp; me, is that there will be rather less difference in some of our opinions, &amp; he will see some things more as I have been accustomed to see them: &#8211; particularly the amiable character of the Opps. &#8211; The sooner you can let me have the clean sheets the better, for I shall very shortly want to refer to them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> If you will not promise to bring <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">your brother</ref> here I will write to her, &amp; tell her to bring you. You ought to have a <hi rend="ital">Lady Mare</hi> to rule you as I have.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. the unmarried Bedford needed a wife.</note> Is not that title as good as <ref type="m" target="people.html#CampbellHenry">Lord Horse</ref>? I invented it the other day after <hi rend="ital">a peck</hi>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A pun on the double meaning of &#8216;peck&#8217;: a kiss on the cheek; and, a measure of grain that might be given to a horse.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">   RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1822-03-02">2 March. 1822.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>