<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3814. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 19 March 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3814Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3814. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 19 March 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3814Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3814" type="letter">
        <head>3814. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-03-19">19 March 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 22 MR 22/ 1822<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.122. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-03-19">19 March. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have to trouble you with a commission which will cost you a walk to Upper Norton Street.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A bust of Southey had been sculpted in 1813 by James Smith (1775&#8211;1815). Smith&#8217;s business was continued by his sons, Charles Raymond Smith (c. 1798&#8211;1888) and Thomas Smith (b. 1800) at 57 Upper Norton Street.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &amp; I having agreed to make an exchange of loggerheads,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Literally a stupid, thick-headed person, but here used in a joking way to describe a sculpted bust.</note> I must beg you to order one of mine from poor Smiths, which they will send by waggon, directed to him, Rydal Mount, Ambleside, near Kendal, &#8211; pay the carriage thereof, &amp; come to you for payment of bust packing-case &amp; carriage. For this, for the frames &amp;c <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will reimburse you whenever you please. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ChantreyFrancis">Chantrey</ref>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Francis Chantrey had completed a bust of Wordsworth in 1820. It is now in the Wordsworth Room, Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington.</note> has made a very fine bust of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>: the likeness is not striking at first, but the more it is looked at, the more the resemblance appears, &amp; the art of the sculptor.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I have been spending two or three days at Rydal, for the sake of shaking myself up a little, &amp; changing the air. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> I hope will go early in the spring to Harrowgate with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref>; &amp; in that case, I shall go to bring them home, &amp; spend a week or so in that part of the country seeing the sight: &#8211; the only excursion for which I am likely to afford time &amp; money this year.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My first volume<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is far advanced in the press, &#8211; 568 pages. I have obtained some very interesting communications from Whittingham<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant General Sir Samuel Ford Whittingham (1772&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), a British soldier who served with Spanish forces in the Peninsular War 1808&#8211;1813.</note> by means of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Bart. Frere</ref>; their recollections have given me a great deal of that information which is not to be found in official papers. I have also received some most important papers from <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymple</ref>. The French will not be pleased with this volume, nor any of the admirers of Buonaparte:<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note> &amp; my friends the Whigs will not find much to gratify them in the introductory chapter.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 3&#8211;61, which contained a great deal of criticism of the Whigs for opposing war with France, especially at pp. 55&#8211;58.</note> In the rest of the work I shall have little occasion to comment upon their conduct; the worst punishment which it is possible to inflict upon them <del>will be</del> is by carefully recording <del>their</del> the series of their predictions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am sorry to see the rumours which are thrown out of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Kings</ref> intended marriage,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George IV&#8217;s mistress from 1819 was Elizabeth Conygham, Marchioness Conygham (1769&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>). Her demand that the government provide employment for her relatives and friends was causing some strain between the King and his Cabinet.</note> &#8211; a measure, to use the lightest expression, imprudent in every point of view, &#8211; unless it be promoted by ministers for the purpose of destroying an influence which is always mischievously directed. But the remedy may prove worse than the disease. At any rate it would induce a great expence, &amp; in case of his having children, a long minority, thereby giving great advantage to faction, which, God knows, requires none. I do not think any monarchy in Europe <del>xx xxxxx</del> &lt;will stand&gt; fifty years <del>xxxxx xxxx</del> but if they are overthrown, whatever the process may be, the end must be an iron tyranny every where.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> is on a bed of roses.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Christopher Marlowe (1564&#8211;1593; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;The Passionate Shepherd to his Love&#8217; (1599), line 9. Wynn had joined the Cabinet in January 1822, with the office of President of the Board of Control. This gave him ultimate responsibility for overseeing the affairs of the East India Company and the government of its possessions in India. He disagreed with Southey, though, by favouring Catholic Emancipation.</note> I am glad he is there; for except upon the Catholic question, no man has sounder opinions upon all great points. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Phillimore</ref>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Phillimore had been appointed to the Board of Control on 8 February 1822, serving until 1828.</note> is a man with whom I was upon good terms at school &amp; at College; <del>&amp; whom</del> every body liked &amp; respected him. He is, I think, likely to distinguish himself in proportion as he is called forth, &amp; he has the great advantage of one of the most powerful voices I ever heard.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Have you seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> lately? I am anxious to know how he is going on, &amp; not a little apprehensive that his last accounts are unfavourable ones, because I have not heard from him.</p>
        <p rend="indent2">  Our love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">Mrs Gonne</ref>
        </p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>