<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3816</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3816Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3816" type="letter">
        <head>3816. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#AtherstoneEdwin">Edwin Atherstone</ref>, <date when="1822-03-25">25 March 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] London Twenty Eight March/ 1822/ E. Atherstone Esq/ Taunton/ Fm/ J Rickman<lb />
               Postmark: FREE/ 28 MR 28/ 1822<lb />
               MS: Somerset Record Office. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-03-25">25 March. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I have been endeavouring to recollect what books may be useful in affording hints &amp; materials for the poem on which you are engaged.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Atherstone was intending to write a poem set in Anglo-Saxon England, centring on Alfred the Great (849&#8211;899; King of England 871&#8211;899). This was not written, but Atherstone published a novel on the same theme, <title>The Sea-Kings in England: An Historical Romance of the Time of Alfred</title> (1830).</note> You have the most important in <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, but I hope you have the last edition of his work, (which is the third, in three volumes octavo,) &#8211; for each edition differs very materially from the other.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sharon Turner, <title>The History of the Anglo-Saxons: Comprising the History of England from the Earliest Period to the Norman Conquest</title>, 3rd edn (1820), no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Earlier editions had appeared in 1799&#8211;1805 and 1807.</note> There is also an earlier Edda than that which you have in Mallet.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The medieval Icelandic <title>Prose Edda</title> was translated by Paul Henri Mallet (1730&#8211;1807), <title>Monuments de la Mythologie et de la Poesie des Celtes, et Particulierement des Anciens Scandinaves</title> (1756) and was known to most English readers through the English edition by Thomas Percy (1729&#8211;1811; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Northern Antiquities: or, a Description of the Manners, Customs, Religion and Laws of the Ancient Danes and other Northern Nations</title>, 2 vols<title> </title>(London, 1770), II, pp. 1&#8211;223, no. 2046 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> One volume was translated about five &amp; twenty years ago by my poor friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#CottleAmos">Amos Cottle</ref>,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Amos Cottle, <title>Icelandic Poetry, or the Edda of Saemund Translated into English Verse</title> (1797), no. 983 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a translation of the <title>Poetic Edda</title>, believed at this time to be earlier than the <title>Prose Edda</title>.</note> &amp; you may find there &lt;some&gt; wild<del>er</del> parts of Runic mythology which will be new to you, if you have never seen this book. I understand that more of these ancient poems have since that time been printed at Copenhagen, &amp; indeed am in expectation of procuring them from thence.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edda Saemundar hinns Froda. Edda Rhythmica seu Antiquor, Vulgo Saemundina Dicta</title> (1787&#8211;1818), no. 918 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. He never acquired the third volume, published in 1828.</note> Some, I believe, have been translated by the Honourable William Herbert, (our best Northern scholar) &#8211; in whose poems you might probably find much that would be useful.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Herbert (1778&#8211;1847; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Select Icelandic Poetry, Translated from the Originals with Notes</title> (1804&#8211;1806).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">You should read Lingards History of the Anglo Saxon Church, &#8211; an octavo volume published in 1810.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Lingard (1771&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Antiquities of the Anglo-Saxon Church</title>, 2nd edn (1810), no. 1728 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Whitakers &#8220;Life of St Neot, the oldest of all the Brothers of <del>xx</del> Alfred&#8221;,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Whitaker (1735&#8211;1808; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of Saint Neot, the Oldest of All the Brothers to King Alfred</title> (1809), no. 3002 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> tho it is, like all Whitakers works almost merely hypothetical, might give you some hints, &#8211; certainly that of a most interesting character if you thought proper to adopt his opinion concerning the Saint.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">St Neot (d. 870) was a Cornish saint; some legends attested he was a relative of King Alfred.</note> Sharpes translation of William of Malmesbury (4to. 1815)<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William of Malmesbury (c. 1095&#8211;c. 1143; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Gesta Regum Anglorum</title>, translated by John Sharpe (1769&#8211;1859) as <title>The History of the Kings of England and the Modern History of William of Malmesbury</title> (1815), no. 1664 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> would give you an excellent view of the Saxon times, with many characteristic traits of manners: &amp; you should look at the works of Strutt (the engraver)<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Strutt (1749&#8211;1802; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Regal and Ecclesiastical Antiquities of England </title>(1773), <title>Manners, Customs, Arms, Habits etc of the People of England</title> (1774&#8211;1776) and <title>Chronicle of England</title> (1777&#8211;1778).</note> who took a great deal of pains with our antiquities, &amp; has collected much curious matter concerning the times upon which you are employed. If you wish to see the whole mass of monkish fables concerning the British &amp; Anglo Saxon Church, it has been brought together with perfect credulity in a large folio volume by F. Cressy, an English Benedictine in Charles the Seconds reign.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Hugh Paulinus Cressy (c. 1605&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Church History of Brittanny or England, from the Beginning of Christianity to the Norman Conquest</title> (1668), no. 707 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Cressy was a Benedictine monk active in the reign of Charles II (1630&#8211;1688; King of Great Britain 1660&#8211;1688; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Pyes Alfred<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry James Pye (1745&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), Poet Laureate 1790&#8211;1813 and author of <title>Alfred: an Epic Poem</title> (1801).</note> is as much forgotten as Sir Richard Blackmores,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Richard Blackmore (1654&#8211;1729; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Alfred, an Epick Poem, in Twelve Books</title> (1723).</note> &#8211; &amp; my old friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle&#8217;s</ref>
          <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Cottle, <title>Alfred; an Epic Poem, in Twenty-Four Books</title> (1801), no. 742 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> (one of the best men in the world) need not stand in your way. You have the great advantage of living almost upon the spot. &#8211; I would have given a limb for the power of making myself perfect master of the ground in any of my poems which have a foundation in history. All my subjects have taken me from home; &#8211; &amp; a poet pays dearly for thus expatriating himself; &#8211; for all localities &amp; peculiar images he must trust to others eyes instead of his own. There are some scenes in Roderick<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Roderick, the Last of the Goths</title> (1814), set in Spain, which Southey had visited in 1795&#8211;1796.</note> which I had seen, &amp; I felt in describing them <del>what I</del> how different <del>it is</del> to paint from description, is, <del>from</del> to painting from nature</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PooleThomas">Poole</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#StandertHughChudleigh">Standart</ref>. And if ever you come to these lakes &amp; mountains (as all poets &amp; painters ought to do) &#8211; put yourself under my guidance here. I shall be right glad to shake hands with you. Meantime go on in your pursuits &amp; prosper.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">yours faithfully</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>