<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3817" type="letter"><head>3817. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-04-01">1 April 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ 9. Stafford Row/ Buckingham Gate/ London<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
               Postmark: E/ x AP 4/ 1822<lb/>
               Endorsement: 1 Ap<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 1822/ Vegetable Marrow.<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <salute>My dear G.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Thank you for the clean sheets.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of the first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> I wish you had read them, because I should have liked to have known that you liked the work as far as it has proceeded.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> I write now to request (&#38; I trust you are concerned in the affair as much as myself) that you will send me <hi rend="ital">sub franco Sui Recti Honoris</hi>,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">‘under the frank of his Right Honour’, i.e. Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, who had become ‘Right Honourable’ when he was made a Privy Councillor on 17 January 1822.</note> <del>a pac</del> some seeds of the Vegetable Marrow, or Quashey (vulgo<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘vulgarly’.</note> Squash) which I believe is its other name. This is the season for raising them. I use to get them from my poor friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneWade">Mr Browne</ref> of Ludlow, – but last year deprived me of him as well as of poor dear <ref type="m" target="people.html#NashEdward">Nash</ref></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> It is just four &#38; thirty years <hi rend="ital">this day</hi> since I went to Westminster, &#38; thirty years this Easter since I left it. And here I am in the eight &#38; fortieth year of my age with as light a heart &#38; as thin a pair of breeches as when I began my way in the world, but not without a full sense of the years which have past over my head, – of what they have brought, &#38; what they have taken away.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Remember Grosvenor that you &#38; I are at a time of life when we cannot afford procrastination, – or rather <hi rend="ital">proannulation</hi> in the enjoyment of each others society. Come to me while you can, while I am here, &#38; heart-whole to welcome you. We know not what every year may bring forth, – nay not what any week – or day – or hour. Leave his Majestys X X Xs<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey here writes three ‘X’s meaning the ‘Exchequer’, where Bedford worked.</note> &#38; as soon as you can after the leaves open, &#38; as soon as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">Henry</ref> can accompany you, &#38; tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref> to bespeak forthwith a pair of thicker shoes than she ever wears in London, &#38; to make such other preparations for mountaineering &#38; lakeing as she may think proper, for I shall not forgive you if you do not bring her.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
               <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed></closer>
            
            <postscript><p rend="indent1"><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref></placeName></address> <date when="1822-04-01">Monday Apr 1. 1822</date></p></postscript>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
