<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3823. Robert Southey to Amelia Opie, 11 April 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3823Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3823. Robert Southey to Amelia Opie, 11 April 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3823Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3823" type="letter">
        <head>3823. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#OpieAmelia">Amelia Opie</ref>, <date when="1822-04-11">11 April 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Opie/ Norwich<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               MS: Pforzheimer Collection, New York Public Library, tipped into a graingerised copy of Cecilia Lucy Brightwell, <title>Memorials of the Life of Amelia Opie, Selected and Arranged from Her Diaries, Letters, and other Manuscripts</title>, 2nd edn (Norwich and London, 1854), between pp. 188&#8211;189. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Previously published: Cecilia Lucy Brightwell, <title>Memorials of the Life of Amelia Opie, Selected and Arranged from Her Letters, Diaries, and other Manuscripts</title> (Norwich and London, 1854), pp. 190&#8211;191.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-04-11">11 Apr. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Madam</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Madeline<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madeline, A Tale</title> (1822), Opie&#8217;s final novel. The eponymous heroine suffers a long illness, but recovers at the end of the novel.</note> is a great favourite here, &amp; well deserves to be so. The tale is beautifully told, &amp; every where true to nature; &#8211; if there be a little of that ideal colouring which belongs to this species of composition as much as to poetry, it is in your hero rather than your heroine. The tragic catastrophe would, as you say, have made the story more perfect, &#8211; but it would have made the book painful instead of pleasing in recollection. I am sure that I should not have looked at it a second time, compared one part with another, &amp; dwelt upon particular scenes, if there had been death at the end. And this I think is not so much the weakness of my individual temper as it is a natural feeling. The theatres show it to be so, by the preference which is given to comedy. They who have borne a part in the tragedies of real life (&amp; who is there that can go thro the world without it?) &#8211; shrink even from the sorrow which is produced by fiction.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Quarterly Review will be much better employed in recommending Madeline to notice, than in pointing out in the Pirate beauties which every body has seen, &amp; defects which nobody can have overlooked.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Scott, <title>The Pirate</title> (1822). It was reviewed by Nassau William Senior (1790&#8211;1864; <title>DNB</title>) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26 (January 1822), 455&#8211;474, published 30 March 1822.</note> The part which I bear in that Journal is greatly overrated, &amp; the influence which I possess there quite as much so. For two <del>days I ha</del> years I have been vainly endeavouring to get a book by <ref type="m" target="people.html#DouglasHoward">Sir Howard Douglas</ref>
          <note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had tried in vain to persuade the <title>Quarterly</title> to review Howard Douglas&#8217;s <title>Observations on the Motives, Errors and Tendency of M. Carnot&#8217;s System of Defence</title> (1819), which provided a critique of Lazare Nicolas Marguerite Carnot&#8217;s (1753&#8211;1823) classic work on fortifications, <title>Trait&#233; de la D&#233;fense des Places Fortes</title> (1810), on issues such as the effectiveness of vertical fire by defending forces.</note> reviewed there, tho the subject is of great importance, &amp; national interest as well as national <del>an</del> credit concerned in it. I could not do it myself, because it required scientific knowledge which I do not possess.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To convince you however that your tale has greatly interested me I will write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gifford</ref>, &amp; ask him to admit an article upon it.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Madeline, A Tale</title> was not reviewed in the <title>Quarterly</title>.</note> Most likely he will consent; &#8211; I cannot be quite sure of this, nor can I promise any thing farther for the paper than that it will be written in right good will. As for my prose, &#8211; any bodys prose is mistaken for mine, &#8211; &amp; what is far more strange any bodys opinions. The guessing at anonymous writings is almost as much a matter of hap-hazard, &#8211; as the attempt to discover any person by their walk &amp; figure at a masquerade</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> desires me to present her compliments. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorWilliam">W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Taylor</ref> when you happen to see him.</p>
        <p>
          Fare well my dear Madam<lb/>
            &amp; believe me yrs truly<lb/>
           Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>