<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3825Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3825Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3825" type="letter">
        <head>3825. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Hew Dalrymple</ref>, <date when="1822-04-12">12 April 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Sir Hew Dalrymple. Bart/ &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c/ Upper Wimpole Street/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 15 AP 15/ 1822<lb />
               Seal: red wax; arm raising aloft cross of Lorraine<lb />
               Endorsement: 1822. April 12/ Robert Southey<lb />
               MS: National War Museum, Edinburgh, Dalrymple-White Collection, 1.12.1. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-04-12">12 Apr. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I was this day preparing to return your papers,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Dalrymple had sent his papers to help with Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). He lived at 23 Upper Wimpole Street.</note> when I perceived that your address as given in your letter did not specify the number of your house. And it seems better to retain them till you have the goodness to let me know this, than to dispatch them with an imperfect direction</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> These papers have given me great light; upon some points they have confirmed the opinion which I had previously been led to entertain, &#8211; upon others they have imparted information altogether new to me. Unfortunately the chapter in which the first transactions in Andalusia are comprized was printed before I received them. They will render it necessary to alter a few passages, &amp; to add others;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey dealt with the Battle of Bail&#233;n in Andalusia, 16&#8211;19 July1808, the first great success of Spanish forces in the Peninsular War, in his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 382&#8211;386. On pp. 389&#8211;390, Southey inserted material concerning Dalrymple&#8217;s role in the attempts of Spanish commanders to change the terms of surrender of the French army, but it did not have to appear as &#8216;Corrections&#8217;.</note> &#8211; &amp; these in such scattered places that all cannot be done, as I should wish, by reprinting part of the chapter. What cannot be done in this way, must be inserted as corrections at the end of the volume.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Till I perused these papers I did not know, indeed it was not possible that I could, how great the service was which you had performed at Gibraltar,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Dalrymple was Acting Governor of Gibraltar 1806&#8211;1808.</note> under circumstances wherein you were left wholly to act upon your own judgement, &amp; on your own responsibility.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> With regard to the subsequent campaign I believe that if you had landed a few hours sooner, the defeat of the French would have been followed up &amp; compleated.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Dalrymple was appointed to command British troops in Portugal and landed there on 22 August 1808, the day following the defeat of the French at Vimeiro. He stopped any pursuit of the French army and negotiated the Convention of Cintra on 31 August, which allowed the French to evacuate Portugal with their arms and plunder.</note> And that if Elvas &amp; Almeida had <del>been</del> not been recovered by the Convention, they would have held out till December, when the object of relieving them would have brought the enemy to Portugal, &amp; led to their possession of Lisbon.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">As part of the Convention of Cintra, the French evacuated the fortresses of Elvas and Almeida. Southey here argues that if they had held out, this would have allowed French armies in northern Spain to invade Portugal and capture Lisbon in December 1808&#8211;January 1809.</note> Nothing could have been of so much consequence as the recovery of Elvas at that time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">These things I have endeavoured to place in their proper light.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 365&#8211;378, had declared the Convention of Cintra (1808), which Dalrymple negotiated with the defeated French forces in Portugal, to be &#8216;scandalous&#8217; (p. 366). Southey&#8217;s treatment of the matter in <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 566&#8211;594, was much more circumspect, pointing out the Convention&#8217;s military advantages, but declaring it contained &#8216;some political errors&#8217; (p. 577).</note> And in expressing a wish that the same high feeling of honour which was shown in all other points throughout these transactions, had been manifested toward the French, by shunning all intercourse with them <del>except</del> beyond what the necessities of business required,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, p. 583, in which Southey had condemned British officers for socialising with their French counterparts after the Convention of Cintra (1808). Given the war crimes that the French had perpetrated in Portugal, this was, to Southey, &#8216;a moral fault, as well as a political error&#8217;.</note> I am sure I shall have offended none but Buonapartes<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815).</note> officers, &amp; those persons who admire or excuse the system of his policy</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">I have the honour to remain</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Sir Hew</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> with sincere respect</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">your obliged &amp; obedient servant</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>