<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3828Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3828Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3828" type="letter">
        <head>3828. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1822-04-20">20 April 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ AP 23/ 1822 F N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 23 AP 23/ 1822<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 216. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 303&#8211;304 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-04-22">20 Apr. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">The Boswell whom you met at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> was Sir Alex&#8217;s<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Alexander Boswell, 1st Baronet (1775&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish poet, bibliophile and MP for Plympton Erle 1816&#8211;1821. He attended Eton 1789&#8211;1792.</note> only brother, &amp; died a few months ago, of habitual drinking,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">James Boswell (1778&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer, poet and literary scholar. He died on 24 February 1822. He had been appointed a Commissioner of Bankrupts in 1819.</note> as his father did before him.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">James Boswell (1740&#8211;1795; <title>DNB</title>), diarist and biographer of Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;1784; <title>DNB</title>).</note> Sir Alex. had just returned from the funeral, when he was called upon by his antagonist.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Boswell was mortally wounded on 26 March 1822 in a duel with James Stuart (1775&#8211;1849; <title>DNB</title>), lawyer, journalist and Whig supporter. Boswell had attacked Stuart vociferously in anonymous articles in the Tory newspaper the <title>Glasgow Sentinel</title> (1821&#8211;1823).</note> &#8211; Poor James Boswell was a thoroughly good-natured inoffensive man, of considerable talents. Malone left him his papers to compleat an edition of Shakespere, &amp; after many years labour he published it last year.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmond Malone (1741&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), Irish Shakesperean scholar and friend of the elder and younger James Boswell. The latter completed Malone&#8217;s <title>The Plays and Poems of William Shakespeare, with the Corrections and Illustrations of Various Commentators: Comprehending a Life of the Poet, and an Enlarged History of the Stage</title> (1821).</note> &#8211; He had not long been made a Commissioner of Bankrupts, before which his means had been somewhat scanty I believe. I have lost in him, not a friend indeed, but a pleasant old acquaintance, whom I was always glad to meet, &amp; of whose good will &amp; good word I was always sure. We were schoolfellows, &amp; when <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> left school, &amp; left a bed vacant in my room, I who became head boy of the house by his departure, chose <del>xx xxxx</del> Boswell to succeed him. A brother of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> (poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref>, &#8211; H. Walpoles<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Horace Walpole, 4th Earl of Orford (1717&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), writer, antiquarian and Whig politician.</note> godson) was at Westminster at the same time, &#8211; we used to call him D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Johnson,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The nickname was a humorous comparison with Samuel Johnson (1709&#8211;84; <title>DNB</title>), author and lexicographer.</note> from an affectation he had of verbal criticism, which he supported by quoting Johnson always, &#8211; &amp; I made Boswell write after my dictation some ridiculous anecdotes of him under this name, to be read for the amusement of the sixth form. Boswell enjoyed this as much as any one, tho he used to say it was a shame to make him mob his father, &#8211; &amp; in latter years he delighted to tell the story, &amp; tax me with tyrannizing over him. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHoraceWalpole">Horace</ref> was allowed to carry off the Memoirs, which he liked well enough himself to give to his brother, &amp; I dare say <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor</ref> has them at this day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Boswell came here in 1815 to visit <ref type="m" target="people.html#SunderlinLord">Lord Sunderlin</ref> (Malones brother) &amp; was one of the party at our midnight bonfire on the summit of Skiddaw.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 23 August 1815, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Four</title>, Letter 2649.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Alex. Boswell was an Etonian. I saw him once when he called in Deans Yard for his brother, &#8211; &amp; indeed Bozzy&#8217;s conversation had made me at that time well-acquainted with all the Auchinleck family.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Boswells&#8217; estate and family home was at Auchinleck in Ayrshire.</note> This is the second fatal duel which has grown out of the licence of the press,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Scott (1784&#8211;1821; <title>DNB</title>), editor of the <title>London Magazine</title>, was mortally wounded on 16 February 1821 in a duel with Jonathan Henry Christie (1792&#8211;1876) that was provoked by attacks on Scott in <title>Blackwood&#8217;s Magazine</title>.</note>
          <del>both parties think</del> neither party scruples at any slander which may injure or annoy its opponents, &amp; the increase of duelling must be one consequence of this disgraceful system.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I will give <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> a letter ere long. Calligraphy is not <del>xxx</del> promoted at Westminster, &#8211; &amp; yet I obtained some silver-pence for it there for what was called fair-shewings.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> I believe, will go to Harrogate next week, &amp; I shall probably go to bring her home, which will be the extent of my travels this year. I had planned a journey thro Holland, if I could have afforded time &amp; money, but that scheme must stand over till a more convenient season.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey visited Holland in 1825 and 1826.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Ostervalds friend<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">A German visitor, called Bielh; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 24 February 1822, Letter 3804. Jean Fr&#233;d&#233;ric Ostervald (b. 1749) was a Swiss from Neuchatel and son of Fr&#233;d&#233;ric Samuel Ostervald (1713&#8211;1795), publisher and founder of the Soci&#233;t&#233; Typographique de Neuchatel (STN). Ostervald was in Portugal in the 1790s and was secretary to the legation and charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires at the British Embassy 1792&#8211;1793 while Robert Walpole (1736&#8211;1810; <title>DNB</title>), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary 1771&#8211;1800, was in Britain. Ostervald was an old friend of Herbert Hill and Southey had written to him during his continental journey in 1817. This letter had produced some correspondence with Ostervald&#8217;s nephew, Jean Baptist Isaac Harl&#233; (1773&#8211;1854), a merchant at St Quentin; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 15 March 1818, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3093.</note> will probably make his appearance here next month. You will not be able to deliver up your paintings to him, &#8211; for he is going to Russia instead of Manheim.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I had a visit lately from <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenJames">Gooden</ref>, who told me of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Sealy&#8217;s<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Sealy (c. 1752&#8211;1821), a Lisbon merchant and the father of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s first wife. He died at Lisbon on 11 July 1821.</note> secret marriage. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref> writes me word that the French are about to revive the Slave Trade, for the purpose of stocking Guiana with negroes<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">France had abolished the slave trade in 1815, but was not taking effective steps to enforce this ban. The French had regained French Guiana in 1817 after its occupation by Portuguese forces during the Napoleonic Wars. It retained slavery until 1848.</note>, &#8211; and also that they mean to attempt the conquest of S Domingo.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The French colony of St Domingue had become independent as Haiti in 1804, but France did not recognise this situation and there were constant rumours that a French expedition would be sent to reconquer Haiti.</note> If this latter <del>xxx</del> account be true, the intent must be to get rid of men who are dangerous at home; &amp; this must be so obvious that I do not think it will be attempted. But I shall hear more of this from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref>, who will no doubt pass a day with me, on his way to Scotland this summer. He resided in this country when first I came into it. &#8211; The Brazilians will pay the full price for their share in the slave trade, if a civil war should break out in Brazil.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The slave trade to Brazil was not banned until 1831 (and not effectively until 1850).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Our love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the children</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>