<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3831Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3831" type="letter">
        <head>3831. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1822-04-28">28 April 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 1 MY 1/ 182x<lb />
               Endorsements: 28 April 1822; 28 April 1822<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for the half notes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> set off yesterday for Harrowgate, being the first time she has ever been from home by herself, except on a visit to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> &#8211; which was like being in another home. I shall join her for the purpose of bringing her back about the end of May. She goes provided with a sketch-book which if the weather permit she will make good use of; for she sketches now so quickly &amp; so well that in this respect I should be very well satisfied with her for a travelling companion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> I hope will visit me early in June. And <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Dogstar</ref> promises to rise here in the autumn. As for Grosvenor Bedford he is a bad fellow &amp; I know not when to expect him. When he thinks of coming there is no being sure of him because Taffy has a house on the way.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a reference to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, whose house at Llangedwin in Denbighshire was closer to London than Keswick, and only a short detour from one of the routes between London and the Lake District.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">An old acquaintance of mine</ref> has taken it in his head to write a book against the Vision of Judgement.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Tillbrook, <title>Historical and Critical Remarks upon the Modern Hexamatrists, and Upon Mr Southey&#8217;s Vision of Judgement</title> (1822).</note> If any body reads it so much the better for me, but I am afraid he will find that he has chosen a subject about which nobody cares.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Our weather is what April should be. This year we have escaped the usually easterly winds, &amp; the country is a full fortnight earlier than usual in all its appearances.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Osiris</ref> tells me you are playing pranks with your diet, which seem not to be by no means suited to your state of health or of feeling. If your deafness is likely to be benefitted by stimulants, I should <del>prefe</del> rather take them in <del>foxx</del> the form of eating &amp; drinking than of potion or pill. &#8211; Mountain air &amp; Lake exercise would be the best remedies.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I hope <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> was angry when he replied to Lord J Russell.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord John Russell, 1st Earl Russell (1792&#8211;1878; Prime Minister 1846&#8211;1852, 1865&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>), Whig politician. He delivered a famous and lengthy speech in the House of Commons on 25 April 1822 in favour of parliamentary reform. Wynn responded for the government but devoted most of his speech to defending his colleagues in the Grenville grouping, who had split from the Whigs in 1817 and joined the government in 1822. Russell had accused them of dishonourable behaviour and of sitting for constituencies with tiny electorates, so they could not be questioned about their change of allegiances in 1822.</note> &#8211; If I had been in town I would have fitted his Ldsp with a leading article in the next days Courier which should have blistered him. Let Lord John carry his plans of reform, &amp; in seven years the Bedford level will become a <del>xx</del> domain for coots &amp; curlews instead of feeding the Geese of Woburn.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Bedford Level is an area of the Fens drained at the expense of the Russell family in the seventeenth century. The main family seat is Woburn Abbey in Bedfordshire.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>. <date when="1822-04-28">28 Apr. 1822</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>