<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3834Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3834" type="letter">
        <head>3834. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1822-05-08">[begun before and continued on] 8 May [1822]</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham<lb />
               Stamped: T P/ Bge St West<hi rend="sup">mr</hi>
            <lb />
               Postmarks: 2 o&#8217;Clock/ 11 MY/ 1822 A S<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; [partial] o&#8217;Clock/ 11/ EV<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 217. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 307&#8211;309 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">Can you find out in your Catalan books why the <hi rend="ital">Somatenes</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, p. 318. In Catalonia, the ruler could require citizens to keep arms and call on them to gather to preserve the peace and defend the country. The name of this body was indeed derived from the ringing of a bell to summon its members.</note> are so called? I take them to be the <hi rend="ital">posse comitatus</hi>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The name since the ninth century in England for a group of citizens assembled by the sheriff to deal with lawlessness. The theoretical right of sheriffs to assemble such a body was not repealed until 1967.</note> called out for the defence of the country; &amp; have some notion (a vague one) that their name is derived from the Bell which is rung to summons them, &#8211; as if <hi rend="ital">Somaten</hi> were equivalent to <hi rend="ital">tocsin</hi>, &#8211; but I cannot where I have read this. The derivation of Miquelet<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The name used in Catalonia since the early modern period for many different kinds of irregular troops; it was sometimes used as an equivalent to Somatenes. The word is often said to derive from Miquelot de Prats, a fifteenth-century Catalan mercenary.</note> I have found in D Francisco Manuel,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Manuel de Mello (1608&#8211;1666), <title>Historia de los Movimientos, Separacion y Geurra de Cataluna en tiempo de Felipe IV</title> (Madrid, 1808), pp. 242&#8211;243, no 3427 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey also owned an edition from 1696, printed at Lisbon (no. 3502 in the sale catalogue of his library).</note> &#8211; but I think he never mentions the Somatenes; &#8211; &amp; if that be the case, it must be a <del>word</del> &lt;name&gt; of later growth, &amp; therefore not to be met with in the old laws: &#8211; &lt;but the <hi rend="ital">unde derivatur</hi>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;whence derived&#8217;.</note> perhaps may.&gt; I bought at Turin<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey bought this book on 11 June 1817, when he visited Turin as part of his continental journey of that year.</note> a French account of the struggle made by the Catalans after they were so basely sacrificed at the peace of Utrecht.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear which book Southey is referring to here. One possibility is Jean-Baptiste Targe (1733&#8211;1806), <title>Histoire de l&#8217;Avenement de la Maison de Bourbon au Trone de l&#8217;Espagne</title>, 6 vols (Paris, 1772), no. 2770 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The War of the Spanish Succession (1701&#8211;1713) was ended by the Treaty of Utrecht (1713). Catalonia had supported the losing candidate, Charles VI (1685&#8211;1740; Holy Roman Emperor 1711&#8211;1740), and lost its feudal privileges after Spanish forces regained control of Catalonia in 1714.</note> It is a vile book. The word is there explained twice &amp; in two different ways, which just serve to show that the Frenchman chose to explain what he did not understand. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ButlerCharles">Mr Butler</ref> the Catholic (Alban Butler&#8217;s<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Alban Butler (1711&#8211;1773; <title>DNB</title>), priest and hagiographer, author of <title>The Lives of the Fathers, Martyrs and other Principal Saints; compiled from Original Monuments and Other Authentick Records; Illustrated with the Remarks of Judicious Modern Criticks and Historians</title> (1756&#8211;1769).</note> nephew) tells a good story of such another Frenchman, who <del>upon</del> &lt;being&gt; asked the difference between the Dryades &amp; the Hamadryades replied with great complacency that it was exactly the same as the difference between les Eveques &amp; les Archeveques.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Dryads were Greek tree spirits; hamadryads were spirits associated with one particular tree and died when that tree died. This was a rather different distinction to that between bishops and archbishops.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> talks of paying me a visit in June, tho his furlough will only extend to a clear fortnight.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> There is no person whom I should be more glad to see, &#8211; except yourself. I shall get the first volume off my hands in the course of this month, having only to refit two chapters which are nearly written to my hands in the Ed. Ann. Register,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Much of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) was based on his earlier work for the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title> (1808&#8211;1811).</note> &amp; to insert some corrections from <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir H Dalrymples</ref> papers concerning the post-communications with the Spaniards in Andalusia.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey dealt with the Battle of Bail&#233;n, 16&#8211;19 July1808, the first great success of Spanish forces in the Peninsular War, in his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 382&#8211;386. At pp. 389&#8211;390, Southey inserted material concerning Dalrymple&#8217;s role in the attempts of Spanish commanders to change the terms of surrender of the French army, but it did not have to appear as &#8216;Corrections&#8217;.</note> This is an awkward job which I am afraid cannot be done in any better way than by appending the new matter as &#8216;Corrections&#8217;.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I think you had better not send the D. of B.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), Whig politician and Lord Lieutenant of Ireland 1806&#8211;1807. He had appointed Herbert Hill to his living at Streatham.</note> a copy of this book. It will be wormwood to all his party. I have done nothing more in the first volume than simply to characterize them in the introductory chapter;<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 3&#8211;61 (esp. pp. 55&#8211;58), criticised the Whigs for opposing war with France.</note> but that sample shows what they have to expect when their conduct during the succeeding years of the war is to be recorded. &#8211; They tell me that in the late duel when the D. fired into the air, he said, it would be a shame to shoot at so-much-too-good-a-mark as the D of Buckingham.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Duke of Bedford had fought a duel in Kensington Gardens with Richard Temple-Nugent-Brydges-Chandos-Grenville, 1st Duke of Buckingham and Chandos (1776&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>) on 2 May 1822. The cause was remarks made by the Duke of Bedford about the terms on which the Grenville grouping, of which Buckingham was the leader, had joined the government earlier in 1822. One of Buckingham&#8217;s seconds was his cousin, Sir Watkin Williams Wynn, elder brother of Wynn; Buckingham&#8217;s enormous girth made him a &#8216;so-much-too-good-a-mark&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It has long been apparent to me that we are rapidly approaching a much more perilous crisis in society than that of the Reformation. The house of Russell seems to be stricken with a judicial blindness, or they would see how impossible it is that they should keep in a second convulsion, what they gained in the first.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">The fortunes of the Russells, later Dukes of Bedford, were made during the Reformation, when John Russell, 1st Earl of Bedford (1485&#8211;1555; <title>DNB</title>) acquired the Abbeys of Tavistock and Woburn and the site of Covent Garden in London.</note> A government which on all occasions is compelled to be directed by popular opinion will soon find itself no government at all. I do not dream of preserving <del>the</del> &lt;our&gt; liberties; &#8211; the question is how much <del>shall</del> will it be possible to save from the wreck, &amp; how long before we arrive at that strong &amp; armed government in which all changes of this nature must end, &amp; with which the gradual but sure decay of the nation will begin. The Catholic question<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The question of whether Catholics should be allowed to hold public office in the United Kingdom. This measure did not pass until 1829.</note> may be staved off for a few sessions, but it will be carried at last; away goes the Test then<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">The Test Act (1673), which confined public office to communicants of the Church of England.</note>: the Dissenters get into the Corporations, &amp; the first hungry &amp; unprincipled Minister<del>s</del> sells the Tithes, &#8211; as Pitt thought of doing.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Local clergymen had the right to receive a proportion of agricultural produce in their parish. This system was much&#8211;disputed and William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>) had ordered a survey of tithes in 1791&#8211;1792, but had not proceeded with any reforms.</note> Parliamentary Reform is become little more than a dispute concerning forms, &#8211; the real mischief is already effected; &amp; popular clamour carries every thing in Parliament under a Ministry who cringe to their enemies &amp; destroy their friends: a miserable crew, who divide their voices upon the greatest questions which can possibly come before them, &amp; who for the sake of putting off a difficulty, or even of escaping from a debate, are ready to say or unsay, to do or to undo anything.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  We shall not be overturned &amp; thrown over a precipice as they were in France, &#8211; our institutions have prepared for us an inclined plane, on which we are descending</p>
        <p rend="center">&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;&#8212;</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent0">
          <date when="1822-05-08">8 May &#8211;</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent0">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> writes in good spirits from Harrogate. The waters have already given her a healthy appetite, &amp; I hope they will do what else is expected from them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Doctor</ref> talks of running down to us in the autumn &#8211; such a change would do him more good than diet or medicine</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the children</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>