<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3836Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3836" type="letter">
        <head>3836. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SenhouseHumphrey">Humphrey Senhouse</ref>, <date when="1822-05-13">13 May 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Humphrey Senhouse Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Netherhall<lb />
               Seal: red wax<lb />
               MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Senhouse</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I cannot be glad at any event which may in any degree inconvenience you; &#8211; &amp; yet as the disappointment of our plan<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had informed Senhouse that he would be unable to travel to the Netherlands that year; see Southey to Humphrey Senhouse 11 February 1822, Letter 3799.</note> was so much like the breach of an engagement on my part, &amp; sate therefore somewhat uneasily on my conscience, there is some satisfaction in knowing that it is better for you at this time to be at home than abroad. &#8211; We may look forward to Holland at a more convenient season, &amp; while we are mountaineering in finer scenery than any which is to be found between the Land of Lakes &amp; the Jura, tho we shall not fare so well upon the way as if the waters of the Rhine placed its wine within <del>x</del> our reach, we shall have the comfort of being near home.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I expect my old friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> (whom I think you have seen at my brother <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry&#8217;s</ref>) on the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of next month.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822</note> His stay is limited to a fortnight, &amp; after that time I shall be ready to take the field with you, whenever you may find it most convenient. I thank you for your friendly invitation to a house where I feel myself at home, &amp; where amusement is never wanting. But I think <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Mrs S.</ref> will not be induced to leave home this year. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> is at Harrogate with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref>, &amp; I think of going thither next week, to escort them home.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My view of the Catholic question<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was totally opposed to opening public office to men who were not members of the Church of England.</note> agrees entirely with yours. It is not for Peter only that we are opening the door, but for all Jacks bastard children.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Here Southey refers to Catholics as &#8216;Peter&#8217;, as the Pope claimed to be the successor of St Peter (d. AD 64&#8211;68), while Nonconformists were followers of &#8216;Jack&#8217;, i.e. the theology of John Calvin (1509&#8211;1564).</note> Away goes the Test Act;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Test Act (1673) confined public office to communicants of the Church of England.</note> the Dissenters make their way into all the <del>xxxx</del> Corporations; their members will attack the Tythes, &#8211; &amp; when we know, (as I certainly do) that an intention of selling them was entertained by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pitt,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Local clergymen had the right to receive a proportion of agricultural produce in their parish. This system was much-disputed and William Pitt (1759&#8211;1806; Prime Minister 1783&#8211;1801, 1804&#8211;1806; <title>DNB</title>) had ordered a survey of tithes in 1791&#8211;1792, but had not proceeded with any reforms.</note> how can we expect that so supple an Administration as the present will risque any thing by defending them against the combined forces of the Dissenters, the Agricultural Interest, &amp; the Liberales of all descriptions? That the Catholic question will be carried ere long, I do not doubt. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">The King</ref> is not a man to make a stand against it on the ground of principle, like his father.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">George III (1738&#8211;1820; King of Great Britain 1760&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>). His opposition to political rights for Catholics had led to the resignation of ministries in 1801 and 1807.</note> The nation will be <hi rend="ital">scribbled</hi> into it, as &lt;they&gt; may be scribbled into any thing: &#8211; &amp; popular opinion is already the supreme power in England. It is idle to talk of a balance of powers, &#8211; the Democracy is every thing, &amp; the inevitable tendency of our institutions has long been to make it so. Every thing will be popularized, &#8211; that is to say, vulgarized &amp; debased.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> But I must conclude, &#8211; for your servant is come for the letter: The Peninsular War<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is far advanced; &#8211; the proof on the table carries me to p. 616. Westall is engraving a series of views to accompany it,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These could be inserted into the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; he has sent me two proofs, which are some of the finest things of their kind. &#8211; The Book of the Church<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> is an odd looking title, of an old fashion but it served my purpose better than any other which I could devise, &#8211; especially as I thought of accompanying it with a sketch of our political history upon a like plan, to be called the Book of the Constitution.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this work.</note> I once hoped that these things would do some good; &#8211; but the evil I fear is too far gone. However order will one day succeed to anarchy, &#8211; our grandchildren will have to build up what their fathers have pulled down, &amp; there will come a generation when these warnings may not be useless.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember us all to your friends</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">&amp; believe me my dear Senhouse</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3"> truly &amp; affectionately yours</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>&gt;<ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-05-13">13 May. 1822.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>