<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3846Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3846Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3846" type="letter">
        <head>3846. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>, <date when="1822-05-27">27 May 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Florence/ Italy<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; ANGLETERRE; CHAMBERY; CORRISP<hi rend="sup">ZA</hi> ESTERA DA GENOA<lb />
               Postmarks: F/ 9/ 22; [illegible]<lb />
               MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 38. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 311&#8211;313.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-05-27">27 May. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I shall rejoice to see your Dialogues.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824).</note> Mine<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> are consecutive, &amp; will have nothing of that dramatic variety which you will make the most. My plan grew out of Boethius,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Anicius Manlius Severinus Boethius (c. 480&#8211;525), <title>De Consolatione Philosophiae</title>, a dialogue between the author and the character of Lady Philosophy.</note> tho it has since been so modified, that the origin would not be suspected. The personage who visits me is Sir Thomas More,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Thomas More (1478&#8211;1535; <title>DNB</title>), Lord Chancellor 1529&#8211;1532.</note> as one who recognizes in me some dispathies but more points of agreement. This age is as climacteric as that in which he lived, &#8211; in fact we are beginning now to perceive the whole effects of the three great events of his age, &#8211; the <del>discovery</del> &lt;invention&gt; of printing, the Reformation, &amp; the discovery of America. You see what a canvas I have taken, if I can but fill up the sketch. By way of relief I introduce some of the dialogues with local scenery, &amp; perhaps I may insert some verses. &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The first volume of my history<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is delayed by the printer,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831).</note> &#8211; my part is so nearly done, that it will be finished before this reaches you. Give me in your next a direction whither to send it; by that time I hope the printer will nearly have done his work: the Vision<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> &amp; some smaller things will go with it,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Expedition of Orsua; and the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821), originally intended to be part of the <title>History of Brazil</title> and first printed in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), i&#8211;l; and a combined second edition of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814) and <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness the Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty the Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814), published as <title>Carmen Triumphale, for the Commencement of the Year 1814: Carmen Aulica, Written in 1814, on the Arrival of the Allied Sovereigns in England</title> (1821).</note> Humboldts Travels<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander von Humboldt (1769&#8211;1859), <title>Personal Narrative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions of the New Continent During the Years 1799&#8211;1804</title> (1814&#8211;1826), no. 1463 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; and <title>Researches Concerning the Institutions and Monuments of the Ancient Inhabitants of America, with Descriptions and Views of Some of the Most Striking Scenes in the Cordilleras</title> (1814).</note> (which you will read with great interest) &amp; two little volumes which <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> sends you, &#8211; the one a series of sonnets Ecclesiastical Sketches<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth, <title>Ecclesiastical Sketches</title> (1822).</note> he calls them, the other poems which he produced during a short tour on the continent.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth, <title>Memorials of a Tour on the Continent, 1820</title> (1822) contained 35 shorter poems and the longer &#8216;To Enterprise&#8217; and &#8216;Desultory Stanzas&#8217;.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  The complaint in <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> eyes is a serious inconvenience to him, but it threatens nothing worse. I have been greatly alarmed about him, this week, by hearing that he had a dreadful fall from a horse; but to day we learn that he is well. The horse ran away with him, &amp; threw him against a wall. His head was cut, &amp; bled profusely, which possibly prevented worse consequences. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ChantreyFrancis">Chantry</ref> has made a noble bust of him.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Francis Chantrey&#8217;s bust of Wordsworth, completed in 1820.</note> [note to self: code some ampersandnbsp; here x 10] Augustus Hare<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Augustus William Hare (1792&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman and writer.</note> showed me yesterday what you had written of Wordsworth in a letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">his brother</ref>. &#8211; It is a great pleasure to me when I meet with a person who knows your writings, &amp; can talk with me about them &amp; about you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You have I suppose seen or heard of the decorous manner in which <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> resented my comments upon the Satanic school of poetry, &#8211; &amp; of the manner in which he introduced your name.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (London, 1821), &#8216;Preface&#8217;, pp. xvii&#8211;xxii, where Southey denounced &#8216;the Satanic School&#8217; of modern poetry, without naming any one poet. In the &#8216;Appendix&#8217; to &#8216;The Two Foscari&#8217;, <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy. Cain, A Mystery</title> (London, 1821), p. 328, Byron had cautioned: &#8216;I am not ignorant of Mr. Southey&#8217;s calumnies on a different occasion, knowing them to be such, which he scattered abroad on his return from Switzerland against me and others.&#8217; Southey had visited Switzerland during his continental tour of May&#8211;August 1817. Byron believed that Southey had subsequently spread rumours that Byron and Shelley engaged in a &#8216;League of Incest&#8217; during their residence in Switzerland in 1816. Byron continued: &#8216;One of his [Southey&#8217;s] consolations appears to be a Latin note from a work of a Mr. Landor, the author of &#8220;Gebir&#8221;, whose friendship for Robert Southey will, it seems, &#8220;be an honour to him when the ephemeral disputes and ephemeral reputations of the day are forgotten.&#8221; [<title>Vision of Judgement</title>, pp. xix&#8211;xx] I for one neither envy him &#8220;the friendship&#8221;, nor the glory in reversion which is to accrue from it, like Mr. Thelusson&#8217;s fortune in the third and fourth generation. [Peter Thellusson (1735&#8211;1797) left his fortune in trust for his descendants, but nothing to his living relatives] This friendship will probably be as memorable as his own epics, which (as I quoted to him ten or twelve years ago in &#8220;English Bards&#8221;) Porson said &#8220;would be remembered when Homer and Virgil are forgotten, and not till then.&#8221; [Byron, <title>English Bards, and Scotch Reviewers; A Satire</title> (London, 1809), p. 9] For the present I leave him.&#8217; (p. 329).</note> I believe he will take the advice which I gave him in reply, &amp; not meddle with me again in prose.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had responded with a letter to the Editor of the <title>Courier</title>, 5 January 1822, Letter 3776. This was published in the <title>Courier</title> on 11 January 1822. In the conclusion to his letter, Southey had advised Byron: &#8216;When he attacks me again let it be in rhyme. For one who has so little command of himself, it will be a great advantage that his temper should be obliged to keep to tune.&#8217; Unfortunately for Southey, Byron responded with <title>The Vision of Judgment</title>, a parody of <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), published in <title>The Liberal</title>, 1 (October 1822), 3&#8211;39.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  We are going on in this country fast &amp; quietly toward Catholic emancipation &amp; Parl: reform; &#8211; both I think must at no distant time be carried, &amp; either one will suffice for the overthrow of our institutions. The only question is whether the Church or the State goes first; &#8211; the trunk will not remain long upon one leg when the other is lopt. The end of course must be a stronger government, &#8211; but God only knows thro what evils it will be reached, &amp; <del>atx</del> &lt;by&gt; what sacrifices it must be purchased. In the days of Charles I.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; King of Great Britain 1625&#8211;1649; <title>DNB</title>), who was defeated in the Civil War of 1642&#8211;1651.</note> there was some consolation in falling before the mighty; such men as Pym Hampden, Milton<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">John Pym (1584&#8211;1643; <title>DNB</title>) and John Hampden (c. 1594&#8211;1643; <title>DNB</title>), leading critics of Charles I in the House of Commons; and John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), poet and Secretary for Foreign Tongues to the Council of State 1649&#8211;1660 under the English Republic.</note> &amp;c. &#8211; But to see the work of ruin effected by such people as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref> &amp; Hume,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Hume (1777&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish radical MP, much disliked by Southey for his campaigns against government expenditure.</note> Cam Hobhouse<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">John Cam Hobhouse (1786&#8211;1869; <title>DNB</title>), friend of Byron and radical MP for Westminster 1820&#8211;1833, who later became a Whig Cabinet Minister.</note> &amp; the house of Russel<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The political family and grouping headed by John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford (1766&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), Whig politician and Lord Lieutenant of Ireland 1806&#8211;1807.</note> &#8211; it is like seeing a temple <del>destroyed</del> pulled down by wretches who would not have been thought worthy to carry a hod for the masons at the building.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Would that the means for raising a fallen nation were as efficacious &amp; as sure, as those which are employed for overthrowing the fabric of our greatness! &#8211; We might then look with more hope toward Spain Portugal &amp; the far more degraded Italians, &#8211; for in the two former countries the degradation has been of the state not of the people. One day I hope you will give us your recollections of Italy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  The French have not yet had enough of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Domingo:<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">The French colony of St Domingue on Hispaniola had become the independent State of Haiti in 1804 after a slave rebellion. The French government did not accept this situation and was attempting to persuade or coerce the Haitian leaders into renewing the country&#8217;s link to France. Haitian forces had invaded the Spanish section of Hispaniola on 9 February 1822, partly in order to stop it being used as a basis for French pressure on Haiti.</note> they have actually made an attempt to establish themselves in the Spanish part of the island; &amp; it is said that they intend to restore the slave trade openly, which they have always carried on in an underhand way.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">France had formally abolished the slave trade in 1815, but this decree was not being enforced effectually. Southey&#8217;s information came from William Wilberforce; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 20 April 1822, Letter 3828.</note> This is quite worthy of them. If they send an army from Europe against the island, I <del>obxxxxly</del> hope it will be numerous enough to give the Pestilence full scope. They are an incorrigible people, incapable of <del>xx</del> shame.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I am going on myself quietly &amp; contentedly, with no other disquietude than what arises from the occasional illness of one or other of my children, more especially <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">my little boy</ref>, &#8211; <del>xxx xxxx xxxxx xxxxxxx abjxxxxxxxx xxxxxxx xxxxxxx xxx</del>. He has just recovered from a bilious attack, &#8211; which is the disease in this country most incident to children. But he is a fine joyous creature, &#8211; an object of the greatest hope, &#8211; if I could look upon him without fear. &#8211; Yours<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor&#8217;s children: Arnold Savage Landor (1818&#8211;1871); Julia Elizabeth Savage Landor (1820&#8211;1884); Walter Savage Landor (1822&#8211;1899). They were followed by Charles Savage Landor (1825&#8211;1917).</note> will have the advantage of acquiring two languages at once with equal facility.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>