<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3847Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3847" type="letter">
        <head>3847. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-05-27">27 May 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey./ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 30 MY 30/ 1822<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">The pictures arrived safely,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Portraits of the Southey family made by Edward Nash. Southey had sent them to London for framing.</note> &#8211; the frames are very ill made as you will perceive when you see them beside those which they ought to have resembled &#8211; &amp; the wrong portrait of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> has been framed, being an unfinished one. This however can be remedied when the other arrives. You must trouble Bowyer<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The artist and publisher Robert Bowyer (1758&#8211;1834) was working on a painting, &#8216;View of the Interior of the House of Lords, during the important investigation of 1820&#8217;, and wished to include Southey in the crowd in the Strangers Gallery in the House of Lords. Southey had lent him a miniature painted by Edward Nash in 1820 (now in the National Portrait Gallery); see Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 4 May 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3681.</note> with a note if he does not send back the miniature</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> We shall all rejoice to see you in the autumn. It is no wisdom to put off enjoyments of this kind, which the accidents of life may so easily interfere to embitter or prevent. I hope you may find <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">Aunt Mary</ref> here, she talks of returning to us &#8211; but I am very anxious about her at this time, for she tells me she is under preparation for having one of her eyes couched,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A hazardous procedure to treat a cataract by using a sharp instrument to push the cloudy lens to the bottom of the eye.</note> &#8211; <del>xx</del> where one eye alone is affected I am afraid the operation ought not to be hazarded, &#8211; &amp; yet I cannot venture to tell her this, &amp; alarm her, so much in this case depending upon the tranquillity of the patient. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lonsdale</ref> gave his operator<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Alexander (d. 1859), fashionable eye surgeon, with a large practice in London&#8217;s West End; he specialised in cataract operations.</note> the other day 1000 guineas. I wish you were his physician.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">EMay</ref> is just gone off for Harrowgate, whither I purpose going to bring her home about the end of next month. We are afraid that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kates</ref> complaint is not removed, care has been taken to spare the eyes at night, so that they have not fairly been put to the proof. I suppose we must repeat the doses of calomel if the heaviness decidedly returns.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Calomel was a commonly used purgative.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">When you go into the city, call at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref> &amp; desire him to send you the Brazil.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The second edition of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note> Ask also for Aguirre,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Expedition of Orsua; and the Crimes of Aguirre</title> (1821), originally intended to be part of the <title>History of Brazil</title> and first printed in <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1810</title>, 3.2 (1812), i&#8211;l.</note> &amp; the small edition of the Carmena,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">A combined second edition of <title>Carmen Triumphale</title> (1814) and <title>Congratulatory Odes. Odes to His Royal Highness the Prince Regent, His Imperial Majesty the Emperor of Russia, and His Majesty the King of Prussia</title> (1814), published as <title>Carmen Triumphale, for the Commencement of the Year 1814: Carmen Aulica, Written in 1814, on the Arrival of the Allied Sovereigns in England</title> (1821).</note> if they were not sent to you. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Tillbrooke</ref>
          <note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Tillbrook, <title>Historical and Critical Remarks upon the Modern Hexamatrists, and Upon Mr Southey&#8217;s Vision of Judgement</title> (1822), a critique of Southey&#8217;s Vision of Judgement (1821). The only debate this pamphlet provoked was when Southey published extracts from his reply to Samuel Tillbrook, 17 June 1822, Letter 3856, in his <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837&#8211;1838), IX, pp. xviii&#8211;xxi.</note> has written a book against my hexameters; &#8211; a service undoubtedly this may be, but it is not the kind of service one expects from an old acquaintance. I <del>suspect</del> am afraid nobody will think it worth while to enter into a controversy with him <del>xxx</del> nor even to read what he has to say upon such a subject.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I see the end of my first volume,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> which will be a bulky one. I have obtained some very interesting communications from Whittingham,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant General Sir Samuel Ford Whittingham (1772&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), a British soldier who served with Spanish forces in the Peninsular War 1808&#8211;1813.</note> thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">B. Frere</ref>. This work will make me as popular among the Buonapartists in France as I am among the Whigs in England. I am thinking of dedicating it to Lord Sidmouth,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth (1757&#8211;1844; Home Secretary 1812&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>). The work was eventually dedicated to George IV.</note> for motives which cannot be misapprehended now that he is no longer in office.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My poems are seldom touched &#8211; yet a fourth part of Oliver Newman<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s unfinished epic, &#8216;Oliver Newman&#8217;, set in New England. A fragment was published posthumously in <title>Oliver Newman: a New-England Tale (Unfinished): with Other Poetical Remains by the Late Robert Southey</title> (London, 1845), pp. 1&#8211;90.</note> is written, &amp; a third of the Tale of Paraguay.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> I must rouse myself to the task &amp; compleat the latter. Both satisfy me well as far as they are advanced.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  You will do me a great service if you send me a good pen-knife by <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>. Love to all</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-05-27">27 May. 1822.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>