<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3848" type="letter"><head>3848. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Thomas Clarkson</ref>] [fragment], <date when="1822-05-29">29 May 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Special Collections, The Johns Hopkins University, Raymond Dexter Havens Papers, MS. 24. AL; 1p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName> </address><date when="1822-05-29">29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May. 1822.</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am glad you are in this country once more, tho you are come to our <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydal</ref> friends at a most unhappy time.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Wordsworth had fallen from his horse and badly gashed the back of his head. Dorothy Wordsworth had also been nursing Jemima Quillinan, née Brydges (1793–1822), the wife of Edward Quillinan (1791–1851; <title>DNB</title>), the Wordsworths’ neighbour, after she was badly burned in a fire. Mrs Quillinan died on 25 May 1822.</note> – When shall we see you? Will you take us on your way to the north? Or come from <ref type="m" target="places.html#RydalMount">Rydal</ref>, &#38; return there, that you may not lose your favourite passage of Kirkstone, over which you first guided me more than eighteen years ago?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Charles Danvers, 1 March 1804, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 905. The Kirkstone pass connects Ambleside to Patterdale.</note> Fix your own time, – &#38; stay with us as long as you can. – The last time we parted was in Paterdale, – in 1809.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Tom Southey, 30 July 1809, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Three</title>, Letter 1661.</note> We drank tea in poor Luffs<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Captain Charles Luff (d. 1815), a friend of the Clarksons and the Wordsworths, who lived at Glenridding in Patterdale. He later took up a position on the Paymaster-General’s staff in Mauritius.</note> garden. He is gone, &#38; so are both the men who were my companions<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Danvers; and James Rickards (d. 1812), who was probably an old friend of Southey’s from Bristol.</note> at that time. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Tilbrooke</ref> is lamed,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Tillbrook had also been in the party who drank tea in Charles Luff’s garden.</note> – you &#38; I have suffered nothing more than the wear &#38; <del>tears</del> &#60;tear&#62; of time; – this however I have begun to feel, &#38; you no doubt will see.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Clarkson</ref>. We shall be truly glad to see her under this roof. [remainder of MS missing]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
