<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3851</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3851Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3851" type="letter">
        <head>3851. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1822-06-04">4 June 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 236&#8211;237.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I thank you heartily for your last kind note. You may be sure that your silence had excited no surprize; your leisure for letter-writing must now be much less than mine, which is little enough.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Both <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridges</ref> sons are beyond the age at which they could have benefitted by your kindness.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn had written on 28 May 1822, offering a cadetship at Addiscombe Military Seminary to one of Coleridge&#8217;s sons, with the proviso that they must be between fourteen and twenty-two years old. The Seminary trained officers for the East India Company&#8217;s army. As Wynn was President of the Board of Control he had the authority to nominate cadets to Addiscombe.</note> They are no burthen to me, &#8211; since they went to College their means of support have come from other quarters. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDavidHartley">The eldest</ref> with extraordinary abilities is turning out deplorably ill; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeDerwent">the other</ref> will I dare say do better; we hear well of him hitherto.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> is looking forward to the necessity of finding a successor for himself in the management of the Q. R. I do not imagine that either he or <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murraylemagne</ref> have a thought of me; yet if it were made worth my while, so as to offer me the certainty of an income adequate to my expenditure, I <del>should</del> &lt;might&gt; think seriously of fixing myself near London, when, next year, I must give notice whether I mean to enter upon the third term of my lease.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s lease of Greta Hall, Keswick, where he had lived since 1803. He signed a twenty-one year lease in 1809.</note> Whether I wish it or not is a different question. But I am growing old, &amp; have sometimes cause to wish that my subsistence were less precarious.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have not seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#MilmanHenryHart">Milmans</ref> two last productions.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Hart Milman&#8217;s <title>Samor, Lord of the Bright City: an Heroic Poem</title> (1818) and <title>The Fall of Jerusalem: a Dramatic Poem</title> (1820).</note> Samor was an unwieldy, ill-constructed poem, full of power &amp; promise, &#8211; just what was to be wished from an aspirant. The Jerusalem I thought ominous. That is a subject which no man who saw &amp; felt it as he ought, would venture to treat. I should as soon think of writing another Paradise Lost<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667).</note> as of describing the destruction of Jerusalem after Josephus.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Titus Flavius Josephus (AD 37&#8211;c. 100), <title>Books of the History of the Jewish War against the Romans</title> (75), which related the Roman destruction of Jerusalem in AD 70.</note> It is not only the most aweful, but it is also the impressive <del>part of</del> &lt;event in&gt; all history.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  My first vol. of the War<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is nearly finished, but it lingers in the printers hands. The sketch of our religious history<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> will not be long in following it, &amp; if I can succeed in composing a sketch of our political history to form a companion volume, I may effect some good, by giving young minds a right bias in time, which is perhaps the greatest good that can be done.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write this companion work.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I asked you in a former letter if you thought a paper upon Welsh antiquities in the QR. would be any way serviceable to the objects of the Cymrydorion?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The letter containing this proposal does not seem to have survived. Wynn had played a central role in re-founding the Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion in 1820 as a society of London-based Welshmen interested in the history of Wales. Southey was elected a member in 1821. He did not write on Welsh antiquities for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> Of course I should take care to state that it came from one who was not acquainted with the language &amp; likewise take care to have it overlooked by <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, lest any mistake should arise from that ignorance.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1"> God bless you my dear Wynn<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs affectionately<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">   RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>I am sweltering at 8 in the evening, without my coat. The glass has been at 84 to day.</p>
          <p>
            <date when="1822-06-04">June 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1822</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>