<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3860" type="letter"><head>3860. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1822-06-27">[27 June 1822]</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ J Rickman Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi><lb/>
               Endorsements: RS to JR 27 June/ 1822; 27. June 1822<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 423. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
         <opener>  <salute> My dear R.</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FeldborgAndreas">A good-natured Dano</ref> has desired me to direct to him to the care of John Reeves,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John Reeves (1752–1829; <title>DNB</title>), barrister, writer and ultra-conservative. In 1800 he was appointed the King’s Printer and became a treasurer of the Literary Fund.</note> – &#38; as I know not whether the said J Reeves has the privilege of franking, I have taken the safe side, &#38; inclosed the inclosure to you.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">My annual cold has this year made a somewhat serious attack upon the chest, from which, thank God, I believe myself to have nearly recovered. But it took strong hold upon me, &#38; for a while fairly laid me up.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> The first vol. of the war is finished as far as concerns me;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> – the Printer<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766–1831).</note> however has a good many sheets in his hands. I hope &#38; think you will like it in the main. The Whigs will not. They will find in the first chapter a foretaste of the reputation with which they will descend to posterity.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 3–61 (esp. pp. 55–58), criticised the Whigs for opposing war with France.</note></p>
          <p rend="indent1">  Agricultural distress is hardly felt here in comparison with what it is in the South. There are several causes for this, the principal being – that so many persons cultivate their own small estates, – &#38; that in other property the system of rack rent very generally prevailed, – so that rents which were screwed up during the war, having unscrewed in due proportion since the peace.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Rack rents gave the landlord a full economic return on his investment in the land. They were usually revised regularly according to varying economic conditions.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">So you have had a pleasant report of the Plague! When I send my Colloquies for the benefit of your remarks thereon, you will find an ugly opinion expressed of the probability of some such visitation.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829), I, pp. 49–58.</note> When I was too unwell for any other employment I transcribed some of their compositions, &#38; I shall send them to you when I think you are at leisure for such speculations</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Mrs R.</ref> – &#38; tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Mr Telford</ref> when you see him, that I am afraid he has forgotten that <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is only one stage out of the road to Carlisle.</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">God bless you,</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
