<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3861. Robert Southey to Joseph Blanco White, 28 June 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3861Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3861. Robert Southey to Joseph Blanco White, 28 June 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3861Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3861" type="letter">
        <head>3861. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Joseph Blanco White</ref>, <date when="1822-06-28">28 June 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] London July one 1822/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. J Blanco White/ Little Gaddesden/ Herts/ CW Williams Wynn<lb />
               MS: University of Liverpool Library, R.P.V.4.46. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Hamilton Thom (ed.), <title>The Life of the Reverend Joseph Blanco White</title>, 3 vols (London, 1845), I, pp. 380&#8211;381 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-06-28">28 June. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Blanco</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> It gave me great pleasure to receive a letter from you.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">For Blanco White&#8217;s letter, 15 June 1822, see Vicente Llorens, &#8216;Blanco White and Robert Southey: Fragments of a Correspondence&#8217;, <title>Studies in Romanticism</title>, 11 (1972), 150&#8211;151.</note> I intended to have ordered Leucadio Doblado&#8217;s letters, because the name had led me to fix upon the right author.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from Spain by Don Leucadio Doblado</title> (1822). &#8216;Leucadio&#8217; was derived from the Greek word for &#8216;white&#8217; and &#8216;Doblado&#8217; is Spanish for &#8216;doubled&#8217;, so the pseudonymous author&#8217;s name could be translated as &#8216;white doubled&#8217;, as in &#8216;Blanco White&#8217;.</note> The book reached me two days ago, &amp; I have read it, as I expected with great delight. The only fault is that there should be only one volume. I will take it as a text in the Q Review, &amp; use it to introduce some speculations upon the state of Spain &amp; Portugal.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not review this in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">My feelings respecting those countries differ not a shade from yours. Both nations appear now to be <del>suffer</del> experiencing the dreadful consequences of that abominable church-tyranny which has so long been dominant there, &amp; which <del>no where</del> in no other part of the world has ever been exercised with such remorseless rigour. The nature of the disease cannot be mistaken, nor the deep hold which it has taken. But where to look for my remedial causes I know not. At present I see little more in either country than a change of evils, &amp; the imminent danger of a civil war which if there be any thing &lt;like&gt; a balance of parties will be carried on with all the tremendous obduracy of the national character.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Military revolts in both Spain and Portugal in 1820 had led to the adoption of liberal Constitutions, but both regimes were threatened by royalist disaffection.</note> I happen to know some of the members of the Portugueze Cortes,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Henrique Xavier B&#227;eta (1776&#8211;1854), doctor, educated at the University of Edinburgh; and Felix Avellar Brotero (1744&#8211;1828), Professor of Botany at the University of Coimbra. Southey had met Brotero in Portugal on 13 March 1801. Both men were Deputies for Estramadura in the Portuguese Cortes elected in 1821.</note> &amp; perfectly understand that the constitution of that body is just like that of the neighbouring assembly, that it contains the same mixture of atheism &amp; bigotry, ignorance &amp; presumption, good intentions &amp; deplorable opinions.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The more I know of history, &amp; the more I know of what is going on in this disturbed age of the world, the less am I able to expect good from popular assemblies. Like most persons in this country, I hoped every thing from a Cortes in Spain.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The Cortes elected in 1812 under the liberal constitution of that year and abolished in 1814.</note> This was the last prejudice to which I clung, &amp; the result has <hi rend="ital">disabused</hi> me (to use a Portugueze phrase.) Had I been a Spaniard or Portugueze beyond all doubt my heart would have <del>bust</del> burst its fetters, if it had not broken in the attempt, &amp; in my abhorrence of slavery I should have rushed into the opposite extreme. But looking at these dispassionately, &amp; from a safe retirement, it appears to me that great beneficial changes in countries not accustomed to a representative government, <del>are</del> may best be brought about by the ascendancy of a single mind, &#8211; if indeed they are practicable in any other manner. For instance: &#8211; if Ferdinand<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). He had restored royal absolutism in 1814, before being forced to re-establish the Constitution of 1812 in 1820.</note> had had a minister with the strength of character that Ximenes<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Jimenez de Cisneros (1436&#8211;1517), Archbishop of Toledo 1495&#8211;1517 and leading statesman in Castile and Aragon.</note> possessed, as well adapted to the spirit of this age, as that Franciscan was to the spirit of his own, such a minister might have reformed both the church &amp; state, &amp; have prepared the people for liberty, by a wise use of despotism. Pombal<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sebastiao Jose de Carvalho e Melo, 1st Marquis of Pombal (1699&#8211;1782), Prime Minister of Portugal 1750&#8211;1777.</note> would have done this in Portugal, had he lived half a century later.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am glad to hear that you are employed upon a Spanish historical subject.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Blanco White was writing memoirs of either the reign of John II (1405&#8211;1454; King of Castile 1406&#8211;1454) or John II (1398&#8211;1479; King of Aragon 1458&#8211;1479). Blanco White does not seem to have completed this project.</note> I know the period well, &amp; have perused the works from whence your chief materials must be drawn. It is not long since I went thro P. Martires Epistles, &amp; there to my utter surprize I found siphilis described as the scourge of the age, by its Spanish &amp; French names, <del>xxx</del> in a letter written four years before Columbus sailed upon his first voyage.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Peter Martyr d&#8217;Anghiera (1457&#8211;1526), <title>Opus Epistolarum</title> (Amsterdam, 1670), p. 34. Christopher Columbus (1450/1&#8211;1506) was an Italian explorer, commissioned by the Spanish Crown in 1492 to find a new route to Asia across the Atlantic; instead he discovered America. The theory that Columbus&#8217;s sailors brought syphilis back to Europe was much debated.</note> The origin of that disease is a subject which has been so much investigated, that I cannot conceive how this decisive testimony should have been overlooked. I wish you could obtain access to the Portugueze Cancioncero, as well as to the Spanish, but I doubt whether there is a copy in England.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Cancionero General</title> (1511) was an anthology of Spanish lyric poetry, originally created by Hernando del Castillo (dates unknown). The <title>Cancioneiro Geral</title> (1516), compiled by Garcia de Resende (1470&#8211;1536) contains nearly 1,000 lyrics in Portuguese and Castilian.</note> I have only some extracts which I made at Lisbon. Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref> intended to edite the Spanish one, which he was well qualified to have done.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Nun of Arouca is not mine.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Russell, 1st Earl Russell (1792&#8211;1878; <title>DNB</title>), was the author of <title>The Nun of Arrouca, A Tale</title> (1822).</note> I have not seen it, &amp; know not whose it is. I have long been almost wholly engaged in prose. It will not be long before I shall send you an epitome of our religious history, written for the purpose of making the rising generation feel &amp; understand what they owe to the Church of England.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> I hope &amp; trust that it will not be without effect: &amp; I am sure you will approve the spirit in which it is composed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The first volume of the Hist. of the Peninsular War is nearly compleated &amp; waits only for the printer.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). The printer was Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831).</note> I am also preparing a series of dialogues upon the progress &amp; prospects of society,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title> (1829).</note> taking for my text three words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bernard, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">Respice, aspice, prospice</hi>.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Look to the past, the present, the future&#8217;, words attributed to St Bernard of Clairvaux (1090&#8211;1153). These words did appear on the title page [unpaginated] of vol. 1 of <title>Sir Thomas More: or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829).</note> &#8211; It is a comfort to know that the world will never be worse for any works which I shall leave in it. My endeavours are to strengthen the moral &amp; religious feelings, &amp; to uphold those institutions upon which the welfare of society depends.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you my dear Blanco<lb/>
            Yrs most truly<lb/>
          Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>