<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3866</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3866Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3866" type="letter">
        <head>3866. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1822-07-07">7 July 1822</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 25 To Miss Caroline Bowles/ Keswick 7 July 1822<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 26&#8211;28.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have just received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref>, in which he says &#8211; &#8220;you mention my namesake Caroline. If you write, do make my warmest congratulations known to her. &#8211; Have I read Ellen Fitzarthur?<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles, <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820).</note> &#8211; There was only one copy in Bath, &#8211; no one read a word of it, no one thought of buying it, no one spoke of it. I was the first in this neighbourhood to bring it into notice. I spoke to every one with the utmost warmth of it, as deeply affecting in story, &amp; beautiful in genuine language of poetry. I trumpeted it to Lord &amp; Lady Lansdowne,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, 3rd Marquess of Lansdowne (1780&#8211;1863; <title>DNB</title>), Whig politician and great landowner; and his wife, Lady Louisa, n&#233;e Fox-Strangways (1785&#8211;1851). Their country seat was Bowood, Wiltshire.</note> Miss Fox,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Caroline Fox (1767&#8211;1845), sister of Lord Holland.</note> &amp; all the literati of Bowood, &amp; <hi rend="ital">without knowing the name</hi>, I flatter myself I contributed in some degree to its more general notice among some distinguished ornaments of taste &amp; literature. I should be happy to know Caroline, &amp; more to think her a relation. I think a poem so remote from the golden &#8211; silvery &#8211; diamond &#8211;alabaster &#8211; Pontypool-style <note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Pontypool&#8217; was a form of decorated domestic tinplate.</note>of the present Cockney race of Dandy Poetasters<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The &#8216;Cockney school&#8217; was a dismissive term for London-based poets, especially those associated with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Leigh Hunt</ref>.</note> cannot be too much noticed; &amp; I am rejoiced the real touches of nature &amp; passion have awakened attention.&#8221;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Thus for <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref>, &amp; in a postscript he adds &#8216;I think I shall write a note to Caroline, with my poem.&#8217;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If authorship in its notoriety brings with it some evils, they are overpaid, where there is desert, by a large portion of good. I owe to it not merely many pleasant acquaintance, but some valuable friends &amp; you will reap the same fruits. My question to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref> was concerning your last volume,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Widow&#8217;s Tale: and Other Poems</title> (1822).</note> as well as Ellen Fitzarthur: &#8211; if he has not seen it, he will look for it now, &amp; he will find there all that he found in the former publication &amp; more. I have shown it to many persons &amp; in no one instance have I been disappointed of seeing it produce the effect which I expected.
               I have <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">a friend</ref> with me now whom I had not seen since we parted at College, eight &amp; twenty years ago &#8211; <del>xxx</del> &lt;tho&gt; our occasional communication by letter had never been interrupted. We parted <del>xxx</del> just as mere commencing men, <del>in youth &amp; xxx</del> with the world before us, &#8211; &amp; we meet just at that time of life when age &amp; decay are beginning to make themselves felt. You can better feel what the feelings of such a meeting are, than I could express them. I should not have recognized him so much is he changed: he says he should have known me any where. We have been comparing notes, &amp; find our hearts &amp; views just as much in unison as they were when we, literally, lived together at college, &#8211; for we breakfasted together every morning, read together, &amp; past every evening together. In this respect I have been peculiarly fortunate, that most of my friendships have been formed for eternity, &amp; grown stronger as they have grown older.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is a very bad translation of Herman &amp; Dorothea by Holcroft,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Holcroft (1745&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Herman and Dorothea. A Poem, from the German</title> (1801), a translation of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749&#8211;1832), <title>Hermann und Dorothea</title> (1797).</note> but it would show you the plan of the poem. The original I am told is a piece of finished versification: the translation is meant for blank verse by a man who was no poet &amp; did not even understand the common rules of metre.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You mention <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley.</ref> &#8211; I should like to show you some letters which past between that wretched man &amp; me about two years ago.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">At this point is added in another hand: &#8216;Note. These letters are in possession of Southey&#8217;s family &#8211; &amp; very remarkable ones they are.&#8217; [Editors note: In a letter of 26 June 1820, Shelley had accused Southey of writing a hostile review of <title>Laon and Cythna, or the Revolution of the Golden City</title> (1818; published late 1817) and <title>The Revolt of Islam. A Poem, in Twelve Cantos</title> (1818); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 358&#8211;359. Southey responded with his letter to Percy Bysshe Shelley, [c. 29 July 1820], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3517. Shelley replied in a letter to Southey, 17 August 1820, Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 361&#8211;363. Southey to Percy Bysshe Shelley, 12 October 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3538, closed the correspondence.]</note> He came to this place with his wife immediately after his marriage.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley had stayed in Keswick November 1811&#8211;February 1812, shortly after his marriage to Harriet Westbrook. He met Southey a number of times.</note> I saw a great deal of him then, &amp; hoped that he would outgrow the insane opinions which had <del>held</del> &lt;their root&gt;, as I then thought, in mere ignorance not in a corrupted heart &amp; will. And I know a great deal of his accursed history since.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  How are you? &amp; what are you doing? &#8211; I have been very much out of order. A cold which comes regularly every year with the summer &amp; continues ten or twelve weeks, has this year attacked my chest; &amp; tho materially better I cannot yet say that it is fairly dislodged. I shall soon have a volume of the Peninsular War<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> abroad; a noble story, which will set foul tongues railing, while it makes sound hearts throb with generous emotions. My Book of the Church<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> will speedily follow it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">God bless you &#8211; sister-poetess. I have a right to call you so, tho I cannot look for a relationship like <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesWilliamLisle">Bowles</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">yrs truly<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">  Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-07-07">7 July. 1822</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>