<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3869. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 14 July 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3869Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3869. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 14 July 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3869Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3869" type="letter">
        <head>3869. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-07-14">14 July 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: E/ 17 JY 17/ 1822; [illegible]<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-07-14">14 July 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I hope you may not come when <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> is here<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> for this reason only, that I like to husband my enjoyments &amp; as it is badly management to introduce venison at a turtle feast<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Green sea turtle had been one the most expensive and high-status foods served at feasts since the mid eighteenth century.</note> so is it bad economy of pleasure to have two friends at the same time. I am looking every day to hear from him. Meantime my old college friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> is with me, whom I had not seen for eight &amp; twenty years. He is now a married man with five children;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806&#8211;1882), Southey&#8217;s god-daughter; Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808&#8211;1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810&#8211;1889); Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811&#8211;1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846&#8211;1855, Rector of Islip 1855&#8211;1881.</note> &#8211; his life has been uniform &amp; laborious, but singularly fortunate; he has realized a respectable fortune as a schoolmaster,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Lightfoot had been Master of Queen Elizabeth&#8217;s Grammar School, Crediton, since March 1800. Although Lightfoot&#8217;s stipend had at first been only &#163;20 p.a., his admission of boarding pupils, and improvements in the schools endowments, gave him a respectable, if not secure, income. In 1818 he received a stipend of &#163;50 as headmaster, plus a house and an allowance for taxes. He was also paid &#163;5 p.a. for each day pupil and charged 30 guineas p.a. for boarding pupils (of whom he had 37 in 1811). In addition, the Governors of the school had presented him to the nearby Rectory of Kennerleigh in 1807, with a stipend of &#163;100 p.a.; Nicholas Carlisle, <title>A Concise Description of the Endowed Grammar Schools in England and Wales</title>, 2 vols (London, 1818), I, pp. 254&#8211;265.</note> &amp; during one &amp; twenty years, that he has been married,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768&#8211;1856) on 13 July 1801. They had met when he was usher at Kingsbridge Grammar School in Devon 1795&#8211;1800.</note> has never had so much anxiety as to deprive him of a single nights rest. A happier man I never saw, &amp; no man is more deserving of happiness. He stays here till Tuesday the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> arrives before that time the young John must sleep in the town, otherwise we have so managed matters as to find rooms for father &amp; son.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> One of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">my New England friends</ref> has sent me a cargo of Yankee books which I wish you would enquire for because they ought to have reached me before this time. They come from <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Mr Ticknor</ref> of Boston &amp; were sent by the same vessel which brought me advice of them, to the care of his bookseller John Miller 69 <hi rend="ital">Fleet Street, Strand</hi>,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Miller (dates unknown), publisher who specialised in marketing and distributing American books and journals.</note> with directions to forward them to me by coach. This is the American direction, &amp; whether Miller live in Fleet Street, or in the Strand I cannot tell but think it is in the former. When you go that way call, &amp; make enquiry concerning them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A spell among the mountains will do you good. I was on Skiddaw yesterday, &#8211; &amp; am trying whether by persevering in exercise I can, as on former occasion, put my system in such tone as for awhile to suspend my complaint.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably Southey&#8217;s rectal prolapse.</note> It annoys me greatly on waking &amp; I have little doubt but that it will effectually lay me up at last, if I live long enough for it to take its course. My cold is very much better tho I cannot yet dislodge it from the chest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">In the coach from Kendal <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> fell in with a Laker of whom <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">Mrs Gonne</ref> knows something. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Heathcote<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles John Heatchcote (1796&#8211;1874) was a BA of Trinity College, Cambridge 1817, a clergyman, Chaplain of Trinity College, Cambridge 1823&#8211;1826 and a teacher at the university at this time. He was Stipendiary Curate of St Thomas&#8217;s, Stamford Hill 1827&#8211;1861. His pupil is unidentified.</note> a son of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Heathcote of Hackney.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Thomas Heathcote (1769&#8211;1820), Vicar of Rodmersham 1799&#8211;1815 and Rector of Little Wigborough 1814&#8211;1820, was Headmaster of Hackney School 1805&#8211;1815.</note> &#8211; He drank tea with us the other evening, &amp; is now lodging near the Grange<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The village of Grange in Borrowdale, about four miles from Keswick.</note> with a young pupil</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Can you make room in your portmanteau for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Teresas life<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">St Teresa of Avila (1515&#8211;1582). The copy sent to Southey by Gooch is unidentified. Southey at some point acquired <title>The Works of the Holy Mother St Teresa of Jesus, Foundress of the Reformation of Discalced Carmelites</title> (1675), no. 2847 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> which is in <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoochDrRobert">Gooch&#8217;s</ref> possession?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Love to all &#8211;</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>