<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3878Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3878" type="letter">
        <head>3878. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1822-07-30">30 July &#8211; [continued on 2 August] 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surry<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: [partial] o&#8217;Clock/ AU/ 1822 N<hi rend="sup">n</hi>
            <lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 220. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 321&#8211;323 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-07-30">30 July. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">D. Joze Marias Ed. of the Lusiad<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Jose Maria de Sousa Botelho Mourao e Vasconcelos (1758&#8211;1825), <title>A Edi&#231;&#227;o Monumental de Os Lus&#237;ades</title> (1817). Only 210 copies were printed, all of which were presented as gifts.</note> is I believe to be seen at Holland House,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The London home of Lord Holland, containing his magnificent collection of Iberian literature.</note> &#8211; but only to be had from the Editor himself &#8211; - an octavo edition, I think, was published for sale. I have never seen either. &#8211; The want of F. y Sousas edition<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Manuel de Faria e Sousa (1590&#8211;1649), <title>Lusiadas de Luis Camoens</title> (1639).</note> was a deficiency which I felt much more, &#8211; his commentary must certainly contain many things which I could have turned to good account.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey is referring here to his review of John Adamson, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Luis de Camoens</title> (1820), no. 10 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey&#8217;s review had been published in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), 1&#8211;39, on 4 July 1822.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I returned from Rydal to day, not the worse for a walk of fifteen miles, the last ten in the rain. A great deal of exercise during the last three weeks has done me great service, &amp; when <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> &amp; his son<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> arrive I shall put them upon their mettle. <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">Dr Wordsworth</ref> is at Rydal, &amp; enquired for you. I had <del>a good</del> some conversation with him concerning Westminster. Without knowing that I had any immediate interest in the question, he took some pains to show me that for a boy of talents it would be more advantageous to be elected off to Trinity Col. than to Ch. Ch.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill&#8217;s eldest son, Edward Hill, was about to attempt to become a King&#8217;s Scholar at Westminster School, which would allow him to proceed to a Closed Scholarship at either Christ Church, Oxford, or Trinity College, Cambridge. Wordsworth as Master of Trinity College may have given partial advice that Cambridge was a better option for a young man seeking a life at university; there was no certainty that a King&#8217;s Scholar would receive a Fellowship once he graduated. But at Christ Church, a King&#8217;s Scholar immediately became one of the body of Students, with a modest stipend that was guaranteed for life, if the recipient wished and he obeyed the rules of the College. If the Students took university degrees in a timely fashion then their stipend would increase. However, the rules governing Studentships were strict and anyone who married, did not take Holy Orders or accepted a paid occupation had to resign. Edward Hill chose Christ Church, Oxford.</note> The scholarship while it lasts (which is till the Masters degree is taken) is worth 40&#163; a year, &#8211; <del>not xxxx</del> not much less therefore, according to his account than a studentship, &#8211; the fellowships are 4 &#8211; or 500&#163;. For these indeed a Westminster scholar has only the same chance as other scholars, but caeteris paribus<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;All other things being equal&#8217;.</note> there would be a wish to prefer him. For one who chuses a college life, the Ch. Ch. destination would be obviously the best, because <del>tho of inferior value in its</del> the Studentship there is every thing; but in any other case <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">Dr W.</ref> is perhaps right in representing the Cambridge chance as worth more than the Oxford certainty.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">
          <date when="1822-08-02">Friday morning</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">We have been overrun with visitors since my return. I found in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> my old acquaintance <ref type="m" target="people.html#SharpRichard">Sharpe</ref>, &#8211; &amp; also &#8216;Randolph&#8217; of Roanoke,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John Randolph (1773&#8211;1833), Virginia tobacco planter and Representative or Senator almost continuously for his State between 1799 and 1833. Southey favoured the Federalists as a pro-British party, but Randolph was not a member &#8211; though he did oppose the war of 1812 with Britain. The Federalists were fading away by 1822 and had last fielded a presidential candidate in 1816.</note> &#8211; so he styles himself on his card; &#8211; the Randolph who was considered as the head of the Federal party in America while any such party existed. A singular but very interesting man. &#8211; Sir John Malcolm<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Malcolm (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish soldier, East India Company administrator and historian. He had effectively governed most of central India 1818&#8211;1822, but had returned home disappointed not to receive further promotion.</note> breakfasted with me this morning, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Duncan<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Duncan (1774&#8211;1846; <title>DNB</title>), Minister of Ruthwell, Dumfriesshire, who had founded the savings bank movement in 1810.</note> a Scotch pastor who first set the Savings Banks on foot. Malcolms Herculean form is much shaken since I saw him last, &amp; well it may, for during his last five years residence in India, he did not spend three months under a roof. But he is recovering, &amp; his spirits are as exuberant as ever. He is on his way to London to publish a book, which from the specimens which he has shown me, must be a very curious one.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Memoir of Central India, including Malwa, and Adjoining Provinces</title> (1823).</note> It is in substance &amp; perhaps in form also, the official report of his Government.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Yesterday I had a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref>
          <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall was collecting material for <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These could be inserted into the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> asking for the sketch of Elvas. I thought he had been on his way northwards, but business will detain him at home. I send you his direction (19 Mornington Place, Hampstead Road) that you may either send the sketch, or take it, if you feel inclined to see what he has already done. If you <del>xx</del> see him ask him to show you <del>xxx</del> &lt;a&gt; view in Madeira <del>xxxxx x x</del> (if he has it still in his possession) with the platform before a Capuchin Convent &amp; the Bell.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Westall had visited Madeira in 1801 and 1805&#8211;1806, and published <title>Foreign Scenery. A Series of Views of Picturesque and Romantic Scenery in Madeira, the Cape of Good Hope, Timor, China, Prince of Wales Island, Bombay, Mahratta Country, St Helena, and Jamaica. From Drawings made in those Countries</title> (1811&#8211;1814). There was a Capuchin nunnery in Madeira, the Convento das Merces.</note> He has seen New Holland, the East Indies &amp; the West, but considers Madeira as the most picturesque country which he has yet visited.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have followed your advice &amp; sent off Ded. Preface &amp;c as soon as your letter arrived.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">For the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> Three sheets will now compleat the printers<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Davison (1766&#8211;1831).</note> work.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Remember us to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the children. I have not heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> of any change in his intentions.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>