<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3879Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3879" type="letter">
        <head>3879. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#GarnettRichard">Richard Garnett</ref>], <date when="1822-08-01">1 August 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 2p.<lb />
               Unpublished.<lb />
               Note on correspondent: Identified by subject matter. The content makes it likely that this letter is to Richard Garnett. Southey&#8217;s correspondent had been researching the life of Simon Ockley, who was a family connection of Richard Garnett&#8217;s first wife, Margaret Heathcote (1795&#8211;1828). The letter also displays an interest in many of Garnett&#8217;s enthusiasms, including writings published in Germany and medieval literature.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-08-01">1 Aug. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am truly obliged to you for the interesting communications contained in your letter. Ockleys narrative<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;An account of a spirit in Cambridge Castle, 1717, by S. Ockley&#8217;, contained in the Lansdowne manuscripts in the British Museum. The author was the orientalist, Simon Ockley (1678&#8211;1720; <title>DNB</title>), at that time imprisoned in Cambridge Castle for debt. His account of being haunted by a poltergeist later became a famous instance of an allegedly supernatural event.</note> is certainly well worth preserving as one of the many stories for which no satisfactory solution can be offered. It is a case in which imposture is clearly possible, but highly improbable: &#8211; the question <hi rend="ital">cui bono</hi>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;who benefits&#8217;.</note>
          <del>X</del> applying with more force to it if considered as a trick, than as the freak of some superhuman agent of Jefferys family.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, <title>The Life of Wesley; and the Rise and Progress of Methodism</title>, 2 vols (London, 1820), I, p. 442. John Wesley&#8217;s (1703&#8211;1791; <title>DNB</title>) sister, Emelia (1693&#8211;1779), recounted how the Wesley family&#8217;s home was haunted by a ghost, &#8216;Jeffrey&#8217;, but her mother, Susanna Wesley (1669&#8211;1742), was convinced the noises in the house were caused by rats. She used a horn to try and drive the rats out of the house.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The paper upon Astrology &amp; Alchemy<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A review by Francis Palgrave of &#8216;Francis Moore&#8217;, <title>Vox Stellarum, a Loyal Almanack for the Year of Human Redemption 1821</title> (1821) and William Thomas Brande (1788&#8211;1866; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;History of Chemistry&#8217; in <title>A Manual of Chemistry</title>, 2 vols (London, 1821), I, pp. 1&#8211;188, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26 (October 1821), 180&#8211;209, published 21 December 1821.</note> I believe to have been written by <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalgraveFrancis">Mr Cohen</ref>, a young man of German-Jewish extraction, of extraordinary industry &amp; attainments, especially in such out-of-the-way subjects. The only Astrologer whom I happen to have known was <ref type="m" target="people.html#GilbertWilliam">a Gentleman</ref>
          <del>x</del> a scholar, &amp; &lt;a man of genius&gt; but decidedly insane, &#8211; the son of that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gilbert<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Nathaniel Gilbert (c. 1721&#8211;1774), a lawyer, planter in Antigua and Speaker of the Antiguan House of Assembly 1763&#8211;1769. He converted to Methodism in 1758 and after inheriting an estate in Antigua in 1761 began to evangelise his slaves.</note> who first introduced Methodism into the island of Antigua. He learnt it from John Henderson,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Henderson (1757&#8211;1788; <title>DNB</title>), an eccentric polymath. He helped his father, Richard Henderson (1736/7&#8211;1792), to run an asylum at Hanham near Bristol at the time that William Gilbert was an inmate in 1788&#8211;1789.</note> who sported with his own powerful intellect almost as much as he delighted to do with the weaker minds of others. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GilbertWilliam">Gilbert</ref> cast my nativity about five &amp; twenty years ago, &amp; the scheme with a long rhapsodical explication is somewhere among my papers.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Gilbert&#8217;s horoscope for Southey does not survive, but see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 30 September 1797, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part One</title>, Letter 259.</note> It promises me great prosperity where I shall never go to seek it, &#8211; at Berlin, or Algiers. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalgraveFrancis">Cohen</ref> is wrong when he supposes Astrology to be extinct, &#8211; there are certain minds upon which it will always retain its hold</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The Spanish ballads, like our own, have undergone all sorts of alterations; &#8211; every reciter, while they were orally preserved, adding &amp; omitting at pleasure, &amp; frequently supplying parts which he had forgotten, or imperfectly remembered. The German Collection I have not seen.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear which collection of Spanish ballads Southey is referring to here, as a number had been published in Germany, including: Jacob Grimm (1785&#8211;1863), <title>Silva de Romances Viejos</title> (1815); Georg Bernhard Depping (1784&#8211;1853), <title>Sammlung der Besten Alten Spanischen Romanzen</title> (1817); Friedrich Diez (1794&#8211;1876), <title>Altspanische Romanzen</title> (1818&#8211;1821); and Johann Nikolaus Bohl von Faber (1770&#8211;1836), <title>Floresta de Rimas Antiguas Castellanas</title> (1821&#8211;1825).</note> My own version of the two ballads to which you allude (they are two of the best Romances) was made from the Guerras de Granada.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Gines Perez de Hita (c. 1544&#8211;c. 1619), <title>Historia de los Vandos, de los Cegries, y Abencerrages, cavalleros moros de Granada, y los civiles guerras que huvo en ella, hasta que el Rey Don Fernando el Quinto la gano</title> (1731&#8211;1733), no. 3403 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It is not clear which two ballads Garnett alluded to, but they might have been Southey&#8217;s translations, &#8216;Thro&#8217; the city of Granada&#8217; and &#8216;Moor Alcayde, Moor Alcayde&#8217;, published in <title>Chronicle of the Cid</title> (London, 1808), pp. 371&#8211;374, which were drawn from Perez de Hita&#8217;s work.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Farewell Sir. If at any time you should visit the Lakes, it will give me pleasure to have an opportunity of becoming personally acquainted with you</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">yrs with respect</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>