<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3888. Robert Southey to [Bartholomew Frere], 28 August 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3888Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3888. Robert Southey to [Bartholomew Frere], 28 August 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3888Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3888" type="letter">
        <head>3888. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Bartholomew Frere</ref>], <date when="1822-08-28">28 August 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-08-22">28 Aug. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> My first volume<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is now finished, &amp; I am glad to think that you found nothing to require correction in the latter chapters. I have <hi rend="ital">inlaid</hi> some very important particulars from <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymples</ref> papers.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">This material related especially to the war in the south of Spain in 1808 and the Battle of Bail&#233;n, 16&#8211;19 July1808, the first great success of Spanish forces in the Peninsular War. Southey dealt with this in his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 382&#8211;386. At pp. 389&#8211;390, Southey inserted some material concerning Dalrymple&#8217;s role in the attempts of Spanish commanders to change the terms of surrender of the French army.</note> It was difficult to do this, but far better thus to do it, than to have appended them at the end of the volume. A few points of minor importance I leave to be added, or corrected, in an after addition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will either publish this volume immediately, or delay it till the winter, as he thinks best.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) was not published until December 1822.</note> this is his business, not mine. I shall desire him to send you a copy, &amp; also one which you will know how to transmit to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">your brother</ref>, if, as <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Mr Canning</ref> tells me, he is taking root at Malta.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will have seen how largely I profited by your account of Romana,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Pedro Caro y Sureda, 3rd Marquis of La Romana (1761&#8211;1811), a Spanish general. He commanded the &#8216;Army of the North&#8217; and ensured its evacuation to Spain in 1808, where he was one of the more successful Spanish commanders.</note> &amp; by O Donnells journal.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Enrique Jose O&#8217;Donnell y Anatar (1769&#8211;1834), a Spanish General, created Conde de La Bisbal in 1810.</note> Mackenzies<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Colin Alexander Mackenzie (?1778&#8211;1851), a wealthy Scot who was employed on a number of delicate diplomatic missions and may well have been a government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of the Commissioners of Liquidation, Arbitration and Deposit who adjudicated on claims by British citizens for loss of property against the French government. Southey had met him in Paris in May 1817, and Mackenzie had provided the information about his role in the evacuation of the Spanish Army of the North from Denmark that appeared in Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 657&#8211;658.</note> adventures I obtained from himself. The story of the horses is very remarkable.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 663&#8211;664, related that the horses belonging to the Spanish troops were set free on the Danish shore and most of them killed each other in a &#8216;dreadful work of mutual destruction&#8217;.</note> I have since heard from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FeldborgAndreas">a Dane</ref> that three which escaped the battle were named by his countrymen, Romana, D. Quixote &amp; Sancho. &#8211; I have also learnt that the regiments which did not effect their escape, were sent as prisoners into France, &amp; there employed in working upon the roads, &amp; other public labour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The sooner you can favour me with such of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">your brothers</ref> papers as you think proper, the sooner I shall be able to put the second volume to press, which it is my wish to do with the least possible delay.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Gouvion S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cyr<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Laurent de Gouvion Saint-Cyr (1764&#8211;1830), <title>Journal des Operations de l&#8217;Armee de Catalogne, en 1808 et 1809</title> (1821), p. 50.</note> charges the English with gross misconduct in neglecting to bring off the garrison of Rosas.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp. 37&#8211;59. French forces captured the town of Rosas on 5 December 1808 after a month-long siege and this allowed them to proceed to relieve the French army surrounded in Barcelona.</note> Is this charge well founded? What Cabanes<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Francisco Xavier de Cabanes (1781&#8211;1834), <title>Historia de las Operaciones des Exercito de Cataluna en la Guerra de la Usurpacion</title> (1809), no. 3816 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> says seems to confirm it. Perhaps <del>I may find among</del> there may be something among your communications which will satisfy me upon this subject. My opinion, formed upon such information as the newspapers English &amp; Spanish gave, had been that Lord Cochrane<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Cochrane, 10th Earl of Dundonald (1775&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>) commanded British naval forces assisting the Spanish garrison at Rosas. Southey specifically refuted Saint-Cyr&#8217;s arguments in <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp. 46&#8211;47.</note> had done every thing there which great intrepidity &amp; great talents could do.</p>
        <p>
          Believe me my Dear Sir<lb/>
           yours with sincere respect<lb/>
          Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>