<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3889Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3889" type="letter">
        <head>3889. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-08-30">30 August 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 2 SE 2/ 1822<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-08-30">30 Aug. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I have long been expecting to hear that you were about to set forth for <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>; where you will do me some service by keeping up the good work which <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> have wrought upon me. When I began a course of brisk exercise with the former it required <del>x</del> no small resolution to persevere at the cost of so much inconvenience &amp; pain: persevere however I did, &amp; the effect has been surprizing. For the present my complaint<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was suffering from a rectal prolapse and haemorrhoids.</note> is entirely suspended, &amp; I, who eight weeks ago could not walk to church without annoyance from it, am now as well able to climb Skiddaw or Causey Pike as ever I was.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdward">Edward</ref> requesting a small stated allowance as long as he is disabled &#8211; five pounds half yearly he names from each of us. Poor fellow, if his demands were higher I should answer them: &#8211; it shows some grace that he has made so few. Do you tell him that he may reckon upon this, &#8211; &amp; let him have it at proper times. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> will settle the account with you</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Have you made enquiry at Millers<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Miller (dates unknown), publisher who specialised in marketing and distributing American books and journals.</note> about the Yankee Books from <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Ticknor</ref>? I have heard nothing of them, &amp; begin to be apprehensive of some neglect or foul play.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My first volume<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> will be compleated as soon as soon as I shall have received two cancels,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Cancels, new pages to replace ones already printed.</note> in each of which a passage of some importance has been fitted in. &#8211; Will you present it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref>? I have dedicated it to him in very few lines, containing a well-deserved compliment expressed as loosely &amp; plainly as you would wish to see it.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, p. [iii]: &#8216;It is with peculiar fitness, as well as with pleasure, that I inscribe to your Majesty a History of the most glorious war recorded in the British annals./When the Regency devolved into your hands, the fortunes of our allies were at their lowest ebb, and neither arts nor efforts were spared for making the spirit of this country sink with them. At that momentous crisis every thing depended, under Providence, upon your single determination; and to that determination Great Britain is beholden for its triumph, and Europe for its deliverance./To your Majesty, therefore, this faithful History is offered, as a portion of the tribute due to a just, magnanimous, and splendid reign, and as a proof of individual respect and gratitude from/Your Majesty&#8217;s/Most dutiful subject and servant,/ROBERT SOUTHEY.&#8217;</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> will tell you that he spent his time here much to his satisfaction, &amp; saw all the World &amp; his Wife. I sent him round to Waswater while I went to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Canning</ref> at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Boltons.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Storrs Hall on Windermere, the Lake District home of John Bolton (1756&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), Liverpool merchant and leading supporter of Canning as MP for that city.</note> To my great vexation <ref type="m" target="people.html#TelfordThomas">Telford</ref> came with Sir Henry Parnell<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Henry Parnell, 4th Baronet (1776&#8211;1842; <title>DNB</title>), later 1st Baron Congleton. Parnell was an Irish landowner and Whig politician; MP for Queen&#8217;s County 1806&#8211;1832 and Dundee 1833&#8211;1841. He was later Secretary at War 1831&#8211;1832, Paymaster of the Forces 1835&#8211;1836 and Paymaster-General 1836&#8211;1841. His main interest was financial reform, but he was also a close collaborator of Telford&#8217;s and the author of <title>A Treatise on Roads, wherein the Principles on which Roads should be made are explained by the Plans, Specifications and Contracts made use of by Thomas Telford, Esq.</title> (1833).</note> during this short absence, &amp; thus I mist seeing one the men in the world whom I most wished to see here. &#8211; We have Sir John Malcolm<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Malcolm (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), the Scottish soldier, East India Company administrator and historian. He had effectively governed most of central India in 1818&#8211;1822, but had returned home disappointed not to receive further promotion.</note> here, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeberRichard">Heber</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Locker</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FeldborgAndreas">Feldborg the Dane</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">Dr Bell</ref> is here now. The <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">poor General</ref> has had no enjoyment of this concourse owing to a frightful accident which befell young Henry<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. The accident occurred on 2 August 1822 and was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming Henry): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta.</note> &#8211; a tremendous fracture of the skull by the bursting of a cannon. The accident took place this day month, &amp; tho appearances are as fair as they possibly can be, he is far from being out of danger.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The sooner you can come the better, because the days are shortening upon us. I have a great deal to show you. A week here will be worth six months in London, where I am always too much hurried to enjoy any thing, &#8211; except French wines.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Our love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">Mrs Gonne</ref>. The children<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817); Charles Gonne Southey (1819&#8211;1861), later an army officer in India; and Louisa Mary Southey (1821&#8211;1824).</note> I hope are well. Ours are in tolerably good plight, &#8211; but I shall like you to examine <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> about her eyes, &amp; to give me some advice about <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">JMay</ref> will leave &lt;with&gt; you a packet of pencils for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref>, which I will desire him to call or send for</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>