<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3891Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3891" type="letter">
        <head>3891. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1822-09-01">1 September 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 330&#8211;332.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-09-01">Sept. 1. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Taken up as I have been for the last two months by a succession of guests and chance visitors, even to a total suspension of all my customary and necessary employments, I would yet have found time for writing to you if I had known of your father&#8217;s decease.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John White, formerly a butcher in Nottingham, had moved to Norfolk with his family in 1821 in order for them to be near Neville White. John White died at Catton, Norfolk, on 3 July 1822.</note> What, however, could I have said more than your own feelings and faith had suggested to you! For the best of us, when our lives are not of essential use to others, death is better than life; and it were weakness, indeed, to desire for our friends a prolonged old age, when, in our sober judgment, we should wish no such lot for ourselves.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">This, though a solemn event, is no evil. It was my lot to lose both my parents<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">Robert Southey,Senior</ref>, and his wife <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">Margaret</ref>.</note> when they were very little older than I am at present, and, in the ordinary course of nature, might have enjoyed many years of life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJames">James&#8217;s</ref> affection of the chest is not necessarily of an alarming nature. I know at this time three instances of persons who have repeatedly discharged large quantities of blood from the lungs; the ailment is of many years&#8217; standing, and yet all three are good lives.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Solomon Pigott<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Solomon Piggott (1779&#8211;1845), Rector of Dunstable, 1824&#8211;1845. Piggott had claimed to be instrumental in Kirke White&#8217;s conversion to Christianity. This statement was refuted in Southey&#8217;s Preface to the 9th edition of <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title>, 3 vols (London, 1822), III, p. vii, which noted it was &#8216;groundless&#8217;. Piggott was presumably planning to argue his &#8216;Case&#8217; in a publication.</note> has written me a letter of remonstrance upon the printed sheet which contains the circular of his &#8220;Case.&#8221; I have neither noticed the case, nor the letter. With regard to the matter of his complaint, he has provoked the treatment which he has received. What became of the intended prints for this third volume?<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">A ninth edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> had been published earlier in 1822. This had an added third volume, which contained a new Preface and previously unpublished poems and letters and poems by Kirke White. The third volume did not include any prints.</note> Let me know in time when it is proposed to distribute these gleanings at their proper places, and I will then alter the Memoir accordingly.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A tenth edition of the <title>Remains</title> followed in 1823. This compressed the three-volume 1822 edition back into two volumes. As a result, Southey had to combine some of the Preface written for the 1822 ninth edition with his earlier &#8216;Life&#8217; of Kirke White; see <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title>, 10th edn, 2 vols (London, 1823), pp. [v]&#8211;lxviii, and [lxix]&#8211;lxxiii.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I congratulate you on your preferment;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Neville White had just been appointed Perpetual Curate of Great Plumstead, only five miles east of Norwich, where he lived. The Great Plumstead living was not wealthy, but it was White&#8217;s first preferment to a benefice. As the post was in the gift of the Dean and Chapter of Norwich Cathedral, White&#8217;s appointment was also a sign of his good standing and local connections.</note> its convenience is its value, and this to you is of the greatest. Moreover, it is a very gratifying proof of the estimation in which you are held by the Dean and Chapter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">My brother</ref> told me of your transit through London. You have now accomplished a great work in removing your family, and in doing so it may reasonably be hoped you have performed the last of a long series of most important services. You are a happy man, Neville, and it is delightful to think, as my experience shows me, that the best men are always the happiest.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> has just been to wish me good night. He is, I think, just as winning for his age as he was when you and your good friends were so well pleased with him. To&#8211;day, for the first time, and by his own earnest desire, he has been to church. His sisters,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> thank God, are well; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">their mother</ref> is better than her usual health, and I myself strengthened almost beyond my expectation by the brisk exercise which I have taken during the last two months. An old college friend, <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> by name (master of Crediton school), whom I had not seen since we parted when we both left Oxford eight and twenty years ago, mustered up resolution to take a longer journey than he had ever before accomplished, for the sake of visiting me. He stayed with me as long as his holidays would allow; and I believe no men ever met more cordially after so long a separation, or enjoyed each other&#8217;s society more. I shall never forget the manner in which he first met me, nor the time in which he said that having now seen me, he should return home and die in peace. We took many of the walks which you and I performed together, and which every year become dearer to me, for the recollection of those friends with whom the scenery is now associated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My old friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> has also visited me for the first time, and stayed with me three weeks. I am now expecting <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref> as soon as he can give himself a fortnight&#8217;s holiday from his profession.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A word or two more of my employments. The first volume of the &#8216;Peninsular War&#8217; is completed.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> Whether <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will publish it now, or delay it till the winter, rests with him. You will, of course, receive a copy as soon as it appears. I have dedicated it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, p. [iii]: &#8216;It is with peculiar fitness, as well as with pleasure, that I inscribe to your Majesty a History of the most glorious war recorded in the British annals./When the Regency devolved into your hands, the fortunes of our allies were at their lowest ebb, and neither arts nor efforts were spared for making the spirit of this country sink with them. At that momentous crisis every thing depended, under Providence, upon your single determination; and to that determination Great Britain is beholden for its triumph, and Europe for its deliverance./To your Majesty, therefore, this faithful History is offered, as a portion of the tribute due to a just, magnanimous, and splendid reign, and as a proof of individual respect and gratitude from/Your Majesty&#8217;s/Most dutiful subject and servant,/ROBERT SOUTHEY.&#8217;</note> The book of the Church lingers,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> and I suspect <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has mislaid the last portion of manuscript. I shall now take it up, and pursue it to the end.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you, my dear Neville,</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2"> Yours affectionately,</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>