<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3893</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3893Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3893" type="letter">
        <head>3893. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-09-06">6 September 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey./ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 9 SE 9/ 1822<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-09-06">6 <del>Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
              </del> &lt;Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>&gt; 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  I am vexed that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">your nervous Lady</ref> should make you the patient now, if however she only delays you till the stormy weather blows over, it will be well.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Louisa Southey was pregnant and gave birth to Henry Herbert Southey, Jnr (1822&#8211;1829) on 6 November 1822.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The bust arrived safely at Rydal.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A bust of Southey had been sculpted in 1813 by James Smith (1775&#8211;1815). Smith&#8217;s business was carried on by his sons, Charles Raymond Smith (c. 1798&#8211;1888) and Thomas Smith (b. 1800) at 57 Upper Norton Street and Southey had ordered a copy to be made, to give to Wordsworth in exchange for a copy of Sir Francis Chantrey&#8217;s bust of Wordsworth, completed in 1820.</note> The Shakspere will no doubt make its appearance next week.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">James Boswell (1778&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>), old school-friend of Southey, lawyer, poet and literary scholar, had died on 24 February 1822. Boswell completed Edmond Malone (1741&#8211;1812; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Plays and Poems of William Shakespeare, with the Corrections and Illustrations of Various Commentators: Comprehending a Life of the Poet, and an Enlarged History of the Stage</title> (1821) and Southey had asked Henry Herbert Southey to send him a copy. It became no. 2539 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> I have a list of the American books, &#8211; but it is a list <hi rend="ital">raisonn&#233;e</hi> in <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Ticknors</ref> letter, with an &amp;c at the end, &amp; what that &amp;c may comprehend I cannot tell. It may however be as well that Miller<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Miller (dates unknown), a publisher who specialised in marketing and distributing American books and journals.</note> should know I have the list, because he had no business to ask the question. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">Ticknor</ref> sends the books thro him as the bookseller whom he employs (<hi rend="ital">largely</hi> I have no doubt both on his private account, &amp; for his College,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Ticknor had an enormous private library, but he was also Smith Professor of French and Spanish Languages and Literature at Harvard University 1817&#8211;1835.</note>) &amp; all he had to do according to his instructions would be to get them on shore &amp; transmit them to me, merely repacking them after they had been opened at the Custom House, &#8211; <del>The duty</del> if they went there. The duty would be the veryest trifle, which <ref type="m" target="people.html#TicknorGeorge">T.</ref> would in all likelihood order to be charged to his account. It is very possible that they may be on the road to me from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> was to have written to me on his arrival in town. I am rather uneasy at not hearing from him, &amp; the more so as you do not mention having seen him since I know it was his intention to have written on Monday last, &amp; to have seen you before he wrote. He seemed to enjoy his visit,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> &amp; we heartily enjoyed his company.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am not sure whether I told you of Charles Henrys<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. The accident occurred on 2 August 1822 and was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming him): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta.</note> accident, a dreadful fracture of the scull by the bursting of a cannon. For a full month the brain continued to protrude through the fracture &#8211; like a large egg, part indeed was knocked out, &#8211; a part came away for a long time with the dressings. It is just five weeks since the accident happened, &#8211; to day he was to go up stairs into the drawing room, &amp; it is expected that in ten days more, if all goes on as it has hitherto done, that the wound will be closed &#8211; a recovery all but miraculous</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The General</ref> had as narrow an escape himself on Tuesday last, but of a less tragical kind. Sir Fred. Morshead<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Frederick Treise Morshead, 2nd Baronet (1783&#8211;1828), lived at Derwent Lodge, Keswick.</note> gave him a little boat which only holds one person, &amp; is corked<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The boat was lined with cork to aid buoyancy.</note> for the sake of lessening that persons danger. <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The General</ref> took advantage of a rough day to circumnavigate <hi rend="ital">Shirt</hi> Island<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A family nickname for one of the islands in Derwentwater.</note> in this cockle shell rain came on with the wind when he was about half way on his return &#8211; he hoisted an umbrella, &amp; in endeavouring to save that when it was caught by the wind, upset the boat. Having done this the wisest man could not have behaved with more compleat presence of mind, he swam to the boat, &amp; contrived to turn it up, &#8211; but it was then more than half full of water, &amp; there was no possibility of getting into it, without its upsetting again. So he laid hold, &amp; holloaed long &amp; lustily for help. They heard him at the island,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Derwent Island, where Peachy lived.</note> &#8211; &amp; three men not one of whom could swim rowed out to him in his own little boat, &#8211; which as you know, ought not in rough weather to carry more than two. It did not do to send them back for the larger boat, &#8211; which was on the other side the water at the time, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">the General</ref> knew that he could not get into this; so he ordered them to fasten the chain to the cockle-shell, &amp; take it in tow, &amp; him at the stern of it, &#8211; &amp; in this way was he towed at the tail of the second boat to his own island, where he came in, in high glee, holding on with one hand, &amp; waving his hat with the other. If the upset had happened out of hearing, or if the wind had set the other way so as to have <del>disperse</del> lost his voice, it might very easily have cost his life, he had on a heavy great coat, which assisted in buoying him, but would soon have acted very differently.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I tell him he should have a picture painted of this adventure &amp; also that <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">Mrs P.</ref> should insist upon his chusing whether to wear a cork waistcoat, or a straight one &#8211; <note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Cork waistcoats were early lifejackets; straitjackets were used to constrain those confined in lunatic asylums.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent1">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">I wanted to consult you about <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert.</ref> He appears in excellent health &amp; spirits, &#8211; but his tongue is always foul in the morning, &amp; he is always hotter than he ought to be, during the night. &#8211; Should I give him small does of calomel?<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Mercury chloride, used as a purgative.</note> I can <del>detect no</del> discover no cause for this. He eats plenty of ripe fruit, &amp; his digestion goes on regularly &amp; well: but there must be something amiss.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>