<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3896Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3896Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3896" type="letter">
        <head>3896. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1822-09-13">13 September 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ Hale/ near Downton/ Wilts<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 16 SE 16/ 1822<lb />
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 228. 1822/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 13<lb />
               September/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 22<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Novem<hi rend="sup">r</hi>:<lb />
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 195&#8211;197.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-09-13">13 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I was truly rejoiced to receive your letter from London, both for the tidings which it contained of your last communications from the Rio, &amp; because it assured me of your safe arrival.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), had visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822. May was deeply concerned about the fate of his business transactions in Rio de Janeiro.</note> The contents of your former letter, upon mature consideration I did not think proper to impart to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridge</ref>, because the total silence upon the subject which she had maintained towards <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">her sister</ref> &amp; me, &amp; which <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> also maintained towards <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">her cousin</ref>, implied either a want of confidence where confidence ought to have been placed, or a sense of impropriety in the affair; &amp; also because no communication was necessary, the attachment having to all appearance been dismissed as lightly as it was established.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">During their visit, the younger John May had become infatuated with Sara Coleridge; however, she seems to have taken the matter lightly.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The influx of visitors has not abated yet. Almost every day brings somebody. I have however found time to get thro half a paper for the Q Review, &amp; it will be sent off by this nights post to be set up by the printer while the other half is preparing.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s next article published in the <title>Quarterly Review</title> was his review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> When a guest leaves me I relapse into habitual inaction; my farthest walks since your departure, have been to the How on one side, &amp; to Castlet on the other. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your goddaughter</ref> &amp; I reached the latter point this morning, &amp; sate there about half an hour enjoying a most delightful autumnal day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The youth at the island is going on well;<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. The accident occurred on 2 August 1822 and was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming him): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta.</note> &#8211; so well indeed that when <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">the General</ref> returns from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Netherhall">Netherhall</ref> I shall remind that it will be proper to return thanks for his recovery, &#8211; prayers having been put &lt;up&gt; for it. <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The General</ref> himself has had an adventure <hi rend="ital">in</hi> the Lake which I will not repeat because you will hear it from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> whenever you see him. The weather has been very stormy, &amp; with much rain; &#8211; the other morning <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupin</ref> heard there was like to be a flood, &amp; immediately said that he would get out his Noahs Ark. &#8211; I hear him now on the way to give me the good-night kiss.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will be glad to hear that your visit compleated what <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoots</ref> had begun; &amp; that in consequence of the exercise which I took with him first &amp; immediately afterwards with you, I am in better bodily condition than I had been for twenty months before, &#8211; being indeed for the present a sound man. But I hardly can hope this will last till I take my journey to the south.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I look back upon your visit with great satisfaction, &#8211; &amp; this more so because I look forward with some confidence to another, at no long interval. This is the sort of intercourse which I desire with those whom I love &amp; esteem; &amp; one thing which endears this place of abode to me is that I enjoy more of it here than I should be likely to do any where else. I should see you, for instance much more frequently, if I lived near London; &#8211; but in twenty years I should not see so much of you as by having you two or three weeks under my roof.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> &#8211; I must not forget to deliver a message from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Locker</ref>, &#8211; that he shall be very glad to show you Greenwich Hospital, &#8211; as a means of becoming better acquainted with you; &#8211; &amp; that he would have said this himself if he had known you were about to depart when he saw you last.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now concerning the QR. Few things would give me more pleasure than to see it in <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridges</ref> hands, because I am assured it would be to the national good, &amp; to his individual comfort &amp; advantage. I have already mentioned it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref>, who is in <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> confidence, &#8211; &amp; I now close the letter in order to mention it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> himself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Kindest remembrances from all. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MaySusannah">Mrs May</ref> I trust will compleat her recovery at Hale<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Hale Park, near Fordingbridge, Hampshire, the home of John May&#8217;s older brother, Joseph May (1768&#8211;1830).</note> &#8212;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">God bless you my dear friend &#8211;</salute>
          <salute rend="indent4">  Yours affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>