<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3897Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3897Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3897" type="letter">
        <head>3897. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1822-09-16">16 September 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] Epsom Nineteenth Sept<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.1822/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>./ Nicholas Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devon/ Free/ JRickman<lb />
               Stamped: EPSOM/ 79<lb />
               Postmark: FREE/ 20 SP 20/ 1822<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 122&#8211;124 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-09-16">16 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I am sure it will give you pleasure to hear that young Henry is now considered fairly out of danger.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. The accident occurred on 2 August 1822 and was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming him): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta.</note> The wound is rapidly closing, &amp; he has been out of doors. Seldom I believe has there been a more providential recovery. The eye which there was great reason to apprehend he would never be able to open, is safe: &amp; he is likely to suffer no other inconvenience than that of wearing a plate upon the forehead to protect the place of the fracture. Had the hot weather which we had about three weeks ago occurred immediately after the accident it is hardly possible that he could have lived thro it. It remains to be seen whether this merciful deliverance will have any effect upon his conduct in after life. Were I his parent I should endeavor to make him profit by it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The General</ref> himself has lately had a narrow tho ludicrous escape. He upset himself with an umbrella in a little skiff which Sir Fred: Morshead<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Frederick Treise Morshead, 2nd Baronet (1783&#8211;1828), lived at Derwent Lodge, Keswick.</note> had given him. It was within hearing of his own island; &#8211; the skiff was corked<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The boat was lined with cork to aid buoyancy.</note> so that it could not sink, but being half full of water after he had righted it, it was not possible for him to get in, &amp; he being well buttoned up against a stormy day in a thick great coat, was in no plight for swimming, so he held on, &amp; holloaed stoutly for assistance. His two men hastened off in his little boat, the large one happening to be on the opposite shore. <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">The General</ref> had presence of mind enough to consider that if he attempted to get into this little boat he should in all likelihood pull her under water, &amp; that neither of the men could swim; he therefore very coolly directed them to take the rope of the skiff &amp; tow it to the island, with him at the end; &#8211; &amp; in this way he came in, like a Triton,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Triton was a Greek sea god, with the upper body of a man and the tail and fins of a fish.</note> waving his hat round his head &amp; huzzaing as he approached his own shores &#8211; I ought to have told you that there came an invitation from him for you to dinner the day after your departure.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> left me this day fortnight,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August&#8211;2 September 1822.</note> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BellAndrew">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Bell</ref> departed some days after him. The exercise which I took with him compleated the good work which was begun with you, &amp; has left me in a better state than I had been in for the two last years. By way of keeping it up while the season permits (nothing being so salutary to me as vigorous exercise) I went up Skiddaw Dod this morning, &#8211; one of the expeditions which is reserved for your next visit. On my return I found a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother Henry</ref> saying he shall be here on Wednesday. This will give me ten days more of laking &amp; mountaineering, if the weather permit</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The temptation which this country holds out to that exercise which is peculiarly necessary for me must be weighed among the many reasons for remaining in it. For with my sedentary habits &amp; inactive inclinations I require <del>all</del>
          <del>the</del> &lt;every&gt; inducement<del>s</del> to draw me out. But whether I remain or remove, I shall see you, my dear Lightfoot, ofte[MS missing] &amp; often (God willing) both in Devonshire, &amp; wherever I may be. I shall certainly come down to you when next I visit London, which will probably be in February or March.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not actually leave home until 3 November 1823.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My young ones thank God, are all well. They often talk of you, &amp; place you very high in their list of favourites. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> pays a visit in the winter with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref>, to her Durham &amp; Yorkshire friends, &#8211; I think therefore she will hardly go to the south with me; &#8211; otherwise I should gladly bring her to Crediton.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">During the little time which I have had for business I have written about half a paper for the Quarterly, upon a History of the Religious Sects of the last Century by the Ex-Bishop Gregoire,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Unusually, Gr&#233;goire was both a devout Catholic and a supporter of the French Revolution, serving as Bishop of Blois 1791&#8211;1801.</note> &#8211; the book is curious for its strange mixture of revolutionary feelings with Catholic bigotry, and for the <del>history</del> &lt;account&gt; which it gives of irreligion in France. It gives me matter for an interesting paper, to be wound up with some seasonable observations upon the progress of infidelity at home.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Lightfoot. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S</ref> &amp; her sisters<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> &#8211; &amp; the girls<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref> and their cousin <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara Coleridge</ref>.</note> join in the kindest remembrances. Present my best wishes to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> L. &amp; to all your children,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768&#8211;1856) on 13 July 1801. Their children were: John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806&#8211;1882), Southey&#8217;s god-daughter; Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808&#8211;1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810&#8211;1889); Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811&#8211;1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846&#8211;1855, Rector of Islip 1855&#8211;1881.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> who has just come in to give me hid good-night kiss, &#8211; has given me an additional one to send to you, &#8211; he is thank God in high health as well as in high glee -</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yrs affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>