<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3907Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3907Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3907" type="letter">
        <head>3907. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1822-10-14">14 October 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmarks: 10 o&#8217;Clock/ OC 17/ 1822 FN<hi rend="sup">n</hi>; E/ 17 OC 17/ 1822<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 222. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 333&#8211;335 [in part].</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">B. Frere</ref> has sent me a box full of <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereJohnHookham">his brothers</ref> papers, &#8211; I have as many bundles fastened with red tape before me, as if I were at the head of a public office, &amp; am a great deal busier with them than if I were paid two or three thousand a year for my work. These papers will carry on my narrative<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">For Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> very satisfactorily to the time when those which I had from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M Wellesley</ref> begin. But I shall very likely spring some other mines when I come to town.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#InglisSirRobert">Sir Robert Inglis</ref> has given me the first &amp; third volume of the Chronicas de la Provincia de Rel. Desc. Da S Francisco en las Islas Philipinas, China, Japon &amp;c<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Francisco de San Antonio (1682&#8211;1744), <title>Chronicas de la Apostolica Provincia de S. Gregorio de Religiosos Descalzos de N. S. P. S. Francisco en las Islas Philipinas, China, Japon &amp;c</title> (1738&#8211;1744), no. 3569 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; printed in their Convent at Manila from whence this imperfect set was brought by some curioso in Sir W Drapers<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant General Sir William Draper (1721&#8211;1787; <title>DNB</title>). He commanded the expedition that captured Manila in 1762, at the end of the Seven Years War.</note> expedition. <ref type="m" target="people.html#InglisSirRobert">Sir R.</ref> purchased them the other day at the sale of a relations books.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> The first vol. contains a fuller description of the Philippines than I have seen in any other work. There is a great deal of curious matter in the book, &#8211; as indeed there is in almost all books of this kind. The good matter is mingled in them as it is in our county histories, &#8211; &amp; the rubbish is better worth raking.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have also added to my stores the two volumes of the earlier Edda published at Copenhagen in 1784 &amp; 1818<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Edda Saemundar hinns Froda. Edda Rhythmica seu Antiquor, Vulgo Saemundina Dicta</title> (1787&#8211;1818), no. 918 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. He never acquired the third volume, published in 1828.</note> &#8211; a third is soon expected to compleat the work. Were it only for its copious glossaries it would be exceedingly curious, but the poems themselves are of the most curious kind. At the same time I obtained a Bibliotheca Danica<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Jens Edvard Kraft (1784&#8211;1853) and Rasmus Nyerup (1759&#8211;1829), <title>Almendeligt Litteraturlexicon for Danmark, Norge og Island</title> (1820), no. 1407 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; I wish it had included Swedish as well as Norwegian &amp; <del>Islandic</del> &lt;Icelandic&gt; authors.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Like you, it is not often that I meet with any one who can enter into my pursuits. People come to look at me as a live poet, little thinking how compleatly I have ceased to exist as such, &amp; that I have as little inclination to write verses, as to play at pottle<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Pottle was a simple card game.</note> or whip a top. Now that I am left to myself &amp; to my ordinary <del>xxxx</del> habits, I take every night after supper with my blackcurrant rum (thanks be to your friend Hoblyn<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Hoblyn (1751&#8211;1839). He was a Christ Church contemporary of Herbert Hill (matriculated 1768, BA 1771) and inherited Nanswhyden House, where Southey and Hill stayed in November 1795 on their way to Falmouth to take ship for Spain.</note> for introducing me to that <del>xxx</del> admirable tincture!) &#8211; a composing dose of Dutch looking thro the huge work of Aitzema,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieuwe van Aitzema (1600&#8211;1669), <title>Sakem van Staet en Oorlogh in emde Omtrent de Vereenigde Nederlanden</title> (1655&#8211;1671), with the continuation by Lambert van den Bos (1610&#8211;1698) of 1685&#8211;1699, and Aitzema&#8217;s <title>Verhael van de Nederlansche Vrede-Handeling</title> (1671), no. 214 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> from which I shall make no inconsiderable gleanings. It is an invaluable repository of facts for the greater part of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century; &amp; a great deal which it contains is not to be found elsewhere.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The other day I finished the Life of Philippes de Mornay,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Philippe de Mornay, Seigneur du Plessy Marly (1549&#8211;1623), <title>Histoire de la Vie de Messire Philippes de Mornay, Seigneur de Plessis Marly &amp;c</title> (1647), no. 1892 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> better known among us by that name, than by his title of Du Plessis. The book is heavy, but it shows how much intrigue was mixed up with the affairs of the Hugonots, &#8211; &amp; Du Plessis himself seems to have been a perfect example of integrity. &#8211; When I come to you in the spring I shall set upon your Sully.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Maximilien de Bethune, Duke of Sully (1560&#8211;1641), <title>Memoires des Sages et Royales Oeconomies d&#8217;Estat Domestiques, Politiques et Militaires de Henry le Grand, l&#8217;Examplaire des Roys, le Prince des Vertus, des Armes &amp; des Loix &amp; le Pere en Effet de ses Peuples Francois</title> (1638), no. 2664 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> By that time I shall have pretty nearly finished the earlier Memoirs as far as my set goes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have written to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">the Marquis</ref>, &amp; made my excuses for not having done so sooner. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Doctor</ref> left me with heavy arrears of correspondence, &amp; business of every kind. I have worked steadily since his departure &#8211; but it was too late for the Q.R. &amp; there will be nothing of mine in the next number.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), published 23 October 1822. It did not contain an article by Southey, who had been working on his review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Between ourselves that journal will be in great danger, whenever <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> drops it, or drops off. It has got itself into deserved disgrace by its silence &lt;&amp; its notice&gt; concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>;<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Murray was the publisher of both Byron and the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. The forthcoming review of Byron&#8217;s <title>Marino Faliero, Doge of Venice. An Historical Tragedy, in Five Acts. With Notes. The Prophecy of Dante, a Poem</title> (1821) and <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy, Cain, A Mystery</title> (1821) by Reginald Heber, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 476&#8211;524, published 23 October 1822, was not the swingeing condemnation that Southey would have liked.</note> &amp; many persons are offended as you &amp; I have been, by its irritating papers concerning America,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Hostility to the United States was a consistent feature of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. See, for example, the review of Henry Bradshaw Fearon (c. 1793&#8211;1842), <title>Sketches of America. A Narrative of a Journey of Five Thousand Miles Through the Eastern and Western States of America</title> (1818), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 124&#8211;167, by Sir John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; [MS obscured]per of its criticism. A New Quarterly has been thought of &amp; if an unfit person were to succeed <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, &#8211; or if his successor were to commit the same faults, &#8211; I have no doubt it would be started. If I would undertake the management, a bookseller of sufficient capital would move into the West end of the town from the city, (Mawman<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Mawman (1759&#8211;1827), bookseller and author from York, who became a well-known London publisher. His firm was based in the City of London, rather than the West End, like Murray. The proposal for a rival journal to the <title>Quarterly Review</title> did not materialise.</note> is the man) secure to me 500&#163; a year, give me half the profits above that sum, whatever they might be, &amp; vest the copyright in me; &#8211; &amp; coadjutors enough are ready to bear a part. This has been intimated to me, for my consideration. I am not inclined to make so great a sacrifice of worthier pursuits, as would be required; &#8211; &amp; would much rather see the existing QR in the hands of an editor who would make it what it ought to be.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &#8211; God bless you</p>
        <closer>
          <signed> rend="indent3"&gt;RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-10-14">14 Oct. 1822.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>