<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3910Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3910Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3910" type="letter">
        <head>3910. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1822-10-30">30 October 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 2 NO 2/ 1822<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 124&#8211;126 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-10-30">30 Oct. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> As soon as you departed I settled regularly to my habitual course of life which had been so much to my benefit broken up thro the summer. At the same time, I very dutifully began to observe your directions, &amp; have walked every day with the exception of one stormy one long enough &amp; far enough to require rubbing down. This is against the grain but I feel how beneficial it is, &amp; therefore do not grumble.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I finished a paper for the QR<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), published 15 February 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; the first part of which I think you saw, &#8211; &amp; the second detachment of proofs is now on the table. Something also has been done to the Book of the Church<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> &#8211; a portion of copy will be ready for the next post. But my main employment has been upon a box of papers from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Bart. Frere</ref>, about half which I have gone thro extracting as I go.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Used in Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> They are very interesting, &amp; will give me all the information I need down to the time when Sydenhams collection<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Benjamin Sydenham (1777&#8211;1828), a soldier in India, friend of Marquess Wellesley and Commissioner of the Board of Excise 1809&#8211;1819, had sent Southey the papers of his brother, Thomas Sydenham (1780&#8211;1816), who had served in Spain 1811&#8211;1812 before becoming Minister Plenipotentiary at Lisbon 1814&#8211;1816.</note>
          <del>xx</del> begins. I have worked, &amp; am working at them, with great perseverance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The American books have arrived<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been sent a consignment of books by George Ticknor.</note> &amp; I am reading with much interest Dwights Travels<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824.</note> in his own country &#8211; a posthumous work. The author (whose unhappy name is Timothy) wrote in his youth some forty years ago an heroic poem upon the Conquest of Canaan,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight, <title>The Conquest of Canaan</title> (1785). The book was reprinted in London by Joseph Johnson (1738&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>) in 1788.</note> which was puffed &amp; reprinted in London. Its stilted versification was admired in those days but it had little or no real merit. Dwight however tho a bad poet, &#8211; because of a bad school,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In heroic couplets, Dwight&#8217;s poem was much influenced by John Dryden (1631&#8211;1700; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Works of Virgil: Containing his Pastorals, Georgics and Aeneis: Adorn&#8217;d with a Hundred Sculptures, Translated into English Verse by Mr Dryden</title> (1697).</note> &#8211; was a sensible man, &amp; he kept a journal of his <del>jourxx</del> travels &amp; prepared it for publication from a conviction that a faithful description of New England in all its parts such as it then was would in a few generations become exceedingly interesting, how unimportant it might appear if published as soon as it was written. A great deal of course is only interesting locally, but on the whole the picture of what the country is, his fair views of the state of society there, with its advantages &amp; disadvantages, &amp; the number of curious facts which are brought together make it very well worth reading. I would give a good deal to see as trustworthy &amp; minute an account of the Southern States. &#8211; This is just the sort of <del>xx</del> book which might be digested into a review.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The QR. will not do itself any good by the mealy-mouthed manner in which it has <del>set xxx</del> dealt with <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The review of Byron&#8217;s <title>Marino Faliero, Doge of Venice. An Historical Tragedy, in Five Acts. With Notes. The Prophecy of Dante, a Poem</title> (1821) and <title>Sardanapulus, A Tragedy. The Two Foscari, A Tragedy, Cain, A Mystery</title> (1821) by Reginald Heber, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 476&#8211;524, was not the swingeing condemnation that Southey would have liked.</note> The excuse for its previous silence is wretched, &amp; to preach a sermon in refutation of so silly a piece of sophistry as Cain is pityful indeed.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 476&#8211;477, provided a list of reasons why the journal had not reviewed Byron&#8217;s recent work, including: &#8216;the conflict of admiration and regret&#8217; over Byron&#8217;s talents and the immorality of his poems; the &#8216;little effect which our advice had, on former occasions, produced&#8217;; and the belief that Byron could only interpret the <title>Quarterly</title>&#8217;s silence as &#8216;an appeal, of not the least impressive kind&#8217; to repent. The fact that Murray was the publisher of both Byron and the <title>Quarterly Review</title> was not mentioned. The article (pp. 514&#8211;524) defended orthodox Christianity against the arguments put forward by the characters in Byron&#8217;s <title>Cain</title>, especially on the issue of the compatibility of a supreme deity with the existence of evil.</note> &#8211; To crown all while they are treating <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref> with so much respect &amp; congratulating themselves on the improved morality of his productions<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 477: &#8216;Whatever may be the other merits of his tragedies, on the score of morals they are unimpeachable.&#8217;</note> &#8211; out comes &#8220;the Liberal&#8221;.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron&#8217;s <title>The Vision of Judgment</title> (1822), a parody of Southey&#8217;s <title>A Vision of Judgement </title>(1821), was first published in the <title>Liberal</title>, 1 (October 1822), 3&#8211;39.</note> I have only seen some newspaper extracts<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Leeds Intelligencer and Yorkshire General Advertiser</title>, 21 October 1822, which had been sent to Southey.</note> from this journal, among them the description of myself. He may go with such satire till his heart aches, before he can excite in me one uncomfortable emotion. In warring with him I have as much advantage in my temper as Orlando had in his invulnerable hide.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Matteo Boiardo (1440&#8211;1494), <title>Orlando Innamorato</title> (1495). The eponymous hero had an invulnerable skin.</note> But there is no necessity for striking a blow at one who has so compleatly damned himself. I wish the Liberals joy of their journal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Do not forget to arrange for the transmission of my cyder from Liverpool, &amp; as soon as you have done this &amp; let me know to whose care it should be directed there. I will write to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> &amp; have it sent off. I should like a glass of it at this moment.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I shall be glad to hear a good account of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">Louisa</ref> &amp; also of your own domiciliary arrangements. This reminds me of a certain letter which it is time that I should write &amp; which therefore shall no longer be delayed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We are all well thank God. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> had her head shaved on Monday.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly a treatment for head lice.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> talks very absurdly about <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">his wife</ref>, he <del>xxx</del> says she has never recovered &#8211; Miss Wilbraham,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Laetitia Wilbraham (1799&#8211;1874), Tom Southey&#8217;s lodger. She had just married Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777&#8211;1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. Fryer was a surveyor, geologist and mining engineer who spent part of each year at Keswick. At this time he was renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick.</note> &amp; that she repents ever having had her under their roof. &#8211; If this sort of language lessened ones anxiety about them as much as it does ones sympathy, it were well.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Love from all:<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">  God bless you<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>