<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3911</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3911Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3911" type="letter">
        <head>3911. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>], <date when="1822-11-01">1 November [1822]</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: [deletion and correction in another hand] &lt;1 Nov&gt; <del>July</del> 1822/ Robert Southey<lb />
               MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 238&#8211;239.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> The mistake concerning the two sheets which I now return, may very possibly have been this, that when they were sent me a second time, I supposed them to be <hi rend="ital">clean sheets</hi>, &amp; laid them aside accordingly.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of Southey&#8217;s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note>
          <hi rend="ital">Three</hi> such sheets, I have with their correspondent proofs; &#8211; please to send me the others which have been struck off, that I may have them at hand to refer to.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Herewith you have a farther portion of copy. I am steadily proceeding with it, &amp; shall go on without interruption till it is compleated.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> When do you publish the first vol. of the Peninsular War?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note>
          <del>I ha</del> Let me know, because I have some letters to write with it. I am working at those papers from <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Mr B. Frere</ref> which you sent me, &amp; have worked two or three hours every day since they arrived. As soon as I have got thro them we may go to press with the second volume. They bring me down most satisfactorily to the time when the papers which I obtained from another quarter commence. Some time ago I requested you to procure a &#8220;History of the War in Catalonia,&#8221; &amp; also &#8220;Anecdotes of Chiefs employed in the Catalonian War&#8221;, by Francisco de Olivarez, both in Spanish &#8211; printed at Seville.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. This had mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877.</note> You may easily have overlooked this in the multiplicity of your concerns, &#8211; but you will see how <hi rend="ital">necessary</hi> it is that I should have them, &#8211; the author being himself a Catalan, &amp; having served actively in that province.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your last number has some very good papers, the second is that which pleases me best.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Francis Palgrave&#8217;s review of the first volume of Lewis Cottingham (1787&#8211;1847), <title>Plans, Elevations, Sections, Details and Views of the Magnificent Chapel of King Henry VII at Westminster Abbey Church, with a History of its Foundation &amp;c</title> (1822&#8211;1829), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 308&#8211;336, published 23 October 1822.</note> The 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is an important one,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Major George Procter (1795&#8211;1842), Adjutant and Superintendent of Studies at the Royal Military College at Sandhurst, reviewed a number of books on the war of 1812 in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (July 1822), 405&#8211;449, published 23 October 1822.</note> &amp; has very little of that tone respecting America which has given so much offence. I very much regret that that tone was ever taken. It gives great pain to those Americans who are friendly to England, &#8211; alienates some of them, &amp; produces nothing but mischief, without the possibility of its doing any good. I am at this time reading a new American work (D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dwights Travels in New England &amp; New York)<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824.</note> from which I could make an exceedingly interesting paper, were it not <del>for</del> that the spirit in which I should write would form such a total contrast to that of the<del>se</del> unlucky articles which have preceded it:<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Croker and Sir John Barrow (1764&#8211;1848; <title>DNB</title>), two of the <title>Quarterly Review</title>&#8217;s most regular and important contributors, were both hostile to America; see, for instance, Barrow&#8217;s article, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 124&#8211;167.</note> The work is in four octavo volumes containing as much as so many English quartos There are not many readers who would go thro it with as much patience &amp; pleasure as I am doing. But it contains a compleat view of society in that country, &amp; a great number of curious facts, &#8211; &amp; the facts as well as the opinions of the author all come in aid of those principles &amp; institutions, &#8211; which, God knows, stand in need at this time of all the aid that can be found for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am grieved to hear of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> state. When he <del>hints to me</del> said to me that he feared he should soon become unable to conduct the Review, &amp; knew not where to look for a successor, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> occurred to me as a person in whom all the main requisites were to be found, &#8211; acquirements, talents, discretion, sound judgement, &amp; a character upon which the most entire reliance may be placed. &#8211; Your interests, &amp; those of the country, could not be in safer hands, &#8211; &amp; both are seriously concerned in the decision.</p>
        <p>
          farewell my dear Sir &amp; believe me<lb/>
          yours faithfully<lb/>
           Robert Southey.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-11-01"> Nov. 1.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">I am desired to request that you will send a copy of Dobrizhoffer<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge, <title>An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822), a translation of Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus Equistri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 844 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontLadyMargaret">Lady Beaumont</ref> (Grosvenor Square) &#8211; <del>with</del> from <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">the Translator</ref>. The Translator herself will be in London shortly.</p>
          <p rend="indent1"> I have not had N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 53.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), published 4 July 1822.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>