<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3913Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3913Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3913" type="letter">
        <head>3913. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1822-11-02">2 November 1822</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 2p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 342&#8211;343.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Who should succeed <ref type="m" target="people.html#LiverpoolLord">Lord Liverpool</ref>, if he were about to retire, would be to me a matter of less interest than who shall succeed poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> as the Editor of the Q. R. in case of his death, or of his inability to continue in that office. The latter probability he mentioned to me some weeks ago, &amp; likewise how totally at a loss he was where to look for one who might supply his place. I mentioned <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> to him, &#8211; &amp; have mentioned him to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> also.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to [John Murray], 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note> &#8211; I have some reason to think that <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> inclines to my opinion, for he has had a conversation with him upon the difficulties of an Editors task &amp;c, &amp; tho he said nothing which in any way committed himself, yet he would not have entered <hi rend="ital">upon</hi> that subject, &amp; <hi rend="ital">into it</hi> as he did, <del>unless he</del> if my suggestion had been totally dismissed. One thing which he said was that his successor must be a man in whom the Government could feel confidence, because of the assistance which they afforded in the way of documents from the public offices. And this leads me to mention the subject to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> There is no question about his abilities, acquirements habits &amp; principles. But he possesses in an eminent degree discretion, a sound judgement, &amp; a right feeling. I am sure he would never admit any thing which should lower the review, &#8211; nothing of that mere insolence which has so often disgraced it, &amp; brought it down to the level of the Edinburgh.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Edinburgh Review</title> (1802&#8211;1929), the main Whig quarterly journal.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The choice is a matter of more consequence than <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is aware of. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is very much disliked by the <hi rend="ital">trade</hi>. They would delight in injuring him, &amp; (this is between ourselves) the project of starting a New Quarterly upon the same principles, has been thought of.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">This proposal came from Joseph Mawman (1759&#8211;1827), bookseller and author from York, who became a well-known London publisher. His firm was based in the City of London. Mawman had proposed to set up a rival journal to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, edited by Southey, though this project did not materialise.</note> I do not wish to see this <del>xxx</del> because it would weaken the effect which the Q. now produces, &amp; it is better to have one efficient journal of this kind, than to divide its power. But if it were made unexceptionable in its tone &amp; temper &amp; consistent in its views, I am sure its influence would be greatly increased.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  For myself it would be a great satisfaction to have an Editor who would not mutilate my papers without consulting me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">But I must conclude. I have said this to you, that you may know what my wishes are upon the subject, &#8211; which tho not a matter of state, is one which no doubt you will hear talked of, &amp; in which very possibly your opinion may have some weight</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1822-11-02">Nov 2. 1822</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>