<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3914" type="letter"><head>3914. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1822-11-03">3 November 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS to JR 3 Nov/ 1822<lb/>
               MS: Huntington Library, RS 426. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 343–344.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><date when="1822-11-03">Nov. 3. 1822</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear R</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">My mornings for the last three weeks have been pretty closely employed upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Frere’s</ref> papers which will occupy a fortnight yet before I shall have got thro them.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was studying these papers for his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823–1832).</note> They gave me all the information of which I was in want for that stage of the war in which my materials were most defective.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> life is so precarious at this time, &#38; the probability of his being unable to conduct the QR. even if he recovers, so great, that the question of <hi rend="ital">succession</hi> becomes <del>one</del> of some interest to me. I wish <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> to be the Editor, being a man who unites in himself all the requisites, &#38; with whom I could act cordially. Unless I am very much mistaken, the character of the Journal would be raised, &#38; its influence greatly increased, by the firm &#38; consistent language which it would hold under his management, &#38; the utter exclusion of such splenetic effusions as often disgrace it now.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">“The Liberal,” is quite what it ought to be.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Byron’s <title>The Vision of Judgment</title> (1822), a parody of Southey’s <title>A Vision of Judgement</title> (1821), was published by John Hunt (1775–1848; <title>DNB</title>), brother of Leigh Hunt, in <title>The Liberal</title>, 1 (October 1822), 3–39. There were only four issues of <title>The Liberal</title>.</note> If I hated <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref> as deeply as he does me, I could not wish it to be worse. It cannot, I think, reach a <hi rend="ital">third</hi> number, even if it proceeds to a second, &#38; escapes prosecution. They must be thorough-paced Whigs indeed for whom it is not too bad, – &#38; moreover <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">his Lordship</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HuntLeigh">Leigh Hunt</ref> will quarrel ere long &#38; break up the infernal firm.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">We are going on well thank God. Since <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother</ref> left me I have settled regularly to my winter occupations, &#38; as regularly taken the daily exercise which he prescribed. A summers mountaineering has been of the greatest benefit to me, &#38; I hope to keep in the same good condition, till you see me early in the spring.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Remember us most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">Mrs R.</ref></p>
            <closer>  <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
           <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
