<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3915</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3915Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3915" type="letter">
        <head>3915. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1822-11-12">8&#8211;12 November 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] London Fifteenth Nov<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.1822/ Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>./ N Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devon/ Free/ JRickman<lb />
               Postmark: [partial] &#8211; FREE/ 1x NO 1x/ 18<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 126&#8211;128 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-11-08">8 Nov. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear Lightfoot</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> By <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother Henrys</ref> means I have found how the impediment between me &amp; your cyder may be removed, if you will direct it for me, to the care of George Sealy Esq<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">George Sealy (1781&#8211;1843) of the merchant firm Sealy, Duncan, Walker &amp; Co. Southey had met him in Portugal in 1800&#8211;1801. He was the brother of Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s first wife.</note> Liverpool, &amp; ship it for that place, &#8211; letting me know by what vessel it is sent, he will look after it there, &amp; forward it to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &amp; then we will all drink your health in the juice of the apple. It will need a case to protect it on the way from a gimlet.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">There is little chance of any circumstance drawing me from this country to reside in the vicinity of London &#8211; at least I can forsee none. The question whether or not the Quarterly Review should do so has been fairly considered &amp; decided in consequence of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> dangerous illness. He had written to me soon after you left us, saying that he could not long continue to conduct the Review &amp; that he knew not where to look for a successor. He was not ill at the time; &amp; therefore my consideration of the matter was not hastily but deliberately made. If I had chosen to propose myself, the office must have been mine, of course. The objections to it were, that the increased expenditure which I must incur near London, would fully consume any <del>advantage</del> increase of income which I should have obtained; &amp; therefore the time consumed in the mere management of the journal, would have been a dead loss. This time would be unpleasantly as well as unprofitably spent, in corresponding upon the mere business of the review, examining communications, &amp; either correcting them myself when there was any thing erroneous, imprudent, or inconsistent with those coherent opinions which the journal should have maintained under my care, &#8211; in persuading the respective writers to amend &amp; alter according to that standard. Lastly it seemed that there was nothing <del>in</del>
          <del>the</del>
          <del>change of</del> which could recompense me for the sacrifice which it needs would be to quit a country in which I take so much delight, &amp; of which all my family are as fond as myself: &amp; there was this weightier consideration that if I gave up the quantity of time which the management of such a journal requires, it would take away all reasonable hope of my compleating the various great works<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In particular, Southey&#8217;s &#8216;History of Portugal&#8217;, which was never finished.</note> for which I have been so long making preparations</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I talked this matter over with <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, who entered entirely into my feelings. The next point having fully made up my mind concerning myself, was to secure the succession (as far as my influences extended) for some person with whom I could freely &amp; heartily cooperate. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> is just such a person: &amp; having ascertained that he would like the <del>xxxx</del> situation, I mentioned him to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Giffords</ref> illness has occurred since, he is better at present, &#8211; &amp; I have good reason to believe it is all but settled that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> is to become the Editor of the Q.R. Without taking him from his profession, it will render him independent of it, &amp; place him at once in a high &amp; important station</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#CoplestonEdward">Copplestone</ref> had proposed Wheatley of Oriel,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard Whately (1787&#8211;1863; <title>DNB</title>), a Fellow of Oriel College, Oxford, 1811&#8211;1821, clergyman and later Archbishop of Dublin 1831&#8211;1863. He was also at this time a private tutor and a writer on a wide variety of subjects, including for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> whom <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> considered quite out of the question. Mitchell<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Mitchell (1783&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), a classical scholar and translator of <title>The Comedies of Aristophanes</title> (1820&#8211;1822). Aristophanes (c. 446&#8211;386 BC) was an Athenian comic playwright.</note> the translator of Aristophanes, &amp; author of many good papers in the Review concerning the Greeks, was <hi rend="ital">talked</hi> of, &amp; so was a M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gregson,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Nobody of this name had contributed articles to the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. This possibly refers to Matthew Gregson (1749&#8211;1824; <title>DNB</title>), a wealthy Liverpool antiquarian and compiler of <title>Portfolio of Fragments Relative to the History and Antiquities of the County Palatine and Duchy of Lancaster</title> (1817). He was a regular contributor to the <title>Gentleman&#8217;s Magazine</title> and to charities in Liverpool, where Canning was one of the local MPs.</note> who is a friend of <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge">Cannings</ref> &amp; an able man: but they were not <hi rend="ital">thought</hi> of. Both <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> were compleatly at a loss where to look, for it is a situation of great confidence, &amp; requiring great discretion, as well as the necessary talents &amp; attainments. It would be very difficult to find a person so qualified as <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">J.C.</ref> &amp; I trust that I have done good service to the public as well as to the publisher &amp; to him, in putting the matter in its present train</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is a long explanation, &amp; yet I think you will like to know the <hi rend="ital">how</hi> &amp; the <hi rend="ital">why</hi> of my proceedings. In consequence I may possibly take more part in the review &amp; certainly more interest in it: because knowing the tenour of his <del>mind</del> &lt;opinions&gt;, &amp; his way of thinking, I am sure he will admit nothing that either in matter or manner could offend a well-regulated mind. He will hold a manly &amp; straight-forward course, &amp; censure will always come with weight &amp; effect, because it will never be unduly, or insolently applied.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> has long delayed my first volume.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> He means to publish it early next month, &amp; is instructed to send a copy to Crediton as soon as it appears.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">And now for domestic affairs in what little room is left. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> have begun their travels, &amp; are at this time performing a visit at Derby.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge took her daughter to visit Elizabeth Evans (1758&#8211;1836), of Darley, near Derby. Sara and Samuel Taylor Coleridge had stayed with Mrs Evans in 1796, when there was a possibility that Coleridge would tutor her children.</note> &#8211; We are all well, thank God, &#8211; a frightful alarm which occurred a week ago concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>, having mercifully, past away. He had an attack of croup in the night, happily of the spurious kind,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Croup is a respiratory infection, whose main symptom is a barking cough. It is usually caused by a virus and affects many young children. It was known at this time as &#8216;false croup&#8217;, to distinguish it from laryngeal diphtheria, formerly known as &#8216;true croup&#8217;, a much more serious bacterial infection that also produced a barking cough.</note> &#8211; but it is always a frightful &amp; most alarming sound. &#8211; Young Henry is perfectly recovered from his horrible accident,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. The accident occurred on 2 August 1822 and was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming him): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta.</note> &amp; no otherwise the worse for it, that than he has a hole nearly three inches long in his forehead. This is truly a marvellous recovery &#8211; I keep up the course of exercise which I began with you, walking about six miles every day when the weather is not absolutely too bad as it has been this day. While you were here I always walked in pain;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suffered from a rectal prolapse and haemorrhoids.</note> but it brought my system into tone; &amp; this change was just effected, when we parted. The good effect has continued ever since, &amp; I shall not relax throughout the winter in my efforts to maintain it. &#8211; Tell me now how you are going on &amp; my unseen friends of your household, whom I certainly intend to see in the spring. Remember me to them all at present, &#8211; take yourself the kindest remembrances from all here, &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">my dear Lightfoot<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs affectionately<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p>
            <date when="1822-11-12"> Nov. 12.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>