<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3920Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3920Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3920" type="letter">
        <head>3920. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#FrereBartholomew">Bartholomew Frere</ref>], <date when="1822-11-17">17 November 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS: Beinecke Library, GEN MSS 298, Series I, Box 1, folder 43. ALS; 2p.<lb />
               Unpublished.<lb />
               Note on identity of correspondent: Southey had received a box of papers from Frere in early October 1822, Southey to Charles Watkin Williams Wynn, 11 October 1822, Letter 3906. These papers were to aid Southey in writing the second volume of his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-11-17">17 Nov. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> My Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Had I known you were returned from France, I should have written to acknowledge the receit of the papers, &amp; to thank you for them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I feel confident that the use which I shall make of these letters, can in no possible manner compromise any person, nor hurt the feelings of any one of the writers. You will indeed perceive by the first volume,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> that where the narrative is drawn from original materials, no reference either general or particular, is made to the authorities; neither have I any where specified the sources to which I have had access. My reason for this was twofold, &#8211; first because some of the communications were confidential, &#8211; &amp; secondly because it behoved me, where I was <del>not</del> writing from unpublished documents, to take upon myself the sole responsibility.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The only person likely to have any uncomfortable feeling in the perusal, is Sir Robert Wilson,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Wilson (1777&#8211;1849; <title>DNB</title>), the radical MP for Southwark 1818&#8211;1831, had commanded the Loyal Lusitanian Legion of Portuguese troops in the Peninsular War. In December 1808 he advanced to Ciudad Rodrigo in Spain and maintained his position, despite the retreat of the main British army to Corunna. Southey believed that Wilson&#8217;s actions helped prevent the French advancing on Lisbon, <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp. 77&#8211;83, 241&#8211;245.</note> &amp; that discomfort will arise not from any thing which is said of him, but from the comparison which he himself will make between what he then was, &amp; what he is now. It is not my business to hint at this. I shall do him full justice for the good service which he performed; &amp; do it the more willingly, because it was neither generally understood nor sufficiently rewarded.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am very cautious with regard to others, however little I may be thought so as concerning myself. But do me the favour to look at the proof sheets in their progress, &amp; I will alter any passage in which you may think I have made an indiscrete use of these materials. &#8211; I shall go to press, as soon as <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> obtains for me Olivarez&#8217;s History of the War in Catalonia.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. This had mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877.</note>
        </p>
        <p>
          farewell my Dear Sir<lb/>
           &amp; believe me thankfully &amp; truly yours<lb/>
           Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>