<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3925Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3925Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3925" type="letter">
        <head>3925. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BartonBernard">[Bernard Barton]</ref>, <date when="1822-11-26">26 November 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS untraced; text is taken from Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965)<lb />
               Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 239&#8211;240.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-11-26">26 Nov. 1822.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Thank you for your portrait, which I am glad to see and glad to think that it probably indicates another edition of your poems.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Barton had sent Southey an engraving of a portrait of himself, probably that made by Robert Cooper (d. 1828). The artist is unknown. There was indeed a 3rd edition of Barton&#8217;s <title>Poems</title> in 1822.</note> I should guess that the painter has not done his part so well as the engraver. It would have been more characteristic if he had taken you with your hat on &#8211; the costume as it now is might be mistaken for that of a Methodist preacher.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Your verses upon <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> (for which I thank you also) are either at <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>, or on their way from him.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Barton&#8217;s <title>Verses on the Death of Percy Bysshe Shelley</title> (1822).</note> I knew that miserable man and am well acquainted with his dreadful history. He resided here for some months<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Shelleys had lodged in Keswick from November 1811 to February 1812, during which they met Southey a number of times.</note> with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyHarriet">his wife</ref>, soon after their marriage &#8211; that wife whom he perverted to atheism, and abandoned when he went to live with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyMary">Godwins</ref> daughter &#8211; his present widow.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Shelley (1797&#8211;1851; <title>DNB</title>), with whom Shelley had eloped to the continent in July 1814. They married on 30 December 1816, after the death of Harriet Shelley.</note> She was thoroughly corrupted by him, followed the example which he had set her, and then in shame at the consequences, threw herself into the Thames.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Harriet Shelley had drowned herself in the Serpentine in Hyde Park in late 1816. Her body was recovered on 10 December, and an inquest into the death of &#8216;Harriet Smith&#8217; the following day returned an inconclusive verdict of &#8216;found dead&#8217;. Harriet Shelley was pregnant when she died, and the circumstances surrounding her death were soon common knowledge in literary circles.</note> Two years ago <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> wrote to me, demanding whether I were the author of a paper concerning him in the <hi rend="ital">Quarterly Review</hi>.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">In a letter of 26 June 1820, Shelley had accused Southey of writing a hostile review of <title>Laon and Cythna, or the Revolution of the Golden City</title> (1818; published late 1817) and <title>The Revolt of Islam. A Poem, in Twelve Cantos</title> (1818); see Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 358&#8211;359. The offending article had appeared in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (April 1819), 460&#8211;471. It concluded with an ad hominem attack that suggested the reviewer knew a great deal about Shelley&#8217;s personal affairs: &#8216;if we might withdraw the veil of private life, and tell what we <hi rend="ital">now</hi> know about him, it would be indeed a disgusting picture that we should exhibit, but it would be an unanswerable comment on our text; it is not easy for those who <hi rend="ital">read only</hi>, to conceive how much low pride, how much cold selfishness, how much unmanly cruelty are consistent with the laws of this &#8220;universal&#8221; and &#8220;lawless love.&#8221; But we must only use our knowledge to check the groundless hopes which we were once prone to entertain of him&#8217; (471). The article had, moreover, described Shelley as &#8216;an unsparing imitator&#8217; and <title>The Revolt</title>&#8217;s language and versification as a &#8216;copy&#8217; of Southey&#8217;s, though &#8216;altogether more luxuriant and ornate than the original&#8217; (461). Shelley had been mistaken in attributing the review to Southey, who had a policy of not reviewing contemporary poetry. Its author was John Taylor Coleridge.</note> I took the opportunity which my denial afforded of reading him a lecture.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s &#8216;lecture&#8217; was Southey to Percy Shelley [c. 29 July 1820], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3517.</note> This produced a sort of controversial reply, and then I read him a second, bringing home to him the fatal effects of his principles.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley had replied to Southey on 17 August 1820. This elicited a further response, Southey to Percy Shelley, 12 October 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3538.</note> His story, taking it altogether, is the most flagitious and the most tragic which I have known in real life. You will probably see some of my household<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref>.</note> ere long at <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarksons</ref>, and they will tell you more of him. By the bye he was remarkably like <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Mr Clarkson</ref>, tho upon a small scale. His eyes were set in the same manner, and the resemblance between son and father could not be stronger.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyPercyBysshe">Shelley</ref> was not, like <ref type="m" target="people.html#Byron">Lord Byron</ref>, wicked by disposition. His actual feelings I believe to have been kind and generous. But he adopted the Devils own philosophy that nothing ought to stand in the way of his gratifications, and to this he acted up.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What a dreadful thought of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShelleyHarriet">his wife&#8217;s</ref> fate must have come upon him, when he saw himself about to perish <hi rend="ital">by water</hi>!<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley had drowned in the Bay of Naples on 8 July 1822 when his boat, the <title>Don Juan</title>, sank in a squall.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> His body was much mutilated when it was cast ashore.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Shelley&#8217;s corpse was washed ashore on 18 July near Viareggio.</note> The fish had half devoured it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> He was the least mischievous of the three &#8220;Liberals&#8221;.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The other two were Byron and Leigh Hunt. All had been associated with the short-lived journal <title>The Liberal</title> (1822&#8211;1823).</note> His writings were not bad enough in some respects to do much harm, and far too bad in others. What merit they had was of too high a kind to be attractive, and their obscurity and extravagance served in some degree to sheath the poison which they contained. Farewell, and believe me Yrs truly</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>