<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3930. Robert Southey to [Unknown Correspondent], 9 December 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3930Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3930. Robert Southey to [Unknown Correspondent], 9 December 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3930Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3930" type="letter">
        <head>3930. Robert Southey to [Unknown Correspondent], <date when="1822-12-09">9 December 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS: Manuscripts and Archives Section, New York Public Library, Montague Collier Family Papers. ALS; 3p.<lb />
               Unpublished.<lb />
               Note on correspondent: It has not been possible to identify the correspondent definitively. A strong possibility is Jane Webb, n&#233;e Blackburne (1775&#8211;1860), the wife of William Webb and sister of Francis Blackburne (1782&#8211;1867; <title>DNB</title>).</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-12-09">9 Dec. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute> Dear Madam</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Accept, I pray you, my thanks for your obliging letter, &amp; communicate them to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WebbWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Webb</ref>, for thinking of me when he is so far away, &amp; with so many objects about him to excite his curiosity &amp; attention.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Webb was travelling in Europe; see his <title>Minutes of Remarks on Subjects Picturesque, Moral, and Miscellaneous, made in a Course along the Rhine, and During a Residence in Swisserland and Italy, in the Years 1822 &amp; 1823</title> (1827).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am so well convinced that his desire of being serviceable to me is sincere, that I have been considering how to make him so, as one way of showing myself sensible of his good will. One commission there is which he may be able to execute with little trouble &amp; no inconvenience. It is by procuring for me a book published at Rome in 1791, by P. Pani, a Dominican, &amp; an Inquisitor,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Tommaso Vincenzo Pani (c. 1730&#8211;1814), General Commissioner of the Holy Office 1779&#8211;1785 and 1789&#8211;1792 and Inquisitor in Bologna 1785&#8211;1789. The work Southey (unsuccessfully) sought was an account, supposed to have been published by Pani in Rome in 1791, of the Societ&#233; des Illumin&#233;s d&#8217;Avignon, founded in 1786. The Society practised a mixture of Freemasonry and mysticism. Southey had already discussed this subject in <title>Letters from England by Don Manuel Alvarez Espriella</title>, 3 vols (London, 1807), III, Letter LXVIII.</note> containing an account of a religious Society at Avignon, &amp; the process against one Ottavio Cappelli,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Ottavio Cappelli (1736&#8211;1800), Italian mystic, who was arrested and imprisoned by the Papal authorities in 1790. He was pardoned and exiled in 1795, but returned to Rome in 1798 and was executed. It is possible that the book about Cappelli and the Societ&#233; des Illumin&#233;s d&#8217;Avignon that Southey was seeking was actually the manuscript account of the indictment of Cappelli drawn up by Pani.</note> who was one of its members. Its precise title I do not know, &#8211; but any bookseller who has the book will recognize it by this account of its contents. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#WebbWilliam">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Webb</ref> can meet with it he will render me a service, &#8211; &amp; I dare say the book is small enough to be allowed room even in a travellers portmanteau.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">May I also beg you to make our remembrances to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilson, &amp; thank him for the Cookery Book, which reached me safely &amp; in good time.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">It is not clear who &#8216;Mr Wilson&#8217; was, though he might have been <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilsonJohn">John Wilson</ref>. Southey owned a copy of &#8216;W.M.&#8217;, <title>The Queen&#8217;s Closet Opened, and The Compleat Cook</title> (1659&#8211;1661), no. 3040 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note> I dare say you will wonder what could induce M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wilson to send me a Cookery Book, &#8211; for I assure you it was for my use, &amp; not for that of the family. He will see in the next Quarterly Review that I have made use of it, &#8211; &amp; you will see there why I wish to possess the publication of the Roman Inquisitor.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title> (1814), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 1&#8211;46, published 15 February 1823. (The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.) Southey recounted the history of the Societ&#233; des Illumin&#233;s d&#8217;Avignon; but he did not mention any subjects connected to cooking (pp. 36&#8211;42). Possibly this material was edited out of Southey&#8217;s article; or, as <title>The Queen&#8217;s Closet Opened, and The Compleat Cook</title> contains medical cures as well as recipes, Southey might have been intending to use it to support statements in his article, such as that &#8216;in former times&#8217; human milk was a commonly prescribed remedy (p. 3).</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Miss Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">her mother</ref> are on their travels in the south, &#8211; otherwise I should have to offer their remembrances to him, &amp; their thanks to you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#JebbJohn">Archdeacon Jebbs</ref> promotion has indeed given me great pleasure, both on his own account, &amp; because it is not possible that such preferment could be more worthily bestowed.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Jebb had been appointed Bishop of Limerick, Ardfet and Aghadoe.</note> I think myself very fortunate in having met him when I was last in town. Such appointments are honourable to those who make them, &amp; tend, as far as human means may avail, to make the Church what it ought to be, &#8211; which is one of the surest means for improving the condition of the world.</p>
        <p>
          Believe me Madam<lb/>
           very truly<lb/>
           Your obliged &amp; obedient servant<lb/>
          Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>