<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">3940Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3940" type="letter"><head>3940. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>], <date when="1822-12-24">24 December 1822</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Houghton, bMS Eng 265.1 (13). ALS; 9p. A fair copy, also addressed to Bedford, is in the British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 11p.<lb/>
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 359–368 [Warter’s copy text was probably taken from the fair copy now in the British Library, which contains minor variants from that in the Houghton.]<lb/>
               Note on the MS: Copy text is taken from the draft now in the Houghton as representing the earliest surviving version.</note></head>
            
            
            <opener> <dateline><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick.</ref> <date when="1822-12-24">24 Dec. 1822</date></dateline>
            
           <salute> Dear Stumparumper</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">So long a time has elapsed since I sent you the commencement of my remarks upon the peculiar language spoken by <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridge</ref> (which I have denominated the Lingo-grande)<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to ‘Stumparumper’ [Grosvenor Charles Bedford], 14 September 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3730.</note> that I fear you may suppose<del>d</del> I have altogether neglected the subject. Yet such a subject, as you must perceive, requires a great deal of patient observation, as well as of attentive consideration; &#38; were I to flustercumhurry over it, as if it were a matter which could be undercumstood in a ji<hi rend="ital">ff</hi>ump, (that is to say, in a mōmper), this would be to do what I have undertaken shabroonily, &#38; you might shartainly have reason to think me faffling &#38; indiscruckt. Upon my vurtz I have not dumdawdled with it like a dangleampeter, which, being explained in the same lingo, is an undecider; or an improvidentipur, too idle to explore the hurtch mine which he has had the fortune to discover. No, I must be a stupossum indeed to act thus, as well as a slouwdowdelcum, or slowdonothinger; &#38; these are appellations which she has never bestowed upon me; tho perhaps the uncommon richness &#38; even exuberance of her language has <del>never</del> &#60;not&#62; been more strikingly displayed &#60;in any thing&#62;, than in the variety of names <del>with</del> which <del>I have been favoured in</del> it has enabled her to shower upon my devoted person.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> I have been called poor Peecrack, Trumpeteerum, King of the Jackus, Crackarum, Detestarumpeter, a Noisiton, a Shockrocket, &#60;Rackskalk&#62; &#38; <del>xx</del> Rascalalker, in addition to the appellations noticed in my former epistle. And I cannot flatter myself that kindness wears the mask of vituperation while she is thus addressing me, as it certainly does when she sends you her hate, &#38; calls you scarecrow. In your case, there is a smile which plays about her towse, &#38; the look belies the spoak, silently but expressively confessing it to be a mere storck. But when one of these appellations is discharged at me, there is no expression of countenance to contradictorum it: it comes like a poal of thunder; &#38; <del>if I were not used to such xxxxxxxx might make xxxxx a xxxxx come into my head</del> &#60;seems intended to strike me dumb at least if not absolutely to crunch me to munch&#62;</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Did I ever shew you a curious book published in 1785 with this title, Letters of Literature, by Robert Heron, Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>?<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">[John Pinkerton (1758–1826; <title>DNB</title>)], <title>Letters of Literature. By Robert Heron, Esq.</title> (London, 1785), Letter XXXIV, ‘Notices on the English tongue. Proposal for a reform of it, and of the Greek characters’, pp. 237–275, no. 2265 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> The copy <del>of</del> in my possession (I beg pardon of the collectors, – <hi rend="ital">penes me</hi><note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘by me’.</note> is the phrase) belonged to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">Henry Kirke White</ref>, &#38; was given me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">his brother</ref>, as having his autograph upon the title page. Pinkerton was the author; &#38; the name which he assumed at random, happening to belong to an unlucky writer who began his career shortly afterwards the real Robert Heron<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Heron (1764–1807; <title>DNB</title>), Scottish editor, translator, playwright, historian and journalist. His career was largely unsuccessful and he was twice imprisoned for debt.</note> found himself in bad odour, thro the prejudice which these very conceited &#38; extravagant letters had excited. But it is a very odd book, as well as a most impudent one, &#38; the most curious thing in it is a plan for improving the English language, by altering its structure. For this purpose it was seriously proposed by the said Pinkerton that the most learned men in the three kingdoms should incorporate themselves in an Academy, publish a grammar &#38; dictionary of the improved English, &#38; use it themselves both in writing &#38; discourse, thus asserting what he called their proper power over the mob, till the revolution in our speech (for it was nothing less) should be compleatly effected. The leading principles of his scheme were to get rid of all sounds which were unpleasing to his ear, to throw away the consonant at the end of a certain class of words, add his favourite vowel O to it in others, &#38; form the plural of all nouns in a. As a specimen he has translated <hi rend="ital">Thea Visiona</hi> of Mirza, from the Spectator,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Addison (1672–1719; <title>DNB</title>), ‘The Vision of Mirzah’, <title>The Spectator</title>, 159 (1 September 1711), pp. 317–318, reconstituted in <title>Letters of Literature</title> (London, 1785), pp. 254–263.</note> into his own improved language. Buy the book if ever it falls in your way, for it is a treasure</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I mention it now, because I have compared the Pinkertonian Lingo with the Lingo-Grande; &#38; it is surprizing how far below <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridge</ref>, Pinkerton must be placed in this department of genius. For example, snuffers he would call thea snuffera; with us they are snuffumpers. Candles he would ask for by the name of thea candela; our inventress calls them candeels-candowls-candoals. He would call the bells, thea bella, our bell is the bellabbity when we are told to twyke it. A gig with him would be a giggo; here it is gidge, <hi rend="ital">euphoniea gratiâ</hi>;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">‘sweet-sounding grace’.</note> &#38; in like manner bag, which he would make baggo, is softened into badje. Then how poor are his doggo &#38; foggo when compared with our dogroggarum &#38; fogogrum or fogrogrum! He would say spasmea for spasms, in our Lingo they are spaddelcoms. Lumbago he would leave unchanged because it terminates in the vowel which he so greatly affects; but here the word is ennobled into lumbaggarum whenever the inventress feels a pange resembling it. Puddles he would call puddela; with us they are pulkers &#38; pillpulkers; &#38; if it be a great, broad, sprawly, disagreeable pillpulker, then it is denominated a pulker-peeler. What would Pinkerton make of thimble which could equal thimblumb, &#38; thimbōlion? And what of that lower region, the seat of frequent aches, which could at once be so euphonious &#38; delicate as belteerian? Here perhaps she would exclaim for forshammanum, if she knew that I were writing that word; but how unjust should I be to her merits, were I to omit it!</p>
            <p rend="indent1">The Pinkertonian scheme is inconvenient, as requiring perpetual attention to its principles; &#38; indeed I may venture to say, that it is impracticable because it requires a total, &#38; therefore an impossible change in <del>our mother tongue</del> &#60;the language of the country.&#62; But the Lingo-grande is not liable to such objections. It does &#60;not&#62; propose to alter our dictionary, but to enlarge it: <del>by</del> &#60;not to reconstruct our mother-tongue, but to adorn &#38; beautify it, – to&#62; enrich<del>ing</del> it with <del>adornments</del> &#60;graces&#62; &#38; elegancies of speech; – flowers, yea rather gems of language. The Pinkerton Lingo displays no invention: whereas this is eminently <del>xxxxxxx</del> distinguished by its inventiveness. When a word is wanted here, there is no tarrying for rule, or reason, etymology, or analogy. I do not mean to say that some remote analogy, – some recondite etymon, the germ, or seminal principle of the word may not sometimes be discovered; this is often the case, &#38; such vocables have a peculiar force; but quite as often &#60;the neologism, if I may so express myself,&#62; is fatherless &#38; motherless, <del>to express myself more clearly by help of these metaphorical words</del>, – a clear case of equivocal generation, – an arbitrary sound, – a pure creation. Instances of both kinds will be found in the examples which I am about to adduce; – &#38; your discrimination will know how to distinguish them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">If the weather is ramping &#38; tearing, this great inventress &#60;complains of rampasity, &#38; says&#62; <del>calls</del> it is a taarampeter of a day. Should one of the childereelions be <del>pakum</del> poakun &#38; frumping &#38; rouking in a work-badje, she tells them not to be dabdobbering there, for it gives her a feeling of pōakãrōakãtur. &#60;Has she been in dull company? she describes the conversation of such stupossums as drigdraggery.&#62; A brook she calls the running splash. &#60;When she takes a dose of physic it is to give her constitution a jerk; &#38; if I sneeze in her presence, she declares that it makes all the addle come into her head.&#62; She objected to a new bonnet one day, as being glombollical. I could not ascertain in what glombollicality consists nor would she explain it to me. I believe it gratifies her when she perceives that I cannot penetrate into the signification of an uncommonly difficult neologism. She has left &#60;me&#62; till this hour entirely unable even to guess at what is meant by spackwhangular; &#38; if she does not accidentally betray the meaning, I verily <del>believe</del> &#60;think&#62; I shall die in ignorance of it.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Drote &#38; thrapple are the throat. The under jaw is called the under-jabbarum, <hi rend="ital">unde</hi> jabbarumpeter one of the words for mouth (mouto in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Pinkertons language.) &#60;By the bye she uses a tooth broom.&#62; The nose is poggarout. Stumper is the stomach: Cruppōkur, the part which is accommodated with a saddle when we ride. The feet are wattlykins, &#38; foottels-toottles, they are known also by other appellations, some diminutive &#38; endearing, others augumentative &#38; opprobrius which were noticed in my former letter. Every body else’s legs are legrums, if not hormangorgrums; but her own, for some reason which I cannot divine, she calls her inconveniences. I know that it was formerly deemed indelicate in Portugal to speak of <del>them</del> legs by their own innocent name, &#38; they were called therefore in all polite circles, the walkers, or the goers; as in some parts of Germany a pettycoat used to be called a consideration, &#38; a pair of gouty shoes, a pair of Excellencies. One understand this, but I cannot comprehend why she should call her legs her inconveniences.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">To get drunk is to tipsificumpus. Her exclamations of <del>xxx</del> disappointment &#38; fatigue may bear comparison with the most imitative of the Greek interjections. &#927;&#953;&#956;&#959;&#953;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Woe is me’.</note> &#38; &#959;&#964;&#959;&#964;&#964;&#959;&#964;&#959;&#953;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">‘That is’.</note> surely are not more expressive that &#333;hd&#333;urm&#333;u, &#38; &#333;hd&#299;ddled&#333;wl&#333;o. I would not depreciate the Greek words, <hi rend="ital">each</hi> is certainly a good mouthfull &#38; throatfull of lamentation. Yet these <del>xxxxx</del> which I have brought in comparison with them from the Lingo Grande, appear to me to <del>express</del> &#60;excell&#62; them in length &#38; breadth of dejection in the plerophory of uncomfortabuttelness which they denote</p>
            <p rend="indent1">&#60;Instead of the second, she usually says the twooth. <ref type="m" target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Her sisters</ref> are generally called sters.&#62; Kincher is a child, gril a girl, oomper a woman. Cupids are denominated kincherums, &#38; petteldeloves. A child just able to tottel about is a shortycum nutofabunch. If she speaks to an infant she calls it noans-da-vara; or tooshden&#333;any – tooshden&#275;edlen&#333;odle – tooshden&#299;dle. When she is vexed with herself she says she could tear goarum, &#38; is ready to go tarradiddle. I have heard her threaten <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> to cōdy her; an indefinite &#38; hitherto inexplicable mode of punishment, by which no doubt something very <del>dreadful</del> &#60;severe&#62; is intended. This is only when <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> is a gidditonian, or an imprawnce; or if she assists me in forming the precious vocabulary which has enabled me to treat upon this curious subject. At other times she speaks of her as a poor lassitudinarian thing. One of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughters</ref> has been favoured at different times with the names of Scampalum, Scarecrok, Snoukarouker, Horsegodmarumpit, &#38; Horsemangander. The collective females of the family are called the Porcaboarabumbels: – &#60;&#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BarkerMary">Miss Barker</ref> was seldom addressed by any other name that that of Barkeerum-barkumpus-barkoop.&#62;</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Among other observables it ought to be noticed that she has peculiar names for her domestic implements. One of her scissors is called pex, another is peckrex, a third is bluestring. Her work bag is pinkrinkit. Her umbrella numpernell, or <hi rend="ital">brevitatis causâ</hi>,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">‘for the sake of brevity’.</note> numper. I hardly need observe that there is a resemblance here to the custom which prevailed in <del>the</del> days of chivalry, of giving swords as well as horses each its proper name. Thus Arthur had his Escalibor, Charlemagne his Joyeuse, Roland his Durlindana, &#38; my Cid the Campeador his Colada &#38; Tizona.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The swords of heroes in medieval romances, as in: Sir Thomas Malory (c. 1415–1471; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Le Morte d’Arthur</title> (1485); <title>La Chanson de Roland</title> (11th century); and <title>El Cantar de Mio Cid</title> (12th century).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">  I must observe also that some very singular, &#38; to me unaccountable notions in natural history, are <del>sometimes</del> &#60;frequently&#62; implied in her discourse, which when she is questioned concerning them, she avows, &#38; maintains with great confidence &#60;&#38; pertinacity.&#62; She insists upon it that stone &#38; wood are the same thing: that all dogs whether male or female, are <del>of the</del> masculine <del>gender</del>; &#38; all cats female<del>xxx</del>, &#38; to prove this last extraordinary, &#38; as I may call it preposterous assertion, she tells me that I never call <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">my son</ref> Puss, tho I do call one of my daughters so, chusing to overlook the manner in which the little girl came to be so called, as being christened <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Katharine</ref>, from whence by easy &#38; natural steps we get to Puss.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The name Katherine can be shortened to ‘Kat’, making the transition to ‘Puss’ an obvious one.</note> But what is yet more singular, all things which she does not exactly like are toads. So general indeed is the use of this word, <del>xxxxxx for that xxxxx xxxxxxxx dislike</del>, that <del>it</del> one might almost suppose it were derived from the Spanish todo, which signifies all &#38; every thing; were it not that she spells it as you see it here spelt, and explains it to mean that poor, calumniated, persecuted, squat, squab animal, who is the frogs first cousin.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  But it is time that this long letter should be brought to a close. I will conclude it therefore <del>when I have</del> &#60;with&#62; offering to your consideration <del>xxxx</del> a thought<del>s</del> which <del>have</del> &#60;has&#62; occurred to me while writing it. There is an hypothesis concerning the origin of language, which (to use an Americanism) has been advocated by some Hebricians, &#38; some Welsh antiquaries. It is that the primal language was not revealed to our first parents;<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden, <title>Genesis</title> 2: 4–3: 24.</note> but was “the result of a natural aptitude in the organs of speech to utter certain definite articulations, according to the impulse of mans internal emotions”.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Humffreys Parry (1786–1825), ‘Essay on the Antiquity of the Welsh Tongue’, <title>Transactions of the Cymmrodorion, or Metropolitan Cambrian Institution</title>, I (1822), 6–18 (7), no. 2829 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> A certain number of imitations &#38; significant radicals were thus produced, &#38; the rest <del>xxx xxx</del> being matter of combination &#38; caprice was of course infinitely variable. Attempts have been made to show that the principle may at this time be clearly traced in the Welsh &#38; Hebrew roots. For some singular illustrations of this theory I refer you to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Davies’s Celtic Researches,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Davies (1756–1831), ‘On the formation of language. Nature of the primitive language’, <title>Celtic Researches on the Origins, Traditions and Language, of the Ancient Britons; with some Introductory Sketches on Primitive Society</title> (London, 1804), pp. 373–389, no. 796 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> a book in other respects well worth reading, being full of Kimbric learning. I have heard that the notion has been pursued much farther by an ingenious, fanciful &#38; patient German:<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Flemish (not German) writer Franciscus Mercurius van Helmont (1614–1698/99), whose <title>Alphabeti vere Naturalis Hebraici Brevissima Delineatio</title> (1667) argued that the letters of the Hebrew alphabet were diagrams which illustrated how the lips and tongue were positioned to express the sounds of the letters. Helmont’s book also contained a series of woodcuts, showing cross sections of heads in profile, to demonstrate how the speech organs have been shaped by God to form Hebrew letters.</note> he supposed that the letters of the Hebrew alphabet are of divine appointment, &#38; carry with them the proof of their superhuman origin each being so shaped as to represent the exact form which <del>the tongue &#38; the larynx</del> organs of speech assume in making the sound denoted by it. He is said to have spent a great many years in pronouncing these letters with his back to the light, a looking glass before him, &#38; his mouth open, &#38; a pencil in his hand to catch the likeness, &#38; finally succeeded in producing a series of <del>xxxxx</del> anatomical drawings to support his hypothesis.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> Something correlative (not to the Germans notion, but to the theory maintained by my brethren of the Cymmrodorion) I remember to have heard more than twenty years ago, when dining, <hi rend="ital">moi quatrieme</hi>,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">‘as one of four’.</note> in company with M. Peltier.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Jean-Gabriel Peltier (1760–1825), a French journalist.</note> He was expatiating to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Mr Coleridge</ref> &#38; myself, for our edification, upon the peculiar excellences of French poetry, &#38; of the French language as adapted for poetry. And he instanced both in these three words from Racine, <hi rend="ital">Roi des Rois</hi>,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean Racine (1639–1699), <title>Iphigénie</title> (1674) Act 1, scene 1, line 82.</note> words he said, which no person could pronounce properly, or hear properly pronounced, without being sensible in himself of an expansion &#60;&#38; elevation&#62; of mind corresponding to the expansion of organs both of hearing &#38; speech, sympathetic with the sound, <del>&#38; xxxx</del> &#60;<del>xxxxxx to</del>&#62; <del>xxxxxxxx</del> &#60;with the&#62; meaning of the words, &#38; the sublimity of the sentiment.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Now that great part of the vocabulary of the Lingo Grande is formed as these <del>xxxxxxx</del> philosophers suppose the primal roots to have been, appears certain: the words evidently proceeding not from premeditation, but from impulse, &#38; an impatience of speech, which will not allow the utterance to wait till the common &#38; conventional term can be recollected. Perhaps I might call it a peculiar intuition a genius, a gifted nature which rejects the conventional term as inadequate to its <del>expressions</del> &#60;conceptions&#62;, &#38; seeking words that burn for thoughts that breathe, brings up from the depths of its own being, the natural &#38; true vocable. There are several cases upon record of persons who under the influence of delirium, or some other derangement of the head, have spoken languages which they had learnt in childhood, but thro the disuse of many years, had utterly forgotten, till the obliterated impressions in the sensorium were thus mysteriously restored. I do not mean to reason upon these cases as analogous, which indeed they are not, unless I took up the opinion of preexistence,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">The idea that each soul was created before the body it was to inhabit and entered that body at some time before birth.</note> which in this sense, assuredly I do not think tenable. What I would ask goes farther. Is it not possible that <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs Coleridge</ref>, when <del>uttering</del> under an irresistible impulse she utters these umpremeditated words, may unconsciously, but actually be speaking the primal language itself? And if so, what a service shall I have rendered to all future etymologists, such as General Vallancey,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Vallancey (1731–1812; <title>DNB</title>), a Lieutenant-General in the Royal Engineers and writer on Irish history and language. His works, such as <title>Prospectus of a Dictionary of the Language of the Aire Coti, or Ancient Irish</title> (1802), claimed there was an affinity between Irish and many other ancient languages.</note> Jacob Byrant<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacob Bryant (1715–1804; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A New System or Analysis of Ancient Mythology</title> (1774–1776), argued that all mythologies derived from the Bible, making some ingenious use of etymology.</note> &#38; Walter Whiter,<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Whiter (1758–1832; <title>DNB</title>), the philologist and author of <title>Etymologicon Universale</title> (1822).</note> by these my humble &#38; patient labours in collecting &#38; preserving its precious fragments! Who knows but that &#60;some&#62; of these identical vocables may be discovered in the Egyptian monuments, when D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Young<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Young (1773–1829; <title>DNB</title>), the physician, scientist, linguist and polymath. He was one of a number of figures at this time who were beginning to have some success in deciphering Egyptian hieroglyphics.</note> shall have succeeded (as I trust he will) in decyphering them? Or in the books of Adam himself, which D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stanier Clarke, upon the testimony of the learned Kissaeus, believes to be at this day in existence; tho unhappily, neither he, nor Kissaeus could tell exactly where they were to be found!<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">James Stanier Clarke (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), Historiographer Royal 1812–1834 and author of <title>The Progress of Maritime Discovery, from the Earliest Period, to the Close of the Eighteenth Century, forming an Extensive System of Hydrography</title> (London, 1803), p. vi; though Stanier Clarke was only quoting the reports of other writers, based on the authority of ‘Kissaeus’, i.e. Muhammad ibn ‘abd Allah al-Kisai (11th century), <title>The Tales of the Prophets</title> (c. 1200). Southey had ridiculed Clarke’s views on ‘the books of Adam’ in his review of this work in the <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 13.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> And so-o-o</p>
            <closer> <salute rend="indent2">Dear Miscumber Bedfordiddlededford</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3"> I subcumscribe myself</salute>
               <salute rend="indent4">Your sincumcere friendiddledend &#38; serdiddledervant</salute>
          <signed rend="indent5">  Robcumbert Southeydiddledowthey.</signed>
            <lb/>
            <signed rend="indent1">Student in the Lingo Grande, Graduate in Butlerology, Professor of the science of Noncumsensediddledense, of sneezing, &#38; of vocal music. P.L. &#38; LLD. &#38;c &#38;c.</signed></closer>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
