<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3942Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3942Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3942" type="letter">
        <head>3942. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1822-12-29">29 December 1822</date>
          </head><p>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 2p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 368&#8211;369.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Your last frank covered a copy of the Cymmrodorion Transactions, sent me by the Secretary, &#8211; thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> hands.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Transactions of the Cymmrodorion, or Metropolitan Cambrian Institution</title> (1822), no. 2829 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Wynn had played a central role in re-founding the Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion in 1820 as a society of London-based Welshmen interested in the history of Wales. Southey was elected a member of the Society in 1821. The Secretary was James Evans (dates unknown).</note> It is a creditable volume, but by much the most important paper is that which you communicated from Peter Roberts&#8217; papers.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Law Triads of the Ancient Britons. Translated by the Late Rev. Peter Roberts&#8217;, <title>Transactions of the Cymmrodorion, or Metropolitan Cambrian Institution</title> (London, 1822), I, pp. 97&#8211;149. Peter Roberts (1760&#8211;1819; <title>DNB</title>) was a Welsh clergyman and antiquarian.</note> This is indeed very curious, &amp; seems to have been committed to a very competent editor.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Humffreys Parry (1786&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), Welsh barrister and antiquarian.</note> I am very anxious that the publication of the Welsh Remains should be fairly compleated, so that nothing which can be of any use to antiquaries, historians or philologists should be exposed to the danger of being lost. When the Cambo-Briton<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Cambro-Briton</title> (1819&#8211;1822), a journal on Welsh history, no. 527 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> reaches me I will put together a Saxons view of the subject for the QR.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>.</note> You should send a qualified traveller to Bretagne to see what could be recovered there.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">By what I hear it seems no easy thing to find a successor for the Bp of Calcutta.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Fanshaw Middleton (1769&#8211;1822; <title>DNB</title>) had been appointed first Bishop of Calcutta in 1814, with jurisdiction over the whole territory of the East India Company. Peter Elmsley had declined the post. Middleton&#8217;s successor was Reginald Heber.</note> The constitution of our Church is such that very few of its ministers are willing to volunteer upon foreign service. I might have appointed a Chaplain to Pernambuco four or five years ago, if I had known where to find one, &#8211; the income was 400&#163; a year, with a house, &amp; 100&#163; for his expences out.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Koster had written to Southey, asking for his help in appointing a chaplain for the British community in Pernambuco; see Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 25 August 1817, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 3017.</note> The person whom <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">the Bp of London</ref> found at last was one of ruined fortunes &#8211; tho of fair character.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Sandby (c. 1761&#8211;1832), B.A. Christ Church, Oxford, 1783. He was Vicar of Swell, Gloucestershire 1795&#8211;1832 and Rector of Honeychurch, Devon 1816&#8211;1832. The bankruptcy of the merchant Samuel Palmer (1762&#8211;1851), of Bourton-on-the-Water, in 1816 had led to actions by Palmer&#8217;s creditors to recover the debts that Sandby owed to Palmer. As Sandby had already spent time in prison for debt, this may have encouraged him to consider the chaplaincy in Pernambuco.</note> &#8211; The question of providing religious instruction &#8211; that is of forming a Church establishment, &#8211; for our new colonies, is one which should be considered without delay; as ultimately of the greatest importance. <del>It is</del> The want of such establishments <del>which</del> has been one main cause why colonists in modern times have been so much depraved than the people from whom they spring. &#8211; e &#8211; g &#8211; the Dutch at Surinam &amp; in Cape. &#8211; With regard to India there are great difficulties no doubt, but it seems to me that the best method would be to educate <del>xxxx</del> some of the half-cast for the ministry there.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Fanshaw Middleton had founded Bishop&#8217;s College, Calcutta, in 1820 to train Indians for the Anglican ministry.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Many &amp; happy returns of this season to you &amp; yours!</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3"> RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-12-29">29 Dec. 1822.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>