<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">3943. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 30 December 1822</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3943Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">3943. Robert Southey to Herbert Hill, 30 December 1822</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3943Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3943" type="letter">
        <head>3943. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1822-12-30">30 December 1822</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
               Stamped: [illegible]<lb />
               Postmarks: [partial] JA 2/ 1823; [illegible]<lb />
               MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 225. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 369&#8211;371 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1822-12-30">30 Dec. 1822</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I am glad you are satisfied with my proceedings in the Peninsular War.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) had just been published; the whole work was dedicated to George IV.</note> &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#KnightonSirWilliam">Sir Wm Knighton</ref> has written to me expressing by <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the Kings</ref> command his satisfaction at receiving the book, &amp; his estimation of the usefulness &amp; importance of my literary labours, &#8211; this is said in terms sufficiently flattering, &#8211; to which <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> has added with his own hand &#8220;entirely approved GR.&#8221; &#8211; This I suppose is a mark of especial favour.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Booksellers will always be booksellers, &amp; estimate books merely by their sale. But I do not believe that if the book had been published seven years ago, which would have been seven years too soon, that fifty copies more if it would have been sold. I have heard nothing from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">him</ref> since its appearance, &amp; little from any body else. Except that <ref type="m" target="people.html#DalrympleHew">Sir Hew Dalrymple</ref> has thanked me for his copy, &amp; expressed himself much gratified by the manner in which he is mentioned; &#8211; at the same time disclaiming any share in the censure conveyed in p. 583;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, p. 583, had condemned British officers for socialising with their French counterparts after the Convention of Cintra (1808). Given the war crimes that the French had perpetrated in Portugal, this was to Southey &#8216;a moral fault, as well as a political error.&#8217;</note> saying that he never saw Junot,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-Andrache Junot (1771&#8211;1813), a French General who commanded the forces that invaded Portugal in 1808.</note> &amp; did not enter Lisbon till the French had embarkd.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> A Major Tomkinson of the Light Dragoons has also written to me, in consequence of reading this volume, to offer me any parts of his journal, which I may wish to see.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tomkinson (1790&#8211;1872) joined the 16th Light Dragoons as a cornet in 1808 and served in Spain 1809&#8211;1813. He was a Captain at Waterloo (1815). His diary was later published as <title>The Diary of a Cavalry Officer in the Peninsular and Waterloo Campaign, 1809&#8211;1815</title> (1894).</note> He joined in 1809, &amp; was in every battle with the <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">Duke</ref> till the end of the war, except that of Talavera, having been left wounded at Porto.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Battle of Talavera, 27&#8211;28 July 1809, in which Anglo-Spanish forces compelled the French army to withdraw. Tomkinson had been seriously wounded at the Battle of the Douro on 11 May 1809 and so missed Talavera.</note> &#8211; I have requested him to let me see the whole Journal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It is not my fault that the second vol. is not in the press. I applied to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> more than six months ago to procure me a history of the war in Catalonia, &amp; a biographical work connected with it , both by the same author Luis de Oliveira (I think) is the name.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note> He served in that province, &amp; is said to be a man of great talents. The first chapter of this volume must include the proceedings in Catalonia from the entrance of Gouvion S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cyr &amp; the siege of Rosas, to the defeat of the Spaniards, &amp; the breaking up the blockade of Barcelona,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp. 37&#8211;59. French forces led by Laurent de Gouvion Saint-Cyr (1764&#8211;1830) captured the town of Rosas on 5 December 1808 after a month-long siege. This allowed them to proceed to relieve the French army surrounded in Barcelona.</note> &#8211; - &amp; of course I will not write this part, till I can have these Spanish works before me. Then I shall get on briskly; being fully provided with matter, &amp; having no difficulties of arrangement.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">At present I am pursuing the B of the Church<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> &#8211; but I must very soon set about a paper for the Review,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), &#8216;Histoire de la Th&#233;ophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu&#8217;&#224; son Extinction&#8217;, part of Gr&#233;goire&#8217;s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55&#8211;171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493&#8211;536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; of all employments that which I like the least, &#8211; but I cannot supply my current expences without it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> is got to the head of his department in his Exchequer.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">James Fisher (c. 1758&#8211;1821), the Chief Clerk in the Auditor&#8217;s Office had died on 15 December 1821. Bedford duly succeeded Fisher as Chief Clerk 1822&#8211;1834, relinquishing his post of Clerk of Registers and Issues, which he had held since 1806. The salary was &#163;1,200 p.a., hence the large amount of stamp duty Bedford had to pay on the documents appointing him to his office.</note> The situation ought to be a good, for the stamps upon his appointment come to 75&#163;. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElmsleyPeter">Elmsley</ref> noluit episcopari<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;did not want to be bishop&#8217;. Elmsley had declined the Bishopric of Calcutta that Wynn had offered him. The post was in Wynn&#8217;s gift as he was President of the Board of Control. Eventually, Reginald Heber accepted the post.</note> at Calcutta, very wisely, &#8211; tho he would have been the better for melting. I believe there is some difficulty in finding a fit person to accept that undesirable promotion. It is a banishment for life, &amp; they require as much personal exertions from the Bishop, as a Manufacturer does from one of his Riders.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. salesmen.</note> A man must have the spirit of a Missionary to <del>a xxxx</del> undertake it. A church in India they ought to have, in every account, political as well as religious; &#8211; but as I have told <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref>, they can never supply it from this country, &amp; therefore ought to educate half-cast men for it, in India.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Our weather is severe. The report in <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> &#8211; which I have just heard, is, that I have prophesied a frost of thirteen weeks continuance, &amp; ice upon the lake eighteen inches thick!!</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> At present, thank God, we are all well. Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; the boys &#8211; Tell <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> that I work as diligently at Dutch &amp; Danish as he can do at Greek.</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
           RS.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">I must get <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Dr</ref> to enquire among his Portugueze acquaintance whether any account of the war has been published in that country subsequent to that of which I have made so m[MS missing] by Jose Accursio das Neves.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Jos&#233; Ac&#250;rsio das Neves (1766&#8211;1834), <title>Hist&#243;rio Geral da Invas&#227;o dos Francezes em Portugal e de Restaura&#231;&#227;o deste Reino</title> (1810&#8211;1811), no. 3164 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> His history ends with the first invasion, &#8211; &amp; I should think as well as hope that there may be some later accounts.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>