<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3945</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3945Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3945" type="letter">
        <head>3945. Robert Southey to [<ref type="a" target="people.html#DibdinThomasFrognall">Thomas Frognall Dibdin</ref>], <date when="1823-01-03">3 January 1823</date>
          </head><p>MS: Tipped into a graingerised copy of <title>The English Bards and Scotch Reviewers, by Lord Byron. Illustrated with Portraits and Views, the First and Fourth Editions, with the alterations from the Fifth Edition</title> (London: n.p., 1811), pp. [141&#8211;2], Hornby Library, Liverpool City Libraries. ALS; 2p.<lb />
Unpublished.<lb />
Note on correspondent: The correspondent is identified by the letter&#8217;s content; see Southey to [Thomas Frognall Dibdin], 9 December 1822, Letter 3929.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-01-03">3 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Your first letter led me into a temptation, from which your second sets me free. &#8211; The sum which the publishers offer for two quarto volumes, is just one half of what I should require for one.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">On 9 December 1822 (Letter 3929), Dibdin had proposed that Southey should undertake a continuation of Thomas Warton (1728&#8211;1790; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of English Poetry from the Close of the Eleventh to the Commencement of the Eighteenth Century</title> (1774&#8211;1781). Southey did not take up the offer and a new edition appeared in 1824, edited by Richard Price (1790&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), no. 2986 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The proposed publisher of Southey&#8217;s continuation of Warton&#8217;s work was Thomas Tegg (1766&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>), well known for producing popular works and abridgements of literary standards. Southey did not undertake any work for him.</note> Of course therefore there is an end of the matter.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I guessed that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HaslewoodJoseph">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Haslewood</ref> was the person to whom you alluded. I called upon him one &amp; twenty years ago in consequence of his Chatterton collections,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Joseph Haslewood, 12 July 1802, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Two</title>, Letter 694. Southey&#8217;s call was to receive assistance with his <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title> (1803), an edition of the writings of Thomas Chatterton (1752&#8211;1770; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; &amp; by what I then saw of him, &amp; have since seen of his labours, <del>xxxxx</del> know how justly you have appreciated him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Can you inform me where there exists a copy of the Comedies of Gil Vicente,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Gil Vicente (c. 1465&#8211;1536) wrote over forty plays. A posthumous edition of his works, <title>Compila&#231;&#227;o de Toda as Obras de Gil Vicente</title> (1562), appeared in five volumes, with the comedies occupying volume two and the farces volume four.</note> whom the Portugueze assert to be the father of the Spanish drama? You, who know every thing about books, are more likely to direct <del>xxxx</del> me in my search for this, than any other person. I should be glad to know also if the Cancioneiro of Resende is to be found in England.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Cancioneiro Geral</title> (1516), compiled by Garcia de Resende (1470&#8211;1536), contains nearly 1,000 lyrics in Portuguese and Castilian.</note> I made considerable extracts from it at Lisbon in the year 1801. But these are not sufficient for my purpose, &amp; whenever it is in my power, I must peruse the book.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If chance should ever lead you this way, it would give me great pleasure to show you my Portugueze collection, &#8211; which in manuscripts I dare say is richer than any other in England.</p>
        <p>
          Farewell my Dear Sir<lb/>
          &amp; believe me<lb/>
          Your obliged &amp; obedient<lb/>
          Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>