<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3949Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3949" type="letter">
        <head>3949. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1823-01-08">8 January 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 6p.<lb />
Previously edited or published: Michael Neill Stanton, &#8216;An Edition of the Autobiographical Letters of Robert Southey&#8217; (unpublished PhD, University of Rochester, 1972), pp. 93&#8211;104; <lb />
Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 58&#8211;68 [with variants; the text draws on a fair copy of the letter and not on the original version sent to May, which we publish here].</note>
        </head>
        <p rend="indent1">The year which I past at Corston<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">The school at Corston that Southey attended 1781&#8211;1782, run by Thomas Flower (d. 1799).</note> had been a mournful one for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref>. She lost my sweet little sister Louisa<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s sister, Louisa (1779&#8211;1782).</note> during that time, &amp; being after a while persuaded to accompany <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> to London, where she had never before been, they were recalled by the tidings of my grandmothers sudden death.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Hill, n&#233;e Bradford (1710&#8211;1782).</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> had found it expedient to <del>brexx</del> break up her establishment at Bath, &amp; pass some time in visiting among her friends. She now took up her abode at Bedminster, till family affairs were settled, &amp; till she could determine where &amp; how to fix herself. Thither also I was sent while <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my father</ref> was looking out for another school at which to place me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have so many vivid feelings connected with this house at Bedminster, that if it had not been in a vile neighbourhood<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mid-eighteenth-century Bedminster was a mixture of the rural and industrial.</note> I believe <del>th</del> my heart would have been set upon purchasing it &amp; fixing my abode there, where the happiest days of my childhood were past. My grandfather<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill (1705&#8211;1765), a lawyer from Bedminster and second husband of Margaret Hill.</note> built it (about the year 1740 I suppose) &amp; had made it what was then thought a thoroughly commodious &amp; good house, for one in his rank of life. It stood <del>upon a bye road</del> &lt;in a lane&gt; some 200 yards from the <del>begx</del> great western road. You ascended by several &lt;semi-circular&gt; steps into what was called the fore court, but was in fact a flower garden, with a broad pavement from the gate to the porch. That porch was in great part lined as well as covered, with jessamine; &amp; many a time have I sate there with my poor sisters,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEliza">Eliza Southey</ref> and Louisa Southey (1779&#8211;1782), who both died in infancy.</note> threading the fallen blossoms upon grass-stalks. It opened into a little hall, paved with diamond-shaped <del>stx</del> flags, on the right hand was the parlour, which had a <del>black</del> brown or black boarded floor <del>&amp; a Lis</del> covered with a Lisbon mat, &amp; a handsome time piece over the fire place. On the left was the best-kitchen, in which the family <del>alway</del> lived. The best-kitchen is an apartment <del>which</del> &lt;that&gt; <del>in now</del> belongs to other days, &amp; is now no longer to be seen except in houses which &lt;having&gt; remained unaltered for the last half century, are inhabited by persons a degree lower in society than their former possessors. The &lt;one&gt; which I am now calling to mind after an interval of forty years, was a chearful room, with an air of such <hi rend="ital">country</hi> comfort about it, that my little heart was always gladdened when I entered it, during my grandmothers life. It had a stone floor, which I believe <del>distinguished</del> &lt;was the chief distinction between&gt; a best-kitchen <del>from</del> &amp; a parlour. The furniture consisted of &lt;a clock&gt; a large oval oak table, with two flaps, over which three or four fowling-pieces had their place, a round tea table of cherry-wood, Windsor-chairs of the same, &amp; two large armed ones of that easy make (of all makes it is the easiest) &#8211; in one of which my grandmother always sate. On one side of the fire place the china was displayed in a beaufet &lt;(that is a cupboard with glass doors)&gt;, on the other were <del>cupboards</del> &lt;closets&gt; for articles less <del>sight</del> ornamental but more in use. <del>There were some old maps against</del> The sides of the room, which were wainscotted, were ornamented with some old maps, &amp; these with a long looking glass &lt;<del>in a white frame</del>&gt; over the fire place &lt;&amp; a tall one between the windows, both in white frames&gt;. The windows looked into the fore court, &amp; were as chearful &amp; fragrant in the season of flowers, as <del>xx</del> roses &amp; jessamine which grew luxuriantly without could make them. There was a passage between this apartment &amp; the kitchen, long enough to admit of a large airy pantry, &amp; a larder on the left hand, the windows of both opening into the <del>yard</del> &lt;barton&gt;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">A farmyard.</note>, as did those of the kitchen; here there was a rack well furnished with bacon, &amp; a misseltoe bush always suspended in the middle of the cieling.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The Green Room (which was my Uncle Edwards)<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Tyler (1744&#8211;1786), son of Margaret Hill by her first husband, William Tyler (1709&#8211;1747).</note> was over the parlour. Over the hall there was a smaller apartment which had been my Grandfathers office, &amp; still contained his desk &amp; his pigeon-holes. &#8211; I remember it well, &amp; the large patterned dark flock paper &lt;with its faded ground.&gt; The yellow Room over the best kitchen was the visitors room, &#8211; &amp; this my mother occupied whenever she slept there. There was no way to my Grandmothers &lt;(the Blue)&gt; room (over the kitchen) but thro this, &amp; an intervening passage where on the left, was a store-room. The Blue Room <del>looked</del> had a <del>dark &amp; dim</del> thorough light, one window looking into the barton, the other into a <del>paved</del> &lt;back&gt; court. The Squire<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tyler (1742&#8211;1789), son of Margaret Hill by her first husband, William Tyler (1709&#8211;1747).</note> slept in the garret, &#8211; his room was on one side, &#8211; the servants on the other, &amp; there was a large open space between, at the top of the stairs, used for lumber &amp; stores</p>
        <p rend="indent1">A door from the hall, opposite to the entrance, opened upon the cellar stairs, to which there was another door from the <del>paved</del> &lt;back&gt; court. This was a square having the house on two sides, the wash-house &amp; brew house on the third, &amp; walled on the fourth. A vine covered one side of the house here, &amp; grew round my grandmothers window, out of which I have often reached the grapes. &lt;The pigeon house was here &amp; the pump under which the fatal dippings were performed.&gt; The yard or barton was of considerable size, its entrance <del>xxx</del> was from the lane thro some large folding gates, with a horse chestnut on each side, &amp; here another building fronted you as large as the house, containing, the dairy, &amp; laundry, both large &amp; excellent in their kind, seed-rooms, stable, hay loft &amp;c &#8211; <del>My grandfather had kept an open carriage there was a shed for this &amp; for the cart, &amp; a horse block beautifully overhung with ivy, from an old wall against which it was placed</del>. The front of this outhouse was almost clothed with yew, clipt to the shape of the windows. At the one gable end were the coal &amp; stick houses. And on the left side of the barton was a shed for the cart &#8211; &amp; <del>for</del> while my Grandfather lived, for an open carriage, which after his death was no longer kept. Here too was the horse block beautifully overhung with ivy from an old wall against which it was placed. The other gable end was covered with fruit trees, &amp; at the bottom was a raised camomile bed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">An old fashioned birds-eye view, half picture, half plan would explain all this more intelligibly I fear than my description can do, &amp; if I had the skill I should delight in tracing one; &#8211; my memory would effectually serve. If I have made myself understood you will perceive that the <del>house had txxx front xxxxx xxx</del> paved court formed a square with the house. Behind both was a piece of waste ground left for the passage of carts from the barton to the orchard; but considerably wider than was necessary for the purpose. It was neatly kept in grass, with a good wide path from the <del>xxxx</del> court to the kitchen garden. This was large &amp; excellently stocked. It was walled off from the waste ground by a <del>low</del> wall about breast high surmounted with white rails, <del>as</del> far as the range of outhouses, &#8211; the back of these was covered with fruit trees &#8211; the green gages I remember were particularly excellent, one side was walled, &#8211; the other separated by a hedge from the lane leading to the orchard, &#8211; from which the garden was divided at the bottom.*<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;*&#8217; [Southey&#8217;s asterisk indicates the following insertion: &#8216;I have called &#8230; in abundance&#8217;. His note is in the left-hand margin of the manuscript letter. We have restored it to its place in his narrative.]</note> &lt;I have called it a kitchen garden because that name was given it, but it was ornamental as well as useful, with grass walks, espaliers, &amp; a profusion of fine flowers. The side of the house in the fore court also was covered with an apricot tree, so that every luxury of this kind which an English sun can ripen was there in abundance.&gt; Just by the <del>gate</del> orchard gate was a fine barberry bush, &amp; the peculiar odour of its blossoms is still fresh in my remembrance .*<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;X see p.8&#8217; [Southey adds a marginal note, to indicate that material found later in his letter should be inserted here: &#8216;Wordsworth &#8230; considerable size&#8217;.  This extra material is actually on p. 7 (not p. 8) of the manuscript letter. We have restored it to its place in his narrative.] </note> &lt;X &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> has no sense of smell. Once, &amp; only once in his life, the dormant power awakened, it was by a bed of stocks in full blossom, at a house which he inhabited in Dorsetshire, some five &amp; twenty years ago,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Racedown, Dorset, which Wordsworth occupied September 1795&#8211;June 1797.</note> &amp; he says it was like a vision of Paradise to him, but it lasted only a few minutes, &amp; the faculty has continued torpid from that time. The fact is remarkable in itself, &amp; would be worthy of notice, even if it did not relate to a man of whom posterity will desire to know all that can be remembered. He has often expressed to me his regret for this privation. I on the contrary possess the sense in such acuteness that I can remember an odour, &amp; call up the ghost of one that is departed. &#8211; But I must return to the barberry-bush. It stood at the entrance of a potatoe garden which had been taken from the orchard. The orchard was still of considerable size.&gt;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">At the bottom <del>of the orchard</del> was &lt;a broad wet ditch with&gt; a little drawbridge, leading into the fields, thro which was the pleasantest way to Church,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">St John the Baptist, Bedminster.</note> &amp; to Bristol. It was just one mile to Church &amp; two to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my fathers</ref> house in Wine Street.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">It was very seldom indeed that my Grandmother went to Bristol. I <del>do but</del> &lt;scarcely&gt; recollect ever to have seen her there. The extent of her walks was to Church, which she never missed, unless the weather absolutely confined her to the house: she was not able to <del>go</del> attend the evening service also, on account of the distance; but in the morning she was constant, &amp; always in time, &#8211; for if she were not there before the absolution she used to say that she ought as well have <del>sta</del> remained at home. At other times she rarely went out of her own premises. &lt;Neighbours of her own rank, there were none within her reach.&gt; Her husbands acquaintances had died off, &amp; she had made no new ones since his death. Her greatest happiness was to have my mother there &lt;with some of the young fry, &amp; we on our&gt; <del>who on her</del> part had no pleasure so great as that of a visit to Bedminster. It was indeed &lt;for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> as well as for us an advantage beyond all price&gt; <del>a great comfort</del> to have this quiet country <del>house</del> &lt;home&gt; at so easy a distance, &#8211; <del>a house too</del> abounding &lt;as it did&gt; with all country comforts. Bedminster itself was an ugly, dirty &lt;poor, populous&gt; village, &#8211; many of the inhabitants being colliers. But the coal pits were in a different part of the parish, &amp; the house was at a sufficient distance from all annoyances.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Coal was mined at Bedminster from the 1740s until the 1920s.</note> There was no beauty of situation, but great comfort: the view was merely to a field &amp; cottage (belonging to the property) <del>just a crx</del> on the other side the lane, <del>with a</del> on a rising ground, but the little world within was our own. And to me it was quite a different world from that in which I lived at other times. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">My fathers</ref> house was in one of the busyest &amp; noisyest streets of Bristol, &#8211; &amp; of course had no outlet. At Bath I was under perpetual restraint, &#8211; but here <del>there was</del> &lt;I had&gt; all wholesome liberty, all wholesome indulgence, all wholesome enjoyments, &amp; the delight which I there learnt to take in rural sights &amp; sounds has grown up with me, &amp; continues unabated to this day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My chief amusement was in the garden where I found endless entertainment in the flowers &amp; in observing insects. I had little fondness for any boyish sports, &amp; less expertness in them, &#8211; my Uncles Edward &amp; William used to reproach <del>xxx</del> me with this sometimes, saying they never saw such a boy.*<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;* see next page&#8217;. [Southey adds a marginal note, to indicate the insertion that follows, &#8216;*One &lt;schoolboys&gt; &#8230; as jet&#8217;, can be found on the fourth and fifth manuscript pages of the letter. We have restored it to its place in his narrative.]</note> &#8216;&lt;One &lt;schoolboys&gt; art however they taught me, which I have never read of, nor seen practised elsewhere, &#8211; it was that of converting a marble into a Black Witch, &amp; thereby making it lucky. You know that if a marble be put in the fire it makes a good detonating ball, &#8211; I have sacrificed many a one so to frighten the cook. But if the marble <del>were</del> &lt;be&gt; wrapt up in brown paper (perhaps any paper might do as well) with some suet, or dripping round about it, it will not explode while the fat is burning, &amp; when you take it out from the fire it is as black as jet&gt; A botanist or entomologist would have found me an apt pupil in those years, &amp; <del>perhaps</del> if I had fallen in with one, I might perhaps at this day have been classifying mosses, &amp; writing upon the natural history of <del>xxxxxxx</del> snails or cockchafers instead of recording the events of the Peninsular War.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> I <del>had</del> discovered that snails seal up their shells in winter, &amp; that ants make their way into the cockchafer thro an aperture in the breast, &amp; eat out its inside while it is yet alive. This gave me a great dislike to the ants &lt;which even the delightful papers about them in the Guardian did not overcome&gt;.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Guardian</title>, 156 (9 September 1713), 164&#8211;172; 157 (10 September 1713), 172&#8211;179. <title>The Guardian</title> (12 March-1 October 1713) was one of the few books in Southey&#8217;s home as a boy.</note> Two curious facts concerning these insects I well remember, &#8211; they spoilt the produce of some of our best currant trees one year, the trees were trained against a wall, these insects walked over them (I cannot tell why &#8211; but probably after the <hi rend="ital">aphides</hi>) &lt;whom as Kirby &amp; Spence tell us<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">William Kirby (1759&#8211;1850; <title>DNB</title>) and William Spence (c. 1783&#8211;1860; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Introduction to Entomology: or Elements of the Natural History of Insects: with Plates</title>, 4 vols (London, 1815&#8211;1826), II, pp. 88&#8211;91.</note> they regularly milked &amp; thus they&gt; imparted so rank a smell to the fruit that it could not be eaten. The ants were very numerous that season, &amp; this occasioned a war upon them. They made a high way thro the porch, along the interstices of the flag-stones &lt;the right of path as you may suppose was not acquiesced in,&gt; &amp; when this road was as full as Cheapside at noon day boiling water was poured upon it. The bodies however all disappeared in a few hours, &#8211; carried away as we supposed, by their comrades; but we know that <del>xx</del> some insects <del>have</del> are marvellously retentive of life, &amp; I have sometimes suspected that an Ant may derive no more injury from being boiled, than a fly from being bottled in Madeira, or a snail from &lt;having its head cut off or&gt; from lying seven years in a collectors cabinet. &#8211; Of the latter fact, (which was already authenticated)<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">See, for instance, <title>The Annual Register, or a View of the History, Politics and Literature, for the Year 1772</title> (London, 1773), pp. 89&#8211;91. </note> my neighbour M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fryer of Ormathwaite,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Harrison Fryer (1777&#8211;1855) of Whitley House, Northumberland. Fryer was a surveyor, geologist and mining engineer who spent part of each year at Keswick. At this time he was renting Ormathwaite, a large house about a mile and a quarter from Keswick.</note> had proof the other day.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">There are three flowers which to this day always remind me of Bedminster. The seringa or Roman Jessamine, which covered an arbour in the forecourt, &amp; another at the bottom of the kitchen garden: &#8211; the everlasting pea, which grew most luxuriantly under the best-kitchen windows, &amp; the evening primrose; &#8211; my Grandmother loved to watch the opening of this singularly delicate flower, <del>in the evening</del>, &amp; called it mortality, because in the briefness of its continuance it reminded her of human life. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The house was sold after her death, as soon as a purchaser could be found <del>for it</del>, &#8211; there being no longer the means for supporting it. Her loss was deeply felt by the two sons who lived with her, &#8211; &amp; indeed it was fatal to their happiness, for happy hitherto they had been, according to their own sense of enjoyment. The Squire was sent to board in a village on the coast of the Bristol Channel, called Worle, &#8211; &amp; Edward Tyler who was very capable of business, took a Clerks place at Bristol. But their stay was gone, &#8211; <del>they had</del> &amp; eventually I have no doubt that both their lives were shortened by the consequences<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">At this point Southey inserts a note, &#8216;A Merchant overleaf&#8217; on the right-hand side of the page to indicate that the narrative continues overleaf.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">A merchant who was engaged in the Slave Trade, Randolph<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">William Randolph (c. 1727&#8211;1791), Bristol merchant, of American origin. One of his main businesses had been transporting criminals to the Americas as a partner in the firm of Stevenson, Randolph and Cheston.</note> by name bought the house. Some years afterwards he sold it to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gee of Locks Mill,<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Gee (dates unknown), a Bristol merchant. Locks Mill House was on Parson Street, in Bedminster. The Gee family owned a brick and tile works in Vale Lane.</note> who had property in the neighbourhood; &amp; almost as soon as the sale had been completed, Gee died, &amp; Randolph hung himself. The widow Randolph<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Randolph, n&#233;e Little (1735&#8211;1811).</note> then applied to Gees son,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Captain George Gee (d. 1827), of Wraxall, Somerset, who was renting Ivy Cottage at Rydal. He seems to have played an important backstage role in organising the Lowther family&#8217;s election contests in Westmorland in 1818, 1820 and 1826.</note> expressing her desire to retain the property, &amp; appealing to his feelings. Accordingly he cancelled the deeds, &#8211; &amp; soon discovered that he had been called upon to do this because M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Randolph found she could get a larger price from a <del>Lady</del> &lt;M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cox&gt;<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">It is possible that these facts had become rather confused. At this time, the best-known family called &#8216;Cox&#8217; in Bedminster was headed by James Cox (1744&#8211;1797), who ran a tannery. After his death, his widow, Katherine Cox, n&#233;e Fitchew (1744&#8211;1816), continued to live in Bedminster and carried on the business.</note> who had taken a fancy to the house. I heard this lately from Gee, whom chance has brought to settle at the Lakes. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Cox still resides there. I went to look at the place <del>tw</del> some twenty years ago, &#8211; it was a good deal altered, &#8211; bow-windows had been thrown out in the front, &amp; a gazebo erected in the roof. After viewing about the front as much as I could without being thought impertinent, I <del>got fxx</del> made my way round into the fields, &amp; saw that the drawbridge was still in existence. <del>Twice since</del> I have seen the gazebo since from the window of a stage coach, &amp; this is probably the last view I shall ever have of a place so dear to me. <del>Th</del> Even the recollections of it will soon be confined to myself, &#8211; for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMary">my Aunt Mary</ref> are now the only living persons who partake them.</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="right">
            <date when="1823-01-08">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 8. 1823</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>