<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3952Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3952" type="letter">
        <head>3952. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1823-01-12">12 January 1823 </date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major-General Peachy/ 49. Albemarle Street/ London.<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 16 JN 16/ 1822<lb />
MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Unpublished.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-01-12">12 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">It gives us great pleasure to hear of your safe arrival in town, &#8211; after a journey, which was trying enough for your invalid<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons. His accident occurred on 2 August 1822 and was widely reported in the newspapers (without naming Henry): &#8216;A young gentleman, by way of saluting some friends who were taking their departure, fired off a cannon, which unfortunately burst in consequence of being overloaded, and the fragments severely fractured his skull&#8217; (<title>Glasgow Herald</title>, 12 August 1822). The cannon was kept outside Peachy&#8217;s house on Derwent Island and was fired as part of the annual Keswick Regatta.</note> to make us in some degree anxious for the result. There can now, I trust, be no reason to apprehend any farther inconvenience from the accident, tremendous as it was, than the trifling one of protecting the part. Regarding the case <del>it</del> in all its circumstances, it may truly be deemed a merciful preservation. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> may now be quite at ease, &#8211; &amp; ease of mind I hope will soon remove any ill effects which so long &amp; severe a trial has produced.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">For the first time, we were glad at your departure. After all that had passed, it was like a deliverance from a place of durance. And during the stormy season, there was a great gulph between us, which allowed of little communication between the Isle &amp; Continent. But had it not been that change of place was so desirable for you at that time, I should certainly have regretted that you went away just as the bad weather ceased, &#8211; for finer than we have enjoyed from that time up to the present <hi rend="ital">hour</hi>, was never remembered in these parts. Up to this hour I have said, because the first snow has just begun to fall. We had mild open weather till Christmas, &#8211; then a week of fine frost, &#8211; a thaw without rain &amp; with a clear sky, for two or three days, then <del>gentle frost</del> slight frost &amp; sunshine till this day. One morning fog is all we have seen of fogs, &#8211; &amp; that gave me some magnificent sights in <hi rend="ital">antejentacular</hi>
          <note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. walks before breakfast.</note> walks to the crag, where I witnessed its disappearance as the sun rose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The news of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> is that <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondsons</ref> brother<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> who was settled in America is dead, &amp; has left a considerable property among his relations here. <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondsons</ref> children,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmondson had at least two sons: John Edmondson (d. 1847), who took over his father&#8217;s practice in Keswick; and James Edmondson (1804&#8211;1873), also a surgeon, who moved to Tetbury, Gloucestershire, to practice.</note> it is said, have 500 &#163; each, besides what is left to the father. Every body rejoices at this. There is some talk of a new road to Penrith, which, if it is effected, will abolish the hill also on the Ambleside road. <ref type="m" target="people.html#LowtherWilliam">Lord Lowther</ref> is the mover in this business, &#8211; he brought M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>Adam<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Loudon McAdam (1756&#8211;1836; <title>DNB</title>), the pioneering road-builder and Surveyor-General of Metropolitan Roads from 1820. McAdam was employed to build a new road from Penrith through Keswick to Cockermouth (now the A66). His principal employer was Greenwich Hospital; he persuaded them to combine all the roads to their lead mines into a single turnpike trust, the Alston Trust.</note> here about six weeks ago, &#8211; &amp; is willing, I have heard, to contribute liberally toward the expence.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">The Kings</ref> acceptance of my first volume<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> has been notified to me by his command, &amp; he has been pleased to signify with his own hand, his approval of the very flattering terms in which it was conveyed.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 21 December 1822, Letter 3939. George IV had added &#8216;entirely approved &#8211; GR&#8217; to William Knighton&#8217;s letter of thanks for Southey&#8217;s presentation copy.</note> My daughter <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> covets this, as you may suppose, for her collection of hand writings. &#8211; The Whigs I hear wince at the character which I have given of them.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 3&#8211;61, contained a great deal of criticism of the Whigs for opposing war with France, especially at pp. 55&#8211;58.</note> They will wince more when the second volume appears, where I shall record their uniform opposition to all measures for the carrying [MS missing] contest, &amp; their uniform predictions of failure, disgrace &amp; ruin, [MS missing] persisted in it. Out of their own mouths will I condemn them.
               <ref type="m" target="people.html#PhillpottsHenry">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Philpotts</ref> has sent me his Letter to <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">Jeffrey</ref>,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Phillpotts, <title>Remarks on an Article in the Edinburgh Review, No. 64, Entitled &#8216;Necessity of Parliamentary Enquiry&#8217;</title> (1820). This was a reply to <title>Edinburgh Review</title>, 32 (October 1819), 441&#8211;453, itself a review of Phillpotts&#8217;s <title>A Letter to the Freeholders of the County of Durham, on the Proceedings of the County Meeting Holden on Thursday, 21st October Instant, and Particularly on the Speech of J. E. Lambton, Esq, M.P.</title> (1819).</note> &#8211; one could not desire a more compleat exposure of gross ignorance, impudent assertions, &amp; rascally misstatements, &#8211; the usual ingredients of an article in the Edinburgh Review. &#8211; By one of Alfreds laws, a public lyar &#8211; (that is a man who told lies upon public <del>subj</del> matters, &#8211; a political lyar) &#8211; was to have his tongue cut out.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey returned to this matter in <title>The Doctor</title>, 7 vols (1834&#8211;1847), VII, pp. 15&#8211;16. He quoted here &#8216;De Rumoribus Fictitiis&#8217; from Alfred&#8217;s Law Code, issued in the 890s by Alfred (847/849&#8211;899; King of Wessex 871&#8211;899; <title>DNB</title>).</note> The Whigs are fond of Alfred&#8217;s Laws, &#8211; if we had them in full force, the operation of this statute would spoil <ref type="m" target="people.html#JeffreyFrancis">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Jeffrey</ref> for an Advocate, &amp; effectually silence <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Brougham</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The Ladies<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> desire me to present their kind regards &#8211; I beg mine also to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henry<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">James Henry (1803&#8211;1884), the elder of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons.</note> &amp; his brother &#8211; Somewhere or other I shall hope to fall in with you in the month of April</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Farewell my Dear Sir</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">&amp; believe me</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">yrs with sincere regard</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>