<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3953Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3953Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3953" type="letter">
        <head>3953. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1823-01-19">19 January 1823&#8211;31 July 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 6p.<lb />
Previously edited or published: Michael Neill Stanton, &#8216;An Edition of the Autobiographical Letters of Robert Southey&#8217; (unpublished PhD, University of Rochester, 1972), pp. 121&#8211;133; <lb />
Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 80&#8211;91 [with variants; the text draws on a fair copy of the letter and not on the original version sent to May, which we publish here].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1823-01-19">Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 19. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">My home for the first two years while I was at Williams&#8217;s,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">William Williams (d. 1811), Southey&#8217;s schoolmaster at Merchants&#8217; Hall School, Bristol, 1782&#8211;1786.</note> was at <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my Fathers</ref>, except that during the holydays I was with <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref>, either when she had lodgings at Bath, or was visiting <ref type="m" target="people.html#PalmerMiss">Miss Palmer</ref> there. The first summer holydays I past with her at Weymouth, whither she was invited to join her friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#DolignonElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dolignon</ref>.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">This Lady whom I remember with the utmost reverence &amp; affection, was a widow with two children, Louisa<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A slip of the pen by Southey. Mrs Dolignon&#8217;s daughter was Marie (Mary) Dolignon (1769&#8211;1804), who married Philip Dauncey, K.C. (1759&#8211;1819). Southey had composed &#8216;Stanzas written after a long absence&#8217;, <title>Morning Post</title>, 20 October 1803, later retitled &#8216;To Mary&#8217;, to celebrate his intense friendship with Marie Dolignon. Her daughter was <ref type="m" target="people.html#DaunceyLouisa">Louisa Dauncey</ref>, who had visited Southey in 1818, and to whom Southey had written in 1819 to console her on the death of her father.</note> who was about four years elder than me, &amp; John<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Dolignon (1774&#8211;1856) attended Charterhouse and then Trinity College, Cambridge (BA 1797, MA 1800). He became a clergyman and was Rector of Wimbish in Essex 1816&#8211;1838 and Hilborough in Norfolk 1838&#8211;1856.</note> who was just my age. Her maiden <del>was</del> name was Delamare, she &amp; her husband<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Dolignon (d. 1776), a wine merchant of Mincing Lane, in the City of London.</note> being both of Refugee race,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The Delameres and Dolignons were both Huguenot families who had fled France after the end of toleration for Protestants in 1685.</note> &#8211; an extraction of which I should be far more proud than if my name was to be found in the roll of Battle Abbey.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A list of those families descended from Norman French knights who invaded England in 1066, formerly kept at Battle Abbey, the site of the Battle of Hastings. It was lost in the sixteenth century, though a number of incomplete copies survive.</note> I have heard how her husband in some delirium died by his own hand, &#8211; &amp; this perhaps <del>had b</del> may have broken her spirits, &amp; given a subdued &amp; somewhat pensive manner to one who was naturally the gentlest, meekest, kindest of human beings. I shall often have to speak of her in these letters. She had seen me at Bath in my earliest childhood. I had the good fortune then to obtain a place in her affections &#8211; &amp; that place I retained &#8211; even when she thought it necessary to estrange me from her family.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, who paints always with the finest touch of truth, whether he is describing external or internal nature, makes his Charoba disappointed at the first sight of the sea,</p>
        <lb />
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l rend="indent2">She coldly said, her long-lash&#8217;d eyes abased,</l>
          <l rend="indent2">&#8220;Is this the mighty Ocean? is this all?&#8221;</l>
        </lg>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">&amp; this he designs as characteristic of a &#8216;soul discontented with capacity.&#8217;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Gebir</title> (1798), Book 5, lines 136&#8211;137 and 139.</note> When I went on deck in the Coru&#241;a packet the first morning,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">When Southey sailed from Falmouth to Coru&#241;a in December 1795. His first full day at sea was 9 December.</note> &amp; for the first time found myself out of sight of land, the first feeling was certainly one of disappointment as well as surprize, at seeing myself in the centre of so small a circle. But the impression which the sea made upon me when I first saw it at Weymouth was very different, &#8211; probably because not having like Charoba thought of its immensity, <del>it filled me with wonder</del> &lt;I was at once made sensible of it&gt;. The sea seen from the shore is still to me the most impressive of all objects, &#8211; except the starry heavens: &amp; If I could live over any hours of my boyhood again, it should be those which I &lt;then&gt; spent upon the beach at Weymouth. One delightful day we past at Portland, &amp; another at Abbotsbury, where one of the few herneries in this kingdom was then existing, as perhaps it may still be.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The Benedictine monastery of St Peter&#8217;s at Abbotsbury, Dorset, managed a colony of mute swans on the Fleet Lagoon. The site was purchased by the Strangways family, later Earls of Ilchester, in the sixteenth century and remains in their ownership. The colony of swans is still maintained.</note> There was another at Penshurst,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">From the fourteenth century onwards, several large estates in England founded colonies of herons to provide food for the estate owner&#8217;s table. That at Penshurst Place in Kent was created in the early seventeenth century, in the beech trees near the keeper&#8217;s lodge, but it died out in the early nineteenth century. Heron started to fall out of fashion as a table bird in the late eighteenth century and maintained heronries had become rare by the 1820s, though one was founded at Ashton Hall in Lancashire as late as 1800&#8211;1810. Southey had visited Penshurst in June 1820 and at some time in his youth &#8211; an event recorded in &#8216;Inscription for a Tablet at Penshurst, the birthplace of Sir Philip Sidney&#8217;, <title>Morning Post</title>, 7 December 1798.</note> &amp; I have never seen a third. I wondered at nothing so much as the Chesil Bank which connects Portland, like the Firm-Island &lt;of Amadis&gt;<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">In <title>Amadis of Gaul</title> (1803), a medieval romance translated by Southey, Firm Island is a peninsula connected to Britain by a long, thin neck of land. It is the site of some of the major incidents in the romance.</note> with the mainland, the <del>pebbles</del> &lt;shingles&gt; of which it is formed <del>gx</del> gradually diminishing in size from one end to the other, till it became a sand bank. The spot which I recollect with most distinctness is the church yard of an old church<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">St Andrews Church at Church Ope Cove on the Isle of Portland. The church was ruinous from the 1750s.</note> &lt;in the Island&gt;, which from its neglected state, &amp; its situation near the cliffs, &amp; above all perhaps because so many shipwrecked bodies were interred there, impressed me deeply &amp; durably.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The first book which I ever possessed beyond the size of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Newburys gilt regiment<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Newbery (1713&#8211;1767; <title>DNB</title>) developed a series of books particularly aimed at being attractive to children. They often featured elements such as gilt and brightly-coloured covers made of paper.</note> was soon afterwards given me by <ref type="m" target="people.html#DolignonElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dolignon</ref>. It was Hooles Translation of Tasso&#8217;s Jerusalem.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hoole (1727&#8211;1803; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Jerusalem Delivered</title> (1783), a translation of Torquato Tasso (1544&#8211;1595), <title>Gerusalemme Liberata</title> (1581). Hoole&#8217;s book was no. 2778 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> She had heard me speak of it with a delight &amp; interest above my years. My curiosity to read the poem had been strongly excited by the stories of Olindo &amp; Sophronia,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">For instance, Abraham Portal (1726&#8211;1809; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Olinda and Sophronia: a Tragedy</title> (1758), a play derived from episodes in <title>Gerusalemme Liberata</title>, especially the rescue of the lovers Olinda and Sophronia by the warrior-maiden Clorinda.</note> &amp; in the Enchanted Forest as versified by M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rowe.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Rowe (1674&#8211;1737; <title>DNB</title>), &#8216;The Enchanted Forest&#8217;, a poem derived from <title>Gerusalemme Liberata</title>, Book 18, published in <title>Friendship in Death: in Twenty Letters from the Dead to the Living. To Which are Added Letters Moral and Entertaining in Prose and Verse</title> (1734), Part III, pp. 25&#8211;31.</note> I had read these in the volume of her letters, &amp; despaired at the time of ever reading more of the poem till I should be a man from a whimsical notion that as the subject related to Jerusalem the original must be in Hebrew. No one in <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my fathers</ref> house could set me right upon this point, but going one day with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> into a shop one <del>xxxx</del> &lt;side&gt; of which was filled up with a circulating library containing not more than 3 or 400 volumes almost all <del>of which were</del> novels, I there laid my hand upon Hooles version a little before my visit to Weymouth. The copy which <ref type="m" target="people.html#DolignonElizabeth">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dolignon</ref> sent me is now in my sight, upon the shelf, &amp; in excellent preservation considering that when a schoolboy I perused it so often, that I had no small portion of it by heart. Forty years have tarnished the gilding upon its back, but they have not effaced my remembrance of the joy with which I received it, &amp; the delight which I found in its repeated perusal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">During the years that I resided in Wine Street I was upon a short allowance of books. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">My father</ref> read nothing except Felix Farley&#8217;s Bristol Journal.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Felix Farley&#8217;s Bristol Journal</title> (1752&#8211;1853), a weekly local newspaper.</note> A small glass-cupboard over the desk in the back parlour held his wine glasses &amp; &#8211; all his library. It consisted of the Spectator;<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Spectator</title> (1711&#8211;1712), a daily newspaper, later collected in seven volumes.</note> three or four volumes of the Oxford Magazine,<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Oxford Magazine: or, Universal Museum</title> (1768&#8211;1776). There were thirteen volumes in all.</note> one of the Freeholders,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Freeholder&#8217;s Magazine, or, Monthly Chronicle of Liberty</title> (1769&#8211;1770).</note> &amp; one of the Town &amp; Country,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Town and Country Magazine</title> (1769&#8211;1796), a monthly publication that focused on society scandals.</note> &#8211; these he had taken in during the Wilkes-&amp;-Liberty Epidemic.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wilkes (1725&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>), the radical politician. In 1768&#8211;1769 there was a huge furore over whether the House of Commons could prevent his return as MP for Middlesex.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother Tom</ref> &amp; I spoilt them by <del>pri</del> colouring, that is to say, bedaubing the prints: but I owe to them some knowledge of the political wit, warfare &amp; scandal of those days, &amp; from one of them that excellent poem <del>of</del> &#8220;the Old Batchelor&#8221; was cut out which I reprinted in the Annual Anthology.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The Old Batchelor&#8217;, <title>Annual Anthology</title>, 2 vols (Bristol, 1799&#8211;1800), II, pp. 176&#8211;183. Southey reprinted these verses from <title>The Town and Country Magazine</title>, 3 (March 1771), 158&#8211;160. The poem was anonymous, but the author was Henry Mackenzie (1745&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>).</note> The other books were Pomfrets Poems;<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">John Pomfret (1667&#8211;1702; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Miscellany Poems on Several Occasions</title> (1702).</note> &lt;the death of Abel,&gt;<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Collyer (c. 1716&#8211;1763; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Death of Abel</title> (1761), a translation of Salomon Gessner (1730&#8211;1788), <title>Der Tod Abels</title> (1758).</note> Aaron Hills translation of Merope, the Jealous Wife &amp; Edgar &amp; Emmeline<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">Aaron Hill (1685&#8211;1750; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Merope</title> (1749), a translation of Francois-Marie Arouet [Voltaire] (1694&#8211;1778), <title>La M&#233;rope Fran&#231;aise</title> (1744); George Colman, the Elder (1732&#8211;1794; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Jealous Wife</title> (1761); John Hawkesworth (c. 1715&#8211;1773), <title>Edgar and Emmeline: a Fairy Tale</title> (1761). All were popular plays.</note> in one volume; Julius Caesar, the Toy Shop, All for Love, &amp; a pamphlett upon the Quack Doctors of George 2<hi rend="sup">ds</hi> days in another:<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">William Shakespeare, <title>Julius Caesar</title> (1599); Robert Dodsley (1703&#8211;1764; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Toy Shop: a Dramatick Satire</title> (1735); John Dryden (1631&#8211;1700; <title>DNB</title>), <title>All for Love, or, the World Well Lost</title> (1677); the pamphlet from the reign of George II (1683&#8211;1760; King of Great Britain 1727&#8211;1760; <title>DNB</title>) is unidentified.</note> the Vestal virgins, the Duke of Lerma &amp; the Indian Queen<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Howard (1626&#8211;1698; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Vestal Virgin: or, The Roman Ladies. A Tragedy</title> (1665), <title>The Great Favourite, or the Duke of Lerma</title> (1668) and <title>The Indian Queen</title> (1665) &#8211; the latter play was co-written with John Dryden.</note> in a third. To these <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> had added the Guardian,<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Guardian</title> (12 March&#8211;1 October 1713).</note> &amp; the happy copy of M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Rowes Letters which introduced me to Torquato Tasso.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The holydays made amends for this penury, &amp; Bulls Circulating Library<note n="30" place="foot" resp="editors">Bull&#8217;s Circulating Library in Lower Walks, Bath, run by Lewis Bull (c. 1732&#8211;1807).</note> was then to me what the Bodleian would be now. Hoole in his notes frequently referred to the Orlando Furioso.<note n="31" place="foot" resp="editors">Ludovico Ariosto (1474&#8211;1533), <title>Orlando Furioso</title> (1516), a continuation of Matteo Maria Boiardo (1440&#8211;1494), <title>Orlando Innamorato</title> (1495).</note> I saw some volumes thus lettered on Bulls counter, &amp; my heart leaped for joy. They proved to be the original: &#8211; but the shopman poor Cruett<note n="32" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> (a most obliging man he was) immediately put the translation into my hand, &amp; I do not think any accession of fortune could now give me so much delight as I then derived from that vile version of Hooles.<note n="33" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hoole, <title>Orlando Furioso: Translated from the Italian of Ludovico Ariosto</title> (1783).</note> There in the notes I first <del>saw</del> saw the name of Spenser, &amp; some stanzas of the Faery Queen.<note n="34" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Spenser (1552/1553&#8211;1599; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Faerie Queene</title> (1590&#8211;1596).</note> Accordingly when I returned the last volume, I asked if they had that book in the library. My friend Cruett replied that they had, but it was written in old English &amp; I should not be able to understand it. This did not appear to me so much a matter of course as he supposed <del>it</del>, &amp; I therefore requested that he would let me look at it. It was the quarto edition in three volumes,<note n="35" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Faerie Queene. By Edmund Spenser. With an Exact Collation of the Two Original Editions</title> (1751). It contained 32 copper plates by William Kent (1685&#8211;1748; <title>DNB</title>).</note> with large prints folded in the middle, equally worthless (like all the prints of that age) in design &amp; execution. There was nothing in the language to impede me, for the ear set me right where the uncouth spelling might have misled the eye, &amp; the few words which are really obsolete were sufficiently explained by the context. No young lady of the present generation falls to a new novel of <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Sir W Scotts</ref> with keener relish, than I did that morning to the Faery Queen. If I had then been asked why it gave me so much more pleasure than even Ariosto had done I could not have answered the question. I now know that &lt;it was&gt; very much by the magic of its verse: &#8211; the contrast between the flat couplets of a rhymester like Hoole, &amp; the fullest &amp; finest of all stanzas<note n="36" place="foot" resp="editors">The Spenserian stanza of eight lines of iambic pentameter and a concluding alexandrine.</note> written by one who was perfect master of his art. But this was not all. Ariosto too often plays with his subject. Spenser is always in earnest. The delicious landscapes which he luxuriates in describing brought every thing before my eyes. I could fancy such scenes as his lakes &amp; forests &lt;gardens&gt; &amp; fountains presented; &amp; I felt tho I did not understand the truth &amp; purity of his feelings, &amp; that love of the beautiful &amp; the good which pervades his poetry.
               When <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> had lived about among her friends as long as it was convenient for them to entertain her, &amp; longer in lodgings than was convenient for herself, she began to think of <del>enquiring</del> &lt;looking out&gt; for a house at Bristol: &amp; owing to an odd accident I was the means of finding one which precisely suited her. M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wraxall,<note n="37" place="foot" resp="editors">Anne Wraxall, n&#233;e Thornhill (d. 1800), the widow of Nathaniel Wraxhall (1725&#8211;1781), Bristol merchant.</note> the widow of a lawyer, had heard I know not how that I was a promising boy greatly addicted to books, &amp; she sent to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyMargaret">my mother</ref> requesting that I might drink tea with her one evening. The old Lady was mad as a march-hare, <del>but</del> after a religious fashion. Her &lt;behaviour to me&gt; was very kind <del>to me</del>, but as soon as tea was over, she bade me kneel down, &amp; down she knelt herself, &amp; prayed for me by the hour, to my aweful astonishment. When this was over she gave me a little book called Early Piety,<note n="38" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly <title>Early Piety: or, An Example for Young Children</title> (c. 1740&#8211;1770), a much-reprinted chapbook of eight pages.</note> &amp; a coarse edition of Paradise Lost:<note n="39" place="foot" resp="editors">John Milton (1608&#8211;1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Paradise Lost</title> (1667).</note> &amp; <del>she</del> said she was going to leave Bristol. It struck me immediately that the house which she was about to quit <del>would</del> was such a one as <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> wanted. I said so, &amp; M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Wraxall immediately answered tell her that if she likes it she shall have the remainder of my lease. The matter was settled in a few days, for it was an advantageous offer. The house would have been cheap at twenty pounds a year at that time, &amp; there was an unexpired lease of five years upon it at only eleven. This old Lady was mother to Sir Nathaniel Wraxall<note n="40" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Nathaniel Wraxall, 1st Baronet (1751&#8211;1831; <title>DNB</title>), a servant of the East India Company, traveller, writer and MP for Hindon 1780&#8211;1784, Ludgershall 1784&#8211;1790 and Wallingford 1790&#8211;1794.</note> who had been bred up &amp; perhaps born in that habituation. The owner was poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">John Morgans</ref> father.<note n="41" place="foot" resp="editors">John Morgan (d. 1806), a Bristol wine merchant and Unitarian.</note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wraxall <del>x</del> many years before had taken it upon &lt;at&gt; a low rent upon a repairing lease, &amp; had expended a great deal of money upon it, at a time when it was a suburban residence. The situation had been greatly worsened, <del>a row of pelting houses having been built just above</del> but it was still on the skirts of the city &amp; out of reach of its noise.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">It stood in the avenue leading from Maudlin Lane to Horfield Lane. When the plan of Bristol for Barretts wretched history of that city<note n="42" place="foot" resp="editors">William Barrett (1727&#8211;1789; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History and Antiquities of the City of Bristol: Compiled from Original Records and Authentic Manuscripts, in Public Offices or Private Hands; Illustrated with Copper-Plate Prints</title> (Bristol, 1789), no. 177 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. The large folding map is unpaginated.</note> was engraved, the buildings ended with Maudlin Lane, &amp; all above was fields &amp; gardens. The plan is dated 1780, but must <del>certainly</del> have been engraved at least 10 years earlier for it marks S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Leonards Church which was pulled down in the beginning of 1771.<note n="43" place="foot" resp="editors">St Leonards was a medieval church that stood over the Westgate to the city. It was demolished as it blocked one of the city&#8217;s main thoroughfares.</note>
          <del>In the plan</del> the avenue is marked &lt;there&gt; by the name of Red Coat Lane, &#8211; running up between fields &amp; with a hedge at each side. It was now however known by the name of Terril Street. There were at the bottom, when the plan was taken four of five houses on the left hand, &#8211; built like the commencement of a street. Where these ended the ascent, which was steep began, &amp; some houses followed which tho contiguous, stood each in its little garden, some <del>forty or fifty feet</del> &lt;30 <del>30</del> yards&gt; back from the street. There were five of these, &amp; the situation was such that they must have in good estimation before some speculator instead of building a sixth erected a cross row of five or six inferior dwellings, &#8211; above <del>which</del> these there was only a steep paved avenue between high walls, inaccessible for horses because there were some flights of steps. The view was to a very large garden opposite, &#8211; one of those which supplied the market with fruit &amp; other vegetables.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The house upon which <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> now entered was small, but chearful. Sir Nathaniel would perhaps remember it with disdain, but to his father it had evidently been an object of pride &amp; pleasure. As is usual in suburban gardens he had made the most of the ground. Tho no wider than the front of the house there was a walk paved with lozenge shaped stones from the gate, &amp; two <del>side</del> gravel walks: the side beds were allotted to currants &amp; gooseberry bushes, the others <del>beds to</del> were flower beds, &amp; there were two large apple trees, &amp; two smaller ones. In front of the house the pavement extended, under which was an immense cistern for rain water; so large as to be absurd, <del>xxx</del> it actually seemed fitter for a fort, than for a small private family. The kitchen was underground. On one side the gate was a summer house, with a sort of cellar &amp; another cistern below it: on the other a <hi rend="ital">Commodit&#233; orn&#233;e</hi>,<note n="44" place="foot" resp="editors">Literally an &#8216;ornate amenity&#8217; i.e. an outside toilet of ornate design.</note> corresponding with it in size &amp; structure, except that it had not a bow window projecting over the street.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">As soon as <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my aunt</ref> was settled here she sent for her brother William,<note n="45" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tyler (1742&#8211;1789), son of Southey&#8217;s grandmother, Margaret Hill (1710&#8211;1782), by her first husband, William Tyler (1709&#8211;1747).</note> who since his mothers death had been boarded at a substantial shopkeepers in the little village of Worle, on the channel about 20 miles from Bristol. I look back upon his inoffensive &amp; monotonous course of life with a compassion which then I was not capable of feeling. For one or two years he walked into the heart of the city &#8211; every Wednesday &amp; Saturday to be shaved, &amp; to purchase his <del>own</del> tobacco &lt;he also went to the theatre sometimes &amp; enjoyed it highly&gt;: on no other occasion did he ever leave the house; &amp; as inaction, aided no doubt by the inordinate use of tobacco &amp; the quantity of small beer with which he swilled his inside brought on a premature old age, even this exercise was left off. As soon as he rose &amp; had taken his first pint of beer, which was his only breakfast, to the summerhouse he went, &amp; took his station in the bow window, as regularly as a sentinel in a watch box. There it was his whole &amp; sole employment to look at the few people who past, &amp; &lt;to&gt; watch the neighbours, with all <del>thos</del> whose concerns at last he became perfectly intimate by what he could there oversee &amp; overhear. &lt;He had a nickname for every one of them&gt; In the evenings <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">my Aunt</ref> &amp; I generally played at five card loo with him,<note n="46" place="foot" resp="editors">A card game in which players were dealt five cards and attempted to win tricks in order to gain a share of a pool of money contributed by all the players.</note> &#8211; at which he took an intense interest; &amp; if in the middle of the day when I came home to dinner he could get me to play at marbles <del>with him</del> in the summer house, he was <del>xxxxxx</del> &lt;delighted&gt;. The <del>great events</del> points to which he looked on &lt;in the week&gt; were the two mornings when Joseph<note n="47" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified beyond the information given here.</note> came to shave him, for this poor journeyman barber felt a sort of compassionate regard for him, &amp; he had an insatiable appetite for such news as the barber could communicate. <del>And</del> Thus his days past <del>with</del> &lt;in&gt; wearisome uniformity he had no other amusement, &#8211; unless in listening to hear a comedy read; &#8211; <del>in himself</del> he had not &lt;in himself&gt; a single resource for whiling away the time, &amp; thus being utterly without an object for the present or the future, his thoughts were perpetually recurring to the past. His affections were strong &amp; lasting, indeed at his mothers funeral<note n="48" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Hill, n&#233;e Bradford (1710&#8211;1782).</note> his emotions were such as to affect all who were present. That grief he felt to the day of his death. I have seen tears in his eyes also when he spoke of my sisters,<note n="49" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEliza">Eliza Southey</ref> and Louisa Southey (1779&#8211;1782).</note> both having died just at that age when he had most delight in fondling them, &amp; they were most willing to be fondled. Whether it might have been possible to have awakened him to devotional feelings may be doubted; <del>however</del> &lt;but&gt; he believed, &amp; trusted, simply &amp; implicitly, &amp; more, assuredly would not be required from one to whom so little had been given.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">He lived about four years after this removal. His brother Edward<note n="50" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Tyler (1744&#8211;1786), son of Margaret Hill by her first husband, William Tyler (1709&#8211;1747).</note> died a year before him, of pulmonary consumption. This event affected him deeply, he attended the funeral, described the condition of the coffins in the family vault,<note n="51" place="foot" resp="editors">The Hill family vault at All Saints Church, Long Ashton.</note> in a manner which I well remember, &amp; said that his turn would be next. One day on my return from school at the dinner hour, going into the summer house, &lt;I found him sitting in the middle of the room, &amp; looking wildly:&gt; he <del>hxxx</del> told me he had been very ill, that he had had a seizure in the head, such as he had never felt before, &amp; that he was sure something very serious ailed him. I gave the alarm, but it past over, neither he himself nor any person in the house knew what such a seizure indicated, &amp; no apprehension of danger was entertained. The next morning he rose as usual, walked downstairs into the kitchen, &amp; as he was buttoning the knees of <del>xx</del> his breeches, exclaimed Lord have mercy upon me! &amp; fell from the chair. His nose was bleeding when he was taken up; immediate assistance was procured, but he was dead before it arrived. The stroke was mercifully sudden, but it had been preceded by a long &lt;&amp; gradual) diminution of vital strength, &amp; I have never known any other case in which when there were so few external appearance of disease or decay, the individual was so aware that his dissolution was approaching.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I often regret that my memory should have retained so few of the traditional tales &amp; proverbial expressions which I heard from him, more certainly than from all other persons in the course of my life. Some of them have been lately recalled to my recollection by Grimms Collection.<note n="52" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacob Ludwig Karl Grimm (1785&#8211;1863) and Wilhelm Karl Grimm (1786&#8211;1859), <title>Kinder-und Hausm&#228;rchen</title> (1812), translated as <title>German Popular Stories</title> (1823) by Edgar Taylor (1793&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>).</note> What little his mind <del>had</del> &lt;was capable of&gt; receiving it had retained tenaciously, &amp; of these things it had a rich store. His death involved <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> in a vexatious litigation with her only surviving brother of the whole blood.<note n="53" place="foot" resp="editors">John Tyler (dates unknown). Elizabeth Tyler also had two half-brothers from her mother&#8217;s second marriage to Edward Hill (1705&#8211;1765): Herbert Hill and Joseph Hill (dates unknown).</note> My poor Uncle William for a year or two before frequently <del>pr</del> wrote his name &#8211; (which was all he could write,) by way of practising before he &lt;was to&gt; sign<del>ed</del> a will, which it was intended he should make to prevent this claim upon his little property. This necessary business was put off till it was too late. All that he had was in <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">his sisters</ref> hands: morally it ought upon his demise to have been hers, &amp; actually she was unable to pay the half which John Tyler demanded. A suit was instituted against her, which was terminated by his death. His latter years had been the only unreproachable part of his life. A kinsman &lt;(father of that D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lamb who proscribed meat &amp; drink)&gt;<note n="54" place="foot" resp="editors">William Lambe (1765&#8211;1847, <title>DNB</title>) recommended a vegetarian diet and the drinking of distilled water. His father was Lacon Lambe (1728&#8211;1807), of Henwood, Dilwyn, who had married Elizabeth Tyler, sister of William Tyler (1709&#8211;1747).</note> had recovered his half pay for him from the Jews, &amp; upon that pittance he lived, inhabiting a small cottage in the village of Dilwyn, within a hundred yards of that Mansion house which <del>would but</del> but for his own improvidence &amp; prodigality he would have inherited.<note n="55" place="foot" resp="editors">John Tyler had been an Army officer during the Seven Years War 1756&#8211;1763. His action in selling his right to his half-pay was not legal and so was easily quashed. He seems to have lived in a cottage near to the Great House, Dilwyn, Herefordshire, which he might have hoped to inherit from his uncle, John Tyler (1703&#8211;1737), who had died childless. </note> Upon his death <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Miss Tyler</ref> became the sole survivor of <del>the family</del> her paternal race.</p>
        <lb />
        <closer>
          <date when="1823-07-31">July 31. 1823</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>