<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3955</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3955Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3955" type="letter">
        <head>3955. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1823-01-21">21 January 1823</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: 231./ 1823/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> January/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March<lb />
MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 3p.<lb />
Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 199&#8211;200.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-01-21">21 Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Here is another biographical letter<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John May, 10&#8211;19 January 1823, Letter 3951.</note> for you, following more closely on the last than you have had any reason from experience to expect. The truth is, that looking at the respectable bulk which my transcript of these recollections begins to assume, I feel a little of what the money-lover feels when he regards the accumulation of his wealth, &amp; am <del>xxx</del> encouraged therefore to go on. Moreover as the recollections of my intellectual life are opening upon me, there is an additional interest in proceeding.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The strong beer is arrived, for which I have sung O be Joyful.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Psalm</title> 100: 1, a great favourite with evangelicals.</note> I have some thoughts of composing an heroic ode thereon, in opposition to the &#7940;&#961;&#953;&#963;&#964;&#959;&#957; &#956;&#8050;&#957; &#8021;&#948;&#969;&#961; of Pindar<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Pindar (c. 522&#8211;c. 443 BC), <title>Olympian</title> 1, line 1, &#8216;Water is best&#8217;.</note> &#8211; which proposition, I think, contains an abominable heresy. Remember that you are to come &amp; drink part of it; &#8211; &amp; that sundry things in this neighbourhood have been left unseen.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have not heard a word from <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> since the publication of my book,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &#8211; &amp; <del>xx</del> very little from other quarters. <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> sent me yesterday a letter of <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbbotCharles">Lord Colchesters</ref> concerning it, &#8211; in the highest terms of praise, &#8211; objecting only to what I do not consider objectionable; the full detail of events at Bayonne.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 206&#8211;236, detailing how Charles IV (1748&#8211;1819; King of Spain 1788&#8211;1808) and his son, Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833), were coerced into renouncing their claims on the Spanish throne.</note> I think you will read the Portugueze chapters with interest, these chapters particularly contain such damning proofs of the villainy of the French as must shame <del>xx</del> some of their admirers, if it does not silence them. &#8211; I am getting on with the second volume, tho it cannot go to press till <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> gets me some books concerning the war in Catalonia.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your good mother<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary May, n&#233;e Coppendale (1745&#8211;1824).</note> I trust is well recovered, tho this weather (if it be as inclement with you as it is here) is trying for the aged &amp; infirm. We have been covered with snow now for nine days &#8211; which is very unusual in this valley &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The Cortes have acted absurdly in requiring an oath from the Q of Portugal.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte (1775&#8211;1830), wife of John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826). Charlotte was an extreme reactionary and opposed the liberal Constitution to which John VI had agreed in October 1822. After she refused to swear an oath to the new Constitution she was confined to the convent of Ramalh&#227;o, near Sintra. As Charlotte was actively involved in politics and took a major part in an attempted coup in 1824, liberals were hardly acting &#8216;absurdly&#8217; in their suspicions of the Queen.</note> I am afraid their egregious folly with regard to Brazil may in its consequences be injurious to you,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The new Portuguese Constitution drafted in 1822 was unacceptable to most Brazilians and led directly to Brazil&#8217;s declaration of independence on 7 September 1822. Portuguese troops in Brazil fought an ineffective campaign against the pro-independence forces until they were finally defeated in 1824. Some of the most intense fighting was in the north-eastern province of Bahia.</note> &#8211; otherwise its evils are likely to be confined to Bahia, &amp; want of money must bring the contest on their part to an end. Neither in Spain or Portugal do I see any thing hopeful in prospect, &#8211; nor can I indeed tell what to wish for in either country.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">There had been a liberal revolution in Spain as well as in Portugal in 1820; both countries had adopted constitutions and both were riven by internal conflict.</note> Poor countries, they needed change God knows! but long, very long will it be before they experience any good from the issue, &#8211; &amp; the evils of the process are likely to continue much longer than you &amp; I shall live to witness them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We are all well at present thank God. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your God-daughter</ref> busy as a bee &amp; joyous as a lark: the little girls<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate Southey</ref>.</note> praying for a continuance of frost that they may not be deprived of their sliding, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> still determined upon being an Archbishop. They all send their kindest remembrances &#8211; present mine to your fireside &#8211; &amp; believe me</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yours most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">R. Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>