<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3968Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3968" type="letter">
        <head>3968. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-02-23">23 February 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer./ Westminster<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 26 FE 26/ 1823<lb />
Endorsement: 23. Feb<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> 1823<lb />
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 136&#8211;138 [in part].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-02-23">23 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Your letter comes in aid of a purpose which I had entertained of putting together what I have said upon the Catholic question in the Ed. An. Register, re-casting it, &amp; publishing it with some needful additions, in the form of a pamphlett.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not publish this pamphlet, but <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title>, 1.1 (1810), 7&#8211;12, 104&#8211;132, and <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title>, 4.1 (1813), 115&#8211;139, were eventually recast and published in <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), II, as Essays XI and XII, &#8216;On the Catholic Question&#8217;, pp. [277]&#8211;328. Southey was totally opposed to equal political rights for Catholics.</note> About a week ago I put down in my note-book the first sketch of an arrangement; &amp; actually began to <del>piece or compose xxx fragments which</del> compose what I have to say, <del>in fox</del> as a letter to some M.P. Not that it was meant to be addressed to any individual one; but having argued with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WilberforceWilliam">Wilberforce</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir Thomas Acland</ref> upon this subject,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Edith Southey, 28 April 1817, <title>Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Five</title>, Letter 2981.</note> I knew in what light they considered it. The course which affairs have taken in Ireland<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">There was persistent unrest in rural Ireland 1821&#8211;1824.</note> will probably have the good effect of quashing the question for this year; &amp; in that hope I am willing to postpone my own purpose till a season which may be more convenient to myself, &amp; when aid of this kind may be more needed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The arguments lie in a nutshell. The <del>law</del> &lt;restraints&gt; which exclude<del>s</del> the Catholics from political power<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The Test Act (1673) confined public office to communicants of the Church of England.</note>
          <del>xx</del> &lt;are&gt; not the cause of the perpetual disorders in Ireland, &#8211; their removal therefore cannot be the cure. Suppose the question carried, two other grow from it, &#8211; like two heads from the hydras neck when one is amputated: &#8211; a Catholic establishment for Ireland, at which Irish Catholics <hi rend="ital">must</hi> aim, &amp; which those who desire rebellion &amp; separation will promote, &#8211; a rebellion must be the sure consequence of agitating this. The people in Ireland care nothing for the Emancipation, &#8211; why the Devil should they? but make it a question for restoring the Catholic Church, &amp; they will enter into it as zealously as ever our ancestors did into a crusade.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The other question arises as home, &amp; brings with it worse consequences than any thing which can happen among the potatoes. The repeal of the Test Act will be demanded, &amp; must be granted. Immediately the Dissenters will get into the Corporations &#8211; every where: <hi rend="ital">their</hi> members will be returned; men as hostile to the Church &amp; to the Monarchy as ever were the Puritans of Charles&#8217;s age;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles I (1600&#8211;1649; King of Great Britain 1625&#8211;1649; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &#8211; the Church property will <del>then</del> be attacked in Parliament, as it is now at mob-meetings, &amp; in radical newspapers: reform in Parliament will be carried, &#8211; &amp; then &#8211; farewell a long farewell to all our greatness. &#8211; I, who see what is coming, shall have time to determine whether I will quit the kingdom, or stay in it &amp; be hanged: &#8211; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> will either lose his senses or break his heart at the miserable consequences of his own infatuation.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Wynn favoured Catholic Emancipation.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">My belief is that if we can stave off this question &amp; that of reform for the next ten years, the country will be tired of both, especially as it becomes prosperous &#8211; And if those who think rightly will exert themselves in Parliament, &amp; out of Parliament, I, for one, will do my duty strenuously &amp; perseveringly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Our constitution consists of Church &amp; State, &amp; it is an absurdity in politics to give those persons power in the <hi rend="ital">state</hi>, whose duty it is to subvert the <hi rend="ital">Church</hi>. This argument is unanswerable. &#8211; I am in good hopes that my Book of the Ch.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> will do yeomans service upon the question.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Thank you for the Cup &#8211; which I shall be very proud of. I shall call it <hi rend="ital">the Bedford-cup</hi>, &amp; endeavor to believe that Benvenuto Cellini<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Benvenuto Cellini (1500&#8211;1571), Italian sculptor. Bedford possessed a glass cup of which he was immensely proud and which he believed to be the work of Cellini. He had ordered a copy to be made for Southey.</note> was the sculptor who made it. Pray get it packed &amp; send it me with &#8220;<hi rend="ital">glass</hi>&#8221; written on it &amp; moreover &#8220;<hi rend="ital">with care</hi>&#8221;. the mail from <ref type="m" target="places.html#BullandMouth">the Bull &amp; Mouth</ref> will be a safer conveyance that the wagon, because it will go upon springs.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have not time to enter upon the question of Spain<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">In Spain the liberal Constitution of 1812 had been restored by a military revolt in 1820. France was preparing to invade Spain to restore royal absolutism and the Whigs were urging the government to pressurise France not to intervene.</note> only I must remark, that foreign ambassadors would be doing us a great service, as well as discharging their own duty, if they required our Government to prosecute such language as <ref type="m" target="people.html#BroughamHenryPeter">Broughams</ref> against their respective sovereigns<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Brougham&#8217;s speech in the House of Commons on 4 February 1823 had strongly criticised Frederick William III (1770&#8211;1840; King of Prussia 1797&#8211;1840), Francis I (1768&#8211;1835; Holy Roman Emperor 1792&#8211;1806, Emperor of Austria 1804&#8211;1835) and Alexander I (1777&#8211;1825; Emperor of Russia 1801&#8211;1825) for advocating the suppression of the constitutional regime in Spain. Brougham was particularly critical of Alexander I, whom he strongly implied had conspired in the assassination of his father, Paul (1754&#8211;1801; Emperor of Russia 1796&#8211;1801), in order to gain the throne.</note> &#8211; when it gets into the newspapers. Half the provincial papers might be silenced by attacking them on this ground, &#8211; I do not mean for what is given as a report of the debates, &#8211; but for the tone which they take from such speakers.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>