<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3969</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3969Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3969" type="letter">
        <head>3969. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-02-24">24 February 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
Stamped: [illegible]<lb />
Postmarks: 10 FNOON 10/ FE 27/ 1823; [partial] 1823<lb />
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 227. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-02-24">24 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> mentioned in his last letter that he was uneasy about his eldest boy;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817). Henry Herbert Southey was possibly worried about consumption; his father-in-law William Gonne had died from this in 1815.</note> indeed he was not without uneasiness on that account when he was here in the autumn. I was not aware that any of the others manifested symptoms of this unhappy taint, but I have always felt an uncomfortable apprehension concerning it, &amp; that apprehension was expressed to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> as something which he would do well to consider before he made up his mind respecting the marriage. &#8211; I am truly grieved at it</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I shall not be in town till the end of April,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In fact, Southey did not leave Keswick until 3 November 1823.</note> having to finish the B. of the Church,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> before my departure, &amp; also a paper for the QR (which is very nearly compleated)<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), &#8216;Histoire de la Th&#233;ophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu&#8217;&#224; son Extinction&#8217;, part of Gr&#233;goire&#8217;s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55&#8211;171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493&#8211;536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; both necessary for my ways &amp; means. One of these journies is a serious affair to me, the whole expences being extraordinary, &amp; the chief source of my means the while being suspended. The B. Ch. I hope may come out in time to bear upon the Catholic Question.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The question of whether Catholics should be allowed to hold public office in the United Kingdom, something that was only resolved in 1829.</note> I had indeed begun a letter upon that subject for separate publication, which has only been suspended because <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyMarquis">M. Wellesley</ref> &amp; his Attorney General appear to have settled the question for this year.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Plunket (1764&#8211;1864; <title>DNB</title>) was the Irish attorney-general 1822&#8211;1827. On 18 February 1823, Plunket had told the House of Commons that he had no intention of bringing forward a measure for Catholic relief before Easter. But he was also embroiled in the convoluted legal proceedings against some members of the Orange Order, who had led a riot in the New Theatre Royal in Dublin on 14 December 1822. Local officials were accused of colluding to prevent prosecution of the rioters, while Plunket was alleged to have abused due legal process to bring charges against the rioters. The matter was debated at length in the House of Commons in May 1823.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Trant<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Brigadier-General Nicholas Trant (1769&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), an Irish army officer who was assigned to command Portuguese forces. He served with distinction in many actions in the Peninsular War 1808&#8211;1813.</note> (now M. General) is to be found at N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 8. Elizabeth Street, Hans Place, which I suppose to be in the district of Sloane Street. I believe you know that his wife<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sarah Georgina Trant, n&#233;e Horsington (d. 1806).</note> has been dead many years; but the little Clara whom you christened is living.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Clarissa Trant (1800&#8211;1844). In 1832 she married John Bramston (1802&#8211;1889), Vicar of Great Baddow, Essex and later Dean of Winchester 1872&#8211;1883. Her diary was published as <title>The Journal of Clarissa Trant</title> (1925).</note> I expect from him his adventures with the corps of Coimbra students, on the Vouga,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Trant had raised a corps from students at Coimbra University in early 1809. With other volunteers he maintained a front on the River Vouga until May 1809 and then participated in the recapture of Oporto.</note> while Soult occupied Porto.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Jean-de-Dieu Soult (1769&#8211;1851), the French Marshal who commanded the invasion of northern Portugal in 1809.</note> &#8211; Palmella,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Pedro de Sousa Holstein, 1st Duke of Palmela (1781&#8211;1850), Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary from Portugal to the United Kingdom 1816&#8211;1817 and 1825&#8211;1827.</note> the present Minister in London, &amp; others whom you would know, were of the number. The matter is not likely to be important, but I think it will give me an interesting &amp; characteristic page or two. <note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp. 197&#8211;202.</note> &#8211; Major Tomkinsons journal<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">William Tomkinson (1790&#8211;1872) joined the 16th Light Dragoons as a cornet in 1808 and served in Spain 1809&#8211;1813. He was a captain at Waterloo (1815). His diary was later published as <title>The Diary of a Cavalry Officer in the Peninsular and Waterloo Campaign, 1809&#8211;1815</title> (1894).</note> is thoroughly soldier like, &amp; will be highly useful.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Murray says he shall write to me fully in a few days. I have as yet only seen two of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref>
          <note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These could be inserted into the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> prints &#8211; Marvam, &amp; Villa Velha, &#8211; the latter is little connected with my narrative, that I interpolated a sentence, mainly for the sake of mentioning it.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, p. 758, where Southey noted that the crossing of the Tagus at Villa Velha was &#8216;a point, which, in former wars, has been considered the key to Lisbon&#8217;.</note> He did not think the sketch of the Puente del Corgul sufficiently made out, &#8211; &amp; the bridge over the Ezla<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The Puente de Corgul is a bridge in Galicia that Southey had crossed in December 1795, described in <title>Letters Written during a Short Residence in Spain and Portugal</title> (Bristol, 1797), p. 54, as &#8216;a scene of tranquil sublimity&#8217;. In the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>, 1.1 (1808), 452, Southey lamented that the failure to destroy the bridge had ruined the best chance the British forces had, while retreating to Corunna in 1808&#8211;1809, to delay the pursuing French. He also referred in a note to &#8216;a sketch, taken upon the spot&#8217; that he had seen &#8211; probably Herbert Hill&#8217;s drawing. The second sketch by Herbert Hill was of bridge over the River Esla at Castro Gonzalo, with the town of Benavente in the distance. It was the scene of a defeat of French cavalry by British forces on 29 December 1808, Southey, <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 782&#8211;783. </note> was not a scene of which he could make enough from the materials which I sent him. for the subsequent volumes <del>the prints</del> there will be less difficulty in obtaining views more connected with important events. He is a delightful artist, &amp; a most estimable man: &#8211; but his head is affected at times, &amp; when that is the case he takes offence at his best friends. I have a great regard for <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westall</ref>, &amp; heartily wish he may succeed in this speculation which he has undertaken mainly out of regard for me.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murrays</ref> agents should not have procured the Sp. books<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911.</note> before my arrival in town, I will try what can be done thro some other channel. But I live in daily expectation of them. They may be of more importance than you suppose, as they cannot but contain a great deal relating to Zaragoza &amp; Gerona; &#8211; these places will be the bright parts of the ensuing volume.<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), II, pp. 101&#8211;159 and 520&#8211;561, dealt with the heroic Spanish defence of the towns of Zaragoza and Gerona in 1808&#8211;1809.</note> The volume will be carried steadily thro the press on my return home, so as to be published about Christmas next.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). It was not published until 1827.</note> It is straight forward work, which I go to altogether as a pleasure, <del>xxx</del> without any unwillingness or exertion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> is going to send me a cast of his cup, which is in a fair way of becoming famous, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ChantreyFrancis">Chantry</ref> having pronounced it the finest piece of sculpture he ever saw. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; I used to fancy that it might be Benvenuto Cellini&#8217;s<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Benvenuto Cellini (1500&#8211;1571), the Italian goldsmith and sculptor.</note> work, because we wished to think so; but whose it was, will probably never be known. The casts are made under <ref type="m" target="people.html#ChantreyFrancis">Chantrys</ref> direction.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">My niece</ref> has got 113&#163; for her translation of Dobrizhoffer:<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Sara Coleridge&#8217;s <title>An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822). The book was a translation of Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. </note> she is a person of extraordinary industry &amp; acquirements, &amp; what is better, makes no show of them, &amp; gives herself no airs. &#8211; She &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">her mother</ref> are probably at <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickmans</ref> at this time. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> will hardly travel with me this next journey, because she cannot resolve to be absent from this place during the summer: &#8211; the consequence will be that I must escort her to town in the winter, unless an opportunity offers of sending her under convoy.<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">As Southey did not leave Keswick until 3 November 1823, Edith May Southey accompanied him.</note> You would be much pleased with her. She &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her Cousin</ref> are good specimens of what may be done without Boarding Schools, without Governesses, &amp; without Masters.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We are all well thank God. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> is four years old this day. My love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my aunt</ref>, &#8211; to <ref type="m" target="Hill">Edward</ref> (who I hope will soon get rid of his cold) &#8211; &amp; to the youngers.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>