<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3970</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3970Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3970" type="letter">
        <head>3970. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1823-02-26">26 February
                  1823</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from
                     the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb /> Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections
                     from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 379&#8211;382.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-02-26">Feb. 26. 1823.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">The corrections, &amp;c., will be in <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman&#8217;s</ref> hands before this
               reaches you. I have incorporated part of the preface to the third volume, added the rest of it after the &#8220;Life,&#8221; and inserted in the
               &#8220;Life&#8221; some things noted from the letters which were last in my possession.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had added a
                  new &#8216;Preface&#8217; to the 9th edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title>, 3 vols (London, 1822), III, pp.
                  [iii]&#8211;xvi. The third volume of this 1822 edition was a &#8216;supplementary volume&#8217; to the original edition of 1807, containing additional
                  letters and poems by Kirke White. The 10th edition of the <title>Remains</title>, 2 vols (London, 1823), compressed the material
                  into two volumes and required Southey to combine some of his &#8216;Preface&#8217; with the &#8216;Life&#8217; of Kirke White at pp. [v]&#8211;lxviii, adding the
                  remainder at pp. [lxix]&#8211;lxxiii. He also added references to letters in the third volume of the 1822 edition to the 1823 version of
                  the &#8216;Life&#8217;.</note> The proofs are to be sent me, that I may carefully revise the whole. One gap is left for you to fill up with the
               name of the college at which Almond was entered.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke
                  White</title>, 2 vols (London, 1823), I, p. xlviii. Robert White Almond (1785&#8211;1853) was an old schoolfriend of Kirke White&#8217;s from
                  Nottingham. He entered Trinity College, Cambridge, on 1 July 1803 (he is identified as a Trinity College student in the
                     <title>Remains</title>), but migrated within a few months to Queen&#8217;s College, Cambridge (BA 1808, MA 1813). He was ordained in
                  1810 and was Rector of St Peter&#8217;s, Nottingham 1814&#8211;1853.</note> I am heartily glad that the supplementary volume has done its work
               so well. The &#8220;Remains&#8221; have yet one stage to reach; they must one day be printed in a smaller form for the pocket, and for popular
               sale.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You ask me concerning the affairs of Spain. Three years ago, I dined at <ref type="m" target="people.html#ButlerCharles">Mr. Butler&#8217;s</ref> (the Catholic),<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">This dinner was on 18 May 1820, during Southey&#8217;s visit to
                  London of that year.</note> when his son&#8211;in&#8211;law, Colonel Stonor,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Lieutenant-Colonel Charles
                  Stonor (1781&#8211;1834) had married Mary Butler (1782&#8211;1829), daughter of Charles Butler, in 1809. He was a member of an old English
                  Catholic family and had served in the Spanish Army.</note> who is a Spaniard, has just received the first packet of pamphlets,
               proclamations, and newspapers, after the Revolution had been effected by the army.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The
                  absolutist regime in Spain was overthrown by an army revolt that began in January 1820.</note> They called upon me to rejoice with
               them, but I could not join in their exultation; &#8211; a bad government, indeed, had been overthrown, but a better had not been substituted
               for it. The Constitution which the Cortes had formed,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The army revolt restored the liberal
                  Constitution of 1812, devised by the Cortes elected in 1810.</note> tended decidedly (and designedly, also, no doubt) to bring about
               a democracy. I had always seen this tendency, and my disapprobation was by no means diminished when I saw it restored through the
               instrumentality of soldiers who thought it better to stay at home and subvert the Government, than obey its order by embarking for
               America.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The Spanish Revolution has been occasioned not by any desire of change on the part of the people, but by the inability
               of the Government to pay its civil and military establishments. Ferdinand<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII
                  (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833).</note> returned to a ruined kingdom, that is, ruined as to its finances: the colonies
               from whence the main revenues had formerly been derived were lost, and the mother&#8211;country in no condition to support taxes, everything
               having been subverted. The same cause would have overthrown the present Government two years ago, if it had not been supported by the
               loans which it raised in England,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">In 1820&#8211;1821, the Spanish government had raised two loans
                  through the Paris firm of Ardouin, Hubbard &amp; Co. and a further &#8216;National&#8217; loan from Spanish citizens.</note> and which, in all
               likelihood, will ruin all who have engaged in them. Meantime, the manner in which they have robbed the nobility and the Church of their
               property has offended both these bodies:<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">The liberal government in Spain issued a stream of
                  decrees in 1820&#8211;1822 ordering the confiscation and sale of the estates of municipal bodies, Spanish military orders, Crown lands and
                  monasteries and convents.</note> the kingdom is overrun with banditti; the rabble in the large towns are become radicals, made so by
               the Government itself; the great majority of the nation detest the new order of things, but would be passive under any order if they
               could; and the braver spirits have taken arms against it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The course which the Revolutionists have taken resembles that of their French exemplars so closely that no doubt can be
               entertained of their going through the same stages of regicide and massacre if left to themselves, unless the Royalists were strong
               enough to recover the ascendency. And here a difficult question arises. Is it <hi rend="ital">expedient</hi> for France to
                  interfere?<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">French forces had been massing on the Spanish border since late 1822 and finally
                  invaded on 7 April 1823 to restore the absolutist regime.</note> To question the <hi rend="ital">right</hi> of interference is
               absurd. If my next&#8211;door neighbours were fighting, endeavouring to kill one another, and likely, moreover, in their quarrel, to set fire
               to the house, it would be madness in me not to interfere, if I could do it to any good purpose.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Therefore, if France were a power which could be trusted, and would interfere as honourably as we did when we rescued
               Spain from Buonaparte,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Napoleon Bonaparte (1769&#8211;1821; Emperor of the French 1804&#8211;1814, 1815)
                  had ordered the occupation of Spain 1808&#8211;1813. Spanish resistance was greatly aided by British military intervention.</note> I
               should approve its interference, and heartily wish it success. But the French are a faithless nation: they have ever been so, and, upon
               the first favourable opportunity, they would gladly revive the wildest schemes of Louis XIV.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis XIV (1638&#8211;1714; King of France 1643&#8211;1714). His grandson inherited the Spanish throne in 1700, leading to the War of the
                  Spanish Succession 1701&#8211;1713.</note> or Buonaparte. Even could we trust them, and their conduct were to be as unexceptionable as I
               verily think the grounds of their interference are, the question of expediency is a very difficult one. When they get to Madrid (which
               may be done without difficulty), the work is far from being over. They may make a new government, or restore the old despotism, but how
               is it to be supported? The old difficulty of the finances recurs; and thus government will require, not our auxiliary troops to keep
               the country quiet, but loans to maintain it, till credit and prosperity are restored. France may have some reason to apprehend
               discontent at home, and the explosion of her own combustibles, if the struggle be prolonged; or, to prevent this, it is not improbable
               that she may be willing to provoke a war with England, for which the Portuguese seem disposed to give her a pretext.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">A liberal regime had been established in Portugal in 1820. It was feared that French forces might invade
                  Portugal and, later in 1823, both a British naval squadron and 5,000 British troops were dispatched to Portugal to prevent this
                  eventuality.</note> If they assist the Spaniards, and the French, in consequence, invade Portugal, we can no longer remain
               neutral.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Here, then, are two evils in prospect; that France may acquire such ascendency over Spain as Louis XIV. aimed at, and
               that we may be drawn into a war, in support of those very revolutionary opinions against which we have struggled so long. And this is
               what the Whigs desire. The very persons who would have had us desert Spain and the Portuguese when they resisted Buonaparte, are now
               endeavouring to force us into a war in their behalf. Undoubtedly they hope that it would end in a revolution at home by the
               embarrassments which it would produce. In this they are greatly deceived, for it would restore agricultural prosperity, and give a new
               spur to our manufactures. But this would be dearly purchased. Our policy is to preserve peace and order wherever our influence
               extends.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have written hastily, and may very possibly have failed to make myself understood. The upshot is this; it is a
               struggle in Spain between two extremes which are both so bad that one can hardly form a wish on either side; and that the one thing to
               be desired is, that order should be restored there. If France were an upright power, her interference would be desirable; &#8211; being what
               she is, it is to be wished that the Peninsular were left to itself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">It will be some eight or ten weeks before I see you. All here are well, and all join in kind remembrances to your
               fireside and circle. God bless you.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yours affectionately,<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent2"> R.S.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>