<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3977</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3977Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3977" type="letter">
        <head>3977. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">George Taylor</ref>, <date when="1823-03-07">7 March 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ George Taylor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Witton le Wear/ near/ Auckland<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Endorsement: 1823 <lb />
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 6. ALS; 4p. <lb />
Unpublished. </p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-03-07">7 March. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I should think it likely that <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, after the good proof which he has of <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">your sons</ref> talents<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (October 1822), 139&#8211;144, published 15 February 1823, where Henry Taylor reviewed Thomas Moore (1779&#8211;1852; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Irish Melodies</title> (1822).</note> would be not unwilling to embark in so small an adventure as that of these poems.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Taylor wrote a great deal of poetry in 1821&#8211;1823 but did not publish any of it; two of the longer poems were &#8216;The Cave of Ceada&#8217; and &#8216;The Flight of Rhadamistus&#8217;, both on classical themes.</note> In octavo they would not exceed six sheets, in duodecimo four would comprize them: my guess must therefore be near the mark when I suppose that five &amp; twenty pounds would cover the expences of 500 copies. &#8211; If you take the risk yourself, I am so well aware how little sale there is for poetry upon the score of its intrinsic worth, that I should advise half that number; &#8211; as for the purpose of feeling his way it is no matter how small the edition is. I read his article with pleasure, tho without the slightest suspicion of it being his. By all means keep that door open. Lord John Russels play I have not seen, &amp; therefore know nothing of its merits.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Russell, 1st Earl Russell (1792&#8211;1868; DNB), <title>Don Carlos, or, Persecution; a Tragedy in Five Acts</title> (1822), a play about Don Carlos (1545&#8211;1568), the eldest son and heir of Philip II (1527&#8211;1598; King of Spain 1556&#8211;1598). After Don Carlos showed signs of growing mental instability and threatened to kill his father, Philip II imprisoned him in the Alcazar Palace, where he died, probably of natural causes.</note> The subject has been treated by two great masters Alfieri<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Vittorio Alfieri (1749&#8211;1803), <title>Filippo</title> (1783).</note> &amp; Schiller,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Friedrich Schiller (1759&#8211;1805), <title>Don Karlos, Infant von Spanien</title> (1787).</note> by the former with his usual severity, by the latter with more than his <hi rend="ital">xxxxxx</hi> extravagance &#8211; in my judgement but there are Germans who esteem it the finest of his compositions. Better materials for criticism could not be desired, than a comparative view of these productions may afford:<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Taylor&#8217;s review of Russell&#8217;s <title>Don Carlos</title> appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title> 29 (July 1823), 370&#8211;382, published 30 December 1823.</note> &#8211; &amp; the real story of the Infante, as it may be found in Llorente&#8217;s Memoirs of the Inquisition<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Juan Antonio Llorente (1756&#8211;1823), <title>Histoire Critique de l&#8217;Inquisition d&#8217;Espagne</title>, 4 vols (Paris, 1817&#8211;1818), I, pp. 151&#8211;182.</note> should by no means be overlooked. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">But I ought to have given a more specific answer to your question. If a bookseller will not take the risk of publication, it would be a fair proposal to <del>shxx</del> take half the loss, <del>xxx</del> or half the profits as the sale might turn out.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The subject which you have turned your attention to is a most important one.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">George Taylor was thinking of writing a history of the end of the Roman Republic and beginning of the Roman Empire.</note> Will not the books of which you stand in need be found in <hi rend="ital">both</hi> the libraries at Durham?<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Durham Cathedral Library and Bishop Cosin&#8217;s Library, a public library founded in 1669.</note> if so, when you return one set, the other would be accessible, &amp; you might <hi rend="ital">ride &amp; tie</hi>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A popular phrase used to describe two people on a journey who had only one horse between them and were forced to take turns at riding and walking.</note> with them. It is a most important period in human history, &#8211; &amp; will lead you into a wider field of research than, perhaps, you are even yet aware of. In fact it is the history of the civilized world during those ages, &#8211; &amp; in the rise &amp; progress of Xtianity, &amp; the destruction of Jerusalem it includes the most important of all topics, &amp; the most aweful event recorded in human history. Nothing ever left so deep an impression upon my mind as the details of that catastrophe in Josephus.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Titus Flavius Josephus (c. AD 37&#8211;100). His works included <title>Bellum Judaicum</title> (AD 78), which related the Romans&#8217; destruction of Jerusalem in AD 70. See Southey to John May, 29 June&#8211;17 July 1824, Letter 4208, for the early effect of Josephus&#8217; work on Southey.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will have to show how surely despotism<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The replacement of the Roman Republic by the Roman Empire, after 30 BC.</note> produces the decline &amp; fall of empires: &#8211; &amp; yet what a blessing was that despotism after the age of Marius &amp; Sylla!<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Gaius Marius (157&#8211;86 BC) and Lucius Cornelius Sulla (138&#8211;78 BC), Roman generals and politicians. Both were central figures in the civil wars that divided the late Roman Republic.</note> From anarchy to despotism, &amp; from despotism to anarchy again, &#8211; this is the sad circle of human affairs which ancient history presents.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> is looking seriously towards Canada, &amp; we are at this time trying what can be obtained for him from the Colonial Office. I wish this measure were not so expedient, as in sad reality it is.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Sir<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yours very truly<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>