<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">3979Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3979" type="letter"><head>3979. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref>, <date when="1823-03-14">14 March 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London Seventeenth March 1823/ The Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> / Nicholas Lightfoot/ Crediton/ Devon/ Free/ JRickman<lb/>
Postmark: FREE/ 17 MR 17/ 1823<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName></address><date when="1823-03-14">14 March. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My Dear Lightfoot</salute></opener>
	<p rend="indent1">Thank you heartily for your liberal shipment,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Lightfoot had sent Southey two barrels of cider.</note> &#38; may all the winds be favourable to the Zephyr<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The <hi rend="ital">Zephyr</hi> was the ship on which the cider was being conveyed from Devon to Liverpool. Zephyr was also the Greek god of the west wind.</note> that conveys it. We shall drink your health with great satisfaction when it arrives tho peradventure, considering the delays between this place &#38; Liverpool, I may visit your roof before it is tasted.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> are at this time at Ottery, for which place they left London about ten days ago.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">Concerning my own movements, they depend upon the progress of the grey goose quill, – which has not the velocity that it possessed in younger years. I have six chapters of the Book of the Church<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, 1–528. In fact, the subjects Southey lists occupied seven chapters (chapters 12–18) and made up the entire second volume.</note> to write, upon the following subjects, – the Reformation, – the persecution under Q Mary, – the settlement of the Church, – its overthrow by the Puritans, – the preservation of our liberties by its means at the Revolution, – &#38; a view of its history &#38; condition from that time to the present.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey planned to deal with the Church of England’s break with Rome in the 1530s; the restoration of Catholicism under Mary I (1516–1558; Queen of England 1553–1558; <title>DNB</title>); the Church settlement of 1559; the Civil War and English Republic, 1642–1660; the Revolution of 1688; and a final overview – this last chapter was not written.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref> is about to enter his eldest son at Exeter, – next week I believe, but <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthJohn">John Wordsworth</ref><note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wordsworth entered New College, Oxford, in 1823. He had attended the local school at Ambleside, run by John Dawes.</note> will not reside till after the long vacation, when I shall provide him with credentials to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">your son</ref>. His name had been entered on the boards at Cambridge,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wordsworth matriculated at St John’s College, Cambridge, in 1820, but never took up his place.</note> but it was his own desire to be removed, &#38; I think a wise one, as he had no liking for mathematics, &#38; had a natural unwillingness to be measured by the same standard as his cousins <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthChristopher">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Wordsworths</ref> children, who have all been at public schools.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wordsworth (1805–1839) attended Winchester College (1820–1824) and Trinity College, Cambridge (1824–1828), becoming a Fellow of the College (1830) and a distinguished classical scholar; Charles Wordsworth (1806–1892; <title>DNB</title>) attended Harrow School and Christ Church, Oxford, after which he entered the Church and became Bishop of St Andrews, Dunkeld and Dunblane (1853–1892); Christopher Wordsworth (1807–1885; <title>DNB</title>) attended Winchester College and Trinity College, Cambridge, and also entered the Church, ending his life as Bishop of Lincoln (1869–1885).</note> He is himself thoroughly steady, &#38; right minded, of slow but sure capacity. I did not give this introduction to young May,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">John May and his son, John May (1802–1879), visited Southey at Keswick 5 August–2 September 1822, overlapping with Lightfoot’s visit. The younger John May was a student at Exeter College, Oxford.</note> because he is volatile &#38; light-minded, in great danger of being led into scrapes, &#38; therefore I thought his acquaintance was not one of which <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John Lightfoot</ref> would be desirous.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">When <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootJohnP">John</ref> begins to look about him, &#38; consider the ways of life, he will probably perceive that there is no course by which he could so soon establish himself, with the prospect of acquiring a good independence before he reaches the middle of life, as by putting on the harness in your stead, – &#38; you would wear it the more chearfully two or three &#60;years&#62; longer, having this transfer in view. – I noted the other day a passage in Michaelis<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann David Michaelis (1717–1791), <title>Einleitung in das Neu Testament</title>, 4th edition (1788), translated by Herbert Marsh (1757–1839; <title>DNB</title>) as <title>Introduction to the New Testament</title>, 4 vols (Cambridge, 1793–1801), I, Part 1, pp. 177, 281–282.</note> – to be mentioned to you. He strongly advises that the Septuagint<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Greek translation of the Old Testament (3rd–2nd centuries BC).</note> should be introduced in schools for the use of those who are intended for orders: – as an indispensable means for obtaining a critical understanding of the Greek of the New Testament. – There is another hint of his which I may as well mention: – that it would be a useful exercise in Greek to have passages written (or printed) as they are in ancient monuments &#38; inscriptions, (that is, – wholly in capital letters &#38; without any division between the words,) &#38; let the boys make them out.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">You ask me about the Spaniards. Between two things so bad as the old despotism, &#38; the present Cortes,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">After a military revolt in 1820, royal absolutism had been replaced by the Constitution of 1812, but Spain was in some disarray and an invasion by France was imminent.</note> if a wish of mine could turn the beam, I should not know in which scale to throw it. The interference of the French is a question not of right, but of expediency. If the family of my next door neighbor are quarrelling to such a degree that there is danger not only of their murder, but of their setting the house on fire, I should certainly reduce them to peace &#38; order, if I could, tho it were necessary to begin by knocking them down. The ruling party in Spain are a minority, ready to go all lengths in revolution. Arguelles,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Agustín Argüelles (1776–1844), a Spanish liberal politician. He was one of the architects of the Constitution of 1812 and was imprisoned by the absolutist regime in 1814–1820. After the 1820 revolution he was Minister of the Interior 1820–1821 and a deputy to the new Cortes 1822–1823.</note> one of the most celebrated of them, said last year to the M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Mackenzie<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Colin Alexander Mackenzie (?1778–1851), a wealthy Scot who was employed on a number of delicate diplomatic missions and may well have been a government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of the Commissioners of Liquidation, Arbitration and Deposit, who adjudicated on claims by British citizens for loss of property against the French government. Southey had met him in Paris in May 1817 and Mackenzie had provided the information about his role in the evacuation of the Spanish Army of the North from Denmark that appeared in Southey’s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823–1832), I, pp. 657–658.</note> (who is mentioned in my history) that he did not like Englishmen, such as Englishmen were now, he wanted them as they were in Oliver Cromwells<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Oliver Cromwell (1599–1658; Lord Protector 1653–1658; <title>DNB</title>).</note> days. Mackenzie told me this.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">It is no matter what becomes of Ferdinand,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784–1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813–1833). At this time he was a virtual prisoner of the liberal regime.</note> – a mere wretch, for in whom poverty of intellect is the only excuse that can be pleaded for the want of every generous &#38; every noble quality. But it is most desirable than an end should be put to spoliation, &#38; murder, &#38; mob, law. That France can effect this is by no means certain. If she can, will <del>xx</del> she be content with doing it? I would not trust her, – but that we have the means of restraining her, &#38; the other continental powers are sureties for her good behavior.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">At present, thank God, we are all well, – &#38; all unite in the kindest remembrances to you. Make my best wishes to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot, my <del>godfather</del> god-daughter &#38; the rest of your family,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768–1856) on 13 July 1801. Their children were: John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806–1882), Southey’s god-daughter; Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808–1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810–1889); Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811–1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846–1855, Rector of Islip 1855–1881.</note> – &#38; believe me my dear friend</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">Yours affectionately</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey</signed></closer>
<lb/>
            <postscript><p rend="indent1">Your former letter brought with it an invitation from <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T. Acland</ref>, but he will be in London, during my visit to Devonshire, – &#38; after giving you a week, a single day is the utmost I can allow to any other person. My absence from home will be inevitably much longer that I can well afford.</p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
