<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3980Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3980Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3980" type="letter">
        <head>3980. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Charles Watkin Williams Wynn</ref>, <date when="1823-03-17">17 March 1823</date>
          </head><p>MS: National Library of Wales, MS 4813D. ALS; 3p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Wynn</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I use your name in favour of a packet of proof sheets for <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">the Great King</ref>. They contain the life of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteHenryKirke">H K White</ref>, in which the preface to the supplementary volume is incorporated.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had added a new &#8216;Preface&#8217; to the 9th edition of Southey&#8217;s <title>The Remains of Henry Kirke White</title>, 3 vols (London, 1822), III, pp. [iii]&#8211;xvi. The third volume of this 1822 edition was a &#8216;supplementary volume&#8217; to the original edition of 1807, containing additional letters and poems by Kirke White. The 10th edition of the <title>Remains</title>, 2 vols (London, 1823) compressed the material into two volumes and required Southey to combine some of his &#8216;Preface&#8217; with the &#8216;Life&#8217; of Kirke White at pp. [v]&#8211;lxviii, adding the remainder at pp. [lxix]&#8211;lxxiii. He also added references to letters in the third volume of the 1822 edition to the 1823 version of the &#8216;Life&#8217;.</note> This book is now going into a tenth edition, &#8211; if any of my own had sold as well, I should be at this time a rich man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Thank you for what you have done in <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> affair.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey was considering emigrating to Canada.</note> The prospect is not a bad one, but there are huge difficulties in the outset. I think he will go over alone to prepare the way, &amp; then return for his family. &#8211; You know not what a weight this is, &amp; long has been upon my mind. Time has not abated the natural chearfulness of my disposition, &#8211; but it has taken from me much of that hopefulness, that unhesitating, &amp; almost unreflecting confidence which I used to possess; &amp; the future will sometimes trouble the present, which it never did in the earlier part of my life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have heard <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">my brother Henry</ref> when speaking of certain constitutional diseases say that the person who has them may very probably live to die of something else. With regard to my own affairs, it is at least an even chance that this sort of comfort is applicable, &#8211; that I shall be able to go on from hand to mouth, freely &amp; fearlessly, &amp; when the head rests from its labours, there will be a respectable provision accruing upon my death. But in the case of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> family<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey had eight children: Margaret Hill Southey (b. 1811); Mary Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813&#8211;1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815&#8211;1864); Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816&#8211;1835); Sarah Louise Southey (1818&#8211;1850); Nelson Castle Southey (1820&#8211;1834); and Sophia Jane Southey (1822&#8211;1859). Thomas Castle Southey (1824&#8211;1896) completed the family.</note> this does not apply, &#8211; &amp; the greatest possible relief that I can have, will be to know that it is well settled in Canada, where, as in all new countries, children are wealth.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If the French were a nation from whom any thing just &amp; honourable could be expected, they would have a fair opportunity of redeeming their national character in Spain.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The French government was considering whether to invade Spain and suppress the liberal regime. French forces crossed the Spanish border on 7 April 1823.</note> But if they mean well (which it is their interest do) still their character will render them suspected. I am far from partaking the Spanish fever which rages at this time in London. Between Ferdinand<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Ferdinand VII (1784&#8211;1833; King of Spain 1808, 1813&#8211;1833). He had been forced to call a new Cortes in 1820 and was virtually a prisoner of the liberal regime 1820&#8211;1823.</note> &amp; the Cortes there is not a pin to chuse. Oh <del>xxxx</del> how difficult, &#8211; how almost impossible it is to introduce a free government among a people who have been accustomed to despotism! If a set of school boys under ten years of age were to play at Parliament, &#8211; they would do it with more decorum than the French observe in their Chambers.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Louis XVIII (1755&#8211;1824; King of France 1814&#8211;1824) had been forced by the victorious allies to agree to govern in accordance with a Charter, whose provisions included an elected Chamber of Deputies and an appointed Chamber of Peers.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Did I ever tell you what Arguelles<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Agust&#237;n Arg&#252;elles (1776&#8211;1844), a Spanish liberal politician. He was one of the architects of the Constitution of 1812 and was imprisoned by the absolutist regime in 1814&#8211;1820. After the 1820 revolution he was Minister of the Interior 1820&#8211;1821 and a deputy to the new Cortes 1822&#8211;1823.</note> said to Mackenzie<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Colin Alexander Mackenzie (?1778&#8211;1851), a wealthy Scot who was employed on a number of delicate diplomatic missions and may well have been a government spy. In 1815 he was appointed one of the Commissioners of Liquidation, Arbitration and Deposit, who adjudicated on claims by British citizens for loss of property against the French government. Southey had met him in Paris in May 1817 and Mackenzie had provided the information about his role in the evacuation of the Spanish Army of the North from Denmark that appeared in Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title>, 3 vols (London, 1823&#8211;1832), I, pp. 657&#8211;658.</note> two years ago? &#8211; that he did not like the English &#8211; he wanted such English as those of Oliver Cromwells<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Oliver Cromwell (1599&#8211;1658; Lord Protector 1653&#8211;1658; <title>DNB</title>).</note> days. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Littletons</ref>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A public dinner was held at the City of London Tavern on 7 March 1823 to support the Spanish liberal regime. The guests of honour were Juan Jabat Aztal (1772&#8211;1825), the Spanish Ambassador 1822&#8211;1823, Jo&#227;o Francisco de Oliveira (dates unknown), the Portuguese charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires 1821&#8211;1822, and Lorenzo Fernandez de Villavicencio y Canas, 3rd Duke of San Lorenzo and Valhermoso (1778&#8211;1859), formerly Spanish Ambassador to France. Littleton was one of a number of eminent speakers and proposed a toast to &#8216;Civil and Religious Liberty all over the World&#8217;. Littleton was a supporter of Canning, but might be expected to know the thoughts of Wellington[WellesleyArthurWellington] and his brother, Marquess Wellesley[WellesleyMarquis], on Spain as he was married to Wellesley&#8217;s daughter, Hyacinthe Mary (d. 1849).</note> appearance at the dinner surprized me, &amp; made me fear that he spoke the sentiments of the Wellesleys. For it appears to me that our plain policy is to remain at peace. France might have done more wisely to have looked on yet awhile; &#8211; but I look upon this as a question of expediency, &amp; one upon which I <del>xx</del> do not pretend to decide.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am heartily glad to see that Hume &amp; id genus omne<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;all that sort&#8217;.</note> are treated somewhat more as they deserve than they used to be treated.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Hume (1777&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>) was a radical MP whom Southey despised. His campaign against government expenditure had gained a great deal of public support, but was making less headway by 1823. His motion attacking the Church of Ireland on 4 March 1823 was heavily defeated in the House of Commons. </note> It is one of those cases in which the way to make superiority felt, is by <del>xxx xxxxx</del> showing it.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent2">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-03-17">17 March 1823.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>