<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3981" type="letter"><head>3981. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref>, <date when="1823-03-18">18 March 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Endorsement: RS to JR 18 March/1823<lb/>
MS: Huntington Library, RS 431. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear R.</salute></opener>
	<p rend="indent1">The inclosure which accompanies this is to return thanks for a new a tail to my name.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been made an Honorary Member of the Royal Irish Academy.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I need not tell you that I do not partake the Spanish fever which is at this time raging, not however with so much violence in the country, as in town.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">French forces were preparing to invade Spain to restore absolute monarchy; they crossed the Spanish border on 7 April 1823 and had totally defeated the Spanish liberals by November 1823. Whigs and radicals in Britain urged to government to pressurise France not to intervene in Spain</note> I am not apprehensive of any evil consequences to this country, – &#38; should have thought any surmise of our being involved in war altogether groundless, if <ref type="m" target="people.html#LittletonEdwardJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Littleton</ref> had not made himself conspicuous at the dinner given to the Ambassadors.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A public dinner was held at the City of London Tavern on 7 March 1823 to support the Spanish liberal regime. The guests of honour were Juan Jabat Aztal (1772–1825), the Spanish Ambassador 1822–1823, João Francisco de Oliveira (dates unknown), the Portuguese chargé d’affaires 1821–1822, and Lorenzo Fernandez de Villavicencio y Canas, 3rd Duke of San Lorenzo and Valhermoso (1778–1859), formerly Spanish Ambassador to France. Littleton was one of a number of eminent speakers and proposed a toast to ‘Civil and Religious Liberty all over the World’. Littleton was a supporter of Canning, but might be expected to know Wellington’s thoughts on Spain as he was married to Wellington’s niece, Hyacinthe Mary (d. 1849).</note> He I think must know what <ref type="m" target="people.html#WellesleyArthurWellington">the Duke of W.s</ref> opinion is, &#38; would not act in opposition to it. But notwithstanding this I have little doubt that we shall remain at peace. – Whether the French act wisely in their interference is another question. <del>X</del> It is not so certain that they can interfere with effect, as it is that they might have looked on safely. The difficulty is not in establishing a better Government, but in supporting one when it is established, in a country whose resources are ruined.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother the Cap<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</ref> is thinking seriously of removing with his family to Canada. – Eight children,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Margaret Hill Southey (b. 1811); Mary Hill Southey (b. 1812); Robert Castle Southey (1813–1828); Herbert Castle Southey (1815–1864); Eleanor Thomasina Southey (1816–1835); Sarah Louise Southey (1818–1850); Nelson Castle Southey (1820–1834); and Sophia Jane Southey (1822–1859). Thomas Castle Southey (1824–1896) completed the family.</note> &#38; the probability of as many more, make this the wisest measure he could adopt. The Colonial Office has promised, – thro <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> – all the civilities &#38; facilities in their power, –</p>
	<p rend="indent1">I am hard at work upon my Book of the Church<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> which must be finished before I begin my journey. It is growing into a volume of respectable size, &#38; will comprehend a connected view of our Ecc. History, – in which some forgotten facts will be usefully revived, &#38; some views taken which have hitherto been overlooked –</p>
			<closer><salute rend="indent3">God bless you</salute>
					<signed rend="indent5">RS.</signed></closer>
<postscript><p rend="indent0"><date when="1823-03-18">18 March. 1823.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
