<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">3986Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3986" type="letter"><head>3986. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-03-22">22 March 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 25 MR 25/ 1823<lb/>
Endorsement: 22 March 1823<lb/>
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb/>
Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 382–384.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-03-22">22 March. 1823.</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Suppose you were <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">a young Lady</ref> in the nineteenth year of your age, very busy in preparing certain remembrances to be transmitted by a safe opportunity to her distant friends, – &#38; that some of these remembrances could not be finished for want of ultra-marine;<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A pigment for use in watercolour painting. Ultramarine is a deep blue colour.</note> &#38; that one of your fathers oldest &#38; dearest friends, holding a high situation in his Majestys Exchequer, had promised to send you a cake of this indispensable colour, under cover of an official frank, – should not you think that the whole business of the Exchequer &#38; all things connected therewith might be suspended, while the said ultra-<del>marine</del> &#60;marine&#62; was procured?</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Will you send me some Vegetable marrow seeds under the same cover, – &#38; I will promise you that their produce shall be excellently cooked, when you come &#38; help me to drink <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> cyder which is now upon the road.</p>
	<p rend="indent1">The Royal Irish Academy sent me, the other day, another tail to my name,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had been elected an Honorary Member of the Royal Irish Academy (founded 1785), a body that existed to promote Irish scientific and cultural activities and studies.</note> for the benefit of my next title-page. – I am glad this was done after my Irish Ode was written, &#38; before it has appeared in the world.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">‘Ireland’, <title>Sir Thomas More: or. Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society</title>, 2 vols (London, 1829), I, pp. [295]–302. The poem, Southey’s New Year’s ode for 1822, was inspired by George IV’s State visit to Ireland, 12 August–3 September 1821. Southey used his new honour on the title page of his next publication, <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, p. [iii].</note></p>
	<p rend="indent1">I have to day received the proofs of my paper upon the Theophilanthropists in France &#38; the Rise &#38; Progress of Infidelity,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), ‘Histoire de la Théophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu’à son Extinction’, part of Grégoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55–171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493–536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> – &#38; of course seen it for the first time as a whole. What opinion may be formed of it I cannot foresee; – but that with regard to individuals it will do some of the good which was intended, I do not doubt. And upon this first consecutive perusal, I am glad that I have written it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> has not written to me since his recovery. It is <hi rend="ital">possible</hi> that he may not be in good humour with me for endeavouring to procure a successor for him, tho it was in consequence of his expressing to me the necessity of looking out for one. I certainly wish the Journal were in <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridges</ref> hands, both for personal &#38; public considerations. The good which it might do is grievously counteracted by the gross inconsistencies which are now to be found in it, – its cruel &#38; unmanly injustices on some occasions, – &#38; its wretched cowardice on others. – I shall ask him if he will have an article upon Spain &#38; Portugal,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write an article on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> in 1823.</note> – a question upon which I am quite willing to take the field against all the Whigs in the world. Oh how I could trample upon them!</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I mean to ask <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to print a selection of <del>xxx</del> my papers with restorations &#38; revisions, in some such arrangement – as Essays – moral &#38; political, which would fill two volumes,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">This project became Southey’s <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title> (1832).</note> – then as many more of Essays, historical &#38; ecclesiastical, – &#38; lastly critical &#38; miscellaneous,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">These two further collections were not published.</note> keeping each collection distinct, not to alarm the public with too much at once. In this manner he might put some money in my pocket &#38; in his own. I should include some papers from the Annual Review &#38; make up some from the Ed: An: Register<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had reviewed extensively for the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803) until the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809) and written the historical sections of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810) until the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813). Essays I-III in <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), I, pp. [3]–72, and Essays XI–XII in <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), II, pp. [277]–328, were mainly drawn from the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. None of Southey’s pieces in the <title>Annual Review</title> formed the basis of an essay, but parts of Southey’s review of Thomas Malthus (1766–1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population</title> (1803), <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292–301, were grafted onto Essay IV of <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), I, pp. [73]–155, which was mainly from Southey’s review of Patrick Colquhoun (1745–1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Propositions for Ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and for Improving the Moral Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring People</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319–356.</note></p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
	   <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
