<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">3992Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3992" type="letter">
        <head>3992. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1823-03-28">Good Friday [28 March] 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15 Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 31 MR 31/ 1823<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 3p. <lb />
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, p. 243&#8211;245.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-03-28">Good Friday. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear H.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">At length I can write to you respecting <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref>. Two lions, of the great family of lions in his way,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Proverbs</title>, 26: 13: &#8216;The slothful man saith, There is a lion in the way; a lion is in the streets.&#8217;</note> are removed, he has got rid of his farm,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Emerald Bank in the Newlands valley, about four miles from Keswick.</note> &amp; of his debt to the Fenwicks,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey had possibly written to Dr John Ralph Fenwick (c. 1762&#8211;1855) and his wife Dorothy, n&#233;e Spearman (dates unknown). Fenwick lived in Durham when Tom Southey farmed in the county and was well known to Henry Herbert Southey. He was a wealthy local radical.</note> &#8211; the latter at a very easy rate, by their cancelling his note of hand,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey&#8217;s written guarantee to repay the money that he owed.</note> &#8211; the former by a temporary arrangement sufficiently convenient &amp; indeed advantageous at present, but which may bring the lion back hereafter. His intention is to go himself to Canada as soon as possible, do what he can there, return in the autumn &amp; remove his family thither in the spring of next year. Robert<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Castle Southey (1813&#8211;1828), Tom Southey&#8217;s eldest son.</note> goes with him, as old enough to be useful, &amp; likely to be better with his father than anywhere else: &amp; I think there is also an eye to the likelihood that this Matthew Bell<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Matthew Bell (1769&#8211;1849), a wealthy merchant, iron manufacturer and land speculator, originally from Berwick-upon-Tweed.</note> (a great man at Quebec) who is distantly related to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheySarah">Sarah</ref>, &amp; intimate with the Taylors,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">George Taylor</ref> and his son, <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry Taylor</ref>.</note> may prove a friend to him. His stock is to be sold next week, &amp; he is going to look at a Maryport vessel which is to sail for Quebec on the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of April<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey sailed from Whitehaven on 20 April 1823 on the brig <hi rend="ital">Maria</hi> and reached Quebec on 27 May.</note> &#8211; I have given him 30 &#163; for the present; &#8211; &amp; when I am in London will lodge what I can in his agents<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hinxman (1759&#8211;1844), a navy agent, whose business was based at 72 Great Russell Street. Southey did not leave for London until 3 November 1823 and so asked John May to lodge &#163;100 with Hinxman; see Southey to John May, 3 June 1823, Letter 4026.</note> hands to answer his bills. Will you now get what introductions M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robinson<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Beverley Robinson, 1st Baronet (1791&#8211;1863), Solicitor-General for Upper Canada 1815&#8211;1818, Attorney-General for Upper Canada 1818&#8211;1829, Chief Justice of Upper Canada 1829&#8211;1841 and of Canada West 1841&#8211;1862. At this time, Robinson was in London seeking to promote legislation to put Upper Canada&#8217;s finances on a sounder footing, resulting in the Canada Trade Act (1822).</note> &amp; Wilmot<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Robert Wilmot-Horton (1784&#8211;1841; <title>DNB</title>), Under-Secretary of State for War and the Colonies 1821&#8211;1828.</note> can give; &amp; leave to chuse his grant either in Upper or Lower Canada,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">This division was established in 1791; Upper Canada was in modern Ontario and Lower Canada in modern Quebec.</note> as he may find reason to prefer when he is on the spot. This <del>can</del> there can be no difficulty in I should suppose; &#8211; &amp; if the license may extend to a power of choice <hi rend="ital">in</hi> either, so much the better tho <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">R&#8217;s</ref> advice of taking all that can be got, is good worldly wisdom.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">His first intention was to go bag &amp; baggage at once. Tho I see reason enough to wish that this were advisable, it certainly is not to be advised: &amp; therefore I declared against it from the beginning, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">George Taylor</ref> induced him to change his purpose, &amp; go to prepare the way.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">One of my books<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> represents the right bank of the S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Laurence, opposite Quebec, as having many advantages; &amp; this makes him hesitate between the two provinces. It appears to me that every good situation near the capital<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Quebec City.</note> must long have been occupied: should it prove otherwise, it would certainly desirable to save 1000 miles of travelling &amp; at the expence of s<del>xx</del> a colder climate, settle nearer Quebec, &amp; in a <del>sitx</del> part which would be safe during war.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Any future war between the United Kingdom and the United States; the last conflict was in 1812&#8211;1814.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The whole affair hangs upon me like a mill-stone. I am quite certain that no other course is left for them, &amp; this they feel. &#8211; But there is a feeling on his part that he had a right to look for promotion &amp; Heaven knows what on the score of my merits; &#8211; &amp; to my surprize <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorGeorge">G. Taylor</ref> has been injudicious enough to encourage this. He is dissatisfied with me for not urging this claim, &#8211; forgetful of what has been done, &#8211; &amp; shutting his eyes upon the staring fact that if my <del>xxxxxx xxx</del> influence were what he chuses to suppose it, it would not leave me dependent as I am for two thirds of my income, upon <del>xx</del> constant exertion at my desk.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You had better let his credentials be directed immediately to himself.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am anxious to hear how you are going on. Is there any truth in the account of this strange &#8211; &amp; unaccountable mortality in London?<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;The extraordinary changes of climate to which we have been exposed during the Winter and Spring, (hitherto) have we learn, produced an appalling increase in mortality. It is stated, and we believe on good authority, that the deaths in London, within the last four months, exceed the average of two-thirds of the year at any former common period; apoplexy particularly prevails&#8217; (<title>Berrow&#8217;s Worcester Journal</title>, 27 March 1823).</note> &#8211; If I were in better spirits I would ask if <del>xxx</del> you have practising very extensively this season. &#8211; You will be glad to here that I have kept up my condition during the winter, &#8211; &amp; except for a rough day, have felt no symptom of my old complaint<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey suffered from a rectal prolapse and haemorrhoids.</note> &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you. &#8211; Love to all</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS. </signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>