<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.3993</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/3993Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="3993" type="letter">
        <head>3993. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-03-31">31 March 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmarks: E/ 3 AP 3/ 1823<lb />
Endorsement: 31 March 1823<lb />
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-03-31">31 March 1823.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear G.</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I have had in the course of my life three such twinges in the toe-major as you describe, &#8211; but which I have rather likened to having it injected with scalding water. This I have supposed to be a gouty affection, tho in my case there is no hereditary right to it, &amp; as little personal pretension as in yours. Ask <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Osiris</ref> about it when he rises above your horizon next.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Your mem. concerning the clean sheets is accurate as far as it goes.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Proofs of the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> You sent me afterwards as far as p.744. &amp; it is the remaining sheets, together with the title page &amp;c which I want, to make the set compleat, &#8211; otherwise all this is but waste paper.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The operation of nerving the horse<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A neurectomy that was carried out as a last resort on horses with chronic foot pain.</note> is very curious. The analogous experiment of dividing a nerve to cure the tic doloreux<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Tic douloureaux, or trigeminal neuralgia, is a disorder of the fifth cranial nerve and causes intense facial pain. Attempts to use surgery to relieve the condition had been made as early as 1748 but were unsuccessful.</note> &#8211; I believe has generally failed. We should know more about the nerves if some young <ref type="m" target="people.html#CarlisleAnthony">Carlisle</ref> would make a voyage in a Whaler he would then find them upon a scale &#8211; which would enable him not only to ascertain their structure, but possibly to analyse their contents. &#8211; This reminds me of a friend<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brother Tom&#8217;s</ref>, who when he was upon such a voyage, made some whale-cheese. How <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">his Right Honour</ref> would have delighted in toasting it!</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You seem not to understand that the lithographic prints are <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref>.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823). These could be inserted into the first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> They have not been sent me, probably because Westall expects me in London. There however I can not possibly be before the month of May, &#8211; tho I am working now as hard as any government clerk who is making up accounts upon the motion of some such <del>pest xx</del> public-pest as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Hume.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Hume (1777&#8211;1855; <title>DNB</title>), a Scottish radical MP who was greatly disliked by Southey for his campaigns against government expenditure. </note> I am however now in the full current of composition,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was writing <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> making great way with the stream. This evening, as soon as this scrawl is dispatched I shall conclude all matters antecedent to Henry 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry VIII (1491&#8211;1547; King of England 1509&#8211;1547; <title>DNB</title>). Southey had completed the first volume of <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824).</note> &amp; it will be a pleasure to write the chapters which ensue.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> thinks proper I shall set about a paper upon Spanish &amp; Portugueze affairs,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title> at this time.</note> a subject upon which there can be no difference of opinion among persons who are really acquainted with the situation &amp; character of the two nations, &amp; capable of forming a just judgement upon a plain case. A letter which I received lately from <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco White</ref>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Blanco White to Southey, 16 March 1823; see G. Martin Murphy and Andr&#233; Pons, &#8216;Further Letters of Blanco White to Robert Southey&#8217;, <title>Bulletin of Hispanic Studies</title>, 62 (1985), 357&#8211;372.</note> would have convinced me of this, had I been doubtful of it before. What you tell me of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> is all that I have heard of him. &#8211; We look now for the French blue<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Bleu de France, a blue pigment used in painting. Bedford was supplying this for Edith May Southey&#8217;s use.</note> by every post, &amp; thank you for it by anticipation. Remember me to <ref type="m" target="people.html#Bedfordfamily">Miss Page</ref>, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordHenry">the Consumer of Snuff</ref>. We have had a week of delicious weather here which has just ended in gentle rain.</p>
        <salute rend="indent1">God bless you<lb/>
        <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>