<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="3999" type="letter"><head>3999. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1823-04-14">[14 April 1823]</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major General Peachy<lb/>
MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Dating note: Dating from content. Tom Southey left to sail to Canada early on 13 April, the day before this letter was written.</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am very sorry to hear M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hall<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> is indisposed, – which is the more vexatious, as this would have been so fine a day for beginning your migration.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Catcotts book<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Alexander Catcott (1725–1779; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Treatise on the Deluge</title> (1768).</note> cannot be of much value; I believe it proceeds upon geological arguments, which science was very little <del>un</del> cultivated in his time (if it be well understood now) – his brother George I knew &#38; tried to get information from him respecting Chatterton,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">George Symes Catcott (1729–1802), the Bristol pewterer and patron of Thomas Chatterton (1752–1770; <title>DNB</title>). Southey had written to Catcott to obtain information for his and Joseph Cottle’s edition <title>The Works of Thomas Chatterton</title> (1803); see Southey to Joseph Cottle, [c. 21 August 1802], <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey, Part Two</title>, Letter 708.</note> but I remember that I used to compare the attempting at eliciting any thing like common sense from poor Catcott to that of trying to strike fire with a wooden mallet from a lump of lead. – Townsend of Pewsey has written a book of <del>some</del> good repute with the view as thus concerning which you enquire, – its title I believe is ‘the character of Moses as an historian vindicated.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Townsend (1739–1816; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Character of Moses as an Historian, Recording Events from the Creation to the Deluge</title> (1813), a robust defence of the accuracy of the biblical account of history. It is possible that Peachy’s enquiries were motivated by the appearance of William Buckland (1784–1856; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Reliquiæ Diluvianæ, or, Observations on the Organic Remains attesting the Action of a Universal Deluge</title> (1823), which argued that the Earth was much older than a literal interpretation of the account in <title>Genesis</title> suggested.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">Fouche’s letter<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Fouché (1759–1820), <title>Lettre au Duc de Wellington</title> (1817). Fouché was an old Jacobin who had later served the Napoleonic regime as Minister of Police 1799–1810.</note> appeared in the newspapers, &#38; I think if it had been worth remembering I should not have so totally forgotten it.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother</ref> rode off yesterday at break of day, &#38; desired me to say how sorry he was that the weather had prevented him from paying his respects at the Island.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I shall be glad to hear of your safe arrival, &#38; should you pass the month of April at Bath, I will endeavour to arrange my plans as to see you there.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">God bless you, my dear Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">Yrs very truly</salute>
				<signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent1"><date when="1823-04-14">Monday morning.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
