<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4007" type="letter"><head>4007. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward [Hill]</ref> [fragment], <date when="1823-04-27">[c. 27 April 1823]</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 320. AL; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.<lb/>
Dating note: Dating and identity of correspondent derived from the content. Southey had heard of Edward Hill’s success by 27 April 1823, when he wrote to Herbert Hill (see Letter 4008).</note></head>


<opener><salute>My dear Edward</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">By a letter which I have this day received, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">your Father</ref> informs me of your success.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had received news of Edward Hill’s success in ‘The Challenge’, a gruelling examination at Westminster School to select King’s Scholars. </note> I heartily rejoice in it, &#38; congratulate you on the termination of the longest &#38; severest trial of this kind which you can ever be required to undergo. – A straight &#38; safe course is now before you; – &#38; with only a continuance of diligence &#38; good conduct on your own part, there is every probability that the tenour of your life will be honourable &#38; happy for yourself, &#38; gratifying to all those who are interested in your welfare.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">I know not whether College has been altered from what it was three or four &#38; thirty years ago; or if there be still a <del>xxxxx</del> greater degree of tyranny going <del>the</del> on there, than can ever exist among the town boys. [MS missing]t it is much the same, &#38; varies according as the majority of the Seniors happen to be of good or bad dispositions. If you should have any temporary hardships to endure from this cause, make you a firm determination that you will never exercise upon others such injustice as you have suffered. The worst effect which school-tyranny produces, is when it disposes a boy to treat others ill in his turn because he has himself been treated so. – I am not afraid of its producing this effect upon you. But the advantage of having been at such a school, you will feel thro life.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">It will not be long before I see you. Meantime I shall <del>send</del> lay the foundation of your historical library by sending you one of the best books in our language, – Lord Clarendons History of the Rebellion.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">An edition of Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon (1609–1674; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England</title> (1702–1704) which Southey had first read in 1818.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">Your Welsh nieces<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">nephew</ref> in this household thank God are all well, – &#38; would be very glad to be acquainted with you<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill visited Keswick in August 1824; see Southey to Herbert Hill, 13 August 1824, Letter 4231.</note>.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dear Edward</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">Your affectionate cousin</salute></closer>
<postscript><p rend="indent0">[MS missing]</p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
