<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4008Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4008Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4008" type="letter">
        <head>4008. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-04-27">27 April 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham<lb />
Postmarks: 2 A. NOON 2/ 1823; [partial] 4 N 4/ 1823; [1 illegible].<lb />
Seal: [partial] red wax<lb />
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 231. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 387&#8211;388 [in part].</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am heartily glad to hear of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edwards</ref> success.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Hill had taken &#8216;The Challenge&#8217;, a gruelling examination at Westminster School to select the King&#8217;s Scholars. He had placed fifth, thus guaranteeing himself a Scholarship.</note> &#8211; He has had the disadvantage of not having the Westminster grammars<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Westminster School had its own instruction manuals from which boys learnt Latin and Greek; for example, <title>A Short Introduction to the Latin Grammar for the Use of the Lower Forms in Westminster School</title> (1821).</note> &#8211; (abominable ones they are!) at his fingers ends, &#8211; &amp; therefore must have &lt;been&gt; more likely to make trifling slips himself, &amp; less alert at detecting them in another than his opponents. Success in such a contest is no more a test of capacity, or proficiency, than the full crop of a turkey who is in training for the cook, is a proof of the birds appetite.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> has <del>xxx</del> done with all such trials, if <del>xx</del> he should be elected to Ch. Ch: &#8211; there is nothing for him to get there. If to Trinity he will be contented with the scholarship while it lasts, unless he should determine upon an academical life, &#8211; which is not the most conducive either to happiness, or to intellectual improvement.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">King&#8217;s Scholars could proceed to a Closed Scholarship at either Christ Church, Oxford, or Trinity College, Cambridge. There was no certainty that a King&#8217;s Scholar would receive a Fellowship once he graduated from Trinity College, Cambridge. However, at Christ Church, a King&#8217;s Scholar immediately became one of the body of Students, with a modest stipend that was guaranteed for life, if the recipient wished and if he obeyed the rules of the College. If they took university degrees in a timely fashion their stipend would increase. However, the rules governing Studentships were strict and anyone who married, did not take Holy Orders, or accepted a paid occupation had to resign. Edward Hill chose Christ Church, Oxford. The Studentships at Christ Church were initially worth about &#163;50 or &#163;60 a year, those at Trinity College about &#163;25.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The principle of emulation is carried much too far in modern education. Many men are absolutely killed by it at the Universities, &amp; many more injure their constitutions irreparably. No one with whom I have any influence shall ever suffer from that cause. The habit to be encouraged is that of placid diligence. What is thus healthily acquired is retained: whereas the cramming system hurts the digestion. My chief reason for wishing that <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> may be elected to Oxford, is because they cram there less than at Cambridge</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am not surprized at <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunts</ref> determination concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Erroll</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had offered to ask Wynn, as President of the Board of Control, to nominate Erroll Hill to either: a cadetship at Addiscombe Military College, which trained officers for the East India Company&#8217;s army; or to a writership (the lowest civil service post) in the East India Company. This latter option often involved two years&#8217; training at the East India College at Haileybury. Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">Catherine Hill</ref>, had declined this offer of help.</note> Indeed I rather expected it; &amp; yet, as the thing would (I have no doubt) have been in my power, it seemed proper to mention it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">It is well for us that in youth we do not see the objections which <del>xxx</del> &lt;exist&gt; to every profession in life, &#8211; if we did, life <del>would</del> &lt;might&gt; be at an end before one could venture to make the choice. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edwards</ref> I hope will be made for the Church. He will take a little Hebrew with him from Westminster; &#8211; little enough, but still a foundation. I shall advise him before he leaves school to master the German grammar, &#8211; which ten minutes a day would enable him to do. No person knows better than I do what small gains amount to, in accumulations of this kind. <del>&amp;</del> This language is of main importance in most literary researches.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s reading knowledge of German was limited, though he could understand Dutch, mainly due to his historical research for the <title>History of Brazil</title> (1810&#8211;1819).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will not wonder (knowing how prone, in Persian phrase my &#8216;pen of the steed is, to expatiate in the plain of prolixity.&#8221;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Jonathan Scott (1753&#8211;1829; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Bahar-Danush: or, Garden of Knowledge. An Oriental Romance</title>, 3 vols (Shrewsbury 1799), II, p. 109. Southey&#8217;s copy was no. 94 in the sale catalogue of his library.</note>) that the Book of the Church is swelling into two ordinary sized octavos.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824). The first volume ran to 394 pages and the second to 528.</note> The fact is that I intended to deal in generals, but found as I went on that it was the particulars which must &lt;give&gt; life &amp; effect to the composition. As far as it has gone I am well satisfied with it. A view of the papal system is just printed,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. 283&#8211;320.</note> which is likely to produce a proper effect. I do not quite see my way <del>xx</del> in the last chapter,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 468&#8211;528, covered 1660&#8211;1688, but ended abruptly.</note> but it will open before me when I arrive at it. I think of dedicating it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">the Bp. of London</ref>.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title> was dedicated to Peter Elmsley.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Doctor</ref> I see has been at court,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey had been present at the first lev&#233;e of the new season on 21 April 1823.</note> &#8211; a ceremony which I hope to escape. He writes in good spirits, but makes no mention of poor Robert.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Love to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref>, &amp; the young ones.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-04-27">27 Apr. 1823.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>