<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4015Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4015Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4015" type="letter">
        <head>4015. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-05-11">11 May 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ G.C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Exchequer/ Westminster<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 14 MY 14/ 1823<lb />
Endorsement: 11 May 1823.<lb />
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 391&#8211;392 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>
              </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-05-11">11 May. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I have been so eagerly at work since the seeds arrived that I did not even allow myself time to thank you for them &#8211; tho the act of writing to you is always a sort of relaxation &amp; refreshment. With regard to these said Quasheys<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Quashey&#8217; was usually used as a term for the pumpkin, a type of squash, but Southey may be using it here for another type of squash, the marrow.</note> (which I believe is their name, &#8211; first cousins to the Squash Pumpkin) the best way of dressing them is to stew them in cream. Young cucumbers might be as good, but cucumbers are not so easily raised. This gourd is raised with less trouble, &amp; produces much more abundantly than any other culinary plant. One plant which we raised from your last years seeds produced a gourd which exceeded in bitterness any thing I <del>xx</del> ever tasted: insomuch that I concluded it at once to be the very identical fruit of Zaccoums bitter tree &lt;to eat of&gt; which, according to the Mohammedans is part of the punishment of the damned<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801), Book 7, lines 175&#8211;176. Southey derived this reference from the <title>Qur&#8217;an</title>, 17: 60, 37: 62&#8211;68, 44: 43&#8211;46, 56: 52.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">What is become of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> &amp; the QR? I shall be put to my shifts sorely, if it be delayed much longer.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), &#8216;Histoire de la Th&#233;ophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu&#8217;&#224; son Extinction&#8217;, part of Gr&#233;goire&#8217;s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55&#8211;171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493&#8211;536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">It is frightful to think of what I have to do before I can start for London! But I am in deep water, &amp; must swim for it. My Book of the Church<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> was intended to be one duodecimo volume, &#8211; it will be two octavos. I send off by this post the third sheet of the second volume, &amp; am 50 pages ahead of the printer<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Roworth (c. 1765&#8211;1851), a printer based at Bell-yard, Temple Bar, London.</note> 6 of my pages making one printed sheet. But I have yet 100 pages to write &#8211; <hi rend="ital">vae mihi</hi>!<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Woe is me!&#8217;</note> I should think nothing of this, if I did not wish to be in town at this time, &amp; were not in danger of wanting the produce &#8211; before it arises. The Book however is a good ticket in the wheel,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Wheels&#8217; were the boxes from which tickets in the state lotteries (held 1694&#8211;1826) were drawn, so Southey saw his <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824) as a hopeful entry in the lottery of trying to write a best-selling publication. </note> &#8211; much more likely, I think, to produce permanent profit, than any which I have yet sent into the world. If I were a clergyman, most certainly it would make my fortune.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">What do you think <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> says? that she will wear in a broche that relic of poor Snivel<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Bedford&#8217;s dog, when he and Southey were boys.</note> which I have religiously preserved (now) thirty years(!) &#8211; if you or I will give her a very handsome one to wear it in, &#8211; &amp; she consents that on the inner side of the broche &#8211; locket or shrine there be this inscription Oh rare Snivel! &#8211; I have a lock of your hair which is of the same date.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We have had delightful weather. This is the first thoroughly wet day for many weeks.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have two barrels of cyder in my cellar, &amp; one of strong beer, &#8211; thanks to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>