<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4024. Robert Southey to John Abraham Heraud, 1 June 1823</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4024Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4024. Robert Southey to John Abraham Heraud, 1 June 1823</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4024Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4024" type="letter">
        <head>4024. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HeraudJohn">John Abraham Heraud</ref>, <date when="1823-06-01">1 June 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> J. A. Heraud Jun<hi rend="sup">r</hi>/ Carey Street/ Lincolns Inn <lb />
Stamped: [illegible]<lb />
Postmark: [illegible]<lb />
MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p. <lb />
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 246&#8211;247.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-06-01">1 June. 1823.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent0">You would certainly have seen me had I been in London, &amp; you will see me there God willing before the summer is over.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I wish there were not the necessity for doing something to increase your income, which your letter too surely shows there is. My recommendations of your Nero<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud had sent Southey his tragedy &#8216;Nero&#8217;, centred on Nero Claudius Caesar Drusus Germanicus (AD 37&#8211;68; Roman Emperor AD 54&#8211;68). Heraud did not publish this work.</note> can be of no avail. The question that a bookseller will ask is not whether it be a work of merit, but whether it is likely to sell. Without this assurance the praise which I should bestow &#8211; to wit &#8211; that it is a work of great power &amp; promise, would not suffice: nor indeed with it, unless the bookseller himself saw reason to expect a remunerating sale. You can do no harm by offering it to a publisher, &#8211; but I am afraid you will not find one who will take upon himself the risque of publication, &#8211; much less advance any thing for the copyright. Nor am I sure that eventually it would be serviceable to you to have it before the world. With all its merit it is a juvenile performance; &amp; you have already given proof of poetical genius.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am glad to hear of your lecturing, because it leads you to prose composition; &amp; it by writing for magazines that you may with most facility help out your ways &amp; means. But your great object with this view should be to get a piece upon the stage, something of the mixed drama rather than tragedy, of an attractive, romantic character, &#8211; designed to please, <del>xxx</del> rather than to affect too deeply. Construct the plan first if you succeed in that, you have little or nothing to learn in execution.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The Deluge<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud was planning an epic poem, eventually published as <title>The Judgement of the Flood</title> (1834). Southey discouraged him from publishing hastily or by subscription.</note> is not a subject upon which you can derive any aid from books. The Bible is the sole history of that early age of the world, &amp; every thing relating to manners must be matter of invention, not research. What the circumstances of the world then were it is impossible to know: your business therefore is to describe them such as they may with some appearance of reason be supposed to have been. There is a German poem upon the subject, in hexameters, by Bodmer;<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Johann Bodmer (1698&#8211;1783), <title>Noachide</title> (1752).</note> &#8211; of which a bad translation in <del>prose</del> inflated prose was published some fifty years ago.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Collyer (d. 1776; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Noah. Attempted from the German of Mr. Bodmer. In Twelve Books</title> (1767), no. 311 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I must not omit to notice what you say <del>xxx</del> concerning dedicating your Nero. If the play be published (which I think is not likely) there is no man of letters who would not be gratified by such a compliment. I would recommend you therefore to address it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ScottWalter">Sir W. Scott</ref>, &#8211; a most kind hearted man. His good wishes &amp; good word might be worth something to you: &#8211; mine you have, &amp; unluckily they can be of little value.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You have taken a bold step in marrying.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Heraud married <ref type="m" target="people.html#HeraudAnnElizabeth">Ann Elizabeth Baddams</ref> on 15 May 1823.</note> I will not call it an imprudent one, because it will not be so if you can depend &lt;upon&gt; yourselves for strict frugality &amp; good management. Without these necessary virtues you will have every thing to fear; with them you may have every thing to hope. &#8211; God bless you! I shall look for you as soon as I arrive in town, which will probably be in the course of next month &#8211; </p>
        <p>
          farewell, &amp; believe me<lb/>
          yrs faithfully<lb/>
          Robert Southey.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>