<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4026</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4026Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4026" type="letter">
        <head>4026. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1823-06-03">3 June 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ Richmond/ Surrey<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmarks: E/ 6 JU 6/ 1823; 10 FNoon 10/ JU. 6/ 1823<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 234./ 1822/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> June/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> July<lb />
Watermark: F/ 1821<lb />
MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 201&#8211;203.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-06-03">3. June. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent3">I thought that by this time my intended journey would have been compleated, &amp; that I should have returned to enjoy the summer here, where of all places in England, the lakes &amp; mountains render it most enjoyable. And so it would have been if my Book of the Church had been comprized in one volume, according to the original design.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> I have never dilated, or even dwelt upon parts that are either uninteresting or unimportant; but the subject led me into more details than I had anticipated. I came to events, &#8211; especially in the age of the Martyrs,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 141&#8211;251, dealing with the martyrdom of Protestants under Mary I (1516&#8211;1558; Queen of England 1553&#8211;1558; <title>DNB</title>).</note> where I found &#8211; in the worthy old Fuller&#8217;s words, that all <hi rend="ital">compendium</hi> would be <hi rend="ital">dispendium</hi> thereof:<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;For it is all so excellent, that compendium would be dispendium thereof&#8217;, Thomas Fuller (1608&#8211;1661; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Abel Redevivus; or, the Dead yet Speaking. The Lives and Deaths of the Modern Divines</title> (London, 1651), p. 18, no. 1133 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey had used this quotation from Fuller before in his review of <title>The Works of the Reverend William Huntington, S. S. Minister of the Gospel, at Providence Chapel, Gray&#8217;s Inn Lane, Completed to the Close of the Year 1806</title> (1811), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 483, published 6 April 1821.</note> &#8211; &amp; so, as it was better to spoil my summer than my book, here I am still at my desk, &#8211; the printer is nearly half thro the second volume, &amp; I am far advanced in the chapter relating to Elizabeths reign, better pleased with the work than with the delay which it occasions in my movements.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Book of the Church</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, pp. 252&#8211;312, dealing with the reign of Elizabeth I (1533&#8211;1603; Queen of England 1558&#8211;1603; <title>DNB</title>).</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">My attention has been for some time devoted to this one object more entirely than is comformable either to my inclination or usual habits. But as the extent of the work has been doubled, &amp; as my ways &amp; means depend mainly upon it this becomes unavoidable. The terms with <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> must of course be re-considered, &amp; I believe I shall recur to the original ones, that I have half the profits of this first edition, &amp; two thirds of any succeeding ones.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824) went through three editions in 1824 and reached a ninth edition in 1885.</note> Perhaps it would have been more productive, (relatively so at least) in one volume. Still I think it a more promising adventure than any which I have yet sent abroad; &#8211; for I know no view of our Ecclesiastical history which is in so succinct, continuous &amp; readable a form. &#8211; One inconvenience arises, &amp; for this I must have recourse to you. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">My brother Tom&#8217;s</ref> ways &amp; means for his Canadian expedition are dependent upon me, &amp; were to have arisen from this book.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey was considering emigrating to Canada but decided against doing so after visiting the country.</note> But this delay compels me to request you before the end of this month to pay into the hands of his agent 100&#163; &#8211; the Agents name is Hincksman, &amp; he lives in Great Russell Street &#8211; the number I do not know, but he succeeded to Peytons business.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">John Hinxman (1759&#8211;1844) was a navy agent, whose business was based at 72 Great Russell Street. William Grenfell Peyton (b. 1784) had gone bankrupt in 1822.</note> Will you have the goodness to call upon him &amp; tell him this in case any draft from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> should arrive in the meantime.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I think I have a fair prospect of getting in advance of the world during the next few years, if it please God to continue me in health &amp; ability. Just now I am, according to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harrys</ref> advice, fighting strenuously against my annual catarrh, which has made its regular attack, &amp; has hitherto been kept with some success at bay. Today I had a consultation with <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmondson</ref>, &amp; the result is that on the day when I succeed in suspending the cold, I am to fortify the system with bark.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Willow bark, a common remedy for colds and headaches. </note> This is to be tried tomorrow, &amp; with good hope of subduing a very troublesome enemy.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>. Coleridge</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">her daughter</ref> are now at Bristol, from hence they will commence their journey home in a few days.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I hear nothing of <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref>, except a report from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref> that he is very ill: that he is incapacitated the delay of the Review seems to prove. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> seems to know little of him, &#8211; probably his new office allows him little leisure to see his friends. But it will never do for the Review thus to have its wheels clogged; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> will soon feel this in the failure of his quarterly returns. Heartily do I wish that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> were at the helm, &amp; right gladly should I begin to communicate with him concerning it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The French will be more lucky than they deserve, if after having marched into Spain, they can find a decent excuse for marching out again.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">French forces had invaded Spain on 7 April 1823 to suppress the liberal regime in the country.</note> Abisballe<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Enrique O&#8217;Donnell, Count of Abisbal (1769&#8211;1834), a Spanish general and member of the Council of Regency 1812&#8211;1813. He reluctantly served the liberal regime in 1820&#8211;1823, despite his absolutist convictions.</note> is not a man of good character. Of the persons now upon the stage I should suppose Morillo<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Pablo Morillo y Morillo, Count of Cartagena and Marquess of La Puerta (1775&#8211;1837), a Spanish general. He had fought the revolutionaries in Venezuela 1814&#8211;1820, before returning to Spain to support the liberal regime.</note> to be the one of most ability, Eroles<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Joaquin Ibanez Cuevas y de Valonga, Baron de Eroles (1784&#8211;1825), a Spanish commander during the Peninsular War. He opposed the liberal regime and supported the French invasion of 1823.</note> the one of the highest honour. If they can suppress the Exaltados<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The extreme radicals in Spain.</note> it will so far be well: &#8211; but where are the revenues for any government to be found, the colonies being lost, &amp; property, industry, &amp; subordination destroyed? I see <hi rend="ital">no</hi> prospect of any thing but barbarism for that unhappy country. It will be overrun by banditti till a government arises strong enough to kept all quiet by military force.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref> view of Cintra<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Herbert Hill&#8217;s summer home at Sintra, where Southey had lived June&#8211;October 1800. This engraving was included in <title>A Series of Views of Spain and Portugal, to Illustrate Mr. Southey&#8217;s History of the Peninsular War; Drawn on Stone by W. Westall, A.R.A., from Sketches by General Hawker, Mr. Locker, Mr. Heaphy, &amp;c. Part I, containing Eight Views, illustrating Vol. I</title> (1823).</note> seems to be taken from the road some hundred yards below <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle&#8217;s</ref> house. &#8211; I have had some interesting papers from Trant,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Brigadier-General Nicholas Trant (1769&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>), an Irish soldier who commanded Portuguese troops and militia in the Peninsular War 1808&#8211;1813.</note> &#8211; &amp; that which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> sent me from the Portugueze Ambassador<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Crist&#243;v&#227;o Pedro de Morais Sarmento, 1st Viscount of Torre de Moncorvo (1788&#8211;1851), a Portuguese diplomat. He served in the Portuguese Embassy in London for nearly forty years and was briefly charg&#233; d&#8217;affaires in 1822. His brother, Alexandre Tom&#225;s de Morais Sarmento, 1st Viscount of Banho (1786&#8211;1840), was also a diplomat. Both men had served as volunteers in a Portuguese force raised in Coimbra which had defended the Vouga river against a French army in 1809 and Alexandre Sarmento had written an account of the campaign which had been forwarded to Southey. Southey needed this material for his <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> will be of considerable value, as far as it goes. The second volume<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832). It did not appear until 1827.</note> will not be long in the press, whence once it gets there, &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> is promised the books for which I have so long been waiting, but he gets them thro the American Consul at Madrid,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Hugh Nelson (1768&#8211;1836), an American politician from Virginia and Minister Plenipotentiary from the United States to Spain 1823&#8211;1825. Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877 and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had now written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> &amp; by the circuitous course of a merchant vessel. If my poor correspondent <ref type="m" target="people.html#AbellaManuel">Abella</ref> had been living, I would have had them over in the dispatches.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I know nothing now of what is going on in Portugal, for the Correio Braziliense<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Correio Braziliense</title> (1808&#8211;1822), a liberal Portuguese journal published in London, no. 3203 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> has ceased to be published regularly. The Editor<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Hippolito Jos&#233; da Costa (1774&#8211;1823), editor of <title>Correio Braziliense</title> (1808&#8211;1822).</note> has succeeded in bringing on a revolution, &#8211; &amp; is of course heartily out of humour with the course which it is taking. The aspects however are not so dark as they were. The old abuses cannot be restored, &amp; there is some hope that more of a mixed government may be formed than the Liberales <del>xxx</del> would desire.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Following an army revolt in 1820, a Cortes had been elected in 1820 and John VI (1767&#8211;1826; King of Portugal 1816&#8211;1826) had accepted a new Constitution in October 1822.</note> Without <hi rend="ital">order</hi> &amp; <hi rend="ital">justice</hi> any government, whatever be its form, &amp; by whatever name it may be called, is a detestable tyranny.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">All here desire their kindest remembrances. You have quite won <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your god-daughters</ref> heart. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> goes on well but likes his play better than his book: &#8211; all in good time. Let me hear of you &amp; yours, &amp; remember me most kindly to them. I thought Johnny<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">May&#8217;s son, John May (1802&#8211;1879). He had entered Exeter College, Oxford, in 1823.</note> would have had <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthJohn">John Wordsworth</ref>
          <note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">John Wordsworth entered New College, Oxford, on 21 March 1823 and graduated BA (1826), MA (1830).</note> for a fellow collegian, but he has been placed at New College. God bless you my dear friend.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have a brief letter on the stocks.<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to John May, 20 August 1823&#8211;27 May 1824, Letter 4055.</note>
        </p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2">Yrs affectionately RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>