<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4029" type="letter"><head>4029. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-06-09">9 June [1823]</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmarks: +/ 12 JU 12/ x823; 10 F.NOON 10/ JU.12/ 1823<lb/>
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb/>
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 233. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


            <p rend="indent1">I can only give you the title of the Spanish History from the French translation of it, – Histoire de la Guerre d’Espagne contre Napoleon Buonaparte, par une Commission d’Officiers de toutes armes, etablie a Madrid, aupres de S. Ex. Le Ministre de la Guerre.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Histoire de la Guerre d’Espagne contre Napoléon Buonaparte. Par une Commission d’Officiers de Toutes Armes Etablie a Madrid, Auprès de S. Ex. le Ministre de la Guerre; Traduite de l’Espagnol, Avec Notes et Eclaircissemens</title> (1818).</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">The works which I want are “the War in Catalonia, 4 Vol. Seville. 1815. Anecdotes of Chiefs employed in the Catalonian War, 1816. – &#38; Memoirs of the Sp. Monarchy from the reign of Ferdinand &#38; Isabella, to the usurpation of Joseph Buonaparte, 6 vol. All by Francisco de Olivarez.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford’s ‘On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez’, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221–223. It mentioned Olivarez’s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title> (1815) in four volumes, published at Seville, 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &#38; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist.</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">I am glad to hear of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry’s</ref> prospects.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey had been elected a Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians on 25 June 1823; the <title>London Gazette</title>, 1 July 1823, announced he had been appointed a Physician in Ordinary to George IV.</note> A feather in the cap, leads to something in his profession. – Remember me to Fred. Blackstone,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Frederick Charles Blackstone (1795–1862), a clergyman and a relation by marriage of Hill. Blackstone’s mother was Margaret Bigg-Wither (1768–1842), a sister of Hill’s wife, Catherine. </note> it is well to hear of his recovery as soon as of his illness. Tell him, if he does not already know it, that <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landors</ref> Dialogues<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Landor’s <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title> (1824).</note> are at last in the press, under <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">Julius Hare’s</ref> direction. – I having, at his desire &#38; the publishers,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">John Taylor and Augustus Hessey (1785–1870), publishers, including of the <title>London Magazine</title>.</note> taken upon myself the responsibility of passing, or expurgating such passages as <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">the publisher</ref> (a sensible &#38; conscientious man) objects to.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">A Bostonian<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Samuel Atkins Eliot (1798–1862), brother-in-law of George Ticknor, a prominent figure in Boston society, philanthropist and Mayor of Boston 1837–1839.</note> is coming to me this evening. I shall soon have <del>as many</del> &#60;more&#62; acquaintance in that city than in any English one, London alone excepted.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed></closer>
<lb/>
<postscript><p rend="indent1"><date when="1823-06-09">Monday 9. June.</date></p></postscript>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
