<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4042Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4042Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4042" type="letter">
        <head>4042. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">Herbert Hill</ref>, <date when="1823-07-13">13 July 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ The Reverend Herbert Hill/ Streatham/ Surrey<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmarks: E/ 16 JY 16/ 1823; 10 F. NOON 10/ JY.16/ 1823<lb />
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, WC 234. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Unpublished. </note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-07-13">13 July.</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward&#8217;s</ref> broken head, as it has been brought to light, may do him some service: any exposure of this kind serves for a time to check the abominable system which <ref type="m" target="people.html#GoodenoughEdmund">the head master</ref> wants either feeling, or courage, or sense to suppress. I am more sorry for <ref type="m" target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Phillimore</ref> the father,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">John George Phillimore (1808&#8211;1865; <title>DNB</title>), the eldest surviving son of Joseph Phillimore, had assaulted Edward Hill, a fellow pupil at Westminster School. Like his father, Phillimore was educated at Westminster School (1817&#8211;1824) and Christ Church, Oxford (BA 1828, MA 1831). In later life he was variously a Clerk at the Board of Control 1827&#8211;1832, a barrister and a Liberal MP for Leominster 1852&#8211;1857. In 1820 Phillimore had passed &#8216;The Challenge&#8217; examination and became one of 40 King&#8217;s Scholars at Westminster. They had their own house known as &#8216;College&#8217; and considerable privileges, including the right to proceed to closed scholarships at Trinity College, Cambridge, or Christ Church, Oxford. Edward Hill had just become a member of &#8216;College&#8217;.</note> than for <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref>. He was contemporary with me, &amp; a more inoffensive &amp; thoroughly respectable boy never went thro the school. I never knew him do an ill-natured thing, or say an ill-natured word. But it has been his fate to be notoriously hen-pecked<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Phillimore had married in 1807 Elizabeth n&#233;e Bagot (d. 1859), daughter of Walter Bagot (1731&#8211;1806), a Warwickshire landowner and clergyman.</note> &amp; so <hi rend="ital">mala avis malum ovum</hi>.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;Bad egg of a bad crow&#8217;.</note> Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#PhillimoreJoseph">Phillimore</ref> would have been employed more to his own &amp; to the general good if he had used his influence for putting S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter&#8217;s College to rights, than in meddling with the Marriage Act, &amp; with Catholic Emancipation.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Phillimore was a member of the Grenvillite group that had joined the government in 1822. He was one of the prime movers behind the Marriage Amendment Act (1822), which legalised marriages that had been undertaken in contravention of the terms of the Marriage Act (1753), where both parties were still living together and if neither one of the parties sued to end the union in an ecclesiastical court. He also favoured Catholic Emancipation.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> reached Quebec on the 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> May.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey sailed from Whitehaven on 20 April 1823 on the brig <hi rend="ital">Maria</hi> and reached Quebec on 27 May. He investigated emigrating to Canada but decided against this option.</note> &amp; seems to have been very hospitably received there by Symes,<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">George Symes (c. 1768&#8211;1833), originally from Tenby. He emigrated to Quebec City and in 1802 married Marie Angelique Girard (1763&#8211;1843), widow of Augustin Cuvillier (dates unknown). Symes became a wealthy merchant, trading in wheat, rum, furs and timber, and an important figure in Quebec. He was Master of Trinity House 1818&#8211;1824, the body that regulated shipping and the city&#8217;s harbour and arbitrated disputes between merchants.</note> an old shopman of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyRobertSnr">my Fathers</ref> who married a French-Canadian widow, &amp; is now a rich merchant. On the 31<hi rend="sup">st</hi> he set off in the steam packet for Montreal.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">The Doctor</ref> has been applied to to know whether it would be agreable to me to be elected an Associate of this Royal Society of Literature,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The Royal Society of Literature had been founded in 1820. However, its first Annual General Meeting did not take place until 17 June 1823. This resolved to create 20 Associate Fellows, recommended by the Society&#8217;s Council, on the terms outlined by Southey. </note> &#8211; certainly it will not, seeing the scheme is so excellently miscontrived that such an appointment carries with it neither honour nor profit. The person so appointed is to write an annual essay, &amp; receive 100 guineas a year. Now it is quite as well to receive 100 &#163; for an article in the Q.R. as far as profit is concerned, &amp; in other points a great deal better. I could do no worse that to accept such an offer, if it were come to <hi rend="ital">date obolum</hi>.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;spare a farthing&#8217;, the cry of a beggar. In other words, Southey saw this as a charitable offer to one in desperate straits.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith-May</ref> has had a severe bilious attack, which has left her very weak. To day has brought with it the first appearance of a convalescents appetite. I shall probably send her shortly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworths</ref> for change of air, &amp; delay my own journey till the middle of the autumn for the sake of taking her with me. She has invitations to the East &amp; the West, &amp; will make a wide progress before she returns home. &#8211; For myself I have not been able to subdue the annual visitation of catarrh, &amp; it has brought on a return of my old infirmity,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s rectal prolapse.</note> &#8211; but in a slight degree. I am now trying for it the balsam of Copaiba,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Balsam of Copaiba is derived from the South American tree of the <hi rend="ital">Copaifera</hi> genus. It has been used to treat a wide variety of ailments including bronchitis, constipation and haemorrhoids.</note> with good opinion of its efficacy A companion who would walk with me from ten to twenty miles a day would prove the surest physician. &#8211; The rest of my household are in tolerable condition, thank God. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> has insensibly past from infancy into that stage of childhood when the character of the individual physical &amp; moral begins to assume its permanent features. He grows very thin, &#8211; &amp; it is not without some secret apprehension that I perceive how much the intellectual is likely to predominate over the animal part of his <del>xxxx xxxx xxxx</del> nature.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">That I may pass to a lighter subject &#8211; here are eight conundrums for the boys, each containing the name of a Greek author</p>
        <p rend="indent1">1 Anna, my wife.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">2 A common play thing belonging to Henry &amp; his brother.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">3 What happens if when I am looking into the glass, you [MS missing]ok in it too?</p>
        <p rend="indent1">[MS missing]hat a pair of turtle doves who are offered for sale would say to the Duchess of Gloucester<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Princess Mary, Duchess of Gloucester and Edinburgh (1776&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), sister of George IV. As Mrs Gonne&#8217;s first name was also Mary, and &#8216;Polly&#8217; was a common nickname for &#8216;Mary&#8217;, Southey&#8217;s conundrum can be unravelled.</note> (or to <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref>) if they could speak.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">5 Lady Diana, highly perfumed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">6 A woman&#8217;s peculiarities.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">7 A wandering young Gentleman</p>
        <p rend="indent1">8 Lay your hand upon your breeches pocket, &amp; then ask &#8220;what part is this?</p>
        <p rend="indent0">On the opposite page is the key to this nonsense.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The answers are written upside down at the foot of fol. 1r. </note> If it be nonsensical enough to make <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">my Aunt</ref> &amp; Miss Bigg<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Alethea Bigg (1777&#8211;1847), sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife.</note> smile, I shall be glad</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">1. Menander. 2 Harry&#8217;s top and his. 3 Isaeus. 4 Polly, buy us! 5 Diodorus. 6. Her oddities. 7 Strabo. 8. Your hip it is.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">These, the answers to Southey&#8217;s riddles, correspond to: Menander (c. 342/341 BC&#8211;c. 290 BC), Greek dramatist; Aristophanes (c. 446&#8211;c. 386 BC), Greek comic playwright; Isaeus (fl. early 4th century BC), Greek orator; Polybius (c. 200&#8211;c. 118 BC), Greek historian; Diodorus Siculus (fl. 1st century BC), Greek historian; Herodotus (c. 484&#8211;c. 425 BC), Greek historian; Strabo (64/63 BC&#8211;c. AD 24), Greek geographer, philosopher and historian; and Euripides (c. 480&#8211;c. 406 BC), Greek tragedian.</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>