<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4047. Robert Southey to John Murray, 19 July 1823</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4047Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4047. Robert Southey to John Murray, 19 July 1823</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4047Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4047" type="letter">
        <head>4047. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">John Murray</ref>, <date when="1823-07-19">19 July 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John Murray Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Albemarle Street/ London <lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 22 JY 22/ 1823<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
Watermark: F/ 1821<lb />
Endorsement: July 9. 1823/ R. Southey Esq<lb />
MS: National Library of Scotland, MS 42552. ALS; 3p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-07-19">19 July. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">My advice to you concerning Irving<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Irving (1792&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), a Scottish clergyman, and a celebrity preacher currently attracting large congregations in London, including many from high society. Irving&#8217;s popularity had begun to wane by 1827, and in 1833 he was expelled from the Church of Scotland.</note> is to let him alone, &#8211; &amp; in a very short time he will sink as low as Col. Wardle<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Gwyllym Lloyd Wardle (c. 1761&#8211;1833), the MP for Okehampton 1807&#8211;1812, who had gained temporary fame when he publicised alleged corruption in army appointments in January 1809. However, his reputation plummeted later that year when it was revealed he had paid substantial sums to gain evidence of the events he condemned and was in collusion with some of the parties he had accused. </note> &amp; the Young Roscius.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Henry West Betty (1791&#8211;1874; <title>DNB</title>), child actor, known as the &#8216;Young Roscius&#8217;, after the famous Roman actor, Quintus Roscius Gallus (c. 126&#8211;62 BC). Betty had caused a sensation in a number of roles in 1804, but his reputation soon waned and his attempts at acting as an adult were complete failures.</note>
          <del>it xxxx</del> His delivery I suppose imposes upon the persons whom you have mentioned, but surely it is not possible that they &lt;can&gt; admire the bloated affectation of his book.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Irving, <title>For the Oracles of God, Four Orations. For the Judgement to Come: an Argument, in Nine Parts</title> (1823), no. 1487 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; I have long thought of writing a paper upon our Divines, when the new edition of South comes out<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert South (1634&#8211;1716; <title>DNB</title>), Anglican clergyman and theologian. A new edition of his <title>Sermons Preached upon Several Occasions</title> (1823) was shortly to be published, but Southey did not write on this subject for the <title>Quarterly Review</title>. This edition was no. 2574 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">You shall have Charles 2.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Bishop Burnet&#8217;s History of his Own Time: with the Suppressed Passages of the First Volume and Notes by the Earls of Dartmouth and Hardwicke, and Speaker Onslow, Hitherto Unpublished; to Which are Added the Cursory Remarks of Swift, and Other Observations </title>(1823), no. 498 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a new edition of Gilbert Burnet (1643&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of My Own Time</title> (1724&#8211;1734), edited by Martin Routh (1755&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>). Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 165&#8211;214, published 27&#8211;28 September 1823, and used the occasion to survey the reign of Charles II (1630&#8211;1685; King of Great Britain 1660&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>).</note> in the course of four weeks &#8211; The only book of Norths which I have is his Life of the Lord Keeper Guilford.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Roger North (1651&#8211;1734; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Life of the Right Honourable Francis North, Baron of Guildford</title> (1808). This was a biography of Francis North, 1st Baron Guildford (1637&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>), the lawyer, judge and Lord Keeper of the Great Seal 1682&#8211;1685. A later edition of 1826 was no. 2045 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; I am inclined to think that one of the most useful books you could supply <del>with</del> me with would be Sir Roger L&#8217;Estranges Observator,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Roger L&#8217;Estrange (1616&#8211;1704; <title>DNB</title>), a royalist journalist and editor of <title>The Observator</title> (1681&#8211;1687), a pro-Tory newspaper and no. 1678 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> if you could lay your hands upon a set.
                  <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco White</ref> is of all men the fittest to write upon the state of Spain<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Blanco White published a review of Michael Joseph Quin (1796&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Visit to Spain; Detailing the Transactions which Occurred during a Residence in that Country in the Latter Part of 1822, and the First Four Months of 1823. With an Account of the Removal of the Court from Madrid to Seville; and General Notices of the Manners, Customs, Costume and Music of the Country</title>, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823) 240&#8211;276, published 27 or 28 September 1823.</note> He is thoroughly acquainted with his countrymen, &amp; is moreover a most judicious &amp; right-minded man.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Hayleys book seems to me a good thread for the literature of that age in which he was <hi rend="ital">in flower</hi>, &amp; it contains anecdotes enough to make an interesting life, if well put together.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title> (1823), no. 1179 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 31 (March 1825), 263&#8211;311.</note> There is an admission on the editors part that his course of life had not been what it ought.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">John Johnson (1769&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq. the Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself; with Extracts from his Private Correspondence, and Unpublished Poetry; and Memoirs of his Son Thomas Alphonso Hayley, the Young Sculptor</title>, 2 vols (London, 1823), II, p. 218. William Hayley (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>) had a complex private life. He separated from his first wife, Eliza Ball (1750&#8211;1797), in 1789 and from his, much younger, second wife, Mary Welford (1781&#8211;1848), in 1812 after only three years of marriage. He also had at least one illegitimate child, Thomas Alphonso Hayley (1780&#8211;1800; <title>DNB</title>).</note> As you say he survived his works, &amp; yet he has the merit of having awakened that taste for Italian &amp; Spanish Literature from which we are deriving so much.<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">William Hayley, <title>An Essay on Epic Poetry; in Five Epistles to the Revd Mr. Mason. With Notes</title> (London, 1782), pp. 202&#8211;273, included accounts of the life and work of Lope F&#233;lix de Vega y Carpio (1562&#8211;1635) and Alonso de Ercilla y Zu&#241;iga (1533&#8211;1594), with quotations and translations. This provided Southey&#8217;s introduction to Spanish poetry.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Faust has disappointed me.<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Lord Francis Leveson Gower (1800&#8211;1857; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Faust; a Drama, by Goethe: and Schiller&#8217;s Song of the Bell</title> (1823), no. 1110 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was an early translation of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1749&#8211;1832), <title>Faust, Part One</title> (1808).</note> The merits no doubt lie in the <hi rend="ital">manner</hi>, &amp; are therefore untranslatable, as is the case with Horace &amp; Virgil.<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Quintus Horatius Flaccus (65&#8211;8 BC) and Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), Roman poets.</note> It is plainly an imitation of the Spanish drama, &#8211; &amp; our Elizabethan dramatists judged I think more rightly than Lord L Gower, when they preferred our dramatic blank verse to the manner of their Spanish prototypes. He has rhymed it with great skill &amp; freedom; &#8211; but in the drama this is doing a bad thing well.</p>
        <p>
          Yrs very truly<lb/>
          RS.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">The French, you see, are announcing just such a collection of English Memoirs as I advised you to undertake.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to John Murray, 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693. However, Murray had not proceeded with this project. Possibly to try and stir Murray into action, Southey is here drawing Murray&#8217;s attention to the following report: &#8216;The success of the Collection of Memoirs, relative to the French Revolution, has induced the publication of a Collection of Memoirs relative to the English Revolution; two volumes are published, containing Memoirs of Warwick, in the reign of Charles I., and the first volume of Thomas May&#8217;s History of the Long Parliament. The following livraisons will contain the Memoirs of Fairfax, Ludlow, Price, Thomas Herbert, Sir William Temple, Major Huntington, Bishop Burnet, Lord Clarendon, &amp;c.&#8217; (<title>London Magazine</title>, 7 (April 1823), &#8216;Sketch of Foreign Literature&#8217;, 471).</note>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>