<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4050Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4050" type="letter">
        <head>4050. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1823-08-02">2 August 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-<lb />
Watermark: F/ 1821<lb />
Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 235/ 1823/ Robert Southey/ Keswick 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> August/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<lb />
MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 203&#8211;205.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-08-02">2 Aug. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear friend</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">There is one omission in your letter, which I interpret in good part: you say nothing of your own health; but as you are well enough to go thro a regular course of Brighton stage-coaching, I conclude therefrom that it is thoroughly reestablished, &amp; that neither the disease nor the remedies have left any weakness behind them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">My annual cold has, I hope, now run its course &amp; taken its departure. I shall not recover from its effects so soon as if I had a guest with me to lead me over the mountains; however I take all opportunities that occur &amp; use more solitary exercise than is agreable. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your goddaughter</ref> went on Monday last to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth&#8217;s</ref>, for change of air. She has had a somewhat severe bilious attack, the effects of which were hanging upon her. We have good accounts from her &#8211; she has horse-exercise there which she is very fond of; but I believe she will not be persuaded to remain there longer than next Monday. She <del>xx</del> is very much attached to <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthDora">Dora Wordsworth</ref> &#8211; fond of <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthMary">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
          </ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthDorothy">Miss W</ref> &#8211; as intimate with <ref type="m" target="people.html#HutchinsonSara">Miss Hutchinson</ref> as difference of age will allow, &#8211; &amp; familiar with <ref type="m" target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam                ">W.</ref> himself whom she has known from her infancy, &amp; who has a great regard for her. so that there is no place except her own home where she could possibly feel so much at home as there. But still she feels that she never is or can be so happy any where else as here. However she has made up her mind to pay her visits in the South when I go to London.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Edward Coleridge<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Coleridge (1800&#8211;1883), brother of John May&#8217;s friend, <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Taylor Coleridge</ref>. He was a Master at Eton College 1825&#8211;1857, Fellow of Eton College 1857&#8211;1883 and Vicar of Mapledurham 1862&#8211;1883.</note> made his appearance on Wednesday last. On Thursday I gave him a mornings boating, yesterday he was weather-bound &amp; this morning he set off with your guide William Bird<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">William Bird (dates unknown) acted as a guide for visitors to the Lake District; he had guided John May on his visit in 1822.</note> for the Waswater tour, from which we expect him back on Monday. &#8211; </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I must now tell you what <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Coleridge</ref> told him in my presence, &amp; no doubt with the intention that I should hear it, tho she has never at any time spoken a word to me on the subject, nor even hinted at it. Upon mention of your son&#8217;s name,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John May (1802&#8211;1879). On a visit to Southey at Greta Hall in August&#8211;September 1822 he had become infatuated with Sara Coleridge &#8211; a feeling that was not reciprocated.</note> she told him that he was then in North Wales, &amp; that he talked of coming to this place: &#8211; an intention which I find he has communicated to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> by letter a few days ago. &#8211; This as you will at once perceive places me in a difficult situation. I think if your opinion upon this point had undergone any change you would have informed me of it; &#8211; &amp; unless I were assured that this attachment on his part <del>were</del> had now received your approbation; I should feel myself acting very culpably in entertaining him here; &amp; affording him those opportunities which can only be had by being under the same roof with her. Yet on the other hand it will be very unpleasant, &#8211; not to say painful, &#8211; to receive him coldly &amp; repulsively. That he has continued to write to her is now evident. What encouragement he has received I know not. &#8211; Tell me how I am to act, &#8211; if there should not be time for you to prevent the visit &#8211; I did not expect this perseverance on his part: &#8211; &amp; had his attentions been discontinued I am quite certain that <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> would <del>xxx</del> &lt;long ago&gt; have felt herself disengaged. An expectant attachment of this nature may often I believe be highly useful to the man, as giving him the surest of all preventatives against the greatest danger which lies in the way of youth. But it is not so on the womans part.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Enough of this &#8211; &amp; I am afraid too much for your comfort.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2">God bless you</salute>
          <salute rend="indent3">Yrs most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent4">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>