<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4055Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4055Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4055" type="letter">
        <head>4055. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref>, <date when="1823-08-20">20 August 1823&#8211;27 May 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. AL; 5p.<lb />
Previously edited or published: Michael Neill Stanton, &#8216;An Edition of the Autobiographical Letters of Robert Southey&#8217; (unpublished PhD, University of Rochester, 1972), pp. 137&#8211;147; <lb />
Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), I, pp. 91&#8211;100 [with variants; the text draws on a fair copy of the letter and not on the original version sent to May, which we publish here].</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1823-08-20">August 20. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">My memory strengthens as I proceed in this task of retrospection &amp; yet while some circumstances &#8211; even to a look, a sound, a gesture, tho utterly unimportant recur to me more vividly that the transactions of yesterday, others which I would willingly <del>recover</del> call to mind are irrecoverably gone. I have sometimes fancied when dreaming upon what may be our future state, that in the next world we may recover a perfect recollection of all that has occurred to us in this, &amp; in the prior stages of progressive existence, thro which it is not improbable that our living principle has ascended. And yet the best &amp; happiest of us must have some thing or other <hi rend="ital">alt&#226; mente repostum</hi>
          <note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;stored deep in the heart&#8217;, a quotation from Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), <title>Aeneid</title> (19 BC), Book 1, line 26.</note> for which a draught of Lethe<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">In Greek mythology, Lethe was a river of the underworld that gave complete forgetfulness to all who drank from its waters.</note> would be desired.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The pleasantest of my school-years were those which I past at Williams&#8217;s,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">William Williams (d. 1811), Southey&#8217;s schoolmaster at Merchants&#8217; Hall School, Bristol, 1782&#8211;1786.</note> especially after I took up my abode in Terril Street,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The home of Southey&#8217;s aunt, <ref type="m" target="people.html#TylerElizabeth">Elizabeth Tyler</ref>.</note> for I then dined at home, &amp; found much more satisfaction there in my own pursuits than in his contracted play ground. What I learnt there indeed was worth little, &#8211; it was just such a knowledge of Latin as a boy of quick parts &amp; not without diligence, will acquire under bad teaching. When I had gone thro the Metamorphoses,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Ovidius Naso (43 BC&#8211;AD 17/18), <title>Metamorphoses</title> (c. AD 8).</note> Williams declared his intention of taking me from the usher<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Henry Bevan (c. 1761&#8211;1824), Pembroke College, Oxford BA (1783), later Stipendiary Curate of Congresbury, Somerset 1797&#8211;1818, Vicar of Congresbury 1818&#8211;1824 and Preacher throughout the Diocese of Bath and Wells 1818&#8211;1824.</note> &amp; instructing me in Virgil himself, &#8211; no other of his pupils having proceeded so far. But the old man I supposed discovered that this little classical learning which he <del>had</del> ever possessed had past away as irrecoverably as his youth, &amp; I continued under the Ushers care, who kept me in the Eclogues<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Publius Vergilius Maro (70&#8211;19 BC), <title>Eclogues</title> (37 BC).</note> so long that I was heartily sick of them, &amp; I believe have never looked in them from that time. No attempt was made to ground me in prosody, &amp; as this deficiency in my education was never remedied (for when I went to Westminster I was too forward in other things to be placed low enough for the regular training), I am at this day as liable to make a false quantity<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Faulty pronunciation or metrical use of a vowel when reading Latin poetry.</note> as any Scotchman. I was fond of arithmetic, &amp; have no doubts that at that time I should have proceeded with pleasure thro its higher branches, &amp; might have been led on to mathematics, of which my mind afterwards became impatient, if not totally incapable.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Sometimes when Williams was in good humour, he suspended the usual business of the school, &amp; exercised the boys in some uncommon manner. For example, he would bid them all take their slates, &amp; write as he dictated, &#8211; this was to try their spelling &amp; I remember he once began with this sentence As I walked out to take the air, I met a man with red hair, who was heir to a good estate, &amp; was carrying a hare in his hand. Another time he called upon all of a certain standing to write a letter, each upon what subject he pleased. You will perhaps wonder to hear that <del>not</del> no task <del>had</del> ever perplexed me so wofully as this. I had never in my life written a letter, except a formal one at Corston before every holydays, every word of which was of the masters dictation.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had attended a school at Corston 1781&#8211;1782 run by Thomas Flower (d. 1799).</note> &#8211; Some of the boys produced compositions of this stamp, others who were a little older wrote in a tradesman like stile, soliciting orders, or acknowledging them. For my part I actually cried for perplexity &amp; vexation. Had I been a blockhead this would have provoked Williams but he always looked upon me with a favourable eye, &amp; expressing wonder rather than anger he endeavoured both to encourage &amp; shame me to the attempt. To work I fell at last &amp; presently presented him with &#8211; a description of Stonehenge in the form of a letter, which compleatly filled the slate. I had laid hands not long before upon the Salisbury Guide,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Salisbury Guide, Giving an Account of the Antiquities of Old Sarum, and the Ancient and Present State of New Sarum, or Salisbury; the Cathedral, Stonehenge, Seats of the Nobility and Gentry etc.</title> appeared regularly from c. 1770 to 1826 and described the city and its environs for visitors. Stonehenge, a ring of standing stones dating from 3000&#8211;2000 BC, is only eight miles from Salisbury.</note> &amp; Stonehenge had appeared to me one of the wonders of the world. The old man was exceedingly surprized, &amp; not less delighted, &amp; I well remember how much his astonishment surprized me, &amp; how much I was gratified by his praise. I was not conscious of having done anything &lt;odd or&gt; extraordinary: but the boys made me so; &amp; to the sort of envy which it excited among them I <del>xxxx</del> was indebted for a wholesome mortification One morning upon entering the school a few minutes before the Master made his appearance some half dozen of them beset me, &amp; demanded whether I with all my learning could tell what the letters i.e.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. is the standard abbreviation for the Latin phrase &#8216;id est&#8217;, meaning &#8216;in other words&#8217;.</note> stood for. The question was proposed in the taunting tone of expected triumph, which I should well have liked to disappoint. But when I answered &lt;that I supposed it was for&gt; <del>why</del> John the Evangelist<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">John the Evangelist, the name traditionally given to the author of the Gospel of John, the fourth book of the New Testament.</note>
          <del>I suppose</del> &#8211; the unlucky guess taught me never again to be ashamed of confessing myself ignorant of what I really did not know: It was a useful lesson, especially as I was fortunate enough to perceive early in life that there were very many subjects of which I must of necessity be so.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Of all my schoolmasters Williams is the one whom I remember with the kindliest feelings. His Welsh blood was too easily roused, &amp; his <del>x</del> spirit was soured by the great decline of his school. <del>There had been a time</del> when Its numbers &lt;in its best days had been&gt; <del>were</del> from seventy to a hundred, &#8211; now they did not reach forty, when the times were dearer by all the difference which the American War<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The War of American Independence (1775&#8211;1783) had affected Bristol badly as the city depended on transatlantic trade.</note> had occasioned, &amp; his <del>price</del> terms could not be raised in proportion to the increased price of every thing, because schools had multiplied. When his ill circumstances prest upon him, he gave way perhaps more readily to impulses of anger, because anger like drunkenness suspends the sense of care &lt;&amp; an irascible emotion is felt as a relief from <del>uneasy</del> painful thoughts&gt;. His old wig, like a bank of morning clouds in the East, used to indicate a stormy day. At better times both the wig &amp; the countenance would have beseemed a higher station, &amp; his anger was the more frightful because at those better times there was an expression of good <del>nature</del> &lt;humour&gt; &amp; animation in his features which was singularly pleasing, &amp; I believe denoted his genuine character. He would strike with a ruler sometimes, when his patience was greatly provoked by that incorrigible stupidity which of all things <del>tries</del> perhaps puts patience to the severest trial. There was a hulking fellow &#8211; a Creole<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Someone born in the West Indies. The term did not necessarily denote a person of mixed race.</note> with a shade of <del>negro</del> African colour in him who possessed that stupidity in the highest degree, &amp; Williams after flogging him one day <del>xxx</del> made him pay a halfpenny for <del>requiring</del> the use of the rod &lt;because he required it&gt; so much oftener than any other boy in the school. Whether Gumbes<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">The Gumbes (or Gumbs) family had been leading plantation-owners on the Caribbean island of Anguilla since the early eighteenth century, and Southey&#8217;s fellow pupil may well have been part of this family.</note> were most sensible of the mulct or the mockery I know not, but he felt it as the severest part of his punishment. A tyrannical act it certainly was, but the only one I ever knew <del>him</del> &lt;Williams&gt; guilty of.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">There were a good many Creoles at this school, as indeed at all the Bristol schools. <del>Acajou nuts &amp;</del> Cassava bread<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Acajou nuts are cashew nuts. Cassava bread is a flat bread made with flour from the grated root of cassava, a woody shrub native to South America. Its alternative name is manioc. It was a staple food in the West Indies.</note> was among the things which were frequently sent over to them by their parents, &#8211; so that I well knew the taste of mandioc long before I <del>ever</del> heard its name. These Creoles were neither better nor worse than so many other boys in any respect, indeed tho they had a stronger national cast of countenance they were I think less marked by any national<del>ity of temper</del> &lt;features of mind&gt; or disposition than the Welsh, certainly much less than the Irish. <del>Some of</del> One of them, evidently by his name of French extraction<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> was however the most thoroughly fiendish human being that I have ever known. There is an image in Kehama drawn from my recollection of the devilish malignity which used sometimes to <del>xx</del> glow in his dark eyes,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, <title>The Curse of Kehama</title> (London, 1810), p. 43; Book 5, stanza 12, lines 1&#8211;4: &#8216;That Spectre fix&#8217;d his eyes upon her full;/ The light which shone in their accursed orbs/ Was like a light from Hell,/ And it grew deeper, kindling with the view.&#8217;</note> &#8211; tho I could not there give the likeness in its whole force for his countenance used to darken with the blackness of his passions. Happily for the slaves on the family estate he, tho a second brother was wealthy enough to settle in England, &amp; an anecdote which I heard of him when he was about thirty years of age well shows that I have not spoken of his character too strongly. When he was shooting one day his dog made a fault; he would have shot him for this upon the spot, if his companion had not turned the gun aside, &amp; as he supposed succeeded in appeasing him. But <del>xx</del> when their sport was over, to the horror of that companion (who related the story to me) he <del>suddenly</del> took up a large stone &amp; knocked out the dogs brains. I have mentioned this wretch, who might otherwise have better been forgotten, for a charitable reason: because I verily believe that his wickedness was truly an original, innate, constitutional sin, &amp; just as much a family disease, as gout or scrofula. I think so because he had a nephew<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> who was placed as a pupil with <ref type="m" target="people.html#KingJohn">King</ref> the surgeon at Clifton, &amp; &lt;in&gt; whom at first sight I recognized a physiognomy which I hope can belong to no other breed. This nephew answered in all respects to the &lt;relationship, &amp; to the&gt; character which Nature had written in every lineament of his face: &#8211; he ran a short career of knavery, profligacy &amp; crimes, which led him into a prison, &amp; there he died by his own hand.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Another of my then schoolfellows, who was also a Creole came to <del>the same</del> &lt;a like&gt; fate, but from <del>xx</del> very different circumstances. He was the natural son of a wealthy planter by a woman of colour, &amp; went thro school with the character of an inoffensive gentlemanly boy, who never quarrelled with any body, not ever did an ill natured thing. When he became a young man, he was liberally supplied with money, &amp; launched into expences which such means tended to create, &amp; seemed to justify. The supplies <del>however</del> suddenly ceased. I am not certain whether <del>xx</del> by an experiment of rigour <del>on the fathers part</del>, or owing to his fathers dying without providing for him in his will: &#8211; the latter I think was the case; poor Herbert<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">John Herbert (dates unknown), the illegitimate son of John Richardson Herbert (d. 1793), President of the Council of Nevis and owner of the Montpelier Estate; and Maria (dates unknown), a free mulatto. Southey was incorrect. Herbert (who was still living in Bristol at the time of his father&#8217;s death) was left a total of &#163;2,500, plus several valuable items, including his father&#8217;s gold watch chain and seals. By 1794/5 he had moved to Warren Street, St Pancras, London, and may have been working as a merchant. Mounting debts led to his assigning &#163;1,000 of his inheritance. Herbert&#8217;s date of death is uncertain but was before 1824.</note> however was arrested for debt, &amp; put an end to his hopeless prospects in prison by suicide.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Colonel Hugh Baillie<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Hugh Duncan Baillie (1777&#8211;1866), son of Evan Baillie (1741&#8211;1835), a Scottish landowner and soldier who settled in Bristol and became a wealthy West Indies merchant. Hugh Duncan Baillie had an undistinguished army career, finally becoming a colonel in 1810, and then took over the joint management of the family firm in 1812, also becoming a partner in the Bristol Old Bank. He was later MP for Rye 1830&#8211;1831 and Honiton 1835&#8211;1847.</note> who made himself conspicuous some few months ago by very properly resenting the unjust expulsion of his son from Christ Church by the late Dean<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Baillie was the author of the pamphlet <title>A Letter from Colonel Hugh D. Baillie to the Very Reverend the Dean of Christ Church; Together with a Correspondence Relating to the Removal of Mr Henry Baillie from that College</title> (1823). His son, Henry James Baillie (1803&#8211;1885), was later Conservative MP for Inverness-shire 1840&#8211;1868. He was expelled from Christ Church for participating in a riot in May 1823, despite protesting that he took no part in the proceedings. Baillie was expelled by Charles Henry Hall (1763&#8211;1827; <title>DNB</title>), Dean of Christ Church 1809&#8211;1824, and Dean of Durham 1824&#8211;1827.</note> was one of my contemporaries at this school. My old Latin master Duplanier<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">Du Planier (dates unknown) was a French expatriate who ran a school in Bristol and taught part-time at the school Southey attended in Corston. He returned to France in 1790.</note> kept a French academy next door, &amp; by an arrangement between the two Masters, his boys came three mornings in the week to write &amp; cipher with us. Among these intermittent schoolfellows, were poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#MorganJohnJames">John Morgan</ref> who housed <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> for several years, &#8211; Gee<note n="24" place="foot" resp="editors">Captain George Gee (d. 1827), of Wraxall, Somerset, who was renting Ivy Cottage at Rydal. He seems to have played an important backstage role in organising the Lowther family&#8217;s election contests in Westmorland in 1818, 1820 and 1826.</note> whom I have already mentioned, &amp; a certain Harry Overend,<note n="25" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Overend (dates unknown). Overend was clearly searching widely for solutions to his financial problems. On 9 November 1797 he patented &#8216;a machine which may be used as a wagon, cart or dray, in a more perfect or expeditious manner, and with fewer horses, than usually and heretofore done&#8217; (<title>Annual Register</title>, 29 (1800), 409).</note> with whom I had an adventure in after life far too curious to be forgotten. This youth was about three years older than me; of course I had no acquaintance with him, nor did I ever exchange a word with him unless it were when the whole school were engaged in playing <del>at</del> prisonbase,<note n="26" place="foot" resp="editors">The old children&#8217;s game of prisoner&#8217;s base. The children divided themselves into two teams who faced each other. Each team nominated a &#8216;prisoner&#8217; who was placed in a designated area behind the other team. The object was for each team to rescue its prisoner and prevent the other side&#8217;s prisoner escaping.</note> &#8211; in which he took the lead as the &#960;&#959;&#948;&#945;&#962; &#969;&#954;&#965;&#962;<note n="27" place="foot" resp="editors">A partial quotation of Homer&#8217;s <title>Illiad</title>, Book 1, line 84, where &#8216;&#960;&#959;&#948;&#945;&#962; &#969;&#954;&#965;&#962; &#913;&#967;&#953;&#955;&#955;&#949;&#965;&#962;&#8217; can be translated as &#8216;swift-footed Achilles&#8217;.</note> of his side. His father<note n="28" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly William Overend (dates unknown), a Bristol merchant engaged in the West Indies trade.</note> was a merchant, concerned among other things in the Irish linen trade; my father had some dealings with him, &amp; in his misfortune found him, what I believe is <hi rend="ital">not</hi> a common character, &#8211; an unfeeling creditor. They were a proud family, &amp; <del>xxxxx</del> a few years after my fathers failure, failed themselves, &amp; <del>went x</del> as the phrase is went to the dogs. This Harry Overend was bred to be an Attorney, but wanted either brains or business to succeed in his profession, &#8211; I daresay both. I had forgotten his person, &amp; should never have thought of him again except when the game of prisonbase was brought to my mind, if in the year 1798 I had not been surprized by hearing one day <del>xx</del> at <ref type="m" target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottles shop</ref>, that he had been there twice or thrice to enquire for me, &amp; had left a message requesting that if I came into Bristol that day, I would call on him at an Attorneys office at a certain hour. Accordingly thither I went, rang at the bell, enquired for Mr Overend, gave my name, &amp; was ushered into a private room. Nothing could be more gracious that his recognition of a person whom he must have past twenty times in the street during the last three months &#8211; we had been schoolfellows at such a place, at such a time &#8211; &amp;c all which I knew very well, but how we came to be acquaintances now was what I had to learn, &amp; to explain this cost him a good deal of humming &amp; hawing, plentifully intermixed with that figure of speech which the Irish call <hi rend="ital">blarney</hi>, &#8211; &amp; which is a much more &lt;usual as well as&gt; useful figure than any of those with the hard names of which poor boys used to be tormented in the Latin Grammar. From the use which he made of this figure he appeared to know that I was an author of some notoriety, &amp; that one of my books was called Joan of Arc<note n="29" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Joan of Arc</title> (1796).</note> &#8211; the compliments which he laid <del>me</del> &lt;on&gt; were intermingled with <del>great</del> expressions of &lt;great&gt; regret for the deficiencies of his own education, he had learnt a little Latin &#8211; a little French, -but then it had stopt, &#8211; in short I knew &lt;what must be&gt; the extent of his <del>teaching</del> &lt;acquirements), for you &amp; I M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey you know were schoolfellows,&#8221; &#8211; &amp; at length it <del>appeared</del> &lt;came out&gt; that from a consciousness of these deficiencies he had been led to think that a Glossary of the English language was a <del>thing</del> work very much wanted, &amp; that no <del>person</del> &lt;one&gt; could be more competent to supply such a desideratum than the gentleman whom he had the honour of addressing. I was as little able to guess what his deficiencies had to do with <del>any such x</del> a Glossary as you can be; &amp; not feeling any curiosity to get at a blockheads meaning endeavoured to put an end to the scene by declaring at once my utter inability to execute such a work, for the very sufficient reason that I was wholly ignorant of several languages the thorough knowledge &lt;of which&gt; was indispensable in such researches. This produced more blarney, &amp; an explanation that <del>such a work as I seemed to</del> my answer did not exactly apply to what his proposal intended. What he meant was this, there were a great many elegant words, which persons, like himself, &#8211; whose education had been neglected, &#8211; would often be glad to use in conversation, &#8211; (<del>he spoke</del> he said this feelingly, &#8211; it had often been his own case,) &#8211; they would be glad to use them, if they only knew their meaning: &amp; what he wanted was a Glossary or Dictionary of such words, &#8211; a little book, which might be carried in the pocket; it would certainly command a large sale: I could make the book; &#8211; he had a large acquaintance, &amp; could procure subscribers for it, &#8211; &amp; we might make a thriving partnership concern in this literary undertaking. Before he arrived at this point, the scene had become far too comical to leave any room in my feelings for anger. I kept my countenance &#8211; (which has often been put to much harder trials than my temper, &amp; is moreover a much more difficult thing to keep,) &#8211; declined his proposal decidedly but civilly, took my leave in perfect &lt;good&gt; humour, &amp; hastened back to <ref type="m" target="people.html#CottleJoseph">Cottle&#8217;s</ref> to relieve myself by telling him the adventure.</p>
        <lb />
        <closer>
          <date when="1824-05-27">May 27. 1824</date>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>