<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4058" type="letter"><head>4058. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">John Taylor</ref>, <date when="1823-09-09">9 September 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ John Taylor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Waterloo Place/ Pall Mall/ London<lb/>
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb/>
Postmark: E/ 12 SE 12/ 1823<lb/>
MS: Robert H. Taylor Collection, Princeton University Library. ALS; 3p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1823-09-09">9 Sep<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">The impression which that dialogue between Middleton &#38; Magliabechi has left upon me is, that its tendency would be to expose the superstitious <del>xxxx of</del> abuse of prayer in idolatrous countries, rather than to weaken a Christians trust in it.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Dialogue XVIII in Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), I, pp. 345–362, between Conyers Middleton (1683–1750; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman widely suspected of unorthodox views, and Antonio di Marco Magliabechi (1633–1714), a bibliophile and librarian to the Grand Dukes of Tuscany, 1673–1714. At his death, Conyers left a manuscript on the ‘inefficacy of prayer’, which Landor used as the starting point for a discussion on the subject between his characters.</note> The cause is plainly betrayed by the advocate for it. And I have no doubt that the conversation was written for the purpose of exposing such abuses, tho the writer has <del>xxxxxxxed</del> &#60;revealed&#62; an unhappy error of mind, in which I hope &#38; <hi rend="ital">think</hi> he will not always continue.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">If <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> were deceased, &#38; this dialogue had come into my hands with his other papers, I should have felt no scruples about publishing it, tho I should have deemed it my duty to annex a note showing, as briefly &#38; as strongly as I could, the duty, &#38; the necessity &#38; the advantages of prayer.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I have however no hesitation in saying, after the trouble you have taken with the work, &#38; in deference to a sense of duty which is no where more needed than in it is your profession, that I had much rather have the dialogue omitted, than transfer the volume to another publisher.</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent1">I remain Sir</salute>
               <salute rend="indent2">yours faithfully</salute>
			<signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
