<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4059Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4059" type="letter"><head>4059. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1823-09-11">11 September 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb/>
Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 401–404.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName></address> <date when="1823-09-11">Sept. 11. 1823.</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Neville,</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">I am very glad that the desire of introducing a young officer to you puts an end to all reasons for longer delaying a letter. Mr. Charles Malet,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles St Lo Malet (1802–1889) had a long army career, rising to Lieutenant-Colonel in the 8th Foot Regiment in 1842.</note> by whom this will be delivered to you, is brother to Sir Alexander Malet.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Alexander Malet, 2nd Baronet (1800–1886; <title>DNB</title>), a diplomat who served in many British embassies to European courts, ending his career as Minister Plenipotentiary to the Germanic Confederation 1849–1866.</note> His father, the late Sir Charles Malet,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), diplomat in India and Resident at the court of the Maratha Confederation 1785–1797.</note> was many years resident at Poonah, the Mahratta court at a time when the Mahrattas were the most formidable power in India. He was also uncle to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">General Peachey’s</ref><ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma"> first wife</ref>, a woman for whom I had the highest esteem and regard. Her two sisters<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782–1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754–1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, who had lent them his home on Derwent Island.</note> (old friends of mine) are now inhabiting the Island with Lady Malet,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, née Wales (1779–1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752–1815; <title>DNB</title>), the maternal uncle of the Charter sisters.</note> the General having lent it them for this season. And the young officer (I have neglected to ask whether he be ensign or lieutenant) having been removed from Ipswich to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref>, Lady Malet, who is a most estimable person, is very thankful for so good an introduction as this which I have offered for her son.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Now for my movements. Instead of seeing you in the spring or summer, it will be in mid-–winter. I set out at the end of October with my daughter, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>; and my intention is to make my western visits first, and then escort her to your hospitable roof; making some two days’ halt at Cambridge on the way, and with <ref type="m" target="people.html#ClarksonThomas">Clarkson</ref> (near Ipswich) on the way back. This will hardly be before January has begun, at the latter end of your Christmas festivities. My book of the Church<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> will precede me. I am now set–to to complete it, having laid it aside for some time in order to be ready with a paper for the next “Review.”</p>
               <p rend="indent1">You would recognise me in the last number, on the growth of Infidelity, where, as usual, I have to complain of injurious curtailments.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s review of Henri Grégoire (1750–1831), ‘Histoire de la Théophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu’à son Extinction’, part of Grégoire’s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu’a l’Epoque Actuelle, sont Nées, se sont Modifiées, se sont Éteintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55–171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493–536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library.</note> When I see <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref>, I mean to make some arrangements with him for publishing a selection of my papers in a separate form; and then I shall restore what has been struck out (where it can be recovered), and in other respects improve them.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">This project became Southey’s <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title> (1832).</note> The paper which I have just finished is on the reign of Charles II., – the new edition of “Burnet’s own Times” giving occasion for it.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>Bishop Burnet’s History of his Own Time: with the Suppressed Passages of the First Volume and Notes by the Earls of Dartmouth and Hardwicke, and Speaker Onslow, Hitherto Unpublished; to Which are Added the Cursory Remarks of Swift, and Other Observations </title>(1823), no. 498 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library. This was a new edition of Gilbert Burnet (1643–1715; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of My Own Time</title> (1724–1734), edited by Martin Routh (1755–1854; <title>DNB</title>). Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 165–214, published 27–28 September 1823, and used the occasion to survey the reign of Charles II (1630–1685; King of Great Britain 1660–1685; <title>DNB</title>).</note></p>
               <p rend="indent1">A singular and interesting person called on me about ten days ago, and told me that he had had some acquaintance with you in the way of business formerly, – Mr. Morrison of Fore Street.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">James Morrison (1789–1857; <title>DNB</title>), an immensely wealthy businessman. His main business at this time was a general drapery firm in Fore Street, City of London. Neville White had been a hosiery merchant in London.</note> He was bound to New Lanark, with the intention of vesting 5000<hi rend="ital">l</hi>. in the proposed experiment of an Owenite Quadrangle, if what he sees at Owen’s own establishment should confirm him in his present opinion of the scheme.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Owen (1771–1858; <title>DNB</title>), the manager and owner of the textile mill at New Lanark 1799–1825 and a utopian thinker. Morrison invested in the proposed community to be founded on Owen’s principles at Orbiston, near Motherwell.</note> I was exceedingly pleased with him. He talked to me about the Free–thinking Christians,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">The ‘Free Thinking Christians’ were a denomination founded in 1798. At this time, their meetings were in High Holborn, London. They rejected the sacraments and the Trinity and had attracted some notoriety.</note> with whom Cokes, Thompson, and Fearon<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Thompson (1766–1837; <title>DNB</title>), a spirits merchant, was the founder of the Free Thinking Christians. William Coates (dates unknown) was a wine merchant in the City of London and Thompson’s son-in-law; Henry Bradshaw Fearon (c. 1793–1842) was also Thompson’s son-in-law and his business partner in a ‘gin palace’ at 94 High Holborn. His <title>Sketches of America. A Narrative of a Journey of Five Thousand Miles through the Eastern and Western States of America</title> (1818) had been savaged in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 21 (January 1819), 124–167.</note> are the chiefs of the synagogue. With these persons he appeared to be intimate, and very much to admire the society, on account of the strict discipline which they observe, and the strict regularity of conduct which they require from their members. A clerk (Dillon<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">John Dillon (c. 1792–1868) was the son of a book-dealer. He served as librarian to the Welsh clergyman and poet, Charles Symmons (1749–1826; <title>DNB</title>), but had ambitions to be a playwright. After <title>Retribution, or the Chieftain’s Daughter</title> (1818) was a failure, he joined Morrison’s firm as a clerk, rising to be a senior partner.</note> by name) in whom he has great confidence, is one of their preachers, or lecturers, and the principal defender of their faith in their magazine.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Freethinking Christians’ Quarterly Register</title> (1823–1825).</note> I found, however, that Morrison was far from being satisfied with their creed. We had a good deal of conversation on the subject; and he took down from me the title of some books which may assist the better tendency of his own mind at this time. His place of residence is Balham Hill, where I shall probably see him, being within an easy walk of <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my uncle’s</ref> house at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">Hughes the traveller was here with his bride,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Smart Hughes (1786–1847; DNB), clergyman, Fellow of Emmanuel College, Cambridge, and author of <title>Travels in Sicily, Greece and Albania</title> (1820), no. 1386 in the sale catalogue of Southey’s library, had married, in April 1823, Anna Maria Forster (d. 1890), daughter of John Forster (c. 1751–1837), Vicar of Tunstead 1782–1837.</note> early in the season; and Professor Sedgewick<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Adam Sedgwick (1785–1873; <title>DNB</title>), Fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge, and Woodwardian Professor of Geology 1818–1873.</note> is now hammering away in the heart of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref>. We are now enjoying fine weather, which is the more delightful after the long reign of St. Swithin.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">St Swithun (c. 800–863; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Winchester 852–863. According to legend, if it rained on St Swithun’s Day (15 July), it would rain for 40 days.</note> On Monday last we had a grand party upon Causey Pike, the ascent of which you will remember. We were thirteen persons on the summit, and we dined by the side of the stream below, where <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Mrs. Southey</ref> with <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Mrs. Coleridge</ref> and two other ladies, who were not equal to the task of climbing the mountain, waited for us. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> remained below with <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">his mother</ref>; the other young ones<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors"><ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel Southey</ref>.</note> scaled the height like goats. To–day we have a lake party, and my daughter, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>, has cut out more expeditions for me, against which I must not rebel, for if they impede my pursuits they are conducive to my health.</p>
               <p rend="indent1">There is <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">a lady of our party</ref> to–day who has published two volumes of poetry, which, if Mrs.White and your sisters<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte White, née Sewell (1799–1873) had married Neville White in 1820. White’s two sisters were Frances Moriah White (1791–1854) and Catherine Bailey White (1794–1889).</note> have not read, I would recommend to their perusal. “Ellen Fitzarthur” is the title of one, “The Widow’s Tale” of the other.<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles, <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) and <title>The Widow’s Tale and Other Poems</title> (1822).</note> There is nothing in them but what is good and beautiful. <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Miss Bowles</ref> has not put her name to either. She is in very delicate health, but, I hope, is deriving benefit from this wholesome air. Remember us most kindly to all your circle, and tell me how transplantation agrees with your excellent mother. Your young ones, I hope, continue to thrive; I shall have great pleasure in seeing them. My little <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref> is as happy as health, fine weather, and the thoughts of making a fire for dinner by the side of the lake can make him. God bless you, my dear Neville.</p>
                  <closer><salute rend="indent1">Yours affectionately,</salute>
		<signed rend="indent2">R.S.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
