<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4066Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4066" type="letter">
        <head>4066. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#PeachyWilliam">William Peachy</ref>, <date when="1823-10-04">4 October 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ Major General Peachy/ Post Office/ Canterbury<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 7 OC 7/ 1823<lb />
MS: British Library, Add MS 28603. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 250&#8211;252.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-10-04">4 Oct. 1823.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I received with much pleasure the account of your ubiquitarian movements, &amp; the assurance of good health &amp; good spirits which such movements imply. For myself, tho having (thank God) no cause to complain on the score of either, I have not moved beyond the limits of this vale since you left it. Neither an invitation, twice repeated to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#CanningGeorge ">Mr Canning</ref> at Storrs,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Storrs Hall on Windermere, Lake District home of John Bolton (1756&#8211;1837; <title>DNB</title>), a Liverpool merchant and leading supporter of Canning as MP for that city.</note> nor another from <ref type="m" target="people.html#YorkRichard">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> York</ref> to Wighill Park to the Musical Festival<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Richard York invited Southey to the &#8216;Yorkshire Grand Music Festival, for the Benefit of York County Hospital, and of the General Infirmaries of Leeds, Sheffield and Hull&#8217; on 22&#8211;25 September 1823 in York Minster.</note> could draw me from home. Whatever time could be spared from my desk I wanted to enjoy in excursions with our friends of the Island.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782&#8211;1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and nieces of Sir Charles Malet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), 1st Baronet, a prominent diplomat with the East India Company. Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island. They were accompanied by Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), the maternal uncle of the Charter sisters. Their other companion was one of Sir Charles Malet&#8217;s three children in India with Amber Kaur (b. 1772): Eliza (b. 1791); Henry Charles (1793&#8211;1844); and Louisa (b. 1795). They accompanied Malet to Britain in 1798 and were brought up with his children by Susanna Malet. Eliza Malet married, in 1812, Robert Ekins (1785&#8211;1874), Vicar of Godalming 1810&#8211;1833, Rector of Folke, Dorset 1833&#8211;1843, Perpetual Curate of North Wootton 1843&#8211;1854. Southey is probably referring here to Louisa Malet.</note> The season has been singularly unpropitious for such parties, &#8211; by much the worst within my remembrance which extends now to twenty years in this country. Thro the spring we lived in hope of what summer might bring with it, thro the summer our hopes were for autumn, October is now come &amp; the weather still as unsettled as <del>however</del> ever. However we have taken advantage of every interval.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We made successful ascents of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Skiddaw">Skiddaw</ref> &amp; of Cawsey Pike, down chimney of which the Ladies came in great style, Miss Charter, <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; one or two more (for we moved in great force) who were afraid of the ascent, awaiting us at the bottom with a very respectable pic-nic set out. Our next dinner of the same kind was by the Lake side in Manesty Woods. Another day I led the ladies up Walla Crag by a way which would not have suited your friend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Awdrey.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Awdry (1766&#8211;1844) was married to Jane, n&#233;e Bigg-Wither (1770&#8211;1845), sister of Herbert Hill&#8217;s wife. Awdry was a solicitor and minor landowner, and Southey had stayed with him in Switzerland in 1817 soon after Peachy had visited Awdry.</note> Last Monday we dined just where the descent into Borrodale, from Buttermere Haws commences &#8211; we were three carts &amp; five saddle horses, &amp; I know not how many more than twenty persons (your friends M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Portel &amp; his daughter<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Probably William Portal (1755&#8211;1845) of Ashe Parke, Hampshire, his wife Sophia, n&#233;e Slade (1760&#8211;1837), and their daughter, Sophia Portal (d. 1875). The Portal family were descended from Huguenot refugees and owned the firm that produced banknotes for the Bank of England.</note> among them) the mountains have seldom seen such a caravan. We are planning much more, if Jupiter will permit, &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Miss Bowles</ref> the authoress of those sweet poems which I once recommended to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref>
          <note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had recommended Caroline Bowles&#8217;s, <title>Ellen Fitzarthur; a Metrical Tale, in Five Cantos</title> (1820) and <title>The Widow&#8217;s Tale and Other Poems</title> (1822) widely to friends and acquaintances.</note> has been with us in most of these excursions. She is lodging at Timmy Ladymans,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Ladyman (1774&#8211;1846), a Keswick ironmonger.</note> but takes her departure in the course of next week. Your friends are very much pleased with her, &amp; she with them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will be more grieved than surprized to hear that we have lost <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Edmondson</ref>. After ten weeks lingering, his old complaint has carried him off. When the disease was for a time removed, Nature had not the strength to rally, &amp; thus he sunk under a renewed attack. It was his desire that I should assure you that your plate would be as secure in the care of his family, as it was during his life time. He was buried on Thursday, &amp; I believe few persons have ever gone to the grave more deservedly, or more generally regretted in their sphere. <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref> &amp; I have been talking today upon the fitness of erecting a subscription tablet in the Church to his memory, as was done (with far less reason) in the case of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Denton.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Isaac Denton (c. 1758&#8211;1820), Vicar of Crosthwaite, Keswick 1786&#8211;1820.</note> A man so skilful in his practise, so conscientiously moderate in his charges so friendly in his services, &#8211; so eminently useful in his generation deserves the tribute of respect &amp; gratitude. <ref type="m" target="people.html#CalvertWilliam">Calvert</ref> will propose it to Sir Frederic Vane<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Frederick Fletcher-Vane, 2nd Baronet (1760&#8211;1832), of Hutton in the Forest, though he mainly lived at Armathwaite Hall on Bassenthwaite. Fletcher-Vane was a leading local Whig and opponent of the Lowther interest, serving as MP for Carlisle 1796&#8211;1800 and 1801&#8211;1802, and MP for Winchelsea 1792&#8211;1794 and 1806&#8211;1807.</note> &amp; Sir Fred. Morshead.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir Frederick Treise Morshead, 2nd Baronet (1783&#8211;1828), of Derwent Lodge, Keswick.</note> I undertook to mention it to you, &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref>. And we shall find some fit person to call upon the people of the place, who will feel how fitting it is, &amp; how creditable to themselves, that this should be done.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">A tablet to honour John Edmondson was commissioned and placed in St Kentigern&#8217;s, Crosthwaite.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will see in the last Quarterly a paper of mine upon the new edition of Burnet,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Bishop Burnet&#8217;s History of his Own Time: with the Suppressed Passages of the First Volume and Notes by the Earls of Dartmouth and Hardwicke, and Speaker Onslow, Hitherto Unpublished; to Which are Added the Cursory Remarks of Swift, and Other Observations </title>(1823), no. 498 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a new edition of Gilbert Burnet (1643&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of My Own Time</title> (1724&#8211;1734), edited by Martin Routh (1755&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>). Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 165&#8211;214, published 27&#8211;28 September 1823, and used the occasion to survey the reign of Charles II (1630&#8211;1685; King of Great Britain 1660&#8211;1685; <title>DNB</title>).</note> &amp; a most excellent one upon Spain by my friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco White</ref>,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Blanco White&#8217;s review of Michael Joseph Quin (1796&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Visit to Spain; Detailing the Transactions which Occurred during a Residence in that Country in the Latter Part of 1822, and the First Four Months of 1823. With an Account of the Removal of the Court from Madrid to Seville; and General Notices of the Manners, Customs, Costume and Music of the Country</title>, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 240&#8211;276, published 27 or 28 September 1823.</note> whose Letters on Spain under the title of Leucadio Doblado,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Letters from Spain by Don Leucadio Doblado</title> (1822).</note> if they should not have fallen in your way, I recommend to your perusal. In the preceding number you would perhaps recognize me upon the Progress of Infidelity,<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), &#8216;Histoire de la Th&#233;ophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu&#8217;&#224; son Extinction&#8217;, part of Gr&#233;goire&#8217;s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55&#8211;171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493&#8211;536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; a paper which underwent some injurious curtailments. I have now begun an article upon D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dwights Travels in New England &amp; New York.<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">The Book of the Church<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> (extended to two volumes) is now drawing near its conclusion. My intention is to join company with the Island Ladies on their departure, taking with me <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my eldest daughter</ref>, &amp; accompanying them till we turn off to pass a few days with <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G Beaumont</ref> at Coleorton. I shall run down into Somerset &amp; Devonshire before Christmas, &amp; to Cambridge &amp; <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref> afterwards, then return home &amp; get into harness again.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">A miserable man has been walking against time in your stable field, &#8211; &amp; broke down in the attempt, but begins again tomorrow.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Pedestrian feats were very popular in the 1820s, walking &#8216;against time&#8217; being an attempt to cover a certain distance in a certain time. Pedestrians usually walked for money and the sport often involved large wagers and disorderly crowds.</note> Were I a magistrate most certainly I would not suffer him to collect a rabble there, &amp; endanger his life in this useless manner. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lynn<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">James Lynn (1776&#8211;1855), Perpetual Curate of Strood 1805&#8211;1814, Rector of Caldbeck 1814&#8211;1820, Vicar of Crosthwaite, Keswick 1820&#8211;1855.</note> is gone to the south, &amp; as he will be mostly about Maidstone, you may perhaps fall in with him. My womankind <del>desire</del> unite with me in kind remembrances to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Peachy</ref> &#8211; whom they have often wished for, as well as for yourself in our excursions. Remember me also to Charles Edward,<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Edward Henry (1807&#8211;1833), the younger of Peachy&#8217;s two stepsons.</note> &amp; believe me my Dear Sir ever yours very sincerely</p>
        <signed rend="indent3">Robert Southey.</signed>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>