<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4067. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 8 October [1823]</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4067Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4067. Robert Southey to Henry Herbert Southey, 8 October [1823]</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4067Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4067" type="letter">
        <head>4067. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1823-10-08">8 October [1823]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey/ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
Postmark: E/ 11 OC 11/ 1823<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
MS: Keswick Museum and Art Gallery, 1996.5.327. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute>My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Miss Fricker</ref> will send to your house a packet for which I shall be obliged to you to procure a potential frank, &#8211; the shortest way will be for you to send it to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> with an intimation to that effect. It contains some law papers which <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith</ref> &amp; her two sisters<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>.</note> must sign, &amp; by virtue of which they will receive about 160&#163; each, from the effects of their Uncle<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">George Fricker, a Bristol accountant, had died at Wells, Somerset in August 1823. Because he had died intestate, his estate was divided amongst his nearest surviving relatives, who included his nieces Edith Southey and her four sisters. </note> who has lately died intestate. Our Uncles<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyJohn">John Southey</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyThomasUncle">Thomas Southey</ref>, both wealthy men, had made wills that left nothing to Southey and his brothers.</note> were not so obliging as to <del>xxx</del> let the law dispose of their property.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">We shall probably set out the first week in November, &#8211; tho in consequence of this arrangement I must take work to finish at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824), which Southey wished to complete.</note> However it is not a bad place for working. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> &amp; I are to accompany the Miss Charters &amp; Lady Malet,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782&#8211;1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and nieces of Sir Charles Malet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), 1st Baronet, a prominent diplomat with the East India Company. Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island. They were accompanied by Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), the maternal uncle of the Charter sisters.</note> which will be pleasant for all parties &#8211; we shall fill two chaises &amp; see a few sights on the way, if the weather permit. If <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir G. Beaumont</ref> should be at Cole-Orton we then part company at Derby, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">E May</ref> &amp; I going to pass a day or two with him, &#8211; I shall finish a paper for the QR before we start.
               Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#EdmondsonDr">Edmundson</ref> is dead &#8211; to the great sorrow &amp; loss of the neighbourhood I believe we shall get a subscription tablet placed in the church, in testimony of the respect which was felt for him.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A wall tablet commemorating John Edmondson was placed in St Kentigern&#8217;s, Crosthwaite.</note> You know he had suffered many severe attacks of iliac passion.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Severe intestinal obstruction.</note> Latterly he had found such speedy relief from the oil of Croton<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">An oil prepared from the seeds of the tree <hi rend="ital">Croton Tiglium</hi>, native to the Far East. It was used as a laxative.</note> that he almost thought himself possessed of a safe specific. But a cough came on in the latter end of spring, which he could not, or did not attend to in time. In itself it was not alarming, but it became frequent &amp; teizing &amp; the irritation which it occasioned brought in a most distressing hiccup, with which, &amp; with repeated attacks of the intestinal complaint he struggled ten weeks, losing so much strength at each attack that he was not able in any degree to recruit during the intervals. &#8211; I do not know what appearances were found after death; &#8211; but as you may suppose it was his desire that the body should be opened, there being proof enough of some organic derangement.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GiffordWilliam">Gifford</ref> appears to have rallied, I have a letter from him, &#8211; the first since the commencement of his illness. He has promised <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to conduct the Review till the 60<hi rend="sup">th</hi> N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Gifford&#8217;s final contribution to the <title>Quarterly Review</title> was to co-edit the issue published on 30 December 1824: 31 (April 1824). </note> &#8211; rather he says to satisfy <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> than with any real hope of so doing. When I am in town I shall of course enquire into the affair of the succession. The reviewal of the Peninsular War has all the marks of particular personal <del>xxx</del> civility.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The first volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) was reviewed in the <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 53&#8211;85, published 27 or 28 September 1823, by George Procter (1796&#8211;1842), Adjutant at the Royal Military College, Sandhurst. Prior to publication the article had been substantially amended by John Wilson Croker.</note> I do not know who wrote it. The paper upon Spain which is as good as that in the former paper was good for little, is by <ref type="m" target="people.html#WhiteJosephBlanco">Blanco</ref>.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Blanco White&#8217;s review of Michael Joseph Quin (1796&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), <title>A Visit to Spain; Detailing the Transactions which Occurred during a Residence in that Country in the Latter Part of 1822, and the First Four Months of 1823. With an Account of the Removal of the Court from Madrid to Seville; and General Notices of the Manners, Customs, Costume and Music of the Country</title>, in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 240&#8211;276, published 27 or 28 September 1823. Southey compared it favourably with the review of <title>The Crisis of Spain</title> (1823); <title>Constiticion Politica de la Monarquia Espanola</title> (1820); A.L.B., <title>De l&#8217;Excellence de la Guerre avec l&#8217;Espagne</title> (1823); Giuseppe Pecchio (1785&#8211;1835), <title>Anecdotes of the Spanish and Portugueze Revolutions</title> (1823), by Robert William Hay (1786&#8211;1861; <title>DNB</title>), with William Jacob (c. 1761&#8211;1851), in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 536&#8211;580, published 8 July 1823.</note> &#8211; My present subject is taken from D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Dwights Travels,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library, reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824.</note> &#8211; first I gut the book of its miscellaneous facts &amp; speculations, &#8211; then take up the political subject of America; as to the stability &amp; tendency of its institutions. I believe that I have some things to say which are worth saying, &#8211; &amp; I wish to say them in a friendly &amp; conciliatory temper. It is bad policy, &amp; indeed wrong in every respect, to irritate the Americans. They cannot possibly hold together, &amp; our business should be to regard the Eastern states as our natural allies, &#8211; the people of all others whom it is our interest to be upon good terms with, &amp; with whom we have the most points of resemblance.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your niece</ref> is much improved in health by the exercise into which our old friends of the Island have led her. We see a great deal of them &amp; if the weather had not been worse than any body ever remembers it, not a mountain summit within reach would have been left unvisited. They often talk of you, &amp; of former times, &#8211; &amp; some of these recollections are not the worse for the melancholy which is mingled with them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I hope Robert<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817), the eldest son of Henry Herbert Southey.</note> continues to amend. Our love to all &#8211;</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
          RS.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-10-08">8 Oct.</date>
          </p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>