<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4068Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4068Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4068" type="letter">
        <head>4068. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Grosvenor Charles Bedford</ref>, <date when="1823-10-15">15 October 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ G. C. Bedford Esq<hi rend="sup">re.</hi>/ <del>Exchequer</del> &lt;Post Office&gt;/ <del>Westminster</del>. &lt;Dover&gt;<lb />
Stamped: [partial]KESWICK/ 2<lb />
Postmarks: E/ 18 OC 18/ 1823; [partially illegible] 1823; [partially legible] Txxhill/ Street<lb />
Endorsement: 15. Octo<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. 1823.<lb />
MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. c. 26. ALS; 4p.<lb />
Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-10-15">15 Oct. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Grosvenor</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">The time of my departure is now as well fixed as any thing beforehand can be in this uncertain world, for Monday the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of November. But how long I may be on the road depends upon circumstances. I take charge of four ladies,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#CharterLouisa">Louisa Charter</ref>, and Elizabeth Charter (1782&#8211;1860), friend of the poet George Crabbe (1754&#8211;1832; <title>DNB</title>). They were the sisters of <ref type="m" target="people.html#PeachyEmma">Emma Peachy</ref>, first wife of William Peachy, and nieces of Sir Charles Malet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), 1st Baronet, a prominent diplomat with the East India Company. Peachy had lent the Charter sisters his home on Derwent Island. They were accompanied by Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>), the maternal uncle of the Charter sisters. Their other companion was one of Sir Charles Malet&#8217;s three children in India with Amber Kaur (b. 1772): Eliza (b. 1791); Henry Charles (1793&#8211;1844); and Louisa (b. 1795). They accompanied Malet to Britain in 1798 and were brought up with his children by Susanna Malet. Eliza Malet married, in 1812, Robert Ekins (1785&#8211;1874), Vicar of Godalming 1810&#8211;1833, Rector of Folke, Dorset 1833&#8211;1843, Perpetual Curate of North Wootton 1843&#8211;1854. Southey is probably referring here to Louisa Malet.</note> besides <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref>. We shall fill two chaises, &amp; if the weather permits we mean to see the Yorkshire caves, Gordale scar, &amp; Bolton Abbey,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">A limestone ravine in North Yorkshire; and the ruins of a twelfth-century Augustinian monastery.</note> on the way, &amp; moreover the posteriors of Beelzebub in the Peak,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The Peak Cavern, near Castleton, Derbyshire, also known as the Devil&#8217;s Arse.</note> &#8211; all which will occupy a whole week before we reach Derby. And there we are to separate if <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont</ref> should by that time be at Cole Orton, in which case <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> &amp; I must visit him for a few days. Upon leaving him we shall get into some coach at Loughborough &amp; endeavor to reach London on the Saturday. Send me I pray you 40 &#163;. I have to make arrangements with <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> about the B. of the Church,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> when I arrive, on which I depend for my ways and means. It is too good a chance in the lottery for me to part with it, if I can help it. He was to have given me 500 &#163; for it in one volume. By doubling its size I very well know that I have not doubled its marketable value; &amp; I think it will be better to recur to a former agreement whereby I am to have half the profits of the first edition, &amp; two thirds of every succeeding one. But I shall need 200 &#163; while I am in town, &#8211; &amp; must bargain accordingly, &#8211; for I am wofully on the wrong side of the <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmens</ref> books.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The truth is (&amp; it is not a comfortable one) that I neither write so much, nor compose so fast, as I was wont to do when younger. My health requires more exercise, &#8211; absolutely requires it. &#8211; And as I am more careful what I write, an over-scrupulous solicitude has been contracted, for looking into every accessible source of information upon the subject before me, at an injurious expence of time.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have proposed to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> to publish a selection of my papers from the QR. I do not expect any objection to the proposal, &amp; if he assents to it I shall begin with the Essays Moral &amp; Political, altering, restoring &amp; adding as may seem best, &amp; incorporating somethings from the Register, &amp; from the Annual Review.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">This project became <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title> (1832). Southey had reviewed extensively for the <title>Annual Review for 1802</title>, 1 (1803) until the <title>Annual Review for 1808</title>, 7 (1809) and written the historical sections of the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1808</title> (1810) until the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register, for 1811</title> (1813). Essays I&#8211;III in <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), I, pp. [3]&#8211;72, and Essays XI&#8211;XII in <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), II, pp. [277]&#8211;328, were mainly drawn from the <title>Edinburgh Annual Register</title>. None of Southey&#8217;s contributions to the <title>Annual Review</title> formed the basis of an essay, but parts of Southey&#8217;s review of Thomas Malthus (1766&#8211;1834; <title>DNB</title>), <title>An Essay on the Principle of Population</title> (1803), <title>Annual Review for 1803</title>, 2 (1804), 292&#8211;301, were grafted onto Essay IV of <title>Essays, Moral and Political</title>, 2 vols (London, 1832), I, pp. [73]&#8211;155, which was mainly taken from Southey&#8217;s review of Patrick Colquhoun (1745&#8211;1820; <title>DNB</title>), <title>Propositions for Ameliorating the Condition of the Poor: and for Improving the Moral Habits, and Increasing the Comforts of the Labouring People</title> (1812), <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 8 (December 1812), 319&#8211;356.</note> They will very well bear to be thus brought forward. The Historical &amp; Ecclesiastical Essays might follow, &#8211; &amp; lastly the Critical &amp; Miscellaneous, &#8211; leaving the biographical for another use.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">These further volumes did not appear.</note> I hope you may have saved the copy or the proofs of some of my papers, which have undergone wicked mutilation. The last escaped pretty well.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>Bishop Burnet&#8217;s History of his Own Time: with the Suppressed Passages of the First Volume and Notes by the Earls of Dartmouth and Hardwicke, and Speaker Onslow, Hitherto Unpublished; to Which are Added the Cursory Remarks of Swift, and Other Observations </title>(1823), no. 498 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This was a new edition of Gilbert Burnet (1643&#8211;1715; <title>DNB</title>), <title>History of My Own Time</title> (1724&#8211;1734), edited by Martin Routh (1755&#8211;1854; <title>DNB</title>). Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 29 (April 1823), 165&#8211;214, published 27&#8211;28 September 1823.</note> But the article upon the Progress of Infidelity,<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s review of Henri Gr&#233;goire (1750&#8211;1831), &#8216;Histoire de la Th&#233;ophilantropie, depuis sa Naissance jusqu&#8217;&#224; son Extinction&#8217;, part of Gr&#233;goire&#8217;s <title>Histoire des Sectes Religieuse, qui, Depuis de Commencement du Siecle Dernier Jusqu&#8217;a l&#8217;Epoque Actuelle, sont N&#233;es, se sont Modifi&#233;es, se sont &#201;teintes dans le Quatre Parties du Monde</title>, 2 vols (Paris, 1814), II, pp. 55&#8211;171, <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 28 (January 1823), 493&#8211;536, published 8 July 1823. The book was no. 2838 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> &#8211; Dobrizhoffer,<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey reviewed Sara Coleridge&#8217;s <title>An Account of the Abipones, an Equestrian People of Paraguay</title> (1822) in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 26 (January 1822), 277&#8211;323, published 30 March 1823. The book was a translation of Martin Dobrizhoffer (1717&#8211;1791), <title>Historia de Abiponibus Equestri, Bellicosaque Paraquariae Natione</title> (1784), no. 843 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library.</note> Camoens,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">John Adamson, <title>Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Luis de Camoens</title> (1820), no. 10 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. Southey reviewed it in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 27 (April 1822), 1&#8211;39, published 4 July 1822.</note> &amp; the Sinner Saved<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">The preacher and religious writer, William Huntington (1745&#8211;1813; <title>DNB</title>), who added &#8216;S. S.&#8217; &#8211; &#8216;Sinner Saved&#8217; &#8211; to his name, to indicate his spiritual state. Southey&#8217;s review of <title>The Works of the Reverend William Huntington, S. S. Minister of the Gospel, at Providence Chapel, Gray&#8217;s Inn Lane, Completed to the Close of the Year 1806</title> (1811), appeared in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 24 (January 1821), 462&#8211;510, published 6 April 1821.</note> suffered grievously. &#8211; If this scheme takes effect it may very materially lessen my cares for three or four years, should I live so long.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You will hardly recollect <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">my daughter</ref> when you see her. She will pass her time chiefly with her godmother <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonne</ref> (<ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Dogstars</ref>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs"> </ref>mother in law) &#8211; but will be a little while in Gloucester Place with Lady Malet, one of our fellow travelers. &#8211; The time of year will be fa[MS missing]rable to me in one respect, that it will leave me more to my friends than if the town were full. If the Rickmans<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">John Rickman</ref> and his family.</note> should be in town, my quarters will be a short time with them, &amp; how many recollections will that house bring with it! But I must be chiefly at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>. I bring up work with me to finish &amp; as soon as it is done, shall hurry down upon a series of flying visits to Devon &amp; Somersetshire, &#8211; &amp; on my way back must fly also into Suffolk &amp; Norfolk. It almost dismays me to think of all this, &#8211; but I hope that change of air, plenty of motion, &amp; a good allowance of claret will put me in better <del>xxx</del> tone than I have been since the relaxation brought on by my last annual attack. </p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Osiris</ref> will send you a packet which requires an official frank. It contains some deeds to be signed by <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; her sisters,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">Sara Coleridge</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Mary Lovell</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#Frickerfamily">Martha and Eliza Fricker</ref>.</note> by virtue of which they will share some trifling property from the effects of an Uncle who died intestate<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">George Fricker, a Bristol accountant, had died at Wells, Somerset, in August 1823. Because he had died intestate, his estate was divided amongst his nearest surviving relatives, who included his nieces, Edith Southey and her four sisters.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Bad as the season has been we have had some glorious caravan parties at which it would have done your heart good to have been present. Yesterday we were at Watenlath, &amp; dined on the fell side, looking down upon Borrodale, thirteen persons &amp; five horses, &#8211; &amp; this was the smallest force with which we have taken the field this year. It is a symptom of sound heart at least that my inclination for such things increases rather than diminishes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I wish you could see <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">your godson</ref>; &#8211; you would see in him every thing that you could desire</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you.<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent2">RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>