<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4085</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4085Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4085" type="letter">
        <head>4085. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebenezer Elliott</ref>, <date when="1823-11-09">9 November 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ E. Elliott Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Burgess Street/ Sheffield<lb />
Stamped: BAKEWELL/ 152<lb />
MS: Sheffield City Libraries and Archives, MD 2191&#8211;28. ALS; 3p.<lb />
Previously published: E. R. Seary, &#8216;Robert Southey and Ebenezer Elliott: Some New Southey Letters&#8217;, <title>Review of English Studies</title>, 15 (October 1939), 416&#8211;417.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Bakewell.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-11-09">9 Nov. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">I thought so much of you after we parted last night that I will not go to bed again without saying something to you both concerning your son,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey and Elliott had met in Sheffield on 7 November and discussed Ebenezer Elliott (1807&#8211;1871), eldest son of Ebenezer Elliott. He matriculated at Peterhouse College, Cambridge in 1825 as a sizar (i.e. a student receiving some form of financial assistance) and obtained his BA in 1829. He became a clergyman and was Perpetual Curate of New Mill, Huddersfield 1841&#8211;1843 and Lothersdale, near Skipton 1844&#8211;1848, later going to St Kitts in the West Indies and serving as Rector of Christ Church, Nichola Town, and St Mary&#8217;s, Cayou.</note> &amp; your own state of mind.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">If your sons abilities are above the common standard, &amp; you can rely upon him for diligence &amp; prudence, the best <del>x</del> course which could be chosen for him is to place him at one of the Universities, with a view to his gaining a fellowship. With good abilities &amp; good conduct the way would be plain before him, &amp; if that step were gained, he becomes immediately independent, the means of fortune are within his reach, &amp; his advancement in life would depend less upon accident or patronage than upon his own exertions &amp; desert. What nature has done for him, you are well able to judge, &amp; also to <del>x</del> judge whether his <del>possesses the</del> disposition is such as would lead him to <del>xx</del> employ his talents to the best account. Diligence, regularity, &amp; that spirit of just frugality without which there can be no independence, are indispensable to his success in this career, &#8211; as they are indeed to his happiness in any.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The next point is &#8211; what are his acquirements? how far has he advanced? &amp; at what school has he been placed. Eighteen is a good age for going to college, &#8211; &amp; a great deal may be done in two years. &#8211; The choice between Oxford or Cambridge would depend in a great degree upon his aptitude for mathematics.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Cambridge BA required at least competence in mathematics.</note> &#8211; I will enquire at both, find out what helps can be obtained there, &amp; if you determine upon sending him there, I will use my best endeavours to secure something for him in time, &#8211; that is, the promise of it. And at either University I will recommend him to some persons who if any good offices should be in their power will gladly render them.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">A word now concerning your own state of mind. In the point of difference between you, M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> E.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Gartside (b. 1781). She and Ebenezer Elliott had married in 1806 and the couple had thirteen children.</note> is right. You have past from one extreme to another, &amp; will rest when you are in the right mean between them. Unitarianism is not tenable ground. There are books which would <hi rend="ital">demonstrate</hi> this to you, but I am not sure that it is not better &amp; easier for you to discover this yourself, &amp; this you will infallibly do, if you read the scriptures. I will tell &lt;you&gt; <del>what</del> the way of reading them, which I have found most profitable in my own progress, &#8211; that of duly taking the psalms &amp; lessons of the day.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The verses of the Bible appointed to be read on each Sunday at Church of England services, according to the <title>Book of Common Prayer</title> (1662).</note> In so doing it is delightful to perceive how the system of revelation unfolds itself. At every fresh perusal you will find &amp; feel the force &amp; importance of some passages &amp; texts which you had not previously observed, &#8211; &amp; it cannot be long before you will say with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Thomas &#8211; My Lord &amp; my God!&#8221;<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">The words spoken at <title>John</title> 20: 28, by the apostle St Thomas, when he recognised the risen Jesus.</note> &#8211;</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Meantime do not disquiet yourself, nor be disquieted upon this subject. You are in the right way. No one ever yet who sought for the truth with humility &amp; sincerity of heart, failed to find it.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I shall be glad to hear your estimate of your sons character, &#8211; &amp; interested in any thing you may tell me concerning your family &amp; yourself. If you write <del>within</del> before Thursday next, direct to me at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BeaumontSirGeorge">Sir George Beaumont&#8217;s</ref>
          <del>Xxxx Xxxxxxxx</del> Cole Orton Hall, Ashby de la Zouch. &#8211; afterwards at N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 15 <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Queen Anne Street</ref> &#8211; Cavendish Square London &#8211;</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yrs with sincere regard<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent4">Robert Southey</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>