<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4097. Robert Southey to Edith Southey, 30 November 1823</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4097Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4097. Robert Southey to Edith Southey, 30 November 1823</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4097Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4097" type="letter">
        <head>4097. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1823-11-30">30 November 1823</date>
          </head><p>Address: [in another hand] London First Dec 1823./ M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Southey/ Keswick/ Cumberland/ Free/ JRickman<lb />
Postmark: FREE/ 1 DE 1/ 1823/ +<lb />
Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p. <lb />
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 254&#8211;257; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 154&#8211;157 [in part].</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <date when="1823-11-30">Sunday. 30 Nov. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Edith</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">We have been this morning to hear Rowland Hill.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Rowland Hill (1744&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>), a popular evangelical preacher who was not formally attached to any denomination. He built Surrey Chapel in Blackfriars Road, Southwark, in 1782&#8211;1783 and preached there when he was in London.</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref> called at his house last week to know when he would preach, &amp; was answered by a demure looking woman, that the Lord willing her master would preach on Sunday morning at &#189; past ten &amp; in the evening at six. So this morning I set off with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">EMay</ref>, <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
          </ref> &amp; Ann R.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Ann Rickman (b. 1808), Rickman&#8217;s daughter.</note> We were in good time, &amp; got into the free seats, where &lt;there were&gt; a few poor people, one of whom told to go round to another door &amp; we should be admitted. Another door we found with orders that the doorkeepers should take no money for admittance, &amp; a request that no person would enter in pattens.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">A protective overshoe, with a wooden or metal sole, to prevent the shoe coming into contact with the ground.</note> Doorkeeper there was none, &amp; we therefore ventured in &amp; took our seats upon a bench beside some decent old women. One of these with the help of another &amp; busier old piece of femininity, desired us to remove to a bench behind us, close to the wall, the seats we had taken, they said, belonged to particular persons, but if we would sit where she directed till the service was over, we should then be invited into the pews, if there was room. I did not immediately understand this, nor what we were to do in the pews when the service was at an end, till I recollected that in most schism shops<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Nonconformist chapels.</note> the sermon is looked upon as the main thing &lt;for&gt; which the congregation assemble. This was so much the case here that people were continually coming in during all the previous part of the service,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">At Surrey Chapel the church service closely followed the Church of England service.</note> to which very little attention was paid: the people <del>coughing al</del> sitting or standing as they pleased, &amp; coughing almost incessantly.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I suppose what is properly called the Morning service had been performed at an early hour, for we had only the Communion Service. Rowland Hills pulpit is raised very high, &amp; before it at about half the height is the readers desk on his right, &amp; the Clerks on his left, the Clerk being a very grand personage, with a sonorous voice. The singing was so general &amp; so good that I joined in it, &amp; doubtless made it better by the addition of my voice. During the singing after Rowland had made his prayer before the sermon, we, as respectable strangers were beckoned from our humble places by a gentleman in one of the pews. <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanSusannah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> R</ref> &amp; her daughter were stationed in one pew between two gentlemen of Rowlands flock; &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">EMay</ref> &amp; I in another between a Lady &amp; a person corresponding very much in countenance to the character of a light boy<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">A young man who was light-hearted and uninterested in serious matters such as religion.</note> in the old <del>xx</del> Methodistical magazines. He was very civil, &amp; by finding out the hymns for me, &amp; presenting me with the book, enabled me to sing, &#8211; which I did to admiration.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Rowland &#8211; a fine tall old man, with strong features, &#8211; very like his portrait, &#8211; began by reading three verses for his text, stooping to the book in a very peculiar manner. Having done this, he stood up erect &amp; said Why the text is a sermon! &amp; a very weighty one too. I could not always follow his delivery, the loss of his teeth rendering his words sometimes indistinct, &amp; the more so because his pronunciation is peculiar, generally giving <hi rend="ital">e</hi> the sound of <hi rend="ital">ai</hi> like the French. His manner was animated &amp; striking, sometimes impressive &amp; dignified, always remarkable: &amp; so powerful a voice I have rarely or never heard. Sometimes he took off his spectacles, frequently stoopd down to read a text, &amp; on these occasions he seemed to double his body, so high did he stand. He told one or two familiar stories, &amp; used some odd expressions, such as &#8220;A murrain on those who preach the doctrine that when we are sanctified we do not grow in grace!&#8221;<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">The doctrine of perfectionism, associated with early Methodism, which taught that Christians could receive &#8216;entire sanctification&#8217; from God as a second process after conversion. This removed original sin and allowed Christians to enter a state of perfect love.</note> &#8211; &amp; again &#8211; &#8220;I had almost said I had rather see the Devil in the pulpit than an Antinomian!&#8221;<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">The doctrine that those who have been selected for salvation do not need to obey moral laws.</note> &#8211; The purport of his sermon was good, &#8211; nothing fanatical, nothing enthusiastic; &#8211; &amp; the Calvinism which it expressed was so qualified as to be harmless. The manner that of a performer as great in his line as Kean or Kemble.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Edmund Kean (1787&#8211;1833; <title>DNB</title>) and John Philip Kemble (1757&#8211;1823; <title>DNB</title>), the leading actors of their day.</note>
          <del>Tx</del> And this manner it is which has attracted so large a congregation <del>xx</del> about him, all apparently of the better order of persons in business. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">EMay</ref> was very much amused &amp; I am very glad I have heard him at last. It is very well that there should be such preachers for those who have no appetite for better drest food. But when the whole service of such a place is compared with the <del>x</del> genuine devotion &amp; sober dignity of the Church service, properly performed, &#8211; I almost wonder at the taste <del>for xx</del> which prevails for garbage.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">One remark I must not omit. I never before understood the unfitness of our language for music. Whenever there was an <hi rend="ital">S</hi> in the word, the sound produced by so many voices, made as loud a hissing as could have been produced by a drove of geese in concert, or by several hundred snakes in full chorus.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I have spoken about <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Bels</ref> ear. The way will be to open the place behind &amp; create a discharge there, &amp; thus it will heal internally.	</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMartha">Martha</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEliza">Eliza</ref> are coming to dine here today. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> tomorrow. The next day we go to <ref type="m" target="people.html#InglisSirRobert">Sir Robert Inglis&#8217;s</ref>, &amp; Wednesday to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HughesMaryAnne">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Hughes</ref>, where I believe the Wynns will meet us <ref type="m" target="people.html#WynnCharlesWW">Wynn</ref> &amp; all his family seem to be very much taken with <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>. She went to the play with them on Friday, &amp; is to go again when <ref type="m" target="people.html#GeorgePrinceRegent">the King</ref> goes.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">George IV attended the Theatre Royal, Drury Lane, on Monday, 1 December 1823. It was his first visit for two years, while the interior of the theatre was refurbished. The play was Isaac Bickerstaffe (1733&#8211;1812?; <title>DNB</title>), <title>The Hypocrite</title> (1768).</note> They are delighted with her manners, which indeed strike all who have seen her. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HerriesJohnCharles">Herries</ref> has asked us down to Montreal near Seven Oaks (Lord Amhersts house,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Montreal Park, near Sevenoaks, Kent, a large Palladian mansion commissioned by Jeffrey Amherst, 1st Baron Amherst (1717&#8211;1797; <title>DNB</title>).</note> which he has taken) &amp; he wished to have us there when there is a ball at Seven Oaks which will bring together all the gentry of those pa[MS missing] He wants me also to meet the Chancellor of the Exchequer (Robinson)<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Frederick John Robinson, 1st Earl of Ripon (1782&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), President of the Board of Trade 1818&#8211;1823, Chancellor of the Exchequer 1823&#8211;1827, and Prime Minister 1827&#8211;1828.</note> there. We shall probably go when we return from Greenwich: our visit there is fixed for Saturday next. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your daughter</ref> you see is made much of: but it will not spoil her.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Dumbee<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">The portraitist Samuel Lane (1780&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>), who was deaf and dumb. The portrait is now in Balliol College, Oxford.</note> is making a picture which promises to be as good as Phillips&#8217;s print<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Phillips (1780&#8211;1845; <title>DNB</title>) painted Southey&#8217;s portrait for John Murray in 1815 (now in the Wordsworth Museum, Dove Cottage). A mezzotint engraving was made by Samuel William Reynolds (1773&#8211;1835).</note> is bad, base, vile, vulgar, odious, hateful, detestable, abominable, execrable &amp; infamous. The rascally mezzotints scraper has made my face fat, fleshy, silly &amp; sensual, &amp; given the eyes an expression which I conceive to be more like two oysters in love than anything else. But Dumbee goes on to the satisfaction of every body, &amp; will neither make me look like an assassin, a Methodist preacher, a sensualist, nor a prig.<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey refers here to various unsatisfactory likenesses. Based on his later &#8216;Epistle from Robert Southey, Esq. to Allan Cunningham&#8217;, <title>The Anniversary: or, Poetry and Prose for MDCCCXXIX</title> (London, 1829), pp. 9&#8211;22, he might have been thinking of the following: an assassin &#8211; the engraving by Christian Gottfried Zschoch (1775&#8211;1833) in <title>The Works of Robert Southey</title> (1820), no. 2696 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library; a Methodist preacher &#8211; the unpaginated frontispiece to <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 1 (February 1814); a sensualist &#8211; the miniature painted by Matilda Betham in 1808; and a prig &#8211; the miniature painted by Edward Nash in 1820 (now in the National Portrait Gallery). </note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">I called yesterday on <ref type="m" target="people.html#RogersSamuel">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rogers</ref> &amp; found &#8211; Semed<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">John Carne (1789&#8211;1844; <title>DNB</title>), traveller and author, who had just returned from an extended visit to the Near East. He had visited Southey in Keswick. Southey calls him &#8216;Semed&#8217; after Carne&#8217;s story, &#8216;The Power of Beauty. A Syrian Tale&#8217;, <title>London Magazine</title>, 10 (August 1824), 165&#8211;176.</note> at breakfast with him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I shall see Edward Collins<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">Edward Collins (c. 1777&#8211;1841), Captain in the 21st Light Dragoons and brother of Charles Collins, Southey&#8217;s old school-friend. Southey had missed seeing him in Perthshire on his Scottish journey in 1819, as Collins had travelled south to deal with matters arising from the death of his father, William Collins (c. 1751&#8211;1819), the naval engineer and inventor, at his home in Maize Hill, Greenwich. </note> at Maize Hill, &#8211; he has left Scotland to reside in what was his mothers house.<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Sarah Collins, n&#233;e Astell (1753&#8211;1822).</note> And I shall endeavor to see poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#DaunceyLouisa">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Bill</ref> at Blackheath, &#8211; did <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> mention the shocking loss of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BillRobert">her husband</ref>, who died by his own hand. It was a clear case of insanity.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">A great deal more must be left for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> to relate. She seems to enjoy herself, &#8211; which is more than I do, for I am thoroughly tired every day, &amp; heartily wish myself at home. Would that I could get away! &#8211; Some of my business I shall be able to do at Greenwich, &amp; when we return from Montreal I must go to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref> &amp; finish it there. As soon as it is possible, off I shall be for the west, hurry thro my visits there, &amp; then back gain, only to be off for Norwich. &#8211; I can remember nothing about what was last paid to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RumneyJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Rumney</ref>. His civilities I must pay by sending him the B. of the Church<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> in return. &#8211; &amp; my easiest way of paying his demand will be by having it ready in a letter to put in at his bedroom window when the mail stops there to exchange bags on my way home.<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">John Rumney was Deputy Postmaster at Brough, Westmorland 1815&#8211;1844.</note> &#8211; You did quite right in sending the venison, which was very acceptable &amp; good.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Did I tell you that the Rotheram man&#8217;s name is <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebenezer</ref>. We all like him hugely, &amp; I have had from him one of the most characteristic &amp; curious letters I every received. He is under a Lady-Mare,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Elliot married Frances Gartside (b. 1781) in 1806.</note> &#8211; but he is both fond &amp; proud of her. &#8211; And now let me write a few lines to Countess Rumpelstizchen.<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">A feline member of the Southey household.</note> So I remain</p>
        <p>
          My Governess<lb/>
          Your <hi rend="ital">Lady</hi>ships dutiful husband<lb/>
          RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>