<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>Digital publisher</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4103" type="letter"><head>4103. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir Thomas [Dyke Acland]</ref>, <date when="1823-12-22">22 December 1823</date>
<note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Watermark: [partial] crest cut in half/ 1818<lb/>
MS: Department of Rare Books, Special Collections and Preservation, River Campus Libraries, University of Rochester, Robert Southey Papers A.S727. ALS; 2p.<lb/>
Unpublished.</note></head>


<opener><dateline><date when="1823-12-22">22 Dec. 1823</date></dateline>

<salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener>
            <p rend="indent1">Short &#38; hurried as my visit to the West must be, I should neither do as I wish nor as I ought, if I did not propose to pass one day of it in your society. I shall be with Kennaway<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Kennaway, 1st Baronet (1758–1836), made a fortune in the East India Company and became a landowner in Devonshire. Southey knew him through his son, Charles Edward Kennaway, who had visited Southey in the Lake District in 1819–1820. His home was Escot House, near Ottery St Mary, Devon.</note> on Saturday the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of Jan<hi rend="sup">y</hi>: with the Coleridges<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey stayed at Chanter’s House, Ottery St Mary, with James Coleridge (1759–1836), the father of Henry Nelson Coleridge, and Lieutenant-Colonel in the East Devon Militia. During this visit he also met many members of the Coleridge family.</note> on Sunday. Monday &#38; Tuesday I propose to pass the one day with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Marryat,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">John Marriott (1780–1825; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman, poet and friend of Walter Scott. He was Curate of St James, Exeter, St Lawrence, Exeter, and St John, Broadclyst. The patron of the latter church was Sir Thomas Acland, who was also a friend of Marriott.</note> the other with you; – if you are <del>xxx</del> not otherwise engaged. My next <del>xxx</del> &#60;point&#62; is Exeter. <del>&#38; as</del> I do not know how your respective abodes are situated with regard to that city, &#38; it would be most convenient for me to take that house last, which should bring me nearest it. Perhaps you will have the goodness to let me know (by a line addressed to <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">15 Q Anne Street, Cavendish Square</ref>) <hi rend="ital">if</hi>, &#38; on <hi rend="ital">which day</hi>, you can receive me. – </p>
               <p rend="indent1">I take the liberty of inclosing a <del>xxxx</del> note to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Marryat, – not recollecting his address.
                  I was sorry not to see Lady Inglis<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Inglis, née Biscoe (1787–1872), the wife of Sir Robert Inglis.</note> during my customary visit at Battersea Rise. But I have seen <ref type="m" target="people.html#InglisSirRobert">Sir Robert</ref> three or four times since, &#38; he speaks always of her amendment, – tho as a matter of precaution she must be confined to two rooms during the winter.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">Present my respects to Lady Acland,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Lydia Elizabeth Acland, née Hoare (1786–1856), wife of Sir Thomas Acland.</note> &#38; believe me</p>
            <closer><salute rend="indent2">Sir Thomas</salute>
               <salute rend="indent3">with sincere esteem</salute>
               <salute rend="indent4">your obliged &#38; obedient</salute>
					<signed rend="indent5">Robert Southey.</signed></closer>
</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
