<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4106Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4106Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4106" type="letter">
        <head>4106. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">Edith Southey</ref>, <date when="1823-12-25">24 December[&#8211;26 December] 1823</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">MS: British Library, Add MS 47888. ALS; 4p. <lb />
Previously published: Kenneth Curry (ed.), <title>New Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 2 vols (London and New York, 1965), II, pp. 255&#8211;260.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Streatham">Streatham</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1823-12-24">24 Dec. 1823</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Edith</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">To-day I thought would have brought me a letter from home, with an acknowledgement of the half bill: probably I shall find it tomorrow on my return to town. And as I have now after six days close work packed up my papers (having finished &amp; sent off the review,<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Timothy Dwight (1752&#8211;1817), <title>Travels in New-England and New-York</title> (1821&#8211;1822), no. 881 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. It was reviewed by Southey in <title>Quarterly Review</title>, 30 (October 1823), 1&#8211;40, published 17 April 1824.</note> &amp; advanced so near the end of the B. Church<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> that three mornings in <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Anne Street</ref> will finish that also) &#8211; I may with a quiet conscience indulge in writing home.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I am afraid I expressed myself more peevishly than <del>xxx</del> I ought concerning <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> C.s</ref> account with Tolson.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Tolson, Jnr (1756&#8211;1842), a commission agent and tea dealer in Liverpool and the owner of Greta Hall since 1815.</note> You would excuse <del>me</del> it if you knew how many needless &amp; senseless demands are made upon my time in town, where every minute is precious.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">I came here on Thursday last. <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorHenrySir">Henry Taylor</ref> walked half the way with me, &#8211; the letter of introduction which I gave him at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> has proved so efficacious, (which of course it would not have been if his own talents had not accredited it) that he is now Editor of the London Magazine.<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Taylor contributed to the <title>London Magazine</title> at this time, but he did not become its editor.</note> &#8211; The boys are all at home, <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Errol</ref>
          <del>xxx</del> brought with him a cold &amp; affection of the chest, in consequence of which <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Harry</ref> came over yesterday to prescribe for him. He appears better to day; but it has altered him a good deal, &amp; kept him in so quiet or rather languid a state that I have scarcely heard his voice, nor seen what kind of boy he is. I believe however that I should like him rather less than <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillEdwardJnr">Edward</ref> &amp; rather more than <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertJnr">his second brother</ref>, tho they are all fine, promising, well disposed lads. Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillAlfred">Alfred</ref> is the <hi rend="ital">wrecklin</hi>
          <note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">A Cumbrian dialect word for the smallest of the litter; Alfred Hill was Herbert Hill&#8217;s second youngest son.</note> of the family, &amp; sorry I am to say that he is as much like a mucken<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Cuthbert Southey&#8217;s word for a monkey.</note> as poor Wilber<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> himself. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillGeorgiana">Georgiana</ref> excels at football, &amp; is the stoutest of the whole, but withal a very fine handsome girl.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> appears to be much the same as when I was last in town. Nothing has failed him but his limbs, &amp; those rather from &lt;the effect&gt; of rheumatism than of age. He goes to London in the stage &amp; returns the same morning, without difficulty or apparent fatigue. His hearing is as good as ever it was; his sight very little impaired, &amp; were it not that the loss of his teeth affects his articulation, his conversation <del>xxx</del> would betray no symptoms of age, for he has the same quiet, chearful, &amp; even playful manner than he had at Lisbon, three &amp; twenty years ago. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillCatherine">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> H.</ref> is much the graver of the two. She is fatter than when you saw her &amp; looks older than you <del>xxx</del>, as indeed I suppose she is.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Catherine Hill was one year younger than Edith Southey.</note> They keep no company, whatever, which I think must rather be owing to her inclination than his. During the six days that I have been here, the only persons who have called have been <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">the Doctor</ref>: not one of the parishioners. My mornings &amp; evenings have been past up stairs in solitude, steadily at work, <del>xx</del> I have had my afternoon &lt;nap&gt; also, &amp; enjoy dining at four o clock, &amp; a glass of arrack punch<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A distilled alcoholic drink, made from the fermented sap of the coconut tree, mixed with fruit or fruit juice.</note> after supper</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Tomorrow I mean to receive the sacrament here, &amp; then put myself on the way to London &amp; take my chance for a stage. We dine at <ref type="m" target="people.html#GonneMrs">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gonnes</ref>, where I shall see <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref>. <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">My Uncle</ref> has given me a beautiful little broche for her, &#8211; it is an <hi rend="ital">agoe marina</hi>
          <note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The Portuguese term for aquamarine, a precious stone of a bluish-green colour.</note> very prettily set. Friday we dine at <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref>. Saturday with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Monkhouse.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Thomas Monkhouse (1783&#8211;1825), a London merchant and cousin of Mary Wordsworth. He lived at 67 Gloucester Place, Portman Square, London.</note> My engagements in Devonshire stand thus &#8211; Saturday being the day of my arrival there, with the Kennaways,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Sir John Kennaway, 1st Baronet (1758&#8211;1836), made a fortune in the East India Company and became a landowner in Devonshire. Southey knew him through his son, Charles Edward Kennaway, who had visited Southey in the Lake District in 1819&#8211;1820. The Kennaway home, Escot House, is close to Ottery St Mary.</note> &#8211; Sunday at Ottery, &#8211; Monday &amp; Tuesday with <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T Acland</ref> &amp; M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Marryat,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">John Marriott (1780&#8211;1825; <title>DNB</title>), a clergyman, poet and friend of Walter Scott. He was Curate of St James, Exeter, St Lawrence, Exeter, and St John, Broadclyst. The patron of the latter church was Sir Thomas Acland, who was also a friend of Marriott.</note> &#8211; Wednesday to Exeter &amp; Crediton, where I must take care not to be killed with kindness.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The inn at Cambridge at which I was quartered is so perfectly clean &amp; commodious that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> will find no inconvenience in being lodged there for two or three <del>days</del> nights, beyond which our stay would not under any circumstances have been prolonged.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Poor Dumbee<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Lane (1780&#8211;1859; <title>DNB</title>). The portrait is now in Balliol College, Oxford.</note> has proved by far the best of all my painters. He took almost an affectionate leave of me, &amp; expressed his regret at not having succeeded better, tho he has in reality satisfied all who have yet seen the picture</p>
        <p rend="indent1">On my return from the West I shall remain no longer in these parts than to make our visit at Richmond. For you may well suppose that I long to be at home. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha&#8217;s</ref> letter amused &amp; pleased me much, &#8211; &amp; knowing what female curiosity is, I must not blame <del>xx</del> her for prying in a part of the desk where pens are not to be found. Another volume of the German stories<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Jacob Ludwig Karl Grimm (1785&#8211;1863) and Wilhelm Karl Grimm (1786&#8211;1859), <title>Kinder-und Hausm&#228;rchen</title> (1812), translated as <title>German Popular Stories</title> (1823) by Edgar Taylor (1793&#8211;1839; <title>DNB</title>). The book was an immense success (including with Cuthbert Southey) and was reprinted in 1824 and 1825, but a second volume did not appear until 1826.</note> is promised. I wish it may be published while I am in town, that I may send it down in a second frank to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert</ref>. Tell him I am glad to hear he is become so studious. Tell him too that of his three <del>xxx</del> Welsh Uncles here, the eldest is to be Master of Westminster, the second Lord Chancellor, &amp; the third Archbishop of York. I could not consent to his having Canterbury, because Canterbury is engaged. &#8211; Oh bless that sweet boy, how I long to see him, &amp; to tell him once more that I am very fond of him.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">You may laugh at <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your daughter</ref> about Hunter the Savage,<note n="16" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> of whom she made half a conquest at Montreal.<note n="17" place="foot" resp="editors">The country home of J. C. Herries, near Sevenoaks in Kent.</note> I am almost sorry &lt;to see&gt; the depth &amp; strength of her attachment to home. Now that she is in London, she says, she will stay out the time she had appointed &amp; do all she intended to do, &#8211; but she will never go to London again. She dislikes it as heartily as I do. And yet she receives as much kindness as you could desire, &amp; is fully sensible of it. &#8211; As for <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedford</ref> he pronounces her to be the most elegant creature he ever saw. &#8211; With regard to drawing I shall follow <ref type="m" target="people.html#WestallWilliam">Westalls</ref> advice whatever that may be, when I can see him again, &amp; as to singing she shall do whatever is thought advisable &amp; <del>acxxds</del> &lt;accords&gt; with her own wishes.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <date when="1823-12-25">Thursday morning.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">A merry Xmas, &amp; a happy new year to you all! To you first &amp; foremost my true &amp; lawful Governess &amp; Lady Mare; next to the great <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> whom I love not with a B alone, but thro the whole alphabet, stopping only at the letter X because it is not possible to love any thing that is cross: next to the very grave &amp; sober <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref>, Countess Pusseycat, the very gravest &amp; soberest of her kind; then to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">my Isabel</ref> who live as long as she will is to be a Belle still; &amp; tho last &amp; least, yet neither least not last in my love, to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Charles Cuthbert Southey</ref> Archbishop <hi rend="ital">in nubibus</hi>,<note n="18" place="foot" resp="editors">Literally &#8216;in the clouds&#8217;: a legal term referring to an event yet to happen (and which may not happen).</note> Rural Dean by courtesy, &amp; in reality a good boy &amp; my very worthy son. And a merry Xmas &amp; happy new year to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSaraSTCdaughter">Sara</ref> also, &amp; the Most Venerable <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerSarah">her mother</ref>, &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerMary">Aunt Lovell</ref>, &#8211; &amp; to Betty<note n="19" place="foot" resp="editors">Elizabeth Thompson (c. 1777&#8211;1862), the Southey family&#8217;s long-standing servant. </note> &amp; Anne, &amp; the Cook<note n="20" place="foot" resp="editors">Servants in the Southey household at Greta Hall, Keswick.</note> (tho I have absolutely forgotten who she is, both name &amp; person) &#8211; &amp; to Rumpelstilzchen, &amp; Hurliburlibus,<note n="21" place="foot" resp="editors">Two feline members of the Southey household.</note> &#8211; all persons &amp; all creatures belonging to my household, a merry Xmas &amp; happy new year to them all.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">God bless you my dearest Edith</salute>
          <salute rend="indent2">Yr RS.</salute>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent0">
            <date when="1823-12-26">Friday afternoon.</date>
          </p>
          <p rend="indent1">I found your letter on my return yesterday. <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Your daughter</ref> seems very chearful &amp; well, &amp; better reconciled to London. Lady Malet<note n="22" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> will not part with her yet. We are to meet <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuelTaylor">Coleridge</ref> at M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Monkhouses tomorrow.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">I inclose the other half bill, &#8211; &amp; take this to <ref type="m" target="people.html#BedfordGrosvenorCharles">Bedfords</ref> that he may get it franked tomorrow. No time for more &#8211; only that I hope your head is better. &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillErrol ">Errol</ref> is so unwell as to give cause for some uneasiness, &#8211; his chest is threatened</p>
          <p>The Mays<note n="23" place="foot" resp="editors">
              <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> and his son, John May (1802&#8211;1879).</note> are come to town for a fortnight. I saw the younger this morning. Once more &#8211; God bless you</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>