<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4130Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4130Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4130" type="letter">
        <head>4130. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BrowneMrs">Elizabeth Browne</ref>, <date when="1824-02-08">8 February, 1824</date>
          </head><p>Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 5.<lb />
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47891. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Richmond.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-02-08">Sunday 8 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>  My dear Madam</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  I am the more vexed at not having seen you in Devonshire, because it has been in no slight degree thro my own sin of omission that the disappointment has arisen. Having a wide circuit to take in the western counties first &amp; then in Norfolk &amp; Suffolk, it was necessary for me every where to fix the day of arrival &amp; departure. I counted upon finding you at Exeter &amp; passing a few hours with you either on my way to Crediton or on the day when I should leave that place &amp; take <ref type="m" target="people.html#AclandThomasSir">Sir T. Aclands</ref> on my return. To my great vexation M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Keenan<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Keenan (d. 1838), an artist and widow of the Irish portrait-painter, John Keenan (d. 1819). Southey had first met them in Exeter in 1799.</note> who had undertaken to find out your direction for me informed me when <del>you</del> &lt;I&gt; arrived, that you were out of reach, &amp; the four &amp; twenty hours which I would willingly have allotted to that visit were no longer at my command, &#8211; for engagements had been made <hi rend="ital">for</hi> me during every day of my short continuance at Crediton, &amp; <hi rend="ital">by</hi> me for a long after journey.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> This would not have happened if I had written to you from town; &amp; I fear the wearying, &#8211; worrying &#8211; life in which I am always involved there will hardly plead my excuse. Yet you would excuse me if you knew by what shoals of people I am persecuted there, with letters upon all sorts of subjects, &#8211; in such numbers that I have now a portfolio full unanswered, &#8211; even of those which deserve as well as require reply.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Nor would it have happened if I had found <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneElizabethdau">Miss Browne</ref> at Leeds. The first thing I did on my arrival there was to enquire concerning her. I learnt that she was no longer in that town, &amp; taking up a Leeds paper, saw there in the announcement of her sisters<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Lydia Browne (c. 1789&#8211;1864) had been widowed on the death of her husband, Joseph Lea (d. 1821) of The Hill, Amblecote, a fact Southey was unaware of until he saw it mentioned in a Leeds newspaper when he passed through the city in November 1823. One possibility is that Southey read this news in the <title>Leeds Mercury</title> of 8 November 1823, which also announced Lydia Browne&#8217;s second marriage to John Addenbrooke (formerly Homfray) (1759&#8211;1837) of Wollaston Hall, Worcestershire. </note> second marriage &#8211; the first intelligence that she had become a widow.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">The long-delayed &amp; long desired time of my return home is now thank Heaven within view, after an absence of fourteen week &amp; <del>xx</del> travelling (already) more than twelve hundred miles. My place is taken in the mail for Friday next, &amp; on this day week I hope to be once more seated by my own fire side: tho not with all my family around me, for <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> will be left in London. It is possible that she may accompany Lady Malet<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Lady Susanna Malet, n&#233;e Wales (1779&#8211;1868), the widow of Sir Charles Malet, 1st Baronet (1752&#8211;1815; <title>DNB</title>).</note> to the Devonshire coast early in the summer. Such an arrangement is talked of, &amp; if it take place, I hope she will find means of seeing you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> &amp; the other children were well when I heard from them last. In every letter she repeats her vexation that I have not seen you, &#8211; almost reproachingly, &#8211; for I have not had time in my letters home fully to explain to her how I was entangled with engagements, so arranged, that the one could not be postponed without dislocating all the others.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> My Book<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> (which I finished at Crediton) was published on Monday last: &amp; as I did not know whether the direction which was given me at Exeter would be as secure for a coach-parcel, as for a letter, I sent your copy to my friend <ref type="m" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Lightfoot</ref> at Crediton requesting him to forward it. In the course of the summer I hope I shall have my Tale of Paraguay<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> ready to send you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Tell me, I entreat, that you forgive me. Tell me of my little friend Marys<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Mary Browne (1810&#8211;1892), daughter of Wade and Elizabeth Browne. She later married William Farwell (1806&#8211;1876), Rector of St Martin&#8217;s, Liskeard 1830&#8211;1876.</note> health, &#8211; <hi rend="ital">little</hi> I suppose she still is, &amp; <hi rend="ital">friend</hi> I must always consider her &amp; call her. Tell me also of <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneElizabethdau">Miss Browne</ref> &amp; <ref type="m" target="people.html#BrowneSarah">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Crump</ref>, &amp; remember me to them most kindly. I live in hopes of again seeing them &amp; you. Indeed the desire of atoning for having left you unseen now, will operate strongly as a motive for drawing me westward whenever I may visit London again. It is not in my nature ever to forget those whom I have esteemed &amp; loved.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me my dear M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Browne<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2"> sincerely &amp; affectionately yours<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3">  Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>