<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4131Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4131" type="letter">
        <head>4131. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">Ebenezer Elliott</ref>, <date when="1824-01-09">9 February 1824</date>
          <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: To/ M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> E. Elliott/ Sheffield<lb />
               Stamped: [partial] RICHMOND/ 1824 <lb />
               Postmark: NIGHT/ FE 9/ 1824<lb />
               MS: Sheffield City Libraries and Archives, MD 2191-29. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: E. R. Seary, &#8216;Robert Southey and Ebenezer Elliott: Some New Southey Letters&#8217;, <title>Review of English Studies</title>, 15 (October 1939), 418.</note>
        </head>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>Richmond. </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-02-09">9 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824.<delSpan />
            </date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> I have been travelling far &amp; wide, East, West &amp; South, since I received your most interesting letter. The last place at which I halted was Cambridge, &amp; there I have succeeded in doing, what I hoped to do. A friend of mine at Peter House, who is one of the Senior Fellows &amp; takes an active part in the management of the College (<ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Tilbrooke</ref> is his name, &#8211; the same person who wrote a pamphlett <hi rend="ital">against</hi> my hexameters &#8211;)<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Samuel Tillbrook, <title>Historical and Critical Remarks upon the Modern Hexamatrists, and Upon Mr Southey&#8217;s Vision of Judgement</title> (1822), a critique of Southey&#8217;s <title>Vision of Judgement</title> (1821).</note> &#8211; will secure a Sizarship for your son,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Ebenezer Elliott (1807&#8211;1871), eldest son of Ebenezer Elliott. He matriculated at Peterhouse College, Cambridge, in 1825 as a sizar (i.e. a student receiving some form of financial assistance) and obtained his BA in 1829. He became a clergyman and was Perpetual Curate of New Mill, Huddersfield 1841&#8211;1843, and Lothersdale, near Skipton 1844&#8211;1848, later going to St Kitts in the West Indies and serving as Rector of Christ Church, Nichola Town, and St Mary&#8217;s, Cayou.</note> which, if you can supply him with 60&#163; a year, will well enable him to go thro College. There is also a possibility &amp; a prospect of obtaining other helps for him, (- such as might cover his whole expences if he were at this time qualified to enter:) <del>xxxx</del> if they fall vacant when he is in a condition to receive them. With diligence &amp; good <del>fortune</del> conduct his success is certain.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> You had better place him now where he can be brought forward in Greek, Latin &amp; Mathematicks. He will not find his progress difficult under good tuition. These are the objects to which he must attend. English will come of itself. Is there a good school at Sheffield? It is of main importance that he should be placed now under judicious guidance. Let <del>xx</del> him but be put fairly into the right course, &amp; your best wishes for him may be accomplished.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  It was on Thursday last that I saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Tilbrooke</ref>, &amp; spoke with him. From that day I have not had ten minutes till now in which I could sit down &amp; communicate this, much as I wished to do it. My place is taken in the Carlisle mail for Friday next, &amp; on Sunday morning I hope to reach home, after the longest absence which I have ever made from my family, <del>since I had one</del>. Direct to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. If you cannot satisfy yourself about any school in your own neighbourhood shall I enquire concerning those in the North? There is one in good repute at Richmond; &#8211; there is one at Sedburg, &#8211; one at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bees.<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Richmond School, a medieval grammar school foundation, which under James Tate (1771&#8211;1843; <title>DNB</title>), Headmaster 1796&#8211;1833, gained a formidable reputation for sending excellent scholars to Cambridge University; Sedbergh School, founded 1525, had the right to send eight of its pupils to scholarships at St John&#8217;s College, Cambridge; and St Bees School in Cumbria, founded in 1583, could send three of its pupils to scholarships at Pembroke College, Cambridge.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">Present my kind regards to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Elliott<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Frances Gartside (b. 1781). She and Ebenezer Elliott had married in 1806 and had thirteen children.</note> of whom you have said so much that I am as solicitous for your sons welfare, on her account, as on yours. &#8211; &amp; believe me to be &#8211; with great esteem &amp; respect &#8211; truly &amp; heartily yours</p>
        <closer>
          <signed rend="indent2">Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
        <lb />
        <postscript>
          <p rend="indent1">Remember me kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#EverettJames">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Everett</ref>, &#8211; &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MontgomeryJames">Montgomery</ref>, to whom I will write when I am settled at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>