<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4135Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4135Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4135" type="letter">
        <head>4135. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#HareJulius ">Julius Hare</ref>, <date when="1824-02-18">18 February 1824</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Julius Hare Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>/ Trinity College/ Cambridge <lb />
               Postmark: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               MS: Berg Collection, New York Public Library. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Unpublished.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-02-18">18 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">  My first business on my return home has been to look for the passage to be inserted in the Dialogue between Cicero &amp; his brother.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, p. 383&#8211;384, no. 1600 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This passage was added to Dialogue XVIII, between the Roman statesman, Marcus Tullius Cicero (106&#8211;43 BC), and his brother, Quintus Tullius Cicero (102&#8211;43 BC).</note> I am glad to perceive on discovering it that the letter gave me no cause to suppose it had <del>been</del> not been sent to you, &#8211; so that I stand acquitted of any neglect in not having transmitted it. The passage it seems was written in consequence of some observations in a letter of mine upon the pleasure from our children.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 8 May 1823, Letter 4013.</note> It is to be added after the sentence in which Cicero speaks of the pleasure of meeting his friends in a future state.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent2"> Quinctus</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> To leave behind us our children, if indeed they will be permitted to stay behind, is painful.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent2"> Marcus</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Among all the contingencies of life, it is that for which we ought to be the best prepared, as the most regular &amp; ordinary in the course of nature. We bequeath to ours a field illuminated by our glory, &amp; enriched by our example: a noble patrimony, &amp; beyond the jurisdiction of Pr&#230;tor or proscriber. Nor indeed is our fall itself without its fruit to them; for violence is the cause why that is often called a calamity which is not so, &amp; repairs in some measure its injuries by exciting to commiseration &amp; kindness. The pleasure a man receives from his children resembles that which with more propriety than any other we may attribute to the Divinity: for to suppose that his chief satisfaction &amp; delight should arise from the contemplation of what he has done or can do, is to place him on a level with a runner, or a wrestler. The formation of a world, or of a thousand worlds, is as easy to him as the formation of an atom. Virtue &amp; intellect are equally his production: but he subjects them in no slight degree to our volition. His benevolence is gratified at seeing us conquer our wills &amp; rise superior to our infirmities; &amp; at tracing day after day a nearer resemblance in our moral features to his. We can derive no pleasure but from exertion: he can derive none from it, since exertion, as we understand the word, is incompatible with omnipotence.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent2">Quinctus</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Proceed my brother. In all temptations of mind &amp; feeling my spirits are equalized by your discourse, &amp; that in particular which you said with rather too much brevity, of our children, soothes me greatly</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent2"> Marcus</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I am persuaded of the truth in what I have spoken. And yet &#8211; ah Quinctus! there is a tear that Philosophy cannot dry; &amp; a pang that will rise as we approach the Gods.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">  May I request you when you send this to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Taylor</ref> to say to him that when he sends off a parcel to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref>, I shall be <del>able</del> much obliged to him if he will pack up with it some books for me, which I will take care shall be deposited in Waterloo Place<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">The firm of Taylor and Hessey, which published Landor&#8217;s <title>Imaginary Conversations</title>, were based at 13 Waterloo Place, Pall Mall.</note> without delay.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Believe me Dear Sir<lb/>
          <salute rend="indent2">   Yrs very truly<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent3"> Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>