<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4136Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4136" type="letter"><head>4136. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LightfootNicholas">Nicholas Lightfoot</ref> [fragment], <date when="1824-02-18">18 February 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [in another hand] London Feb<hi rend="sup">ry</hi> twenty one 1824/ Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> N. Lightfoot/ Crediton/ CWWilliams Wynn<lb/>
               Postmark: FREE/ 21 FE21/ 1824/ +<lb/>
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Eng. Lett. d. 110. AL; 4p.<lb/>
               Unpublished.</note></head>
            
            
           <opener> <dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>. </placeName></address><date when="1824-02-18">18 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>My dear Lightfoot</salute></opener>
           <p rend="indent1"> Your letter would have given me great pleasure if the melancholy conclusion had not thrown a cloud over it. I hardly dare ask you what has been the termination.</p>
            <p rend="indent1"> My movements after I last wrote to you were executed punctually as they had been foreplanned. I visited <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref>, &#38; Playford Hall<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Home of Thomas Clarkson.</note> (near Ipswich,); remained a clear day at Cambridge where <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> saw the place to great advantage by favour of the bright sunshine – returned to town on Thursday the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. in time to keep an engagement for dinner; went to Richmond on the Saturday, back to London on the Tuesday following, on the Friday seated myself in the Carlisle mail, &#38; on Sunday reached my own home in safety, after having been absent fifteen weeks, &#38; travelled fifteen hundred miles. God be thanked I found all well, &#38; arrived in perfect health myself.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> This is the third day, &#38; I am not yet got fairly into joint. I was never before absent for so long a time, – not even when I crost the Alps.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s continental journey of May–August 1817. He left Cumberland for London on 22 April 1817 and did not return until 18 August 1817, making this absence slightly longer than that of 3 November 1823 until 15 February 1824.</note> There is so much to do that I hardly know where to begin. The first business however is to clear off heavy arrears of letter-writing, – for I have brought home with me a huge pile of letters from all sorts of people upon all sorts of subjects: a whole host of unknown persons seeming all perfectly to agree in supposing that I can have no other earthly business than to attend to them &#38; their concerns.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  As yet I seem hardly awakened from a long dream. Already however the days appear to pass as rapidly, as they did slowly a week ago. The journey has been profitable in the best way; it has freshened old recollections, &#38; laid in store of new ones. And I can now retrace at leisure the scenes which I was too much hurried to enjoy thoroughly while they lasted. Crediton has left upon me a very lively &#38; very pleasing impression. A few names indeed have dropt thro the holes of a memory which begins to be the worse for the wear; – but every thing else is clear &#38; vivid. I have nowhere enjoyed myself more; nowhere seen a happier family, a happier man, – one who has more cause to be happy, or more deserves to be s[MS missing]</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> My book,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> as far as could be judged when I left London, was doing well. <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray</ref> offered me 700 guineas for the copyright: this I refused to take, (telling him he must be well aware that of all the authors with whom he had ever been concerned there were none whom he had paid so ill as myself. He admitted this to be the case.) And if the Book should obtain a regular sale, as an essential part of English history, nowhere else to be found in a connected narrative, or legible form, it may become a valuable property.</p>
           <p rend="indent1"> Concerning the University Living,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The University of Oxford had the right to appoint the Vicar of South Petherwin in Cornwall. In March 1824, Robert Stephen Stevens (c. 1778–1856), a Fellow of Wadham College, Oxford, was instituted to the Vicarage after a long campaign to mobilise influential backers at the University. Southey may have been approached to support Stevens by his old friend Thomas Poole, who certainly wrote to Mrs Coleridge, asking her to obtain the backing of her Coleridge relatives at Oxford – both Poole and Stevens were from Somerset and had friends in common; see Sara Coleridge to Thomas Poole [January–February 1824], <title>Minnow among the Tritons: Mrs S. T. Coleridge’s Letters to Thomas Poole 1799–1834</title> (London, 1934), pp. 107–114. Stevens’s main rival was John Williams (c. 1774–1828), a Fellow of Exeter College, Oxford 1809–1826, and friend of John Taylor Coleridge, who became a Fellow at this College in 1813. John Taylor Coleridge may well have asked Southey to support his friend. Williams was eventually rewarded by becoming Vicar of Probus, Cornwall 1826–1828, a rather more valuable living in the gift of the Bishops of Exeter. </note> applications came to me from friends of both candidates at the same time; &#38; consequently I have made no attempt to serve either.</p>
          <p rend="indent1">  I must not forget the thanks of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyBertha">Bertha</ref> <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyKate">Kate</ref> &#38; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyIsabel">Isabel</ref> for their broaches, – nor of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith May</ref> for her beautiful ring. <ref type="m" target="people.html#FrickerEdith">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> S.</ref> sends her kindest regards, present mine also to M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Lightfoot, – to my god-daughter, Kate &#38; Bridget, &#38; Sir Nico.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Nicholas Lightfoot married Bridget Prideaux (1768–1856) on 13 July 1801. Their children were: John Prideaux Lightfoot; Frances Jane Lightfoot (1806–1882), Southey’s god-daughter; Catherine Anne Lightfoot (1808–1898); Bridget Mary Lightfoot (1810–1889); and Nicholas Francis Lightfoot (1811–1881), Vicar of Cadbury 1846–1855, Rector of Islip 1855–1881.</note> Remember that you know the way to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>, &#38; that the sooner you retrace it, the happier you will make us all. – Make my thanks &#38; compliments to all your neighbours for whose civilities I am obliged, – more especially to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> – your brother in-law<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Possibly Roger Ilbert Prideaux (1765–1850), eldest brother of Bridget Prideaux, and a solicitor in Kingsbridge, Devon.</note> – (I cannot call to mind his name) –</p>
            <lb/>
           <postscript><p rend="indent0"> [remainder of MS missing]</p></postscript>
            </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
