<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4138Southey</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4138Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4138" type="letter">
        <head>4138. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#WhiteNeville">Neville White</ref>, <date when="1824-02-19">19 February 1824</date>
          </head><p>MS: MS untraced; text is taken from John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856)<lb />
               Previously published: John Wood Warter (ed.), <title>Selections from the Letters of Robert Southey</title>, 4 vols (London, 1856), III, pp. 409&#8211;412.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>,</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-02-19">Feb. 19. 1824.</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>My dear Neville,</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1">Here I am, once more at my desk, by my own fire&#8211;side. My movements were all punctually performed, as they had been pre&#8211;planned. I reached home on Sunday morning, without impediment or mishap of any kind, and, thank God, found all well. Some little time is required before I can fairly get into joint again, after so complete a dislocation; and I bring back with me a formidable accumulation of letters, which followed and found me withersoever I went, and which it was not possible for me to answer during so hurried a mode of life.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I spoke about the piracy to <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> and <ref type="m" target="people.html#ReesOwen">Rees</ref>.<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s consultation with Longman was about the possibility of bringing legal action to prevent the publication of pirated copies of Henry Kirke White&#8217;s poems and of parts of the <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807). In 1823&#8211;1824 unauthorised versions were published by the firms of Jones &amp; Company, Orlando Hodgson, a congeries led by W. Baynes and Son, and A. Robertson and Co.</note> They argued the point like two lawyers; the former taking my view of the question, the latter holding an opinion that the rascals may shelter themselves under the letter of the law. They promised to consult <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref>, and do everything which could be done. I saw <ref type="m" target="people.html#TurnerSharon">Turner</ref> also, and told him in what manner I considered the case. The matter will now be properly investigated, &#8211; whether justly determined is another thing. It sets upon the wording of the act;<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The Copyright Act (1814) had extended an author&#8217;s copyright in new works from 14 years to 28 years. Works published in 1800 to 1814, and where the author had died before the old term of 14 years was over, were also protected for 28 years. Southey clearly believed that this latter clause meant that copyright in the <title>Remains of Henry Kirke White</title> (1807) was protected for 28 years, as Henry Kirke White had died in 1806. However, the &#8216;pirates&#8217; interpreted the law as meaning that copyright in this work had ended 14 years after its first publication, i.e. in 1821. This was probably because Henry Kirke White was not the person responsible for publishing the <title>Remains</title>, which had appeared posthumously, so it could be argued that the 28 years protection given to works published in 1800&#8211;1814 did not apply in this case. The only way to establish the law&#8217;s meaning was through a suit in the Court of Chancery, which was potentially very expensive &#8211; hence Longman and Rees&#8217;s hesitation in taking action.</note> and if words in law will bear an acceptation by which villany can be covered, and rogues escape punishment, that interpretation is the one which the craft will give it, as if one of the main uses of the law were to defeat justice.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> They would have Doctored me at Cambridge<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">i.e. awarded Southey an honorary doctorate, equivalent to the Doctorate of Civil Law he received from the University of Oxford in 1820.</note> if I would have waited another day for it; but my engagements were made in London, and feathers of this kind are not worth having when fees are to be paid for them; a civil letter of thanks is price enough for them. We had fine weather there, so that <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">Edith</ref> saw the place to advantage, and delighted with it she was; though I must tell you that when we drove into the town she took St. John&#8217;s for a prison. On the Thursday we breakfasted with <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Tillbrook</ref>, and the coach took us up at Peter House Gate. Charlesworth<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">John Charlesworth (1782&#8211;1864), son of John Charlesworth (c. 1742&#8211;1821), Rector of Ossington, Nottinghamshire 1782&#8211;1821, and an old friend of Kirke White. He practised as a surgeon in Clapham, but became an ardent evangelical and was later ordained in the Diocese of Norwich in 1814, serving as Rector of Flowton, Suffolk 1815&#8211;1844 and St Mildred&#8217;s, Bread Street, London 1844&#8211;1864. His career path may have served as a model for that followed by Neville White.</note> came to the coach door at Ipswich as I was stepping into it. I was pleased with the country about that place, and with Bury also. By the hasty view I had of it it appeared to be one of the prettiest country towns in England.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> It was a disappointment to me not to see Mr. Sewell<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Joseph Sewell (1772&#8211;1844), a wealthy Norwich solicitor and father-in-law of Neville White.</note> in town, and thank him for his hospitality and kindness. I wish there was a prospect of my being able to return them here. You, however, I hope and trust, will remember that you have more than half promised to take a course of mountain exercise and mountain air with me early in the season, as the likeliest and best means of recruiting your health, and fairly re&#8211;establishing it. Mrs. Neville<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Charlotte White, n&#233;e Sewell (1799&#8211;1873), wife of Neville White.</note> has given you leave of absence, and all you have to do is provide in time for your churches; set about that business without delay, and set off for <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> as soon as possible after the leaves begin to open. You cannot fix a better time for your departure than May&#8211;day. I am very confident that the air here, and the continuous exercise, will be of more service to you than any regimen or any remedies which could be prescribed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> And now I must thank you and Mrs. Neville, and Mr. and Mrs. Sewell,<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Ann Sewell, n&#233;e Cubitt (1780&#8211;1849), had married Joseph Sewell in 1792. The couple had five children.</note> and your excellent mother and sisters<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">White&#8217;s mother, Mary White, n&#233;e Neville (1755&#8211;1833), and his two sisters, Frances Moriah White (1791&#8211;1854) and Catherine Bailey White (1794&#8211;1889). The family had moved to Norwich from Nottingham in 1821.</note> also, for the truly kind and gratifying reception which you gave us at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref>. Short and seldom as such meetings are, they are nevertheless sunny spots in life; and henceforth, when I make one of my expeditions to the south, I shall look upon it as part of my business to strike eastward on the way. You are, and you have deserved to be, a happy man, Neville. Only attend to your health, to which nothing can be so injurious as sitting and studying too much. You must resume, as far as possible, those active habits to which you were accustomed, or supply their place as you can by some gymnastic exercises within doors, when it is not convenient to ride or walk. Come to me, and I will endeavour to put you in good condition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   My book<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> appeared to be going <hi rend="ital">on</hi>, that is to say, going o<hi rend="ital">ff</hi>, well when I left town. I take my chance for the profits, which appears to me more advisable than it would have been to accept <ref type="m" target="people.html#MurrayJohn">Murray&#8217;s</ref> offer of 700 guineas for the copyright; for if the work should obtain a regular sale as a portion of English history, containing what is nowhere else to be found in one succinct and continuous view, it may become a valuable property. I proceed now with the &#8220;Peninsular War,&#8221; and with the &#8220;Tale of Paraguay.&#8221;<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) and <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> The latter will now be my main object till it is completed.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Remember me to all your circle, not forgetting Miss Lingam,<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> whose gentle and winning countenance I remember with much pleasure, and my country woman, Miss Edmunds,<note n="12" place="foot" resp="editors">Unidentified.</note> herself a fair proof that good things come from Somersetshire. I may send <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cuthbert&#8217;s</ref> love to Mary-Anne,<note n="13" place="foot" resp="editors">Marianne White (1821&#8211;1885), eldest daughter of Neville White. In 1860 she married William Bradshaw (dates unknown) of Nottingham, a doctor who became a homeopathic practitioner later in life.</note> if she will not accept my own, though, perhaps, she likes me better now I am at a distance. Let me hear of you and yours. My god&#8211;son,<note n="14" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had stood as godfather to Neville White&#8217;s eldest son during his recent visit to Norwich. Family histories, including <title>The Homes and Haunts of Henry Kirke White; with some account of the family of White, of Nottingham and Norfolk</title> (London and Nottingham, 1908), p. 260, suggest that Neville White&#8217;s first son, christened Henry Kirke White (d. 1849), was born in 1821, but this information may be inaccurate, as Southey stood as godfather to him in January 1824.</note> I hope, continues to go on well.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
              I had almost forgotten to tell you that <ref type="m" target="people.html#Tilbrook">Tillbrook</ref> will secure a sizarship for Ebenezer Elliott<note n="15" place="foot" resp="editors">Ebenezer Elliott (1807&#8211;1871), eldest son of Ebenezer Elliott. He matriculated at Peterhouse College, Cambridge, in 1825 as a sizar (i.e. a student receiving some form of financial assistance) and obtained his BA in 1829. He became a clergyman and was Perpetual Curate of New Mill, Huddersfield 1841&#8211;1843, and Lothersdale, near Skipton 1844&#8211;1848, later going to St Kitts in the West Indies and serving as Rector of Christ Church, Nichola Town, and St Mary&#8217;s, Cayou. </note> at Peter House, and do for him whatever else may be in his power. <ref type="m" target="people.html#ElliottEbenezer">The father</ref> is apprised of this, and I expect daily to hear from him respecting the plan to be adopted till the youth is qualified for college. God bless you, my dear Neville.</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yours most affectionately,<lb/>
          <signed rend="indent2">  ROBERT SOUTHEY.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>