<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title type="main"><!-- Name of Parent Resource --></title>
                <title type="subordinate"><!--A Romantic Circles Praxis Volume or A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition  --></title> 
                <!--  The reading texts should all be encoded as level="m"  -->
                <title level="a"><!-- Name of Essay --></title>
                
                <author role="primary">
                    <name><!-- Name of writer. For multiple authors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></name>
                </author>
                
                <editor role="editor"><!-- Name of volume/edition editor. For multiple editors copy and paste in the appropriate number of nested <author><name> tags --></editor> 
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
                    <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
                </respStmt>            
                <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Director</resp>
                    <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
                </respStmt>
               
                <respStmt>
                    <resp><!-- Name of section. Ex: Electronic Editions, Praxis --> Editor</resp>
                    <name><!-- Name of Section Editor --></name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
                    <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                <edition><date>YYYY-MM-DD</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
                    <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
                            <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
                            <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
                        </address></p>
                    <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
                            <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Be sure that the name below matches the file name-->
                <idno type="edition">4142Southey<!-- section name.year.shortened name of volume/edition.last name of author or intro, biblio, etc. Example: praxis.2023.psychosis.intro --></idno> 
                <idno type="resource"><!-- shortened name of volume/editio, be sure that it matches what is above. Ex: psychosis --></idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <!-- CHANGE TITLE AND PTR // if this is a book-length unit, level="m" -->
                        <title level="a" type="main"><!-- Essay or manuscript name -->
                        </title>
                        <!-- Referenece the above <idno> tag but only change the final part-->
                        <ptr target="sectionName/shortenedName/sectionName.year.shortenedName.last name of author or intro, biblio"/> 
                        <!-- section name/shortened name of volume or edition/section name.year.shortened name of volume or edition.last name of author or intro, biblio
                        Ex: praxis/psychosis/praxis.2023.psychosis.intro-->
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="m"><!-- Parent name of volume or edition. Ex: Romantic Psychosis --></title>
                        <title level="s"><!-- Section name. Ex: Praxis --></title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
                            <!-- CHANGE DATE RIGHT BEFORE PUBLICATION -->
                            <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation>
                    <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="none">
                    <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
                    <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
                    <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
                    <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization method="markup">
                    <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
                    <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
                </normalization>
                <normalization>
                    <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
                    <p>&#35; has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
                    <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
                <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
            </tagsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext"/>
                <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature"/>
                <!-- ADD IN 4-6 KEYWORDS, THESE WILL BE PROVIDED BY EDITORS -->
                <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    <term subtype="tags"></term>
                    
                </keywords>
                
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <!--  Coder Name and Date Coded  -->
                <name><!-- coder --></name>
                <date></date>
                <list>
                    <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
                </list>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--END OF HEADER-->

   <text>
      <body>
         <div n="4142" type="letter"><head>4142. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#BowlesCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>, <date when="1824-02-24">24 February 1824</date>
            <note type="headnote" place="foot" resp="editors">Address: [deletions and readdress in another hand] To/ Miss Bowles/ <del>Buckland</del>/ <del>Lymington</del>/ Hampshire/ &#60;Calshot Castle/ Southampton&#62;<lb/>
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; [partial] LYM ON 98<lb/>
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 46. To Miss Caroline Bowles <lb/>
               MS: British Library, Add MS 47889. ALS; 4p. <lb/>
               Previously published: Edward Dowden (ed.), <title>The Correspondence of Robert Southey with Caroline Bowles</title> (Dublin and London, 1881), pp. 52–54. </note></head>
            
            
            <opener><dateline><address><placeName><ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName></address> <date when="1824-02-24">24 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1824</date></dateline></opener>
            
            <p rend="indent1">Since I returned I have been replying to the heap of letters which as they followed me about were <del>xxx xxx</del> laid aside till a more convenient season: you will easily understand that such letters are meant as had no right to more ceremonious treatment. I have &#60;been&#62; unpacking, arranging, &#38; idling over the long looked for box of books from Italy, &#38; a parcel of some forty volumes which I dispatched from <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref>. I have been enjoying an old coat &#38; old shoes, – habits so regular that the clock might be regulated by them, – my usual breakfast, my usual hours, my <del>xxx</del> after-dinner sleep – the consciousness of being at rest, – in a word home after a long absence. <del>Every</del> All things are now resuming their old course. The children come to me regularly with their lessons, &#38; I go down to supper with folio under my arm, to be taken with the black-currant rum, as a composer. Rumpelstilzchen arches his back to meet my salutation in the kitchen, &#38; Hurlyburlybuss<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Feline members of the Southey household.</note> greets me with the like demonstration of good will in the garden. Proof sheets are the only things wanting to my contentment, &#38; I shall not be long without them.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">I had been absent fifteen weeks wanting one day. To say nothing of the arrears of business which so long an interruption occasions, there were heavy arrears of sleep; &#38; if on the former score I am debtor, here I am on the creditor side of the account. By a fair calculation not less than three hundred &#38; forty five hours of good honest sleep were due to me when I reached home, at the rate of three hours lost in every twenty-four, besides six nights past in stage coaches. Such arrears are like the national debt, too large to be paid off; &#38; having taken out a small part, I am making a magnanimous resolution to cancel the remainder of the debt, &#38; rise as early as I did in London. The produce of this time before breakfast will find its way to <ref type="m" target="places.html#Buckland">Buckland</ref>, &#38; before you receive this letter I shall have made a beginning.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey was beginning work on ‘Robin Hood’. The resulting incomplete work was published in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [1]–36.</note></p>
           <p rend="indent1"> There can be no more difficulty in your writing the verse of Thalaba,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s <title>Thalaba the Destroyer</title> (1801).</note> than there is in an expert dancer’s acquiring a new step. The simple rule is to consult the ear alone, &#38; when you use lines of less than <del>the</del> ten syllables, let the pause generally be at the end of the line.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">  I sent your sea-poem<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Caroline Bowles had offered to contribute ‘The Mariner’s Hymn’, later published in <title>Solitary Hours</title> (London, 1826), pp. 22–24, to Alfred Pettet’s <title>Original Sacred Music</title> (London, n.d., c. 1825–1827), though it was eventually rejected and replaced by ‘I weep, but not rebellious tears’, later published in <title>Robin Hood: a Fragment. By the Late Robert Southey, and Caroline Southey. With Other Fragments and Poems By R.S. and C.S.</title> (London, 1847), pp. [227]–228.</note> to <ref type="m" target="people.html#PettetAlfred">the poor Musician</ref> at <ref type="m" target="places.html#Norwich">Norwich</ref>. The other &#38; the finer of the two,<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Bowles’s ‘It is not Death’, <title>Solitary Hours</title> (London, 1826), pp. 58–60.</note> is not so appropriate to his purpose, &#38; is moreover too good to be so bestowed. My admiration of <del>xxx</del> &#60;it&#62; is nothing abated by frequent re-reading &#38; re-considering it. The feeling &#38; the movement are in beautiful accord, – &#38; the expression is every where excellent, except in the stanza respecting Lazarus.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors"><title>John</title> 11: 1–46. Lazarus was raised from the dead by Jesus.</note> – It is the second line, which I feel to be faulty – would either of these variations be better?</p>
            <lb/>
            <lg type="stanza"><l rend="indent3">Oer Lazarus’s livid clay, – </l>
               <l rend="indent3">Oer Lazarus where entomb’d he lay – </l>
               <l rend="indent5">a corpse</l>
               <l rend="indent3">When dead &#38; buried Lazarus lay – </l></lg>
            <lb/>
           <p rend="indent0"> The last is the best, – yet neither satisifies me.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">‘It is not Death’, <title>Solitary Hours</title> (London, 1826), p. 60, changed this line to ‘O’er him he loved – corrupting clay! –’</note></p>
            <p rend="indent1">This poem if it were set to music with a thousandth part of the feeling that it breathes, would not fail of doing good. What are <ref type="m" target="people.html#ShieldWilliam">Shields</ref> merits as a composer? He is the only musician whom I know, but whether he has any merit or not in his profession is what others must tell me, for I am utterly ignorant upon that subject. If however you think well of him, he I know would think himself obliged to me if I sent him the poem.</p>
            <p rend="indent1">When you write under cover to <ref type="m" target="people.html#RickmanJohn">Rickman</ref> remember that his privilege extends only to two ounces. I keep two of the <title>old</title> penny pieces<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Copper penny pieces minted from 1797 onwards weighed one ounce exactly and so were a good way of measuring the weight of a letter. Copper pennies minted from the mid-1810s onwards were smaller and weighed less than one ounce.</note> <del>among my weights</del> to ascertain the weight of a doubtful packet, a single letter is not worth the trouble of inclosing; you see I set you the example of sending one direct. But my next I hope will bring with it an attempt at a beginning: &#38; ‘what is well begun is half done.’<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">A proverb, derived from Aristotle (384–322 BC), <title>Politics</title>, Book 5.</note> I hope to do a great deal this year, – &#38; among other things to compleat the series of Inscriptions,<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey’s inscriptions on the Peninsular War, most of which were unpublished until the eighteen finished poems, were collected in <title>Poetical Works</title>, 10 vols (London, 1837–1838), III, pp. 122–156. Southey originally planned to write thirty inscriptions.</note> – the sooner they are published the better, because every year lessens the number of those persons who would be gratified by seeing the tribute paid to their lost friends – God bless you – RS.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
