<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>                      
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part 7: 1822-1824</title>
        <title type="subordinate">A Romantic Circles Electronic Edition</title>
        <title level="a">4145. Robert Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 29 February [1824]</title><!-- Title of Letter -->
        <author role="primary">Southey, Robert, 1774-1843</author>
        
        <editor role="editor">Lynda Pratt</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2024-04-08</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
          University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
            reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
            it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
            and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
            amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
            Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
            accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
            as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
            in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
            editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
            for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
            <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
            conditions: 
            <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
            to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
            of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
            elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
            edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
            to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
            can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
            to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">4145Southey</idno> <!-- Add letter number -->
        <idno type="resource">The Collected Letters of Robert Southey: Part Seven</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">4145. Robert Southey to Walter Savage Landor, 29 February [1824]</title> <!-- Add letter title -->
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4145Southey"/> <!-- Add letter number -->
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="2024-04-08">April 8, 2024</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
            " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
            except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
            have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
            has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
            etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
          font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4145" type="letter">
        <head>4145. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Walter Savage Landor</ref>,<date when="1824-02-29"> 29 February [1824]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ Walter Savage Landor Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ Florence/ Italy.<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298; ANGLETERRE; CHAMBERY; [illegible]; CORRISP<hi rend="sup">ZA</hi> ESTERA DA GENOA<lb />
               Postmark: [partial] F/ 147<lb />
               MS: National Art Library, London, MS Forster 48 D.32 MS 38. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 115&#8211;117 [in part; misdated 29 February 1822].<lb />
               Dating note: Southey misdates &#8216;1822&#8217;; the content makes it clear that the letter was written in 1824.</p>
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <address>
              <placeName>
                <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref>.</placeName>
            </address>
            <date when="1824-02-29">29 Feb<hi rend="sup">y</hi>. 1822<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey misdates the letter &#8216;1822&#8217;.</note>
            </date>
          </dateline>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> Your Dialogues have been delayed some three weeks by an involuntary fault of mine, in not sending a passage for that between Cicero &amp; his brother to <ref type="m" target="people.html#HareJulius ">Julius Hare</ref>.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Walter Savage Landor, <title>Imaginary Conversations of Literary Men and Statesmen</title>, 2 vols (London, 1824), II, p. 383&#8211;384, no. 1600 in the sale catalogue of Southey&#8217;s library. This passage was added to Dialogue XVIII, between the Roman statesman, Marcus Tullius Cicero (106&#8211;43 BC), and his brother, Quintus Tullius Cicero (102&#8211;43 BC).</note> It is not worth explaining how this happened, &amp; how the wrong passage was forwarded to me in London. It is remedied now; the first thing I did on my return home from a long absence, was to transmit the insertion,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey to Julius Hare, 18 February 1824, Letter 4135.</note> the last sheet has probably by this time been struck off, &amp; you may perhaps receive news of its publication as early as this will reach you.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">    I ascertained in London that by a neglect in no fewer than three different quarters, the books which I supposed had been lost on their way to you, had never been sent. I have now given directions that they should be sent to <ref type="m" target="people.html#TaylorJohn">Taylor</ref> &amp; Hessey,<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">The firm of John Taylor and James Augustus Hessey (1785&#8211;1870) published Landor&#8217;s <title>Imaginary Conversations</title>.</note> to be forwarded with your own.<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">See Southey to Julius Hare, 18 February 1824, Letter 4135.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In looking over your volumes, you will I think wherever you perceive that a passage has been struck out, perceive at the same time for what reason it was omitted. The reason for every omission was such that I am persuaded you would without hesitation have assented to it, had you been upon the spot. A most powerful &amp; original book it is, &#8211; in any one page of which, &#8211; almost in any single sentence &#8211; I should have discovered the author, if it had come into my hands as an anonymous publication. Notice it must needs attract; but I suspect that it will be praised the most by those with whom you have the least sympathy, &amp; that the English &amp; Scotch Liberals &#8211; may perhaps forgive you even for being my friend.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I had not been from home since the summer of 1820. Even since that time London has been so altered as to have almost the appearance of a new city. Nothing that I have seen elsewhere can bear comparison with the line of houses from the Regents Park to Carleton House.<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">The former home of George IV, facing the south side of Pall Mall and next to St James&#8217;s Park. It is now the site of Carlton House Terrace. The series of buildings along the route from Regent&#8217;s Park, through Park Square, Portland Place and Regent Street to St James&#8217;s were designed by John Nash (1752&#8211;1835; <title>DNB</title>), George IV&#8217;s architect, to be grand enough to line a future ceremonial route. Building had been intensive from 1818 onwards.</note> A stranger might imagine that our shopkeepers were like the merchants of Tyre, &amp; lived in palaces. I wish the buildings were as substantial as they are splendid; but every thing is done in the spirit of trade; durability never enters into the builders speculations, &amp; the unsubstantial brick walls are covered with a composition which seems to have the bad property of attracting moisture in a remarkable degree. In Regents Park before the houses are finished the cornices are perfectly green with slimy vegetation.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The most impressive sight to me was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls by gas light.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Gas lighting had first been installed in the choir of St Paul&#8217;s Cathedral, London in 1822.</note> I do not think any thing could be more sublime than the effect of that strong light upon the marble statues, &#8211; &amp; the darkness of the dome, which the illumination from below served only to render visible. They have attempted to warm this enormous building by introducing heated air, &#8211; but after expending 800 &#163; in stoves &amp; flues, the effect was to render the quire unendurably cold; for the whole body of cold air from the dome came rushing down, &#8211; so that the attempt has been given up as hopeless.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Heating was not successfully installed in St Paul&#8217;s until 1868. The cathedral was notoriously cold in winter.</note>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1"> In London I scarcely went out of the circle of my own immediate friends. But as I went East &amp; West upon a round of flying visits to old friends &amp; familiar acquaintances, some of whom I had not seen for more than twenty years, &#8211; I had opportunity enough of perceiving a more general disposition to be satisfied with things as they are, than ever existed within my memory at any former time. There happened to be no question afloat with which any party feeling could be connected, &amp; the people were sensible of their general prosperity. Few indeed are they who apprehend the momentous consequences of the changes which are taking place. One effect of general education (such as that education is) is beginning to manifest itself. The twopenny journals of sedition &amp; blasphemy<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Primarily, William Cobbett&#8217;s <title>Political Register</title> (1802&#8211;1836). Cobbett introduced a 2<hi rend="ital">d.</hi> version in 1816 by concentrating on commentary rather than news and so evading stamp duty.</note> lost their attraction when they <del>had</del> no longer found <del>discon</del> hunger &amp; discontent to work upon. But they had produced an appetite for reading. Some journeymen printers who were out of work tried what <del>two</del> a weekly two-pennyworth of miscellaneous extracts would do, &#8211; it answerd so well that there were presently between 20 &amp; 30 of these weekly publications, the sale of which is from 1 to 15,000 each.<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">The most successful and best-known of these publishers was John Limbird (c. 1796&#8211;1883), whose 2<hi rend="ital">d.</hi> weekly miscellany, the <title>Mirror of Literature, Amusement and Instruction</title> (1822&#8211;1847) may well have sold 15,000 copies a week. Limbird had entered publishing as an employee of the radical Thomas Dolby (1782&#8211;1836), but had turned away from political journalism from 1819 onwards.</note> &#8211; How I should like to talk with you concerning the prospects of the old world &amp; of the new</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> I found the box of books, on my return, &#8211; they had escaped all damage from the seas. As yet I have only had time to place them upon my shelves, &amp; to see that many of them are very curious. At present I am going on with the second volume of the Peninsular War, &#8211; &amp; with my Tale of Paraguay.<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832) and <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note>
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">My little boy</ref> has just begun to learn the Greek alphabet</p>
        <p>
          God bless you<lb/>
            RS.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>