<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4148</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4148Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4148" type="letter">
        <head>4148. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry Herbert Southey</ref>, <date when="1824-03-01">[c. 1 March 1824]</date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Southey./ 15. Queen Anne Street/ Cavendish Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 1 MR 1/ 1824<lb />
               Seal: red wax; design illegible<lb />
               MS: Bodleian Library, MS Don. d. 4. ALS; 4p. <lb />
               Unpublished.<lb />
               Note on MS: This letter is written on a sheet of paper printed at the head with the following: TO BE/ PUBLISHED/ BY/ SUBSCRIPTION, IN THREE VOLS. OCTAVO,/ PRICE, &#163;2. S2./ (The money to be paid on delivery,)/ A CHRONOLOGICAL HISTORY OF THE/ WEST INDIES,/ BY CAPTAIN THOMAS SOUTHEY, COMMANDER/ ROYAL NAVY. [Tom Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827) was finally published by Longmans.]<lb />
               Dating note: Dating from postmark.</p>
        <opener>
          <salute> My dear Harry</salute>
        </opener>
        <p rend="indent1"> This is an ugly specimen of <ref type="m" target="places.html#Keswick">Keswick</ref> printing, <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">Tom</ref> never having thought either of inspecting &lt;it&gt; himself before it was struck off, or of desiring the Printer to let me do it for him. However it answers its purpose, as he has left me a quire of them to get rid of, this is the first use I make of paper smooth enough to be very disagreable. I found him equally out of spirits &amp; out of humour, &#8211; complaining that he has only been able to raise five pounds this year, &amp; that by begging from <ref type="m" target="people.html#HillHerbertUncle">my Uncle</ref>. This is the only intimation he ever gave me of ever having had recourse to him. A draft for 20 &#163; which I gave him has so compleatly restored his temper, as to make the change observable to those who know nothing of the cause. As soon as that supply is gone, no doubt he will return to the old subject, &amp; urge me to get something for him &#8211; for that it is in my power to do this is a persuasion in which he seems determined to persist. &#8211; Do not touch upon this subject in your reply.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   I am vexed as well as disappointed that there has been no letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">E May</ref> since my return because I am anxious to hear of the little girl.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Some five minutes after I had seated myself in the stage it occurred to me that I had left you to pay the hackney coachman, &#8211; for an agreable ride to <ref type="m" target="places.html#BullandMouth">the Bull &amp; Mouth</ref>. This arose from the same sort of hurry which made me leave the great coat behind when I set out for Norwich, &#8211; both in some degree proof that my wits are a little the worse for wear, &amp; are not as prompt on <del>xxxxxx</del> sudden occasion as they used to be.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> The consignment of books from Norwich has arrived, &amp; a parcel from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longmans</ref>. The cargo from <ref type="m" target="places.html#QueenAnneSt">Q Ann Street</ref> I do not look for before Thursday next. I found the long expected box sent by <ref type="m" target="people.html#LandorWalterSavage">Landor</ref> from Florence &amp; have made room for all these additions, by converting duodecimo shelves in the Organ Room<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">A room at Greta Hall that used to contain an organ when it was used by William Jackson; it was formerly Coleridge&#8217;s study.</note> into octavo ones, &amp; making octavo shelves in the passage carry a front-rank of diminutives, &#8211; thus after a manner creating space. An extension of this system will give accommodation for the increase of the next seven years if I should live so long.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">  I am going on with the War,<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">The second volume of Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> so that no time will be lost by waiting for the Catalan history,<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Finally, Southey had sought the assistance of George Canning.</note> having a good supply in advance when that comes I shall be able to feed the press well. This is my morning work &amp; for the evening I have taken the Tale of Paraguay<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">
            <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> in hand. And now that my arrears of letters are well nigh cleared off this poem will proceed briskly I trust &amp; with little interruption to its completion.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">The Bp of London</ref> writes thus to me concerning the Methodists &#8220;your communication<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had written to the Bishop of London on 20 February 1824. His letter is currently untraced. It enclosed a letter of 13 January 1824 that Southey had received from Mark Robinson (d. 1836), a Beverley draper, who was seeking to lead a group of local Methodists into union with the Church of England. Robinson&#8217;s letter is published in Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 161&#8211;164. </note> is very interesting &amp; important. Great difficulties I fear lie in the way of an open &amp; formal reunion with the body of the Church; &amp; I am apprehensive the movement, if it has any effect, will terminate in swelling the numbers, &amp; perhaps the reputation of a party, which counts among its members many exemplary Clergymen not sufficiently alive either to the necessity of order or to the prejudice resulting to religion from the aspersions thrown on the characters of their brethren, who differ with them in opinion on particular points. I am however not without hopes that in certain situations, more especially in parts of the colonies a union of purpose &amp; action at least may silently take place, which under discreet management would be productive of much advantage to the one great cause: &#8211; but this must be effected by prudent use of opportunities, &amp; not I think by formal treaty.&#8221;<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">William Howley to Southey, 25 February 1824, Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 165&#8211;166.</note> &#8211; I should like you to read this to <ref type="m" target="people.html#ColeridgeJohnTaylor">John Coleridge</ref> when you have an opportunity</p>
        <p rend="indent1">
          <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">The Bp</ref> writes in high terms of my BC.<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>The Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> wishes that references had been given &amp; that it might be published in a reduced form for the benefit of the lower classes. It cannot fail to be popular, he says, from the beauty of its execution.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> Let me hear of you. Tell Robert<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817), Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s eldest son.</note> his letter was received with great delight. &#8211; Love to him &amp; to <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyLouisa">his Mother</ref>. Love to Charles<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Charles Gonne Southey (1819&#8211;1861), later an army officer in India and Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s second surviving son.</note> also, but if a year or two should elapse before see him, I shall not be able to give him three jumps again unless my strength increases in proportion to his weight. &#8211; I miss your Burgundy but I have some pheasant-eyed Zante<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">A sparkling drink that Edith May Southey had made using the plant Pheasant&#8217;s-eye. Southey compares it to the wine from the Ionian island of Zante (Zakynthos). The island was most famous for Lianoroidi, a sweet white wine, the sort most favoured by Southey.</note> (<ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">EMays</ref> making) which is verily as good as Champag[MS obscured]</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent2"> God bless you</salute>
          <signed rend="indent3">  RS.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>