<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" />
        <title type="subordinate" />
        <title level="a" />
        <author role="primary">
          <name />
        </author>
        <editor role="editor" />
        <respStmt>
          <resp>TEI Encoding</resp>
          <name>EXTERNAL CODER</name>
        </respStmt>
        <sponsor>Romantic Circles</sponsor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Director</resp>
          <name>Thora Brylowe</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp> Editor</resp>
          <name />
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Jessica Tebo</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Assistant Editor</resp>
          <name>Anna Paige Wingfield</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>YYYY-MM-DD</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                    University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Material from the Romantic Circles Website may not be downloaded, 
                        reproduced or disseminated in any manner without authorization unless 
                        it is for purposes of criticism, comment, news reporting, teaching, 
                        and/or classroom use as provided by the Copyright Act of 1976, as 
                        amended.</p>
          <p>Unless otherwise noted, all Pages and Resources mounted on Romantic 
                        Circles are copyrighted by the author/editor and may be shared only in 
                        accordance with the Fair Use provisions of U.S. copyright law. Except 
                        as expressly permitted by this statement, redistribution or republication 
                        in any medium requires express prior written consent from the author(s)/
                        editor(s) and advance notification of Romantic Circles. Any requests 
                        for authorization should be forwarded to Romantic Circles:
                        <address>
              <addrLine>Romantic Circles</addrLine>
              <addrLine>c/o Professor Thora Brylowe</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Department of English</addrLine>
              <addrLine>University of Colorado Boulder</addrLine>
              <addrLine>Boulder, CO 80309</addrLine>
              <addrLine>thora.brylowe@colorado.edu</addrLine>
            </address>
          </p>
          <p>By their use of these texts and images, users agree to the following 
                        conditions: 
                        <list>
              <item>These texts and images may not be used for any commercial 
                                purpose without prior written permission from Romantic Circles.</item>
              <item>These texts and images may not be re-distributed in any 
                                forms other than their current ones.</item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>Users are not permitted to download these texts and images in order 
                        to mount them on their own servers. It is not in our interest or that 
                        of our users to have uncontrolled subsets of our holdings available 
                        elsewhere on the Internet. We make corrections and additions to our 
                        edited resources on a continual basis, and we want the most current text 
                        to be the only one generally available to all Internet users. Institutions 
                        can, of course, make a link to the copies at Romantic Circles, subject 
                        to our conditions of use.</p>
        </availability>
        <idno type="edition">letterEEd.26.4152</idno>
        <idno type="resource" />
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <analytic>
            <title level="a" type="main">
                        </title>
            <ptr target="editions/southey_letters/4152Southey" />
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="m" />
            <title level="s" />
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Romantic Circles, https://romantic-circles.org, 
                                University of Colorado Boulder</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Boulder, CO</pubPlace>
              <date when="YYYY-MM-DD">MONTH DAY, YEAR</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation>
          <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: 
                        " to &#8220; or &#8221;, and ' to &#8216; and &#8217;.</p>
        </quotation>
        <hyphenation eol="none">
          <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed 
                        except in the case of diplomatic transcriptions.</p>
          <p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens 
                        have been typed on the U.S. keyboard</p>
          <p>Em dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
          <p>En dashes have been rendered as &#8211;</p>
        </hyphenation>
        <normalization method="markup">
          <p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
          <p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts 
                        has been indicated as such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
        </normalization>
        <normalization>
          <p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
          <p># has been used for #, the pound sign</p>
          <p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, 
                        etc., have been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="indent1" scheme="css">margin-left: 1em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent2" scheme="css">margin-left: 1.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent3" scheme="css">margin-left: 2em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent4" scheme="css">margin-left: 2.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent5" scheme="css">margin-left: 3em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent6" scheme="css">margin-left: 3.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent7" scheme="css">margin-left: 4em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent8" scheme="css">margin-left: 4.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent9" scheme="css">margin-left: 5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="indent10" scheme="css">margin-left: 5.5em;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="center" scheme="css">text-align: center;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="left" scheme="css">text-align: left;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="right" scheme="css">text-align: right;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="small" scheme="css">font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="large" scheme="css">font-size: 16pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="largest" scheme="css">font-size: 18pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="smallest" scheme="css">font-size: 10pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlem" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="titlej" scheme="css">font-style: italic;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="figure" scheme="css">text-align: center; 
                    font-size: 12pt;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sup" scheme="css">vertical-align: super;</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="sub" scheme="css">vertical-align: sub;</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#Paratext" />
        <catRef scheme="#dcType" target="#Typescript" />
        <catRef scheme="#discipline" target="#Literature" />
        <keywords scheme="http://www.romantic-circles.org/#tags">
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
          <term subtype="tags" />
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <name />
        <date />
        <list>
          <item>TEI encoding the text</item>
        </list>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="4152" type="letter">
        <head>4152. Robert Southey to <ref type="a" target="people.html#MayJohn">John May</ref> [fragment], <date when="1824-03-07">[begun before and continued on] 7 [March 1824] </date>
          </head><p>Address: To/ John May Esq<hi rend="sup">re</hi>-/ 4. Tavistock Street/ Bedford Square/ London<lb />
               Stamped: KESWICK/ 298<lb />
               Postmark: E/ 10 MR 10/ 1824<lb />
               Watermark: HS &amp; S<lb />
               Endorsement: N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 236 1824/ Robert Southey/ &#8211; 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> March/ rec<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> d<hi rend="sup">o</hi>./ ans<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> June<lb />
               MS: Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas, Austin. ALS; 4p.<lb />
               Previously published: Charles Ramos (ed.), <title>The Letters of Robert Southey to John May: 1797&#8211;1838</title> (Austin, Texas, 1976), pp. 205&#8211;206; Charles Cuthbert Southey (ed.), <title>Life and Correspondence of Robert Southey</title>, 6 vols (London, 1849&#8211;1850), V, pp. 170&#8211;172 [in part].<lb />
               Dating note: Dating from endorsement and postmark; the top section of fol. 1 is missing; the contents of the letter suggest this may have contained an advertisement for Tom Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title>; see, for example, Southey to Grosvenor Charles Bedford, 7 March 1824 (Letter 4151).</p>
        <p rend="indent0">  [MS missing]</p>
        <p rend="indent0">  My dear friend</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> What success this proposal*<note n="1" place="foot" resp="editors">&#8216;* Of the Publication of a History of the West Indies by subscription&#8217; [Editors note: This is added in another hand at the foot of fol. 1r.] </note> of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyTom">my brothers</ref> may meet with remains to be seen.<note n="2" place="foot" resp="editors">Tom Southey&#8217;s <title>Chronological History of the West Indies</title> (1827), which he was encouraged to write by Southey.</note> If he can obtain two hundred subscribers, <ref type="m" target="people.html#LongmanThomas">Longman</ref> will take the risk of printing 750 copies. The book will be respectable &amp; useful, comprizing a regular view of all that has occurred in those Islands &#8211; from their discovery to the present time. &#8211; Take it for all in all it is perhaps as disgraceful a portion of history as the whole course of time can afford; &#8211; for I know not that there is any thing generous, any thing ennobling, &#8211; any thing <del>xxx xx</del> honourable <del>to human</del> or consolatory to human nature &#8211; to relieve it &#8211; except what may relate to the missionaries. Still it is a useful task to show what those islands have been &amp; what they are: &amp; the book will do this much more fully, clearly &amp; satisfactorily than has ever yet been done.</p>
        <p rend="indent1"> [MS missing] Three weeks have now nearly elapsed since my return, &amp; they seem like so many days, so swiftly &amp; imperceptibly the days pass by when they are past in regular employment &amp; uniform contentment. My old course of life has become as habitual as if it had never been interrupted. The clock is not more punctual than I am in the division of the day. Little by little I get on with many things, the Peninsular War<note n="3" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832).</note> is my employment in the forenoon, the Tale of Paraguay<note n="4" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>A Tale of Paraguay</title> (1825).</note> after tea, &#8211; before breakfast &amp; at chance times, as inclination <del>xxx</del> leads, I turn to other subjects, &amp; so make progress in all. The only thing at present wanting to my enjoyment is to have something in the press, &#8211; that I might have proof sheets to look for: &amp; I shall not long be without this. For tho M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Chinnery<note n="5" place="foot" resp="editors">George Robert Chinnery (1791&#8211;1825), a Treasury civil servant and secretary to George Canning&#8217;s embassy to Portugal in 1815. On 3 February 1824 he was appointed Resident Commissioner in Madrid for the Liquidation of British Claims on the Spanish Government, under the terms of a British-Spanish Convention (1823).</note> has failed to get the book I wanted<note n="6" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey had read John Mitford&#8217;s &#8216;On Spanish Literature, with some Account of Francisco de Olivarez&#8217;, <title>New Monthly Magazine</title>, 10 (October 1818), 221&#8211;223. It mentioned Olivarez&#8217;s <title>Account of the War in Catalonia</title>, published in four volumes at Seville in 1815; <title>Anecdotes of Chiefs Employed in the Catalan War</title> (1816); and <title>Memoirs of the Spanish Monarchy to the Abdication of Charles 4 &amp; the Usurpation of Joseph Bonaparte</title> (1816). However, none of these works seem to exist. Southey had already asked Murray to try and acquire them; see Southey to John Murray: 10 July 1820, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3509; 27 February 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3641; 11 June 1821, <title>The Collected Letters of Robert Southey. Part Six</title>, Letter 3693; and 27 July 1822, Letter 3877; and 1 November [1822], Letter 3911. Murray had then written to Spain to try and obtain these books for Southey&#8217;s <title>History of the Peninsular War</title> (1823&#8211;1832), and Herbert Hill had also offered to help. Finally, Southey had sought the assistance of George Canning.</note> at Madrid, he has taken measures for seeking it at Barcelona &amp; at Seville; &amp; as it was published in the latter city, there can I think be little doubt of obtaining it; &amp; it cannot be long in reaching me. Meantime I go on with other parts of the history. It is one great advantage of such subjects, that I can have several parts in progress at the same time, &amp; lay any one aside for awhile till I perceive how to proceed with it satisfactorily to myself.</p>
        <lb />
        <p rend="indent1">
          <date when="1824-03-07">Sunday. 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</date>
        </p>
        <p rend="indent1">  Today I have received a letter from <ref type="m" target="people.html#LockerEdwardHawke">Locker</ref>, who delivers me a message from the Bishop of Durham<note n="7" place="foot" resp="editors">Shute Barrington (1734&#8211;1826; <title>DNB</title>), Bishop of Durham 1791&#8211;1826.</note> thanking me for what I have done in the B. of the Church.<note n="8" place="foot" resp="editors">Southey&#8217;s <title>Book of the Church</title> (1824).</note> The <ref type="m" target="people.html#HowleyWilliam">Bp of London</ref> wrote to express his &#8220;high satisfaction.&#8221; Both regret that I have not referred to my authors an omission which appears to be generally thought injudicious. The truth is that when I began the book it was with an expectation that it would not exceed a single duodecimo volume, &#8211; &amp; that even when enlarged it is still a mere epitome for the most part, &#8211; in which I should feel that a display of authorities was out of place. After the proofs of research &amp; accuracy which I have given, I have a right to expect credit: &#8211; &amp; in fact the more my credit is examined, the higher it will stand. Whoever may examine my Collections for this, &amp; for my other historical works (&amp; doubtless they will one day be inspected) will find that I have always prepared many more materials than I have used.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">Poor <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyHenryHerbert">Henry</ref> has had a mournful house since I left him.<note n="9" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s daughter, Louisa Mary Southey (1821&#8211;1824), had just died.</note> &#8211; I hope he may have no cause to be anxious concerning Roberts<note n="10" place="foot" resp="editors">Henry Herbert Southey&#8217;s oldest son, Robert Southey, Jnr (b. 1817).</note> strange attack of fever which came on with so much violence, &amp; went off as suddenly &amp; unaccountably as it went. The life of that child would be felt more deeply &amp; abidingly than that of the poor little girl, not only because he has longer been an object of solicitude &amp; affection, &#8211; but because he is old enough to discover a very sweet &amp; hopeful disposition.</p>
        <p rend="indent1">   My family thank God are well, &#8211; <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyCharlesCuthbert">Cupn</ref> not less engaging than when you saw him. He reads fluently now, &amp; is at this time learning, as matter of amusement rather than business, the Greek alphabet. Of <ref type="m" target="people.html#SoutheyEdithMay">your goddaughter</ref> you perhaps may know more at this time than I do. Remember us most kindly to <ref type="m" target="people.html#MayJohn">M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> May</ref> &amp; your daughters<note n="11" place="foot" resp="editors">May&#8217;s daughters, Mary Charlotte (b. 1804), Susanna Louisa (1805&#8211;1885) and Charlotte Livius (b. 1812).</note> &amp; believe me my dear friend</p>
        <closer>
          <salute rend="indent1">Yours most affectionately</salute>
          <signed rend="indent2">  Robert Southey.</signed>
        </closer>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>